<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Report on Berlin Morale No. 34 - first half of December</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-2fa32e01-4799-413b-bb62-4fddd1721eeb</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-f1ed4b27-9533-4646-bb72-f28e022fd5c7</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-565188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="1">Tel: 86 5778</note>
				<note xml:id="q-575188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="2">Public Opinion Research Office</note>
				<note xml:id="q-585188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">Political Division</note>
				<note xml:id="q-595188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="4">Lancaster House</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="5">HQ CCG (BE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="6">Berlin</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="7">B.A.O.R. 2</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5d5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="8">17 Dec 48</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5e5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="9">To: Public Opinion Research Office</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5f5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="10">Political Division</note>
				<note xml:id="q-605188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="11">229 HQ CCG</note>
				<note xml:id="q-615188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="12">Hannover</note>
				<note xml:id="q-625188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="13">Subject: Berlin Morale Report No.34</note>
				<note xml:id="q-635188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">Attached is a report on Berlin Morale No.34 for the first half of December.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-645188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">Readers are asked to remember that although this report is compiled as objectively as possible, opinions expressed may often seem critical and captious. This is because so-called "opinion formers" among the German population may often be ill informed. PORO is not responsible for the views of the German population but is concerned only with the accuracy of the reporting.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-655188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="16">J.E. Dixon</note>
				<note xml:id="q-665188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="17">P.O.R.O.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-675188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="18">Pol. Div.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-685188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="19">HQ CCG (BE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-695188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="20">B.A.O.R. 2</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6a5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">CONFIDENTIAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6b5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="22">Public Opinion Research Office</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6c5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="23">Political Division</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6d5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="24">Lancaster House</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6e5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="25">HQ CCG (BE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6f5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="26">Berlin</note>
				<note xml:id="q-705188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="27">B.A.O.R..2</note>
				<note xml:id="q-715188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="28">Berlin Morale Report. (First Half of December)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-725188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">1. General Atmosphere and Morale</note>
				<note xml:id="q-735188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">Two events mainly occupied the minds of the Berliners during the first week of December,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-745188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">1. The setting up of the Eastern Magistrat, which completed the splitting up of the Berlin city administration, and</note>
				<note xml:id="q-755188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">2. The elections in Western Berlin on 5th December.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-765188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">The setting up of the so-called "opera Magistrat" (the arena of this "spontaneous manifestation by the democratic, peace-loving, progressive and anti-capitalist masses of Berlin" was the Berlin State Opera in the Soviet Sector) is described by most Western Berliners as unjustified and unconstitutional. With an overwhelming majority (over 80% of the electorate voted) they stood by the legitimate Magistrat under its Oberbuer germeister Reuter.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-775188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">The recognition of and support given to this Western Magistrat by the western Powers and the approval of the pro-Western part of the world were noted by the Berliners with great satisfaction. An opinion which is often voiced is that Western Berlin has now thrown in its lot for better or worse with the Western Powers, and that it is up to the latter to justify this confidence by action. They say the first step should be to look upon the Western Berliners no longer as defeated former enemies, but as equal allies against communism.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-785188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">In this connection, Mr. Bevin's end Mr. Churchill's statements in the debate on foreign affairs in the House of Commons made strong im­pressions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-795188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">In the opinion of most western Berliners, a peaceful solution by UNO to the Berlin question is not expected. They say UNO is like the League of Nations, it can only work out recommendations, but is unable to put them into practice. to put them into practice.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7a5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">The achievements of the Berlin air-lift are acknowledged by the majority of Berliners with gratitude and admiration. In the course of many interviews, P.O.R.O. field workers were asked to convey to the Allied air personnel and to the British and US Military Governments the thanks and good wishes of the population.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7b5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">The Berliners are taking an increasing interest in the situation in China; and it is, noted with misgivings that the Eastern Block is gaining more ground in Asia. Many Berliners think that the British and Americans have hesitated far too long to give energetic assistance, and it is said that the Western Powers can see from this example how detrimental are the results of overlong tolerance. hhh 2. Domestic Fuel Power, Gas and Transport</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7c5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">The problem of fuel remains the Western Berliners' greatest worry. When the 25 lbs. of coal and one measure of wood per household were distributed (these quantities were generally called "a drop in the ocean") many complained that about one third of the coal consisted of inferior slack, the wood was much too fresh and of low calorific value, and these allocations had to be paid for partly in Western currency.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7d5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">The Berliners say that the electricity quotas are still insufficient, especially for cooking purposes and darkness in rooms and flats every evening is described as demoralising. Many say they are unable to raise the Western money required to buy candles and lamp oil. The Berliners request the occupying powers to grant them as a "special Xmas concession" an increase of electricity for the holidays. The typical opinion is "if the Western Powers can give us extra electricity for Election Day surely they can do the same at X-mas.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7e5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">The increase in the gas allocation was welcomed by all but it is still described as inadequate, many claim they have no wood or coal and depend solely on gas for cooking.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7f5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">The transport situation still remains critical and criticism is voiced when empty COG buses pass overloaded tram cars.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-805188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">The inauguration by General Herbert, Commandant of the British Sector, of the Frey bridge in Berlin, Spandau, which again links the district of Spandau directly with Berlin, has been welcomed with satisfaction by Berliners living or working in that area. They particularly appreciate the fact that work was continued in spite of the difficulties caused by the blockade. hhh 3. Food.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-815188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">The rations were delivered punctually and without delay. Although the general food position has appreciably improved owing to the ration increases, food remains a serious problem because of the lack of fresh foodstuffs. Foraging trips to the surroundings of Berlin are virtually hopeless because the Eastern police at the city boundaries confiscate all such "harvests".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-825188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">The following complaints and requests are most frequently heard from all sections of the population:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-835188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">a) The milk powder recently issued was of bad quality.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-845188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">b) The dried potatoes issued were also of inferior quality, and people would prefer to have POM, which was issued up to October, because it is simpler to prepare and has a better taste.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-855188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">c) The dried beans, which were issued for the first time in December, are generally disliked because they had a "bad taste", and in some cases it was reported that they caused nausea.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-865188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">d) Again it is requested that the food brought in by air-lift should be of better quality. Many people cannot understand why, for in­stance; 80 g of lard are issued against 100 g fat coupons, and why tinned meat consists exclusively of beef and never of pork.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-875188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">e) The ration of beverages (25 g coffee and 25g of tea in December) is still described as entirely inadequate.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-885188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">f) It is hoped that special allocations will be made for Christmas. The ration tins distributed last year are frequently recalled.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-895188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">g) The cigarette allocations are found to be too irregular and too small (after an interval of several weeks, 9 American cigarettes per head were distributed at the beginning of December). hhh 4. Financial and Employment Worries</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8a5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">The financial worries of the population of Berlin which arise mainly from the two currencies, have not been migrated in any way, rather have they increased. The majority of the working population state that they cannot manage on their quota of Westmarks, and demand that either the Westmark be introduced as the sole currency or if this is not possible, the proportion of income payable in Westmarks be raised from 25 to 40 per cent.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8b5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">The following are two typical examples of the currency muddle in Berlin:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8c5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">1. An employee with a wife and two 'small children receives 300 M per month, of which 75 M are paid out in Westmarks. In order to make life bearable for his family during the winter months, he requires, among others (per month)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8d5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">45 DM(W) for 3 cwt. coal (for washing of baby linen etc.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">20 " " 4 ltr. lamp oil</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">10 " " 20 candles</note>
				<note xml:id="q-905188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">75 DM (W)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-915188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">This means that his entire income in Westmarks is spent on heating and light. To this must be added the other essential Westmark expenses for clothes, shoe repairs, tailor, hairdresser, soap, cigarettes, etc.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-925188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">2. Two workers (one a communist, the other an anti-communist) are living in the same house, and both have a monthly wage of 250 Marks.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-935188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">The Communist receives 50% of his wages in Westmarks, i.e. 125 DM(W) and 125 DM(East). If he exchanges his Western money at the rate of 1:4 his income is 625 DM(East) a month.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-945188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">The anti-Communist worker receives only Eastmarks, so that, although both wages are equal in theory, in practice he receives 375 DM(East) less than his communist neighbour.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-955188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">The announcement by the Western Berlin in Post Office that Western currency will in future be demanded (subject to confirmation by the Magistrat) for certain fees (telephone rentals, air mail postage, money orders and registered mail for the Western Zones) that met with indignant protest from the people concerned. They say that such an order is in contradiction to the currency regulations issued by the Western Powers, which laid down that certain essential expenses including postal charges, could be paid for in Eastern currency. It is further said that, if the Post Office claims to need Western money in order to pay Westmarks to its staff, all others which have until now-been obliged to accept Eastern currency (house owners for rents, gas and electricity works, food shops, transport) will soon claim the same right.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-965188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">Shops recently offered for free sale: unroasted coffee, marzipan, fish preserves, jam, fruit, tinned vegetables' etc. For all these goods 100% Westmarks were asked and were out of reach of the majority of Berliners, many say it's about time the Western Powers controlled shops offering such luxuries and make shop owners sell their goods on a 50% East and 50% West basis. hhh 5. The Berlin Elections</note>
				<note xml:id="q-975188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">Polling day in Berlin passed without any notable incident. The SPD gained a clear majority (64.5%). The explanation given for this large number of votes for the SPD is that it is considered the strongest and. most active party against communism and has therefore been chosen by the majority, although many of the voters were not clear as to the actual party aims. The decline in votes for the CDJ from 22.1 per cent in 1946 to l9.4 per cent is explained by the fact that the ODU, with its leading candidate and Deputy Oberburgermeister Dr. Friedensburg, has for two years conducted too much of a compromise policy and has consequently lost many sympathisers. The increase in votes for the LDP from 9.4 per cent to 16.1 percent probably comes mainly from the middle and upper classes who are opposed to the SPD programme of socialization and to the controlled economy advocated by it, and are more in favour of a free economy.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-985188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">Many people said after the elections that they saw a danger in the majority gained by the SFD, they say there is a risk that this one party will now attempt absolute domination and will try to put into effect its entire programme to the exclusion of anything else. On the other hand it is thought that the SPD will have a difficult time since it will be held solely responsible for all future failures of the Berlin MAGISTRAT, which appear inevitable in view of the political and economic situation of Western Berlin. hhh 6. Attitude towards the Allies</note>
				<note xml:id="q-995188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">Although the general attitude of the Berliners is strongly anticommunist there are also many criticisms of the Western Powers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">The demolition of the Torpedo Experimental Station at Eckernfoerde and of the dock installations at Wilhelmshaven is regarded by most Berliners as an incomprehensible action on the part of the British.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">They also fail to understand and criticize the statement by the British Minister of Economics concerning the continuation of British exports to the Soviet Union. It is thought (particularly in economic circles and by the intelligentsia) that, although such deliveries may be of material advantage to Britain at the moment, it is unwise and shortsighted to supply a power which may shortly be at war with Britain and would then use this material against the supplier.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">The problem of the Soviet-controlled wireless station Radio Berlin in the British Sector has again become very acute after the elections. The attitude of the British Military Government is described as lax and far too tolerant, and it is said that it is contrary to the will of the population of Western Berlin.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9d5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">Some of the people interviewed stated that the power stations of Harpcke and Luebeck (British Zone) are supplying long-distance power to the Soviet Zone. They were most indignant and thought that such action constituted a betrayal of the suffering Berliners.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9e5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">The temporary interruption of postal traffic from and to Western Berlin was the talk of the city for several days. Until now most Western Berliners thought that their letters were transported by the air-lift, and they were greatly surprised to learn that mail is sent by rail and is therefore exposed to the possibility of control on its way through the Soviet Zone. The general opinion is that with some good will on the part of the Western Powers, it would be quite feasible to transport letters by air. Post is the only direct link the Berliners have with the outside world, and its moral effect should not be under-estimated. The statements made by the British and American authorities that transport space is too limited were called unsatisfactory by many people. They think that while there is enough space to take prominent political refugees from the Soviet Zone to the West in order to give them refuge there, it should be possible to find space for the mail of the democratic population of Berlin.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9f5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">The statements by leading American military officers and politicians on the Berlin question are frequently criticized. One man who was interviewed said: "The Berliner does not expect that he should always have first consideration, nor does he want to be regarded as a hero, but he demands clear and unmistakeable words instead of equivocal diplomatic phrases. hhh 7. Clothing.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a05188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">The announcement that point cards are to be issued to Western Berliners and that soap coupons may be used to buy textiles as from 13th December has been received by the population with mixed feelings. If on the one hand they are glad that the cumbersome-voucher system has come to an end and that textiles are now available to everybody, it is regretted on the other hand that the goods have to be paid for in 50% Western currency, which puts them out of reach for a. large part of the population. hhh 8. Denazification</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a15188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">To an ever-growing extent the present denazification procedure is rejected by large sections of the population as senseless and unfair. Many of those interviewed felt it to be unjustifiable that little Nazis who had been arrested by the Russians in 1945 and are now being released after ­three and a half years in concentration camps, are not denazified, while prominent Nazis, like Dr.Schacht, Leni Riefenstahl, Winifred Wagner and others are classed as minor offenders. hhh 9. Housing Troubles</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a25188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">Owing to the effects of the blockade, building in Berlin has been severely restricted, and many flats and houses have not yet been made habitable for the winter. The population therefore ask that all non­-essential building should stop in favour of house repairs, above all window glazing. hhh 10. Black Market</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a35188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">While the prides of coal and potatoes have on the whole remained un-changed, food has become scarce and more expensive owning to the Christmas season. Prices are as follows:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a45188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">100 g chocolate to 5.50 - 6.00 DM. (W)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a55188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">500g dried milk 13.00 - 15.00 "</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a65188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">500 g coffee 25.00 - 27.00 "</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a75188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">500 g cocoa 26.00 - 28.00 "</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a85188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">.500 g lard 22.00 - 23.00 "</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a95188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">500 g butter . 20.00 - 22.00 " Christmas trees 7.50 - 15.00 "</note>
				<note xml:id="q-aa5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">17-12-48. N.F.</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>