<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Report on Berlin Morale No. 37 - second half of January 1949</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-01bc051e-1be5-45fb-90f0-bc8ff6a90ce0</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-d2611b4f-fc9d-4971-8e63-669cb64fac36</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-895088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="1">Public Opinion Research Office</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8a5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="2">Political Division</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8b5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">Lancaster House</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8c5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="4">HQ CCG (BE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8d5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="5">Berlin</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="6">B.A.O.R.2</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="7">3 Feb 49</note>
				<note xml:id="q-905088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="8">Public Opinion Research Office</note>
				<note xml:id="q-915088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="9">Political Division</note>
				<note xml:id="q-925088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="10">229 HQ CCG</note>
				<note xml:id="q-935088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="11">Hannover</note>
				<note xml:id="q-945088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="12">Subject: Morale Report No. 37.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-955088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">Herewith Report on Berlin Morale No. 37 for the second half of January.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-965088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">Readers are asked to remember that although this report is compiled as objectively as possible, opinions expressed may often seem critical and captious. This is because so-called "opinion formers" among the German population may often be ill informed. PORO is not responsible for the views of the German population but is concerned only with the accuracy of the reporting.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-975088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="15">J.E. Dixon</note>
				<note xml:id="q-985088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="16">P.O.R.O.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-995088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="17">Div. HQ CCG (BE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="18">B.A.O.R.2</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="19">Public Opinion Research Office</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="20">Political Division</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9d5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="21">Lancaster House</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9e5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="22">HQ COG (BE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9f5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="23">Berlin</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a05088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="24">B.A.O.R.2</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a15088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="25">Report on Berlin Morale No. 37. (Second Half of January) hhh 1. General Atmosphere and Morale</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a25088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">The morale of the Berliners is much the same as last month, winter, money, need, fear of unemployment and the political tension are at the root of the present mood. During the months of the blockade the Berliners hoped for an improvement in their position. This hope they say has not been fulfilled and the majority no longer believe in its fulfilment. They reason that it is useless to think of the future and that as Germans they cannot change things anyway, so they have to take things as they came and live from day to day.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a35088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">The trend of questions put to field workers show that there is a lack of understanding as to why the Western Powers did not prevent the blockade by energetic measures from the start and as to why they appear always to leave the first move to the Russians. They wonder if the Western Powers intentionally let the Russians act so that they (the Western Powers) can then appear compelled in the eyes of the world to take counter measures in the name of humanity in order to safeguard the German population.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a45088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">They wonder why the Western Powers are so active in other things (the Ruhr Problem, dismantling, export control) when they appear to act inde­pendently, without first consulting the Russians or the world. They wonder when the Berlin currency problem will be finally settled.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a55088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">The weather is one of the main topics discussed in Berlin today. They appreciate the relatively mild winter. They think of each day without frost as a gain.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a65088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">As usual Berliners are showing very little interest in world political problems. The Palestine question and Britain's attitude, the disturbances in South Africa and development in China are only lightly touched by Ber­liners. Some draw comparisons with the American support for the Nationalist Chinese which, nevertheless, ended in defeat and they conjecture that one day the Americans would lose interest in Berlin and the town would suffer the same fate as experienced by the village of Stolpe.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a75088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">The accident to the British airlift plane at the British-Soviet zonal border was followed by all classes of the population with concern. It was widely considered that a lack of flying organisation caused the delay in publishing the passenger lists and the names of those dead and wounded.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a85088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">That the German pianist Walter Gieseking was forbidden to perform in the U.S. was severely criticised. They were at a loss to explain the attitude of the Americans and thought that it was not conducive to international understanding. In this connection the objection is often raised that 4 years after the end of the war Germans are still forbidden to participate in international sports competition. hhh 2. Domestic Fuel and Light</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a95088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">As before, the heating problem is the biggest question. The sale of coal at 16 Ostmark per cwt. in the free shops of the East Zone (Potsdam and Babelsberg) mentioned in last report has been discontinued and, in view of lack of supplies, is not expected to reopen until February. At the same time, there are good Black Market supplies of coal in the Berlin West Sectors at 14 - 16 DM (West) per cwt. This solves the fuel problem of people with money but poor people must either remain cold in their homes or use heated public halls. The same applies to light. Whilst it presents no problem to people with money to buy candles or lamp-oil (1 ltr. -4.60 Westmark), the poorer classes queued for hours to receive their 1/2 litre of allocation oil. hhh 3. Money Troubles</note>
				<note xml:id="q-aa5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">When the rumour regarding the introduction of the Westmark as the solo currency as from February became very insistent by the middle of this month, it was officially denied by the American Military Government. The reaction of most people to this denial was disappointment, that is of all those whose income comprises less than 25% West Mark or none at all and who are often forced either to change 3.50 Ost for 1 West Mark or to forego things for which West Marks must be paid (and in Berlin this includes nearly everything that makes life pleasant and worth while.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ab5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">Business people reacted somewhat differently - to them the two currencies often mean considerable gains by astute manipulation. Examples of this mani­pulation are numerous enough to strengthen the hostile attitude of the working population to the present currency position in Berlin. hhh 4. Feeling towards the Occupation Powers</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ac5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">As the lesser of the evils the Americans are most popular and termed by Berliners as "not so bad".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ad5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">They say the British are obviously afraid of the competition of German quality output on the World market. They regard the French with contempt, and think they are still full of thoughts of revenge and fear a renaissance of a strong Germany.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ae5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">Attitude towards the Russians remains the same, while Berliners criticise the 3 Western Powers they still fear that one day they will leave Berlin. hhh 5. Employment Worries</note>
				<note xml:id="q-af5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">It is the general view of both employers and of employees that the unemployment figures threaten to rise further, owing to the imminent closing down of more undertakings because of difficulties in providing materials, power and transport. Both the employees of public departments and of Military Government have been affected by this cutting down process.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b05088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">There are hardly any situations offered in West Berlin and even for bombed site clearance and other unpopular work there is a surplus supply of labour. hhh 6. Food</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b15088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">The food position in Berlin is unchanged, i.e. though not good it is adequate. Complaints are made not so much about the quantity as about the quality of the rations (especially with regard to dried potatoes, milk powder, margarine and cereals). The monotony of the food and the limited ways of using it, and the entire lack of foodstuffs, make it very difficult for the housewives to think up varied menus. It is stated that too much is, deducted from the rations of fish, tinned meat, lard and dried eggs, as only up to 80% of the coupon values of these things are issued.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b25088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">The ration of beverages of 75g of coffee per month for adults is still claimed to be entirely inadequate. Mothers would prefer cocoa instead of tea for their children.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b35088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">Again and again the question is raised what has become of the food gifts from Western Germany and abroad, which were so much talked about a few months ago, and which were not to be deducted from the rations.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b45088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">The issue of "Bosco" cigarettes has aroused general annoyance. People consider it an affront that precious air freight space should be used for such inferior goods. Many Berliners said that the opinion seemed to be gaining ground in Western Germany that even the poorest qualities were good enough for the Berliners, who are entirely dependent upon outside help. (This includes the unpopular bean-flakes). hhh 7. City Railway and Transport Controls</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b55088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">Luggage controls at the sector borders continue with unabated stringency. Several incidents have occurred, especially in the city railway trains. It is claimed that Russian Sector German policemen carrying out the controls were forcibly detained in the coaches when the border stations were reached and when the train had passed into the Western Sectors they were assaulted and beaten up.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b65088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">At the orders of the SMA the lightening of the city railway stations and trains has improved in the last few days. Although the passengers naturally welcome this, they see in it not so much a desire on the part of the SMA to help them, as propaganda motives. Many think that the lighting has been improved in order to make it easier for the Eastern police to carry out their controls during the hours of darkness.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b75088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">The counterblockade announced by the Allied Kommandatura, i.e. the export embargo on certain goods from the western Sectors to the Soviet occupied areas, has met with general approval, though many people think that this decision has come too late and should have been taken much earlier. hhh 8. Housing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b85088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">It is evident that housing worries are far less serious in the better and more expensive residential districts of Berlin than they are in the crowded working class districts. The results of an enquiry throws some interesting light on this problem. Whilst in the district of Zehlendorf (good residential district) only 19% of the people interviewed mentioned housing difficulties, 52% did so in the working class district of Kreuzberg. hhh 9. Denazification</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b95088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">The decision taken by the Allied Kommandatura to set up Denazification Boards by professions in the 3 Western Sectors has been met with indifference by the majority of the Berliners.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ba5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">They would have preferred that an end should be made of these denazifications and that the authorities should turn their attention to those people who are again behaving like Nazis. A proclamation of a youth amnesty is considered the most important point. hhh 10. Black Market</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bb5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">The Black Market is slowly disappearing from the streets, where it seems to be operated by veritable organisations. A striking feature lately has been the abundant supply of goods of all kinds in the shops and open markets at excessive prices.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bc5088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">Prices for American cigarettes were rapidly falling at the beginning of the second fortnight of January; they dropped to 27 pfennigs each, Towards the end of the month the price has risen again to approximately 35 pfennigs each. For other goods the price tendency likewise declined temporarily, but in the last few days a general rise could be noted. The present Black Market prices are largely the same as those published in Morale Report No. 36.</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>