<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Home Intelligence Dvision Weekly Report No. 104 - 1 October 1942</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-0b246077-e2b5-4329-a1e5-68f8209a2749</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-af6705bc-c459-434d-91d0-ca42b70cea64</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-775e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-785e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="2">Home Intelligence Division Weekly Report No. 104</note>
				<note xml:id="q-795e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="3">1st October, 1942</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7a5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="4">(Covering the period from 22nd to 29th September, 1942)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7b5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="5">I. GENERAL COMMENTS hhh 1. General state of confidence and reaction to news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7c5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">While there does not seem to have been any substantial change in public feeling as a whole since last week, a slight rise in spirits is reported from seven Regions, almost entirely due, it is said, to continued Russian resistance at Stalingrad. Though anxiety for the city is still very great, and though "there would be no surprise if it were to fall", there now appears to be "a rising hope that Stalingrad may hold". Admiration for the Russians seems to be as widespread and as intense as at the time of the defence of Moscow. The desire to give greater aid to Russia 'is even more strongly reported than last week, and is allied in many cases to a feeling of frustration and shame at "our unprepared­ness to give effective help" - a feeling which Mr. Willkie's utterance in Moscow is said to have stimulated.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7d5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">Interest in other fronts continues to be slight, though several reports mention the cheering effects of:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7e5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">(a) "The successful passage of the great convoy to Russia",</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7f5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">(b) Our attacks behind the German lines in Libya,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-805e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">(c) The Oslo raid.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-815e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">Complacency and lack of urgency are mentioned in reports from three Regions, particularly among "munition workers with money to burn and people living in small towns".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-825e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">The anticipated discomforts of the coming winter, particularly those due to the cold, the blackout and fire-watching, continue to exercise the imagination of a large section of the public. Fuel economy is said to "come only second to Stalingrad as a subject of discussion".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-835e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">Another subject arousing widespread comment, according to reports from nine Regions, is "the unequal distribution and misuse of petrol".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-845e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13.21 Edinburgh, Glasgow, Leeds, Manchester P.C.s.) hhh 2. Russia</note>
				<note xml:id="q-855e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">All reports agree that events in Russia and, in particular the fight for Stalingrad, "overshadow all others in the public mind". While admiration for the Russians, "both the Red Army and the civilians", has increased, anxiety for Stalingrad, though still great, shows signs of giving way to a cautiously expressed hope that "the city may hold if the offensive in the north-west is continued". (Eight Regions). This hope is occasionally qualified by the view that "even if it does fall, it is too late in the year to be the prize the Germans hoped for".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-865e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">The description of the house-to-house and room-to-room fighting has "led to some renewed comparisons with our own poor are from three Regions this week but, unlike similar comparisons made at the time of the defence of Sevastopol, they have not been the subject of German broadcasts in English.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-875e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13) hhh 3. The second front</note>
				<note xml:id="q-885e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">The desire to do something more to aid Russia is implicit in all reports and referred to in nine, but there is a considerable division of opinion on the question of a second front, 'about which renewed interest and discussion are reported. According to two reports the "revulsion of feeling about a second front, following the Dieppe raid, is still general", and there continues to be a fairly 'widespread tendency to leave the decision to the exports. Where an increased demand is reported, it appears in many cases to be "communist-inspired" or to come especially from the workers. En this connection, however, demands chalked on brick walls are said to lose some of their impressiveness through such additions as: "But, please, Mr. Bevin, don't forget we are reserved:"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-895e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">As well as renewed discussion, there is reported to be an increased sense of' expectancy that an offensive is being actively prepared, teat "it won't be long now" and that "we are on the eve of stirring events". The following are quoted as having helped to create this impression:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8a5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">Mr. Willkie's statement in Moscow: This has met with a very mixed reception, but has chiefly stimulated the feeling that "we are not doing enough but are possibly about to do more.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8b5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">Mr. Lyttelton's "30 days" speech, with his further references to sixty and to twenty days.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8c5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">Sir Samuel Hoare's speech (13th September): considered by some as a "definite second front hint".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8d5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">The warning to the French to keep away from coastal areas,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13) hhh 4. The convoy to Russia</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">Though are icing apparently less interest than the recent Malta convoy, the "successful passage" of the Arctic convoy has caused great satisfaction- all the more because it was an example of "tangible aid actually reaching Russia", and great admiration has been expressed for "those responsible for getting it through". Them is said to be "much speculation as to the number of merchant ships, since it was revealed that there were seventy-five ships in the escort".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-905e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">The First Lord of the Admiralty's speech at Sheffield, 20th September: Mr. Alexander's statement on the .replacements of naval losses is described as having "encouraged a more hopeful attitude towards the battle of the seas", though a few are said to blame him for "giving information to the enemy and for the irresponsible release of news".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-915e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">(1.2.4.6.7.10.13) hhh 5. The Allied air offensive</note>
				<note xml:id="q-925e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">Thu sustained air offensive during the first three weeks of September has given great satisfaction (seven Regions), and hopes are expressed that this will be continued. On the other hand, two reports ask what has happened to the thousand bomber raids we were promised, and a minority doubt the effectiveness of the air, offensive because it "does not seem to have helped Russia much". Reports (from three Regions) still express the fear that our proportionate plane losses are heavy, and would like to see those given on a percentage basis.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-935e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">There is continued demand for the bombing of Italy 'where so many munitions: of war are being made for Germany" (Three Regions), and a feeling that Rome is being spared because of Roman Catholic influences.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-945e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">The raid on Oslo: The raid by Mosquito light bombers appears to have caught the public imagination (five Regions), and the broadcast by one of the pilots was much appreciated. (1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12) hhh 6. Egypt</note>
				<note xml:id="q-955e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">Not much interest is reported in this front,. which is described as "all but forgotten by the man in the street". The public are said to have no clear idea as to what is going on: some complain that we make no progress, and say that "it is time it was cleared up", while others are "satisfied that all is under control". It is remarked that "it is impossible to tell from the presentation of the Egyptian news whether Rommel has really suffered a heavy defeat or merely been engaged in large scale reconnaissance".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-965e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">The surprise raids on Gialo and Benghazi have aroused some interest and "the offensive spirit shown in these attacks has been greatly welcomed". There is, however, some feeling that they were "robbed of their real value" by the "failure of the landing at Tobruk", which continues to be regarded as "too expensive for the results obtained".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-975e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.12.13) hhh 7. Madagascar</note>
				<note xml:id="q-985e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">Interest in this campaign seems to be subsiding, and very little comment is reported. The occupation of the capital at such small cost has given satisfaction, but it was taken for granted that we should meet with little opposition and some people are said to be unable to understand "why an outpost of France, outside Nazi control, should put up even passive resistance".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-995e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">The unpopularity of the Free French, referred to last week, is reported this week from two Regions, partly, it is alleged, as a result of their own behaviour, but chiefly as an extension of anti-Vichy fueling and of "a tendency to regard the people of France as antagonistic to our cause"... It is thought that "the very difficult position of Vichy should be more widely recognised" as "there is a danger that our present attitude may have a harmful effect on our future relations with France".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">Some American troops are thought to share these reported views, on the subject of the Free French.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">(2.4.5.6.7.8.13) hhh 8. The Far East</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">Reports again show that there is only a perfunctory interest in the Far Eastern war zone and that comment on the Allied offensive is confined to a minority. Among these few, however, the United States' and Australian forces are thought to be "getting along better". But an occasional note of scepticism is sounded by those who think that "both in numbers and capabilities" the Japanese may have been underestimated.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9d5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">(3.4.6.8.9.10.11.12.13) hhh 9. India</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9e5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">There appears to be very little discussion about India, Such as there is takes the form of curiosity and some disquiet. The recent news of atrocities has caused suspicion and in some cases resentment, because the gravity of the situation is thought to have been concealed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9f5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">(4.8.9.10.11) hhh 10. The Dieppe raid Comments on this raid continue to stress the fact that the casualties are thought to have been high in relation to the results. (No further comments have been received since the Prime Minister's statement on 30th September.) Three reports this week refer to the belief that the reason for the heavy losses was that "news had somehow leaked out, and the Germans had been waiting for us for two days". For this indiscretion the Canadians are believed responsible. Another version of the leakage story is that an advertisement for refrigerators in a technical paper mentioned the name of Dieppe a few days before the raid.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a05e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">(1.4.5.8.10.21 Aberdeen, Inverness, Manchester P.C.s.) hhh 11. Enemy air raids in this country</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a15e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">Belief in recurrence of raids this winter is expressed in reports from five Regions: "the Germans will turn every available plane against us if they can 'tie up' the Russians for the winter". There is fear among some people of the inadequacy of our A.A. defences which they want to see improved (two Regions); "Jerry comes in with comparative impunity". On the other hand, one Region reports high confidence in our night fighters and ground defences.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a25e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">The publication of air raid casualty figures is said to be rousing distrust in our news service (one Region): "We are told only a few raiders have been over - well, look at the hundreds of casualties". The South Eastern Region reports a tendency for people in' raided towns to feel that the raids are "dismissed too lightly in the press and on the radio".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a35e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">Incendiary bombs: Reports from two Regions mention fear of the new incendiary bombs.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a45e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">(1.2.3.7.9.10.11.12) hhh 12. The war situation debate (8th September)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a55e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">The action of members in leaving after the- Prime Minister's speech is still reported as arousing critical comment in three Regions, on the lines of: "What interest can expect people to take in the war, and what effort can you expect people to make, when M.P.s, who are paid to do a job, show slackness in the doing of it?" It is suggested that the public is not fully aware of the other, duties of members of Parliament besides that of taking part in debates.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a65e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">1.8.9) hhh 13. Broadcasting and presentation of news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a75e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">There again seems to be little general criticism of news presentation, and reports from two Regions indicate an increase in satisfaction. The only complaint which appears to be at all widespread relates to the "unnecessary importance given to trifling items", objection to which comes from four Regions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a85e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">Many people are, however, said to be listening to the European service in preference to the Home and Forces News, the reasons given being:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a95e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">(i) The times are more convenient for many.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-aa5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">(ii) The anonymous announcers are not tempted to exploit their individual personalities.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ab5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">(iii) It is strictly limited to a quarter of an hour, and is therefore "terse, pithy and authoritative".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ac5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">Some people are suggesting that the B.B.C. news bulletins should be prefaced with: "As stated in our...o'clock bulletin". "This would prevent a depression which arises through hearing the same loss or withdrawal repeated a number of times. It is quite easy for people to get the impression that the Russians have withdrawn five times when, in fact, there was only one withdrawal".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ad5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">This week an unusually large number of individual broadcasts have been singled out for praise, including:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ae5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">General Sir W. Dobbie's broadcast (22nd September): This has been highly praised and was described as "a great speech from a great man".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-af5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">Sir Ronald Adam's postscript (Sunday) 27th September): This was particularly liked "for taking the line that women could put up with hardships if necessary, and not just telling them that everything in the garden would be lovely".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b05e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">Sir Stafford Cripps' "broadcast sermon" (27th September) from St. Matthew's Church, Bristol.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b15e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">Rotterdam, in the series, "They shall rise again":</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b25e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">The Brains Trust in its new form: "The wider choice of members and visitors appears 'already to have lifted the discussion above the futilities into which some people felt the Original team had drifted".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b35e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">Tommy Handley's return: This is said to have' teen "generally welcomed", as some feel that "Tommy Handley in 'Itma' is still far and away our best war-time entertainment"".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b45e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">(1.2.3.5.6.7.8.9.10.12.32)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b55e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="63">II. SPECIAL COMMENTS hhh 14. Fuel Economy</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b65e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">Reports from eleven Regions show that the discussion of the fuel economy campaign is greater than ever - "it is a major offensive"; genuine efforts are being made to economise, though in many cases with little or no hope of reaching the target figures. These are thought to be impossible to achieve, except by many poorer people who claim never to have reached their targets. Waste on a large scale has also discouraged some people. Large industrial concerns, public buildings, offices, hotels, etc. are still considered responsible for great waste (nine Regions) and it is suggested that the Government should compel factory owners to substitute movable blackout arrangements for permanent fixtures.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b75e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">The Government is still considered to have "muddled it", and one Region reports that the miners and miners' leaders believe that the only real solution of the coal problem is to release miners from the Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b85e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">The ban on fires and central heating until November has brought many protests (six Regions), as it is believed that both health and output of work will suffer; "Without the comfort of fires one's mental tiredness is exaggerated". Parents, also, are perturbed about the effect of cold schools on young children. It is asked if doctors can issue certificates for extra fuel when patients are confined to bed. The Queen's illness is attributed to the fuel shortage. "The poor Queen is the first victim of the new fuel order".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b95e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">Six Regions report that rationing is felt to be almost inevitable and might be preferable to the present uncertainty and inequalities, though there are fears that a "cast iron" system of rationing, such as applies to food, would cause great hardship.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ba5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">Fuel Flashes: These are causing some feeling of irritation and are thought to have been too long continued and sometimes "silly", although one report says that Grisewood's Fuel Flashes are still listened to, and his manner preferred to that of women announcers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bb5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">Facetious remarks are reported from an industrial Region about Commander King-Hall's suggestion to collect wood from private parks. It is felt that fuel control is in the hands of people who know nothing whatever about working-class conditions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bc5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.21. Bristol, Glasgow, Manchester, Nottingham P.C.s. 32.) hhh 15. Women's Fireguard Order</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bd5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">From four Regions come reports this week that criticism and antagonism are dying down and that people are becoming reconciled to the Order. Two Regions and postal Censorship; however, report discontent and increasing dissatisfaction.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-be5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">The main complaint this week, which is said to be growing, is the unequal compensation for men and women.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bf5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">Men are still thought to be dodging their obligations as regards fire--watching. Suspicion is reported that some women will manage to avoid doing any fire-watching, but criticism is said to have been softened in one Region by the statements in the press "that the dodgers will not get away with it".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c05e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">Women are said to object to watching at their business premises, because:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c15e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">(i) the long hours may be damaging to their health,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c25e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">(ii) in an old factory there may be rats and mice,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c35e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">(iii) transport difficulties, in the case of women living at a distance from their work, will result in their being absent for long periods from home.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c45e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">(iv) there is a Shortage of amenities - blankets, feeding facilities.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c55e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">Many men still object to women watching in target areas.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c65e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">People are still alleged to be uncertain of what is required of them. The registration of women for firewatching, which is said to be proceeding well, is reported to have shown "that some confusion existed in the minds of women". In the North Western Region, it is said that some production time has been lost because people who registered last year tried to register again, and in some offices forms were not available.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c75e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">(1.2.3.4.5.7.9.10.11.21 Manchester P.C.) hhh 16. Transport Transport problems, which, according to the South Western Region, "remain as strongly and widely complained of as ever", are reported from eight Regions this week. (In London, however, people are said "to be in general prepared to accept restrictions philosophically".') Comment continues on familiar lines, but specific mention is made of the following sections of the public "who are often left stranded": (i) war workers: "some priority scheme should be evolved for them"; (ii) People who live between main stopping places in rural areas; (iii) Those "Who have further to go" and are crowded out by short distance travellers. (1.2.3.4.6.7.8.10) 17. Petrol</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c85e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">Reports from nine Regions (as against five last week) refer to feeling, variously described as critical, bitter or irritated, about the use of petrol, and "stricter control of its consumption" is again urged. The main allegations continue to be that:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c95e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">(a) Petrol allowances are not being used for legitimate purposes. (Eight Regions). Specific references are made to:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ca5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">(i) Cars seen outside public houses, hotels, cinemas, and dancing places; officials of the Bristol Aeroplane Company, "who drive to and from lunch rather than eat at canteens", are also singled out. vii) Cars used for shopping "every day of the week";</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cb5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">iii) Farmers using agricultural petrol for private purposes.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cc5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">(b) Too many supplementary allowances are granted. (Six Regions). It is believed that petrol supplies "can be wangled if you can tell good story".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cd5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">(c) The use of taxis for non-essential journeys.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ce5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">(Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cf5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">It is reported from Scotland that in view of the petrol shortage "it is preposterous that a special bus takes Italians from the camp at Denny for a round trip of eighteen miles every Saturday to do their shopping".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d05e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">In Wales, the granting of petrol to pacifist Ministers causes growing irritation. In London, the Jehovah's Witness Minister is said to use a large car to visit his flock in Holloway Goal, whereas the Church of England parson and the Catholic priest now travel by bus. hhh 18. Industry</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d15e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">There is again little comment about production as a whole, but the general feeling appears to be that "it is pretty good but could and should be better". Specific references are made to the following matters:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d25e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">(a) The call-up. (Seven Regions) The call-up of older men and women is still producing "a good deal of criticism of the younger men and women who are evading their obligations", along the lines mentioned last week. In addition, "particularly bitter comment" is reported again on "the number of young wives of servicemen and officers' selfish wives, who are still doing nothing". One aspect of this is referred to by a postal Censorship extract: "I feel it's a wicked waste of war effort so many women doing nothing but travel round the country with their blokes from camp 'to camp and leaving it to other people to get the war over".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d35e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">(b) Shopping difficulties of war workers. (Four Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d45e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">(c) Organisation in factories (Three Regions) From the North Eastern, Midland and Scottish Regions, come complaints of bad organisation within industrial concerns. The workers are said to feel that better systems would produce better results. In Scotland, however, when it was suggested that they should report this to a production Committee, they replied: "We have no faith in them".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d55e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">(d) Lack of incentive on the part of workers who, according to the managements, "don't appreciate there's a war on and are just jogging along (Two Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d65e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">(e) Long hours. (Two Regions) There is said to be "some grumbling" from workers about long -hours, overtime and Sunday work, particularly over twelve hour shifts. According to the report from the North Eastern Region, "in certain sections of industry the health of workers is said to be deteriorating, especially among the over-forties and married women".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d75e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">(f) The transfer of women from Scotland to England continues to be "a real source of resentment".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d85e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">Other matters raised, but by reports from one Region only in each case, are: (i) The difficulties for married workers on leaving their homes for hostels; (ii) The difficulty of lorry drivers, etc., sent for short visits, in finding accommodation on the journey or at the end. (iii) "The exploitation of women workers at lower wages than men".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d95e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">(1.2.5.6.7.8.10. 11.16 ) hhh 19. Wages and pay</note>
				<note xml:id="q-da5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">There is further reference in Regional and: postal Censorship reports to "the inadequacy" of .the increase in servicemen's pay, although there is some slight satisfaction that there is an increase it all. To quote from a writer; "What do you think of them raising the soldiers' pay sixpence a day - sixpence! I wonder what the people that's picking up pounds a week would say if they were given that amount rise". Comparison continues to be made between servicemen's ray and that of (i), munition workers, and (ii) U.S. troops.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-db5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">It is suggested in London that "the Communist Party is putting about that it was they who got the rise in Army pay put through".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">High wages; The high wages of "younger people" still appear to be causing concern; it is felt that there should be some system of compulsory saving for them.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">In the North Midland Region there are said to be "many people who view with alarm the advances in wages which are being granted to certain trades, and who are wondering when this business of 'dog chasing tail' will stop".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">(1.3.4.5.6.8.9.10.21 Aberdeen, Inverness, Manchester P. C. s.) hhh 20. Minors and the Essential Work Order</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">There appears to have been little further comment on the passing of the amendment to the Essential Work (Coalmining Industry) Order. Opinions differ as to the reasons for this and range from the view that it has been quietly accepted as a necessary war measure, to the suggestion that the miner knows his present value to the country and feels reasonably sure that the Government will not risk enforcing the amendment. Mental slowness and lack of interest are also thought to be possible causes, although the belief is held that the seriousness of the present position is being more fully appreciated by miners.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e05e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">Among managements and miners' 'representatives the amendment seems to have been welcomed - among the former because it is believed to meet- the need for dealing swiftly and efficaciously...with offenders in the pits, and among the latter because both they and the miners are glad that the question of dealing with absentees has been taken out of their hands. It is suggested that when a prosecution takes place it must be "a good case of a genuine slacker". A case of this kind, it is believed, will not arouse the sympathy of the miners and will discourage absenteeism.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e15e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">The belief that-the only real solution of the coal problem is to release miners from the army is reported by two Regions to be current. Nationalization is also suggested as the solution of the industry's troubles.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e25e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="108">Surprise that it should be found necessary further to restrict the miner's liberty has been mentioned, and impatience with "trifling amendments" compared with the "hideous struggle at Stalingrad" has been expressed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e35e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="109">Among the larger pits there is reported to be satisfaction that transfer to other 'scheduled undertakings is to be prevented.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e45e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="110">The new order, it is suggested, may have been the cause of a reported increase in production last week in some pits in the Durham area.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e55e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="111">(1.8.10.11.12.) hhh 21. U.S. troops in Great Britain</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e65e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="112">Comment on this subject has declined considerably, but it is on the whole favourable. The coloured troops are referred to as "a fine lot of men". The attitude of the white U.S. troops towards them still arouses interest. Two Regions report continued comment on the high pay of U.S. troops, and there is again mention of "careless talk" and fast driving.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e75e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="113">Allegations that U.S. troops are being overcharged in shops and public houses are again made (one Region), and there is an isolated case reported of an American making a similar complaint.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e85e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="114">(3.4.5.6.7.8.11.12.21 Cambridge, Manchester, Bristol, Glasgow P.C.s.) hhh 22. Food</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e95e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="115">Satisfaction with the food situation continues to be reported. Lord Woolton's warning about stricter rationing is said to have been taken well in two Regions; but has "caused perturbation" in the North Eastern Region.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ea5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="116">Unfavorable comments reported on certain aspects of the food situation include;-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-eb5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="117">(a) The shortage of shell eggs.(Four Regions and Postal Censorship).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ec5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="118">(b) The increase in the price of bread. The farthings in the price are said to be leading to the purchase of two loaves when only one is needed, with consequent waste. (Four Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ed5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="119">(c) The small allowance of sugar for jam, making. (Three Regions and Postal. Censorship) Housewives in the North Midland Region are said to be complaining that their jam made in May and June is going bad. The opinion is expressed that this may be happening because the sugar is beet, and not cane.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ee5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="120">(d) The high price and unequal distribution of fruit. (Three Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ef5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="121">(e) The cheese ration is too big. The lack of variety is also commented on. (Two Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f05e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="122">(f) The shortage of fish. From the North Western Region, the conviction is reported among those in the industry that the fish zoning scheme will fail. (Two Regions) v(g) The shortage of vinegar. (Two Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f15e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="123">(h) The habit of sieving national flour is said to be increasing. (Two Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f25e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="124">(i) The purchase of large quantities of oatmeal "for uses other than human 'Consumption". (One Region)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f35e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="125">The public are reported to be interested in the Ministry of Food advertisements and instructions. The widespread publicity in favour of potatoes is generally understood, although not always accepted. In Wales it is said to create suspicion; "Last year it was carrots for health, sight, etc., and we were told we could not expect to live unless we ate carrots. Now the same tale about potatoes".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f45e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="126">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.10.12.21 Cambridge, Edinburgh, Reading, Aberdeen, Carlisle, Manchester, Cardiff.P.0 s.32) hhh 23. Clothing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f55e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="127">The "poor quality" and "shoddiness" of some utility clothing "as compared with the attractiveness and good quality of other utility garments" is reported to be causing dissatisfac­tion. Utility stockings are especially mentioned in this connection. They are said to be shapeless and absolutely lacking in reasonable durability. The popular view is that they are just a waste of coupons".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f65e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="128">The shortage of warm underclothing in large sizes for men and women is reported from Wales. From the North Midland Region comes the complaint that O.S. clothing is not being produced by manufacturers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f75e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="129">The fitting out of children for their first year at a Secondary School and the maintenance of the uniform are said to cause hardship especially in regard to coupons. The general opinion in Wales is "that school uniforms should be optional".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f85e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="130">"The long delays experienced in getting repairs to boots and shoes executed are reported to cause hardship, especially to poorer people who may only possess one or two pairs".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f95e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="131">(1.3.5.7.8.32) hhh 24. Civil Defence uniforms</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fa5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="132">The provision of new uniforms for Civil Defence workers is reported from three Regions to be regarded as "a complete waste of money", not only by the public but by wardens themselves. Some of the latter point out that "much valuable time would be lost in turning out at an alert if they stopped to don the uniform", and that "in practice the uniform would only be used for parades". Displeasure at the idea is also reported from the Army and the Home Guard: "Mere is misunderstanding about rank markings".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fb5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="133">(1.5.6.10.32) hhh 25. Careless talk</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fc5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="134">Careless talk, which is said to have greatly increased in the Southern Region, is reported from three Regions this week; "particularly amongst Service personnel, who seem only too ready to disclose their station and the type of work they are engaged upon". It is suggested that "a fresh campaign against careless talk might prove useful".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fd5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="135">(3.5.6) hhh 26. Rumours</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fe5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="136">The Ark Royal story continues. She is said to be nearly fit to put to sea again. Naval ratings are alleged to have started this rumour in the London area.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ff5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="137">Irish labourer; who leave the country after 6, months to avoid income tax are thought to be a particularly dangerous source of information for the enemy. They are said to queue up outside the German Embassy in Dublin to lay information at £2 a time. It is rumoured that an enemy passenger plane flies over Watford nightly on its way to Dublin, unmolested.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-005f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="138">Second front rumours continue. Portugal is now named as a place for attack. Points on the South Coast which are to be evacuated are discussed. Pipe-lines running down to the sea at certain points are thought to be for oil for refueling when the second front comes.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-015f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="139">(3.4.5.7.10.11.12)</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>