<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Home Intelligence Weekly Report - No. 117 - 31 December 1942</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-f72d6e08-97a5-45e1-aa07-af8303a24c7e</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-cd0492f0-58db-4df2-9365-202d21cc5f2a</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-8d5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="3">HOME INTELLIGENCE WEEKLY REPORT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-905d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="4">No. 117.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-915d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="5">31st December 1942</note>
				<note xml:id="q-925d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">(Covering the period 22nd to 29th December 1942)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-935d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="7">I. GENERAL COMMENTS hhh 1. General state of confidence and reaction to news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-945d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">This week's people have been preoccupied with "the most hopeful Christmas since war began". The only war news to receive much attention is the assassination of Darien, and to a lesser extent, the Russian offensives. Public spirits appear to have risen; this is attributed to:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-955d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">(a) The settling of "the vexed question of Darien".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-965d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">(b) The continued Russian victories.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-975d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">(c) Enjoyment of Christmas, "despite austerities", and the hope or belief that "by next Christmas the war will be ended, or at least the end will be in sight". (Nine Regions and Postal Censorship)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-985d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13. 21 Cambridge, Carlisle, Inverness, Leeds, Manchester, Nottingham P.Gs.) hhh 2. The assassination of Admiral Darlan</note>
				<note xml:id="q-995d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">The news of Darlan's death was received with general relief, as "the automatic solution to a difficult and unpleasant situation". It is felt that "a source of inter-allied friction" has been removed. At the same time, according to two Regions, "the Americans are believed not to be so pleased about it as we are".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">There is reported to be widespread speculation as to "how it happened". People are said to be particularly curious as to i) why the assassin was so rapidly executed (Seven Regions), and ii) why his identity was kept secret (Five Regions). It is thought that the answer to both these questions may be that it was "a put-up job, connived at by some country or faction" (Six Regions), "People hesitate to voice their suspicions", but various suggestions are made as to "who had a hand in it" - the democratic powers, our Government as a whole, some individual member of it, or the Nazis who did it to cast suspicion on England in American eyes. "A full public statement should be made", it is suggested in reports from three Regions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">A few people wonder whether (i) the assassin was executed at all (Three Regions); (ii) Darlan is still alive (One Region); (iii) Dorian committed suicide (One Region).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">There is much discussion on assassination as "a method of removal" (Eight Regions). The variety of feelings expressed range between condemnation of assassination on principle, to pleasure at "this good riddance of bad rubbish". People "feel they ought not to approve of assassinations", but the majority are inclined to make an exception in this case.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9d5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">General Giraud: The appointment of General Giraud as Darlan's 'successor has met with widespread approval. It is felt "to augur well for future French unity" in thee common fight, and the hope is expressed that General de Gaulle and the Fighting. French "will find a place by General Giraud's side".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9e5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">Three Regions report objections among a minority to General Giraud's appointment on the grounds that (i) "he is a reactionary"; (ii) "General de Gaulle must come first".' (1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13) hhh 3. Russia</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9f5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">People are following the Russian offensives with great admiration, interest and satisfaction. There is some expectation that last year's Russian victories may be exceeded this year, and hope is again reported of "even bigger .happenings in the future, and that the retreat may turn into a rout".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a05d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">Other reactions are:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a15d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">(a) Some continued scepticism about the accuracy of the Russian claims, particularly the figures of Germans killed and captured, and of material taken and destroyed. (Ten Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a25d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">On the other hand, some people are "particularly impressed by the huge numbers given", and "even if 'they are exaggerations, the true losses must be a huge strain on German Manpower".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a35d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">(b) Inability to follow what is happening in Russia (Two Regions). It is suggested that the maps given in the newspapers are "bad" or misleading.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a45d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13. 21 Aberdeen, Carlisle, Edinburgh, Glasgow, Leeds, Manchester, Nottingham P.Cs.) hhh 4. North Africa</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a55d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">This week there has been less discussion about this theatre of war. There continues to be some disappointment that "victory does not come more quickly", beat people are said to be "waiting patiently for further developments". They "realise that there are hard tasks ahead particularly in Tunisia, before the Axis forces can finally be cleared from North Africa". General Montgomery is spoken of in one report "as approaching Wavell in popularity".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a65d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">(1.2.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.13) hhh 5. Italy</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a75d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">Reference continues to be made to public feeling about the possibility of Rome being declared an open city: "military considerations alone should determine our choice of targets", not deference to Roman Catholics (Two Regions). There is also some doubt as to "Axis good faith in keeping their side of the bargain".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a85d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">Two Regions report the feeling that "Italy will crack, if the Nazis' hold is not too strong", In the North Western Region, comment on Italy's weakness is said to have died down, however. (2.3.4.5.7.8.10. 21 Inverness, Leeds P.Cs.) hhh 6. Far East</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a95d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">Interest in tile Far Eastern battle zones is still reported to be slight, though it appears to be increasing a little as a result of our advance into Burma. There is some expectation that this will soon develop into a large offensive; General Wavell's name is "still one to conjure with". The improved position in the Solomons and Now Guinea causes satisfaction but little comment. (Four Regions). According to two .reports, however, people are remarking on the way "the Japs hang on" and "'the long time it is taking to clear them out of Buna... a little place like that".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-aa5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">General Tojo's statement on the difficulties facing Japan have led some people to "contrast the present mood of the Japanese Government with their arrogant confidence this time last year". Some even take his warnings to the Japs that the war has only just begun as indicating that "it may-not take such a long time to dispose of them after all". The opinion of the majority still, however, appears to be that "it will indeed be difficult to clear them out of all the places they have over-run".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ab5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13) hhh 7. The Beveridge Report</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ac5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">There appears to have been much less discussion of the Report during the last week: only in two Regions is it described as still a general topic of conversation. Many, however, are said to be reading the abridged edition and to have been "looking forward to Christmas as an opportunity of really getting down to studying the report". There appear to be no new developments of opinion; the desire for "a Government pronouncement about it" continues to be mentioned.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ad5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">The reports from Scotland and Wales refer to adverse comment on the withdrawal of the Beveridge number of "Current Affairs", issued 'by the Army Bureau of Current Affairs. There is said to be "great indication at this undemocratic step" and "curiosity as to the real reasons".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ae5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12. 21 Aberdeen, Bristol, Glasgow, Inverness, Leeds, Manchester, Nottingham, York P.Cs.) hhh 8. German anti-Jewish atrocities</note>
				<note xml:id="q-af5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">Opinions expressed appear to be the same as those reported last week - anger aid disgust at the Germans, but "no evidence that the popularity of Jews in this country has increased". As one report puts it: "Abroad r greatest sympathy; in England - general feeling that they badly went controlling". A minority among the Jews are said to be "apprehensive that anti-Semitism will be encouraged" by the publicity given to the atrocities, and the recent recurrence of anti-Semitic talk, which had largely died down, suggests that these fears are not groundless.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b05d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">The desire that those responsible for the atrocities shall be punished appears to be strong. Some feel that "resolutions of protest are futile" and that "we must smash the German war machine and then punish the Nazi criminals without mercy. If we let them escape we shall lose everything for which we are fighting".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b15d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">(2.3.8.10.11.12.13. 21 Aberdeen, Cardiff, Glasgow, Inverness P.Cs.) hhh 9. Venereal disease and Regulation 33B</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b25d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">The wish for "filler information about infection, symptoms, consequences and treatment of Venereal Diseases is still reported to be very general, particularly in big industrial centres", according to the report from the South Western Region. The reluc­tance of managements for "such information to be given by the firms' health services" is thought to be because "the implication would be that any firm starting to do this must be a centre of infection".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b35d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">"Unless it became simultaneously a practice of all firms", it is not felt that this difficulty could be overcome, but "the desire for complete frankness among the work people continues".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b45d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">In country districts there is still said to be a tendency to "treat the subject as hush-hush"; talk on such subjects is "not considered nice" and "among women, is definitely taboo".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b55d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">About regulation 33B itself opinion differs. On the whole, it is looked on as. a step in the right direction, but many "do not consider it sufficiently drastic".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b65d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">(3. 7. 12) hhh 10. The prospect of air raids on this country</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b75d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">Reference is again made to. an increasing belief that we shall have no more heavy raids here, "till Hitler gets desperate". Our defences are thought to be too good now. The invasion threat is described as "a more bogey".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b85d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">(4. 10. 11) hhh 11. Broadcasting and presentation of news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b95d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">Reports this week contain little reference to news presentation, and "interest in the war news is reported to have decreased, probably due to Christmas influences". There is praise for "the handling of the news from Tunisia by the B.B.C.: it is felt that the opportunity has been taken to give British propaganda what it has lacked - contemporaneous, broadcasting of the work of our Army. Gfrey Talbot's. "Christmas message describing small incidents in the life of the Eighth Army has been highly; praised as a remarkable piece of description, likely to give people with relatives in Libya an admirable and encouraging picture of their life".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ba5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">The summary at the end of the news bulletin is again praised.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bb5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">Christmas broadcasts: While there is approval for "the very appropriate and splendid Christmas messages from the various lenders", which "received the unstinted praise of people of various tastes", opinion differs on the merits of the other holiday programmes. Some listeners "expressed appreciation at the general high level", while others were dissatisfied and considered "their standard as well below that of last year", but the broadcast of the Christmas Eve carol service from King's College Chapel, "gave great pleasure".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bc5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">Favourable comment is reported about the European Service, "Into Battle", John Hilton's broadcasts, and "the increased speed at which Stuart Hibberd has read the news of late and. his more cheerful tone".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bd5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">Unfavourable comment is reported about "too. much American stuff", the excessive number of "serious programmes, talks and highbrow music", and "the pronunciations flavaured by women announcers". Alleged example of the latter are Mr. Cassey, and Chile to rhyme with "guile".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-be5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">Tommy Handley's programme is said to give enjoyment and its opposite - both intense -but enjoyment appears to predominate.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bf5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">(1.2.3.5.6.7.8.9.10; 32) hhh 12. Recent speeches and broadcasts</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c05d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">The King's broadcast (December 23) which "was expected and looked forward to as an established part of Christmas ceremonies", is said to have been "warmly appreciated," and to been regarded as "the best he has made". The King's "improved delivery" has been widely praised (Eight Regions) and has led to many expressions of pleasure: "His Majesty has never been more effective at the microphone". His "sincerity and concern for those in trouble is especially remarked", and he is praised for "putting into words what everyone is thinking", even if "no one considered that he gave forth any momentous news". Particular pleasure was expressed at the anecdote about the boy carrying his brother, and at the mention of Russia. The reference to India caused "interest and speculation", but the lack of reference to China disappointed some.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c15d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">Sir Stafford Grippe' postscript (December 20) has again been praise especially by workers. It is described as "a memorable broadcast" and is praised for "its vigour and forthrightness".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c25d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">The appeal'to the workers was appreciated, and considered to be "needed and timely". A group of workers are reported as saying: "Cripps should see what happens at our works, particularly on night shifts."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c35d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">Sir Norman Birkett's (Onlooker) Postscript (December 27) appears to have had a favourable but not enthusiastic reception. While most people seem to have liked it, there is some feeling that it was "too long and rather dull" and "not as good as his last".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c45d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">President Roosvelt's Christmas message is mentioned in reports from two Regions only. It is said to have given "pleasure, particularly on. Merseyside", but "the comment was made that it was a pity the Americans got in first". People who "thought that he had some very important message to send" were "annoyed that they should have been kept waiting for the news merely for an ordinary Christmas message".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c55d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">Mr. Casey's broadcast (December 22) does not so far seem to have produced much comment, though it is praised for having _"dispelled many wrong ideas about the Middle East".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c65d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c75d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="59">II. SPECIAL COMMENTS hhh 13. Christmas</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c85d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">All reports agree that Christmas has been the major pre Occupation of all but a very few; the general verdict seems to be that, "in spite of austerities, it was enjoyed as no other Christmas since war began" and was "pretty good, all things considered". It was welcomed "as a break in the monotony of going on and on", which "many feel to be one of the most trying features of civilian life in war time", and workers are said to have "benefitted from the break and to feel able to put their backs into things again".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c95d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">Many people made great efforts" to make it as much like the pre-war Christmas as possible", and are said to have been "amazed at the amount of enjoyment it was possible to get from an austerity Christmas". People are described as having been "ready to put up with stringent food supplies in view of the cheerful war news, realising that their short commons were a definite contribution to the turn of the tide".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ca5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">Other reported reactions are as follows:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cb5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">(a) Hope or belief that this will have been the last war Christmas at any rate so far as the war in Europe is concerned (Nine Regions and Postal Censorship).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cc5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">(b) "Many outspoken complaints about the high cost and poor quality of toys available" (Eight Regions and Postal Censor­ship). "Daylight robbery" is one of the descriptions used.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cd5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">(c) Pleasure at the ringing of the bells seems greatly to have outweighed indifference or dislike, especially in rural areas, where "it was lovely to hear them". (Four Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ce5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">(d) An "orgy of spending" is mentioned in two reports. "Shabbily dressed women without a word of complaint paying 12/6d. for very ordinary quality ties" is one of several examples quoted.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cf5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">(e) "Criticism that so many Shops remained shut on Monday, 28th December" (Two Regions). The prospect of getting "no fresh bread between Wednesday and Monday" is said to have led to "lots of people taking more than they needed for fear of running short or of any of it going mouldy".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d05d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">(f) "The number of Christmas cards sent", involving "waste of labour and paper" caused surprise and criticism (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d15d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">(g) Appreciation of the entertainments and parties for children given by Canadian and American troops (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d25d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">Some disappointment is, however, reported "over being let down by U.S. men who had accepted invitations for private hospitality but never turned up".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d35d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13. 21 Cambridge, Cardiff, Glasgow P.Cs.) hhh 14. Production</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d45d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">In spite of the benefits of the Christmas break, there is still some criticism of production. "Conscientous workers" in the Northern Region are said to feel that "production figures could be much increased", and in the Castle Bromwich Aero Works (Midland Region) , production is said to be "only 30% of what it might be - Sir Stafford Cripps should come and see for himself".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d55d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">Production is thought to be adversely affected by:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d65d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">(a) Workers's shopping difficulties (Four Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d75d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">(b) Absenteeism, and workers who "are not going all out". (Three Regions) In Scotland "a large number" of workers transferred to the Midlands are reported "to have come home for Christmas and to intend to stay home till after the New Year", in spite of threats of punishment. ,"Considerable dissatisfaction" is said to be felt amongst these transferred workers because Service personnel and evacuated Civil Servants are granted special leave but "the transferred worker, who is continually told that he is as important to the job of winning the war as the man or woman in the Forces, is considered lucky if he gets one week's leave (without pay) in the whole year, and at the Christmas and Whitsun breaks, everything possible is done to stop him travelling". Married men are said to be "particularly resentful", and a "good deal" of absenteeism is due to the practice of "slipping home for the weekend now and then". It is suggested that "if leave, (even an extended weekend) could be granted every ten or twelve weeks, workers would settle down with a better heart".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d85d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">(c) "Slackness" and "enforced idleness", stories of which are reported from the North Western Region and from the Austin Aero Works and Alders, Tamworth (Midland Region) and the Government dockyards at Falmouth.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d95d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">(d) Loss of working hours, said to be caused by (i) Workers attending outpatients departments of hospitals (Two Regions), and (ii) "Calls on business and work people to attend Tribunals on claims for exemption from Fire-watching duties, often at places a "considerable distance" from their work". (One Region) It is suggested that "the Government should organise a 'Save time' campaign to encourage appointments and rotas at places where people have to wait".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-da5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">Miners: Evidence that miners are "increasingly aware of the importance of their job" is reported from Scotland, and is confirmed by Postal Censorship. Extra shifts, Sunday work and "special production weeks as a tribute to the 51st. Division" are examples given; and miners in the Thorne area (North Eastern Region) are reported to have complained of the closing of the Pits by the management (according to custom) on 29th December. On the other hand, the continuation of the Cortonwood Colliery strike (North Eastern Region) is looked upon with "disgust" and is reported to be having "a bad effect" on fuel economy. (1.2.3.6.7.9.10.11. 21 Edinburgh P.C.) hhh15. Manpower</note>
				<note xml:id="q-db5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">Discussion about "the inefficient use, and the misuse of man and woman power" continues to be reported and is mentioned by eight Regions and in Postal Censorship this week. Criticism follows familiar lines:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">(a) Too many young men in civilian jobs, e.g.: "unskilled sheet metal work suitable for women and youths, being done by able bodied men". (Five Regions). Government plans for further weeding-out" are praised.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">(b) The number of "childless Married women" (especially soldiers' wives) who are not doing any war work, or only part-time work (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">(c) Skilled workers in unskilled work complaints that building workers "are being taken from skilled work and sent to Shuckburgh (Midland. Region) as labourers".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">(1.3.4.5.6.7.9.10. 21 Glasgow, Inverness. P.Cs.) hhh 16. Transport difficulties</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e05d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">There are references from ten Regions this week to transport difficulties. Complaints are again on familiar lines: (a) The curtailment of evening and Sunday morning transport; (b) Overcrowding of buses to the exclusion of workers; (c) Inadequate workers' transport facilities; (d) - The inadequacy of rural bus services; (e) Workers' buses running half empty and leaving queues standing at bus stops; (f) Crowding out of long distance passengers by short distance ones.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e15d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">Christmas travel: Travel in the Southern Region this year is said to have been on a smaller scale than last year, though some of the Great Western trains were very crowded. A minority in the South Western Region "aimed at a gay hotel holiday"; those spending Christmas in hotels included travellers, "not all of whom had good reasons for travelling". The only comment on the travelers who got stranded at Blackpool was: "Serves them right".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e25d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">(1.2.3.5.6.7.8.10.12.15. 21 Birmingham P.C.) hhh 17. Petrol</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e35d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">Eight Regions this week report complaints of the waste and misuse of petrol. The number of cars seen outside dance halls, whist drives, theatres, and the streams of traffic going to dog races and football matches, are unfavorably commented on.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e45d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">Special buses being run to pantomimes in Leeds and Harrogate are also criticised.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e55d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">Other criticisms are as follows:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e65d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">(i) Business Men driving high powered cars when alternative public transport is available (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e75d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">(ii) Waste of petrol by .American troops (One Region). The decision is remove taxi licences from former private cars is said to have met with approval in two Regions. It is particularly welcomed in. Slough where it is thought to have become a serious ramp.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e85d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">(1.2.3.4.6.7.10.11. 21 Inverness P.C.) hhh 18. Fuel Economy</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e95d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">There are fewer references this week to fuel economy. Only three reports make any mention of the campaign. People are thought to be doing well, though there is reported to be a tendency to regard unofficial or semi-official restrictions as the real cause for reduced consumption. The people who read the fuel advertisements are said to be already saving as much as they can.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ea5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">Complaints of the poor 'qua lit and high price of coal are reported from two Regions. In the North Midland Region a .contact has pointed out that "schools are being asked to burn coke but the fuel provided gives out no heat".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-eb5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">(3.6.8.10. 21 Bristol, (Cambridge, Inverness, Manchester P.Cs.) hhh 19. Clothing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ec5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">Children's clothing: The shortage of children's clothing, especially footwear, is reported from six Regions. The poor quality of the clothing is commented on in one Region.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ed5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">Household coupons: Housewives in Wales are said to be crying out for a few more coupons. People setting up now homes are said in the London Region to have difficulty as a result of household linen being on coupons, end the placing of towels on coupons is reported to be unpopular in the South Eastern Region.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ee5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">Utility stockings: The poor quality of utility stockings is complained of from three Regions. Wellington boots: The shortage of Wellington boots is thought to be a real hardship for people living country, especially children.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ef5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">(1.3.5.8.9.10.11.12. 21 Glasgow P.C.) hhh 19. Food</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f05d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">Satisfaction with the food situation and praise for Lord Woolton continue to be reported. Although there was some disappointment at the lack of any extras before Christmas,' praise is reported for the way the Christmas fare available was distributed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f15d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">The following complaints are, however, reported:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f25d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">Fish: The shortage of fish continues to be reported (Ten Regions) and the zoning scheme is still criticised. People are said to blame the fish trade for the failure to work the scheme (Two Regions). Restaurants and canteens are thought to receive more than their fair share of fish, and preferential treatment of customers by fishmongers is again alleged.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f35d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">Poultry: The alleged unequal distribution of turkeys is complained of in three Regions. Stories of racketeering are reported from three Regions, though in the North Western Region the turkey ramp is said to have been substantially reduced this year. Annoyance is reported from the London Region at shop-windows full of turkeys, all marked sold.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f45d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">Milk: The unequal distribution of milk (Three Regions). Eggs: The shortage of shell eggs (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f55d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">Amazement is reported from the Eastern Region that wine is to be imported. However, in the North Western Region, people are said to wonder "why so much song is made about it".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f65d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13. 16. 21 Aberdeen, Birmingham, Bristol, Cambridge, Carlisle, Edinburgh, Glasgow, Inverness, Leeds, Nottingham P.Cs.) hhh 20. Batteries</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f75d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">Complaints about the shortage of batteries appear to be on the increase, and are reported from ten Regions this week as against eight last week. While torch batteries are mentioned in every cases No. 8s are particularly referred to in four Regions, and cycle lamp batteries in five.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f85d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="108">(3.4.5.6.7.8.10.11.12.13. 21 Glasgow P.C.) hhh 21. Shopping difficulties</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f95d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="109">This week references to shopping difficulties come from six Regions and Postal Censorship. The main difficulty mentioned as being experienced by workers is the early evening and lunch hour closing of shops.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fa5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="110">"There has been some grumbling over Christmas shopping difficulties but, on the whole, conditions have been cheerfully accepted, the Board of Trade policy designed to restrict spending being considered eminently sound and wise".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fb5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="111">(2.5.6.10.13. 21 Manchester, Glasgow P.Cs.) hhh 22. Men discharged from the Services</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fc5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="112">Reports from four Regions during the last month have referred to "dissatisfaction with the treatment of men discharged from the Services as unfit". It is asked why, "after twenty years of experience and three more years of war, the Ministry of Pensions have not yet adequate machinery to deal with pensions claims of discharged members of the Forces". Talk Of hardship end unfairness is said to occur where a disability is not admitted to be due to Service causes, although the person concerned Was passed as AI on call-up. Another grievance is that, "during the period that en adjustment is being considered, nothing official is done to help the individual who is in difficulties". The treatment of the men discharged is described as "a bed omen for demobilisation".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fd5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="113">(3.5.7.10)</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>