<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Morale Report for the Period 18 to 25 April 1943</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-f7059d4b-a626-4a52-9e65-72e7ef74580e</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-84ab0633-901f-4a13-ab02-238738a185d4</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-b44d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">CONFIDENTIAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b54d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="2">OFFICE OF THE CHIEF BASE CENSOR</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b64d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">Base Censorship Detachment No.3</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b74d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="4">APO 512</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b84d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="5">26 April, 1943</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b94d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="6">Subject: Morale Report for the Period 18 to 25 April, 1943.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ba4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">To: Commanding General, NATOUSA, APO 512, U.S. Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bb4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">1. HEALTH: 95% of the letters read state or indicate that excellent health prevails in this area, and that troops are in better physical con­dition than heretofore. Patients in hospitals continue to refer to excell­ent care and treatment though complaining that transportation from forward areas is rough and painful. The prevalence of veneral disease is still being commented on. A few medical officers are quite concerned over the possibilities of epidemics during the coming warm weather. The following excerpts are from letters examined this past week:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bc4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">"I can truthfully say that I'm in better health and in better health and in better physical condition than I've ever been in in my life." (20th Air Depot Group, APO 528-3).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bd4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">". . .we have had very little sickness so far. Especially considering the men sleep on the ground or the tile floors. Most are in holes in the ground but quite accustomed." (727 By. Oper. Bn., APO 302).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-be4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">"Writing you and letting you know I'm feeling fine and in good shape." (4.32 CA Bn., APO 302).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bf4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">"The shoulder isn't bad honey, so don't worry: They oper­ated and removed the shell fragment. Was hit April 8 and reached here two days later. The worst part was the damn rough ride back out of the lines. I'm OK now and should be out of here in a couple more weeks. (58 Armd FA Bn., ADO ).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c04d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">"My radio operator is laid up with a veneral disease of which there is an abundance here." (320 B. Group, 443rd B. Sq., APO 520).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c14d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">"Wounds easily become infected here and there are lots of boils to treat for some reason." (1st Arm'd Div. APO 251).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c24d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">"The weather is starting to approach my former concept of African climate. I can foresee some real hot, muggy weather. Personally I can tolerate it, but the accompanying diseases it may bring can incapacitate whole armies with one big, mighty, decisive blow--no war machine in the world can be so deadly nor so ruthless--even mighty Hitler's, or Stalin's. The two big diseases in humble on that will take its share along with Hitler of the "flower" of our Army will be (1) Dysentery and (2) Malaria. Both conditions are too glibly passed over as easy to prevent by certain prophylactic and ordered control measures. When men are on the battle field, practically speaking these two diseases are extremely difficult to control. When Army circular letters spout out this and that measure, it makes me smile. I picture some fool behind a comfortable desk, so remotely from my problems as a Bn "Aid Man", that the measures so stated are much too impossible to exercise. In all these circulars they plead to me as a "Doctor" to help at all other times I'm considered an officer. What is particularly disgusting is their call to us in the name of "patriotism" and "the high standard of American Medicine."--You can now play the 'Stars and Stripes'. As a country doctor I had more facilities to investigate and control these diseases than the Army. I had a militant and genuinely interested Public Health Service at my disposal. These methods have been time tried by 1000's of doctors in practice, and yet the Army has failed to use them. Even suggestions and recommendations have been made to improve the inadequacy; but… An Epidemic will bring about the changes--but it will also be costly and involve loss of life. In these times human beings are worth so little." (Hq. Co. APO ).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c34d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">2. MAIL: That there is an improvement in the mail service is indicat­ed by the decrease in unfavorable comments. Less than 50% of the comments during the past week have been unfavorable. There have been many references to the speed with which the mail arrives, some of it taking less than 10 days. Now that "V" mail is being photographed, there are many comments of dissatisfaction, the majority of complaints being that the "V" mail limits the size of the letter. The following comments are typical.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c44d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">". . .the best part of it all, is that it took only about 10 or 12 days for the whole batch to get across. They surely have done something to the mail service between here and home that makes life a lot more bearable for this Yankee." (Civil Affairs Sect., APO 512).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c54d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">"I certainly have to hand it to the mail service--no matter where we are in these wild hills the mail gets here with very little delay." (Hq. 3rd Air Defense Wing, APO 525).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c64d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">"Mail is coming through fine. Every few days I get a few letters. (Med. Det., 1880 Ord. Bn., APO 302).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c74d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">"I should think that you would know our postal handicaps by now. Seriously though, our service is about a thousand per­cent up and I hope that yours is to." (XII Air Support Com APO 776).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c84d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">"Your letter of April let reached me on April 10 and believe you me that is some service, considering where I am. It is a long and difficult journey from us to an APO. I feel encouraged over the mail service." (Hq. 34th Div., APO 34.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c94d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">"Just got a cable you sent to London on Dec. 6th!! Also, on the same day, I got a letter you wrote on Feb. 24.th!!! This mail service makes one think of how nice it would be to be over in India--or maybe Siam." (34th Service Group, APO 762).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ca4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">"For some uncanny reason there have been several who have deemed it more advisable to forward my mail from my former station to my present station in another part of North Africa by way of the states so that there will be a mere matter of another six weeks or so tacked on to the ordinary time before I will have an opportunity to get caught up on the 'news'." (Signal Section, Force Hq., APO 512).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cb4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">"Plenty of room on the ships for clothes and food for the Arabs but not for our letters packages and food--this whole damned lend-lease proposition is a farce in the way they work it. Stuff is sold here cheaper than in the U.S." (6th Arm'd Inf., APO 251).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cc4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">"It seems funny when you think about this mail being 4. weeks old. It sure is good when it gets here, but the service they talk about in the magazines and newspapers in the States certainly isn't working out here." (12th A.F. APO 650).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cd4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">"We have been notified that V-mail is now the only type of mail that is guaranteed air mail. I think that it is a hell of a note when the Nation cannot provide adequate mail service for the men who are over here fighting and dying." (6th Armd Inf., APO 251).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ce4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">"They've told us that V-mail is the only kind of mail that will be flown back to the States. Personally I don't like it at all, either on the sending or receiving end. When I write a letter I like to write until I run out and then quit. With that damned V-mail, unless one has a typewriter, one can hardly get started before he is out of paper and has to stop. Exasperating! Even if one only has just a page to write the limitation still induces that confined feeling. I don't see why they should insist on V-mail here when they don't even have micro-film equipment as yet." (82nd Bomb Sq., 12th B.G., APO 785).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cf4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">"The V-mail you wrote Feb. 7th got here March 9th and the letter of same date got here April 19th but I would rather have the letters. I know that V mail is encouraged. I have talked with the general in charge of the army postal service and he is sold on V-mail but the soldier isn't. One now and then is OK." (Hq. 34th Div., APO 34.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d04d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">3. TRAINING: There are few comments on training, the majority of these are critical of the training received in the States. The following comments have been noted.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d14d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">"I am afraid that what we have missed most in our hectic train­ing is first: the development of a real discipline. There has been too much molly-coddling and evasion of the point. Respons­ibility for this rests fairly close to the roof. Secondly the vast majority of our new officers and many of our older ones have absolutely no sense of responsibility." (168th Inf., AFO 34).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d24d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">"And although I think Barksdale and its training program were, are, and always will be, way off the beam--I feel as though I am ready for combat." (320 Bomb Gr., APO 520).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d34d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">"They shouldn't let anyone in the States get to be more than a first lieutenant. As a major with a hell of a lot of knowledge that most of the lads didn't have, I'm practically worthless until I get some combat background. All of these kids popping loose over here ought to be reduced to shave tails. This goes for a lot of colonels also." (47th Bomb Gr., AAF, APO 762).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d44d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">4. EQUIPMENT: Over 90% of the references to equipment have been favorable. Comment from Air Corps personnel have consistently praised the "Spitfire", and many of the fliers prefer that ship. There has been some favorable references to our machine guns and artillery. The follow­ing comments are from letters examined:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d54d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">"It sure amazed me when I noticed the difference of the Amer­ican Soldier from the English, French, Italians and the rest. Our equipment and the way we handle it is so very far above there's no doubt in my mind who has the best army in the world. The mor­al here is very high and everyone think the world of us, even the Italian prisoners." (2004. Pipe Line Co. (Sep), APO 763).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d64d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">"Boy, I'm glad I'm flying 'Spitfires'--they are plenty good and one need not fear the Messerchmitt and Fock Wulf in them, if you fly with caution and keep alert." (4th Fighter Sq., 52nd Ftr. Gr., APO 525).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d74d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">"The Dutchmen are more afraid of our machine guns than any other weapon we have." (209 CA (AA) APO 700).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d84d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">"Nellie we are taking up everything right now but the equip­ment the men have on their backs and their blankets. They tell us we are not going to draw cotton clothing and that will leave them with one set of woolens. Where we are going or what will happen to us no one knows." (168th Inf. A10 34).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d94d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">"We are very well taken care of though. We have the best of equipment, and never once that I can remember have I gone hungry or been cold through lack of warm clothes. We also have the best in weapons and beaucoup ammunition and so forth. In spite of the fact that we are in a filthy country where sanitation is unheard of, our health is excellent." (175th FA).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-da4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">5. RATIONS: Approximately 80% of references to rations are favorable, the most consistent complaint being lack of fresh meat, and lack of variety. There was one comment on German rations which may be of interest. In some units there is still a feeling of discontent over the shortage of PX sup­plies. The following comments are typical.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-db4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">"Just to make you jealous, I'll tell you what I had for breakfast this morning. Breakfast is always our best meal and our cooks do a wonderful jab under conditions you cannot possibly imagine." (84th FA Bn., APO 9).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">"We had fresh meat last night. The mess officers had it barbecued and boy was it good." (321 Bomb Gr.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">"But we do very well over here and have no need to complain." (412 Signal Co., AMU, APO 650).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">"A few days ago they took all the E.M. away from the officers mess and installed French waiters. The head waiter was formerly the head waiter on the Normandy, he acts the part but it is rather hard to complete the picture on "C" rations. The addition of a bottle of wine helps him complete the former atmosphere however. We generally eat well over here, much better than the civilians back in the states. I understand now that we are on American rations instead of British, we rather enjoy the meals." (G-4 Sec. Force Hq., APO 512).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">"Are you really interested in our food? Today at noon we had salmon croquettes, spinach, hominy, lemonade (artificial) bread and peanut butter. The other day the officers bought a couple of tough bulls, and for two days we had steak, hamburger and meatloaf. Usually everything comes out of cans, except pan­cakes for breakfast occasionally." (310th Bomb Grp. APO 520).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e04d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">"The food is pretty good now if you want to call it that. It's still all canned. I never want to see another can of spam as long as I live. Leave it to the Americans to overdo things. In the last war it was beans. This time it's spam." (16th Troop carrier SO., APO 650).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e14d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">"We do enjoy reading some of the adds that come out at home though in the magazines. One good one tells all about the wonder­ful butter that some mfgr. developed for the army that wouldn't melt in the hottest African sun and kept so well. Well he is right about it not melting, also about the damn stuff not spoil­ing or rather keeping so long. The reason it keeps so long is because no one will eat it. It's so full of preservation or wax that it is about like eating wax with oil, spam is swell stuff but not three times a day. Another joke is the fresh beef quest­ion. When we first got over here we were told we couldn't have it because it all went to the troops at the front. Well the closer you get to the front the less you see of it. In fact we have had none since we have been up here." (G-3 Sec., Hq. 9th Inf. Div.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e24d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">"The only thing I can't possibly stand is the food here. It's the most sorry food that I have ever tried to eat or ever hope to put in my mouth. I very seldom eat a meal here. Most of us are buying eggs and fruit from the natives and are making out okay. It isn't the best diet in the world but we get along on it," (97 Bomb Grp. APO 520).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e34d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">"The other day we got hold of some German rations, which they abandoned when they ran off, and it sure was lots better than ours. Of course, a good deal of it came from the occupied countries, as indicated by the labels on the cans." (6th Armd Inf., APO 251).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e44d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">"Things like cigars and candy are mostly out with us, for they have to be saved for you jerks back home. I suppose that you get what you want at the PX. You should see our PX. You're lucky if you can get shoo gum here." (379 Bomb Sq. APO 520).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e54d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">6. ENTERTAINMENT: All comments on this subject have been favorable. The system of routing motion picture shows, bands and entertainers to various units is being received with much enthusiasm. Comments on the special service section, and especially of the Red Cross have been except­ionally praiseworthy. The following are some of the comments that have been noted.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e64d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">"The shows we have had here are all good and there are a good many of them." (III Air Service Area Command, APO 528).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e74d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">"Wish you were here tonight. They have a visiting band here and they are playing a short ways up the way. . . I guess we can't complain over here because we have a show about once a week and a band every .Friday." (310 Bomb Grp., APO 520).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e84d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">"Right now they are playing a band outside. Oh! Yes! We get some entertainment, and occasionally we get movies, so you see we don't do so badly." (379 Bomb Sqdn., APO 520).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e94d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">"It is getting better over here all the time. We do have lots of fun when we get to town. We see shows now not so new though." (02 CA Bn., APO 302).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ea4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">"The best entertainment and recreation for the boys overseas are radios and special service movies which are shown from unit to unit. Last night we invited 100 boys of the 713th Op. Bn. to our Co. and we saw the movie "Wake Island." Included were a news reel and an added subject. The Special Service operator played recordings of the well-known dance bands. You should have seen the boys in the courtyard jitterbugging with one another. All enjoyed the program thoroughly." (703rd Ry. Grand Div., APO 529).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-eb4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">"I haven't run across a Red Cross Club yet that wasn't a success. My thanks and congratulations and the thanks of an officer for the wonderful way in which the A.R.C. takes care of the social and personal affairs of our G.I.'s." (751 Tank Bn., APO 302).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ec4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">"The Red Cross have started serving us donuts and coffee when we come back from flying. The Red Cross is really doing a swell job over here. They put on good movies for us set up day rooms for the enlisted men with radios, games, food and other entertainments and in big towns have service clubs where the men can eat and sleep and have a place to hang out. With the few workers over here at present they can't be praised too highly." (34.2 Bomb Sq., APO 52A).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ed4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">7. SPORTS: It is evident that athletic activities are being fostered in many units where they receive favorable response. The sports that seem to predominate are baseball, soft ball and volley ball. All comments on sports have been favorable.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ee4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">"We have a very good softball team here in the company and have played quite a few games." (244 QM Bn.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ef4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">"I have been getting a little exercise these days. We had a baseball tournament and I am patching for the Hq. team. We were beaten in the Semi-finals, but we did have a lot of fun." (310 Bomber Grp. APO 520).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f04d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">8. LEAVE: References to going back to the States at the completion of the African campaign continue to prevail in the theatre as shown by the following comments:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f14d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">"It's OVER and I'm OK--It's OVER! The African campaign is over for us, darling! Our job is done. . .As for my coming home now that our job here is finished, we should know for sure about this before the end of this month. It does seem quite likely that we shall, however. Perhaps I'll be walking in on you within two weeks or so after you get this! I pray so !!!" (135 Inf. APO 34).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f24d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">"Read in the Stars and Stripes that all American troops would return to the States after this African battle, which shouldn't be very long." (813th T. D. Bn., APO 302).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f34d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">9. QUARTERS: There has been very little reference to quarters this week. It has been noted that there is some discontent, presumably by civilian personnel at the possibility of their having to pay for quarters:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f44d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">"Fantastically difficult to find anything (censor: living quarters) and hanging over our heads is the vague possibility of having to pay for army billets. . .nevertheless something must be done if we are not to go on living like cattle." (PWB, APO 512).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f54d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">10. POLITICS: No comment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f64d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">11. NEWS AND PROPAGANDA: All comments on news reports by radio have been favorable though there is some complaint in the lack of home town papers. References to radio broadcasts from Axis countries continue to ridicule their propaganda. One comment that may be of interest pertains to a prisoner of war in Japan who evidently was permitted to broadcast his safety with the provision that he discourage his son, an American army officer, from going overseas. Comments are as follows:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f74d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">"Would certainly like to see a home town paper about now to catch up on the news. About the only reports we get are B.B.C. reports in the evening from London, and those we get sound fine." (135th Inf., APO 34).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f84d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">"I just finished listening to the program from Germany. It's called "The Axis Kids, Pete and Sally". I have never heard such propaganda in my life. If they think for one minute they're putting ideas in my head they're wasting their time. I could get great pleasure in shooting then (Pete and Sally) down like dogs." (20th Air Depot Gr., APO 528).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f94d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">"You will be relieved to hear that Dad is listed as a live prisoner of war at Taiwan, c/o The Red Cross, Tokyo, Japan, In addition heard him talk. . by short wave from Japan. . .Made me feel guilty though when he asked me not to volunteer for overseas duty." (1979 QM Trk Co., APO 528).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fa4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">12. CHURCH AN!) RELIGION: 95% of the comments indicate that the Amer­ican soldier retains his faith in religion. Letters indicate that many, who have not followed their religious training in the past, have now come back to it. The following comments were noted.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fb4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">"I just got of back from church pretty good- -AYE. But it doesn't take long to learn that there's no atheists riding in airplanes not on this side of the pond. One realizes more every day that there is someone up above looking after you and he really has been doing a good job." (414th Bomb Sq., Ai) 520).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fc4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">"Keep on praying darling for that return, though I'm not an expert I find it helps--Truly there is no place for an atheist over here whether in the air or in a trench." (APO 520).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fd4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">"Religion hasn't helped many of our boys over here. As a matter of fact those that more or less ignore it have shown up best all the way round." (109 Eng. Bn., APO 54).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fe4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">13. HOME AFFAIRS: Letters continue to refer to strikes and labor trouble in the States in no uncertain terms and indications are that the American soldier is much concerned in such matters. Advice against join­ing the WAACs or similar organizations are still noted in letters. The following comments are typical.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ff4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">"The days and nights of constant flirting with death nearly dive me crazy though. Too bad a lot of our union leaders and workers in plants at home couldn't be brought over here for a few weeks of it. The loafing on the jobs, the strikes, the wasting of valuable time would immediately cease. If they only knew how many more lives they are costing because of lack of proper equipment ETC. such laggardism would cease. A few bombs dropped at home would help a lot in the opinion of most of us. It makes me bitter when you see a man's head shot off, or another's arm fly 30 feet in the air or another's body blown to bits as I have seen and at home they have to beg them to stay on the job or pay three times what they are worth. And you have to join a union in order to work and pay dues whether you want to or not. What a racket, I wonder what we are fighting for sometimes." (9th Inf. Div., APO 9).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-004e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">"One of the fellows just got a copy of the time magazine--and it gives the story of the Boeing factory going out on strike--the dirty no good bastards--and that's mild. They should draft every one of the sons of bitches and send them to Guadacanal or out here in Africa--what the hell kind of country am I fighting for anyway? Why don't those people who don't like their "working conditions" or "wage scales" come out here and look at ours--if you're to be paid by the amount of effort you put out--there isn't enough money in the U.S. to pay off the kid who gets a German flame-thrower in his face--or a tank cutting him in two or the crew of a ship diving in to hit nose on at 400 miles an hour. What type of stinker do we have exempted from the draft to draw fabulous wages in defense industry and then stop producing even for one minute the stuff that keeps us alive out here? I hear that Eddie Rickenbacker told them off once and got nailed for it--they ought to give 'Rick' a medal and a good platoon of combat men and the job of working over those snotnosed leeches in 'defense work. How can you expect us to do the job of dying like men for democracy if that democracy operates at home like an old maid try­ing to mother a dead end kid?" (XII Bomber Command, APO 520).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-014e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">"Since I have been up I have seen some fireworks. And I'm glad of it. People back home don't seem to realize a war is on it seems. Arguing about little petty things that sometimes don't amount to a hill of beans. Up front it is different. Almost everyone cooperates with each other." (1979 QM Co. APO 528).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-024e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">"From your letters I see that you are very busy with your work-­a work of great importance in the war effort. Sailors and soldiers have to be clothed, and you are helping to do this, and I can well understand your interest in your work. In this great struggle which engulfs the entire world, every worthwhile person is doing and wants to do his part. Who knows better than I, that our enemy is a brutal one, who would have the greater part of the world under his hell if he could." (1st Eng. Bn., APO 1).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-034e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">"And this stuff you have been mentioning about the WAACs is really funny to worry about. If there is one thing I will not allow is that. I and most of the boys over here consider them quite the laughing stock of the Nation and all of us think they stink." (355th CA Bn., APO 700).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-044e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">"Now don't go joining the WAACa or you'll be in for a 'whack' from yours truly." (13th A.R., APO 251).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-054e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">14. RELATIONS WITH THE CIVILIAN POPULATION: The relations between our forces and the local inhabitants continue to be friendly as shown by 95% of the comments.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-064e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">"I like the French people, of whom there are lots--both natives and exiles--very much. They're appreciative, friendly, jolly, well dressed--even though almost in rags in some cases--and even cleaner than some people I could name. They also know how to cook when there's anything around to practice on." (Force 141, APO 512).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-074e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">"Last Monday I was invited by some Spanish people to dine with them. It was a very nice meal. People here are very fine, especially the Spanish-speaking people who treat me wonderfully because I speak Spanish." (3487th Ord. Co., APO 512).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-084e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">"Yes I did go out with some of the French dames and boy what a time I had." (1st General Depot, APO 698).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-094e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">"As for the French girls I have left them strictly alone. Hope I have something better to look forward to." (5th Armd Arty., APO 502).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0a4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">15. RELATIONS WITH THE ALLIED TROOPS: All references to the allied troops are favorable. The American soldier has the utmost respect and feel­ing of friendliness for the British soldier. Many writers state that their opinion of the British has radically changed since they have come in contact with him. Expressions from British and French troops whose mail passes through this office also reflects the favorable relationships between the different forces. The following are only a few of the comments that have been noted.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0b4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">"There is, however, one statement that I want to go on record now and it concerns the British officers and soldiers. The adverse criticism that is heard in the States of the English soldiers is pure Axis bull. I have met hundreds of them personally and they are fine fellows, excellent soldiers and first class fighting men. The only trouble is that there is not enough of them. In the past the enemy had them outnumbered. It is certainly gratifying to see our men and the English getting along so well together. They are real comrades-in-arms. With great respect for each other's good qualities. . . . every last private who has come in contact with the British troops will tell you the same thing." (753rd Ry. Shop Bn., APO 700).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0c4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">"The English armies are wonderful and they know their business and can really use everything they have and we have given them. The 1st and 8th Army are on the ball and Montgomery and Alexander are really men of the battle." (1st Engr. Bn., APO 1).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0d4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">"I myself, am very proud to work with the British Army they are a real bunch of good fellows and hard fighters--and it is my personal belief that we two can whip the daylights out of the Hun--yes sir!! The British and American armies can't be stopped." (813 TD Bn., APO 302).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0e4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">"I don't care what one says about the British, the Tommy over here is all right for my money and I think that every American that has had contact with them over here feels the same way. They work like hell, have very little and make damn good soldiers and there seems to be no limit to the length he will go out of his way to help the American and the boys at the front say he is a damn tough fighter. (310 Service Gp. APO 762).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0f4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">"If anybody tells you that the British and Americans don't get along--they're crazy. We may not agree on a few things but its sure been a mutual feeling of respect and being damn glad to see each other over here." (1st Armd Regt. APO 251).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-104e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">"The news from the other parts of the field has been good as old man Montgomery seems to have Rommel on the run for sure this time and personally he can keep right on the job. He's the best man there is for my money. I'll be quite frank with you and say that when I was back in England I didn't have such a good opinion of the English, but when you fight with them, and next to them, they are really all right. They can surely fight, and they can take it, much better sometimes, I think than we." (135th Inf., APO 34).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-114e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">"My hat is off to the British Army. They are real fighting men and I doubt that we could have done what they have done." (Hq Div. Arty., APO 34).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-124e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">"And let me tell you, the British are no slouches either. A better bunch of fellows I've never seen. They're really tops with all of us. The Tommies and Yanks get along like brothers. (AT Co. 135th Inf., APO 34).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-134e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">"There is profound admiration for the British in the old gang, since we have seen them in operation. They've really got what it takes, and I believe that everyone here would take off their hats to them. (Hq. 2nd Bn., APO 34.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-144e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">"I don't know whether you notice that I am using a lot of American expressions in my letters to you but I'm mixing with the Yanks all day and I guess I can't help talking like they do. They are a hell of a good bunch of lads and we get on very well." (7 A.A. S.C., APO 330).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-154e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">"We have some exceptionally delightful Americans to work with. They are really charming. The tripe that people talk about Americans-­I've met dozens and haven't encountered a loud one yet although I'm not saying they don't exist. You should hear them talk about the Eighth Army and our performance generally in this war. It makes one glow with pleasure." (B.N.A.F.). (letter is written by a French soldier attached to the U.S. Army).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-164e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">"I can tell you at once that Americans are very congenial and that they did not come with empty hands. Their food, for instance, is not levied in Africa. Quite the opposite, they are bringing quite large quantities of provisions for the civilian population." (no address given).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-174e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">16. CENSORSHIP: During the past week a total of 17 Form 912's for censorship violations were sent out, 12 of which were on officers, 3 on enlisted men, and 2 on civilians attached to the army. In addition there were also 319 pieces of mail returned for violations that did not warrant a Form 912. Most of these were due to local money being sent to the States, for sending postcards with geographical locations printed thereon, and for violations of regulations on the use of blue envelopes. Comments on censor­ship are 90% unfavorable. Military personnel consider the censorship reg­ulations too severe, and complain that it limits them in writing interest­ing letters. There are also comments about the censors holding and delay­ing mail. The records will show that mail is not held up over 24 hours for censorship purposes. References in a few units indicate that the new cen­sorship regulations have not been described to them. A few writers, mostly officers, intimate that they have prearranged codes. The mail of such is being watched very carefully. The following comments were noted.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-184e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">"Was in a swell town yesterday and wish the censors were not so peculiar--so that I could write about it. The papers tell all about the town, as far as the fighting is concerned but I am not allowed to tell of my being there! Funny stuff, this Army--isn't it, Mr. Censor?" (Hq. II Corps, APO 302).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-194e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">"As the censor gets stricter and stricter I am afraid my letters will get duller and duller until I am reduced to describing only the food and the sunshine." (149 WAAC Post BA., APO 512).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1a4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">"There is so little to write--censorship is very strict and I certainly don't want to violate it in any way." (73rd Sta. Hosp, APO 700).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1b4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">"We have a batch of new censorship rules that makes it next to impossible to write an interesting letter." (APO 528).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1c4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">"If you were to read the letter, you would never realize that it contained military information and it was not until the Censor pointed out to me what was wrong with it, that I realized. It's really wonderful how they can piece together a letter and get so much out of it." (Hq. Sq., 5th Wing (US) APO 520).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1d4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">"The other about Censorship was published in Yank Magazine. True enough, too, but very necessary, it Should be more strict. Would be very interested to know who the fellows are that paint such beautiful word pictures and tell you all so much." (209 CA (AA), APO 700).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1e4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">"I think a lot of our mail is being delayed on account of very poor handling by Chief Base Censor--everyone has the same trouble but such is the Army." (713 Ry. Op. Bn., APO 763).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1f4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="108">"That reminds me, you said something about British mail getting here in only two weeks. That's really swell but some of your letters are in the Censor's office nearly that long. No foolin', its true and it makes me burn. I'm all for censorship because it is necessary but when it means that much of a delay, I think it's pretty bad. Here's one dated March 25th and postmarked April 8, another dated April 1, postmarked April 11th. I'll be damned if that doesn't go against the grain." (34th C.A. Brigade (AA), APO 529).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-204e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="109">"Honey you keep on saying you're not getting letters from me. I can't understand it unless they are being held up by the Censors. I write every other day." (2nd. Sig. Co., AR) 528).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-214e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="110">"I can't seem to get hold of a copy of the censorship regs for intra theatre correspondence, but I imagine they are amply ridiculous." (321 Bomb Gp., APO 520).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-224e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="111">"Darling, until I tell you different, there isn't any use in using the plan we talked of about writing in because I have told you every bit throu repition if you know what I mean, as I could have that way. What I have kept repeating is supposed to be OK with the spot check censors, but if there comes a time when I can't say something in that manner, then I will use our plan. I will let you know when I am using it though. Please let me know if any of my letters happen to be spot-checked and anything is cut out." (312th Ord. Bn., APO 700).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-234e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="112">17. GENERAL COMPLAINTS: About 5% of the mail examined contain complaints of a general nature. Complaints of non-receipt of allotments and safe arrival cards being most consistent. Other complaints prominent this week include (1) lack of promotions, (2) individual dislike or lack of faith in superior officers, (3) the employment of the same units in the campaign and (4) inactivity.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-244e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="113">"I can't understand why Max didn't get that allotment yet I am going to try and find out why if I can." (2639 QM Truck Bn., APO 763).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-254e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="114">"Wish I knew a Newspaper reporter or two. A write-up in the papers about the soldiers overseas not receiving any allotments, after the soldier had made out one, and in some instances like mine for a period of eight months, would not look so good, But I can't write anything like that to the papers nor can I write to a Congressman for assistance, but the parents of the selectees can write to the Congressman because their sons don't get mail within the time they think they should." (1st Armd Div. APO 251).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-264e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="115">"Please keep check on my allotment and let me know if on April 1st a check for $175.00 was sent." (30th Inf. APO 3).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-274e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="116">"I guess they have them pretty well messed up and the men do not like it so very well. It is difficult to persuade them to buy bonds." (899th TD Bn., APO 302).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-284e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="117">"I filled out several cards that were to be mailed when we arrived here. They were supposed to announce my safe arrival and give my address. Evidently they weren't mailed because you never got it and Aunt Anne in Chicago never got the one I filled out for her. I sent one to Sam also but I don't know if he got his or not." (321st, Bomb Group, APO 520).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-294e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="118">"Guess you are getting tired of hearing me gripe all the time but it just isn't fair. Clark Gable is now a Capt. in the Air Corps. he was in the class after me. I just can't figure it out. The boys in the States are surely riding the gravy train, while we are sweating it out over here. There is liable to be a rebellion if something isn't done for the boys over here who are doing the dirty work and not getting the promotions." (81st Ftr. Gp. 93rd Ftr. Sq., APO 762).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="119">"Sometime I wish I was in the navy I might get some place." (87 Ord. Co. APO 668). "So many of the brass hats seem to be concerned with promotions to the extent that the fellow who is really carrying the load is often not thought of." (Provost Marshall Gen. Office, APO 512).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="120">"I wish they would give these other people a chance to fight this war instead of using one division." (26th Inf. APO 1).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2c4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="121">"If I were in a complaining mood, there are plenty of other more important things that I could kick about, but I won't. I'll only say that the proud records of American Generalship, that was inaugurated in the Civil War, is certainly continuing. I think I'll be a Republi­can from now on." (6th Armd Inf., APO 251).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="122">"This business is OK for a little while, BUT IT gets old after so long. It seems though that the big boys sitting around the H.Q. offices have determined that the pilots of this day and age can stand a lot more than they once thought they could. This is a very grave mistake though believe me." (12th Bomb Grp., APO 785).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="123">"There seems to be a mistaken idea that there is nobody else in this G.D. army and war except the good old and tired 26 inf. That is not censorable. Before we moved in one of the officers expressed the same opinion in the presence of members of the staff. They only glared." (26 Inf., APO ).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="124">"I wish the U.S. Army would find out it has 5,000,000 other soldiers to play around with. It seems he is using about 3 divisions, one of these three divisions all the time to do everything an army should be doing." (1st Engr. Bn., APO 1).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-304e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="125">"It makes me so mad to know that we are sitting here doing absolutely nothing. It isn't just that I want to see tragic and horrible things- my curiosity is not that morbid, but if there are such conditions, we want to work also. If I thought that I could do any better by transferring, I surely would, but my fate would probably be another do-nothing unit, and then I would really give up in despair. I'm so damned disgusted today, that I hate everyone, even myself. Do you mind my ranting? I can't somehow write to my friends at home about it. They try to sacrifice cheerfully to help us overseas, and its rather difficult to let them know that we are hardly worth it. I try to tell myself that it's like a dream that's been broken. Most of us had such illusions of the services we were going to do and it hurts, awfully, to admit to ourselves that we are taking it easy, when others are doing the work. (26th Gen. Hosp., APO 700).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-314e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="126">"This place is becoming very dull and sure wish that we could move on somewhere or do something different for a change." (85th QM Co., APO 302).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-324e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="127">l8. GENERAL: Though over 95 of the references show a very high moral, it is to be noted that comments now are being made to the effect that some writers are dissatisfied and want to be finished with the war. There have been an increasing number of uncomplimentary remarks about the WAACs in this theater, and there are comments written by a WAAC officer indicating that such remarks have gotten to the States. References to Axis personnel con­tinue to indicate that the Italians are eager to surrender, and also an example of apparent sabotage in German munition factories.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-334e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="128">"The morale of everyone is excellent and there are no words which can adequately describe the magnificent work which is being done by all." (20th Air Depot Gr., APO 528).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-344e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="129">"The army is mine from now on out if I have anything to say about it. You will never see me join a union or go into a factory or die of starvation." (68 Armd. PA Bn., APO 251).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-354e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="130">"We have been strafed and bombed, but the Luftwaffe is a weak sister. Their bombs do more ploughing of Arab fields than anything else. There are more cases in the hospital from Jeep accidents than from anything else. The boys here are shooting them down 3 and 4. to 1 all the time," (82 Fighter Control Sect., APO 525).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-364e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="131">"In the past I haven't had personal hatred for the Jerries, but rather a feeling that it was soldiers against soldiers in which each was fighting for what he thought was right. Within the past couple of weeks however I have received a couple of blows that have embittered me. Day before yesterday I lost a very close friend and a loyal follower. If I ever get the opportunities--and I will--I intend to get plenty of revenge for that blow." (18th Inf., APO 1).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-374e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="132">"I know one thing for sure if I am away from you for another year, when I come back home I won't be normal, and you can write to your Congressman about that. And come to think of it, it wouldn't be such a bad idea if a lot of people wrote in and let it be known that they are fed up on this war business, and when I say business it seems to me and looks as if it is starting to be just that. Here, of late I have been reading some of the papers from the States, and the profits the manufacturers are making, I tell you I boil inside. This damn thing has gone far enough and it is up to the people at home to do a little hollering, and end this damn war." (2625 Sig. Ser. Reg., APO 512).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-384e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="133">"If this war don't end soon I'll go crazy." (1st Gen. Depot, APO 698).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-394e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="134">"Thus far I have been on twelve raids and the sooner this is over the better I will like it. I do navigating and bombarding and I have never in my life felt so damned naked as I do when sitting in the greenhouse and Jerry is throwing all manure of stuff at us." (12 Bomb Grp., APO 785).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3a4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="135">"I overheard some conversation by a noisy group of them (WAACs) and their opinions in general seem to be that they wish to hell they were home where they belong. I wish for their sakes (and the army's too) that they were." (68th CA (AA), APO 668).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3b4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="136">"I am sure you will be able to control the publicity so it won't be as bad as ours. We have just heard that one of our company has broadcast from a hospital in the States about her experiences on the war over. I hope you didn't hear her. Cannot imagine why she was allowed to speak. We tried to leave her behind as 'unfit for overseas duty' but were overruled. All in all we seem to be getting some pretty mean digs on all sides and families are writing that they hear we are to be sent home for bad behaviour. Considering how these girls are working and how well they are behaving under the most trying circumst­ances it is a little hard to take. Some of the stories about them come straight from Berlin." (149 WRAC Post Hq., APO 512).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3c4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="137">"Yesterday I questioned two Italian prisoners, of the thousands which we have taken. The Italians don't want to go on fighting. They call to us and when we approach them they come out with their hands up. For example, one of our trucks was filled with Italians when it roiled into a ditch. The American soldiers left to get help. These Italians, without any guard, started working on the truck, and after about a half hour, here came the truck, driven by a prisoner. They were all singing like crazy men. We never have to put them under guard, because we couldn't even drive them away by force. The Americans couldn't lose this war--they are too good. An Italian officer, from Rome, told me, 'Mussolini is a brigant who should have been assassin­ated.' I asked him 'Do you get along with the Germans ' - he replied-'How could we get along with those bastards? They want everything for them­selves and don't give us anything to eat! Most of these Italians are Bersaglieri." (examiner's note- Bersaglieri- an Italian armored force). (6th Arend Inf., APO 251).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3d4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="138">"Some time ago we took a lot of Italian prisoners and they said they were fed up with this war. The Italians are in a bad way, but believe me I don't sympathize with them at all. They can't believe that an American can speak Italian better than an Italian. I told them that I was glad that my parents knew enough to leave Italy years ago." (translation from Italian). (R.C.N. Co., 13th A.R., APO ).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3e4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="139">"Lately we have seen many prisoners both German and Italian. They are a sorry looking bunch of men. The Italians are friendly and seem happy about their capture. On the other hand, the Germans are arrogant and quite disillusioned. One officer in particular stood out above the rest. He marched with his head high, shoulders back, and eyes to the front. He was a fine looking soldier, and drew much comment from the onlookers." (36 Engrs., APO 698).</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>