<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Report on Berlin Morale No. 33 - second half of November 1948</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-97cf6ca4-854c-47f5-abc5-b842e1fdc908</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-53510e35-1566-41be-a90b-9b8a48d85d6c</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-ab5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="1">Public Opinion Research Office</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ac5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="2">Political Division</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ad5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">Lancaster House</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ae5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="4">HQ CCG (BE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-af5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="5">Berlin</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b05188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="6">B.A.O.R.2</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b15188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="7">3 Dec 48</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b25188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="8">To: Public Opinion Research Office</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b35188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="9">Political Division</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b45188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="10">229 HQ CCG</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b55188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="11">Hannover</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b65188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="12">Subject: Berlin Morale Report No.33</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b75188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">Attached is a report on Berlin Morale No.33 for the second half of November.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b85188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">Readers are asked to remember that although this report is compiled as objectively as possible, opinions expressed may often seem critical and captious. This is because so-called "opinion formers" among the German population may often be ill informed. PORO is not responsible for the views of the German population but to concerned only with the accuracy of the reporting.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b95188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="15">J.E.Dixon</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ba5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="16">P.O.R.O</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bb5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="17">Pol.Div.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bc5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="18">HQ COG (BE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bd5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="19">B.A.O.R.2</note>
				<note xml:id="q-be5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">CONFIDENTIAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bf5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="21">Public Opinion Research Office</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c05188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="22">Political Division</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c15188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="23">Lancaster House</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c25188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="24">HQ CCG (BE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c35188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="25">Berlin</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c45188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="26">Report on Berlin Morale No. 33. (Second Half of November).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c55188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">1. General Atmosphere and Morale</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c65188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">Morale in Berlin is at present suffering from the failure of UNO to settle the Berlin crisis and also the coming winter.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c75188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">There is little belief that a peaceful solution of the Berlin crisis will be achieved and the opinion is gaining ground that war in the Spring is inevitable.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c85188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">Since Marshal Sokolovski ordered that uniform identity cards be issued for the Russian Zone and the Russian Sector of Berlin the situation has be­come more tense. This measure is regarded as proof of the imminent and "final" isolation of the Western Sectors. Those Berliners who live in the West and work in the East or vice versa fear that they will soon be unable to go their place of employment and thus join the ranks of the unemployed. The reports published in the Western Berlin press regarding recent removal of S-Bahn rolling stock, rails and repair materials etc., from the Western Sectors to the Russian Sector have added to the general nervousness. The cessation of S-Bahn traffic is expected, though it is generally believed to be impossible that a city such as Berlin can effectively be split into two. On the other hand, it is feared that the SMA will attempt such a split if they think it advantageous irrespective of the disadvantages for the Berlin population. Berliners are asking "That will happen next? and how is it all going to end?".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c95188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">Apart from political anxieties, the problems of winter are the main preoccupation of Berliners, In spite of the efforts of the air-lift, it is believed that "catastrophic" conditions will be unavoidable and the people look towards the winter with considerable anxiety. In spite of distress, anxiety and difficulties, the morale of the Western Berliners remains comparatively firm, and the majority say they are resolved to accept any hardships if it will ensure a future fro from communistic principles. hhh 2. Politics</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ca5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">The coming Berlin elections, which will take place on 5th December, have placed the political parties more in the limelight. The majority of the Western Berliners are likely to go to the poll, not because they agree with the aims of any party, but rather to demonstrate their anti-Communist feelings. A poll of over 80% is likely in which the SPD will probably achieve an overwhelming majority because of its particularly anti-Communist attitude. On the other hand, a considerable number of electors who voted for the SPD at the last elections in October, 1946 have voiced disappoint­ment about the attitude the SPD has taken towards various local affairs, such, as school reform. For that reason the CDU and particularly the LOP may obtain a large increase in votes. Many Berliners criticise a "waste of paper" far election propaganda. They are of the opinion that a "campaign" is unnecessary and this paper could be put to a more useful purpose. hhh 3. Domestic Fuel, Power and Gas</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cb5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">The problem of domestic fuel ranks topmost among the worries of the population. The majority of Berliners think it impossible to supply the Western Sectors of Berlin with enough fuel via the air-lift. This, they say, is borne out by the announcement that only 25 lbs of coal for each household is to be allocated and that briquettes mode of coal dust, tar and sawdust (Branda blocks) will be issued. Hardly anyone has domestic fuel reserves and the majority of Berlin apartments was unheated throughout November.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cc5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">The electricity and gas quotas are still described as inadequate and many still find it difficult to cook one warm meal per day.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cd5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">Berlin transport is thought to be unable to cope with winter requirements and if the cessation of S-Bahn traffic becomes a reality, a transport crisis is expected.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ce5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">Candles and lamp oil can be obtained in most chandlers but only at Black Market prices. They are beyond the reach of the majority of the Working class and Berliners demand that these be controlled at fair prices. hhh 4. Food Position</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cf5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">The food situation has improved during the month of November and rations have been met in full. There have, however, been occasional delays in the issue of egg powder and smoked fish, which resulted in useless queuing for housewives. On the whole it is agreed that any different method in the distribution of tinned foodstuffs (tinned meats, dried potatoes, dried vegetables, dried milk etc.) is not practicable but housewives still complain they are unable to give their families a varied diet. It is believed that the lack of fresh potatoes will soon have a detrimental effect, since the dried potatoes issued in lieu, are claimed to be of poor quality. Complaints are also made about cereals, fats and powdered milk and many think that skimmed milk powder should be replaced with tinned full-cream milk-powder, margarine with butter and maize-meal by pulse. The first allocation of cheese since the end of the war was welcomed by all and its excellent quality is much appreciated.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d05188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">The allocation of coffee and tea is considered to be quite inadequate. Working people claim they cannot manage on the 40 grams of tea or 75 grams of coffee allocated per month. hhh 5. Children and Schools</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d15188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">As a result of the electricity and gas shortages many mothers say they are unable to give their children a daily warm bath or keep their laundry adequately clean. They also complain that schoolrooms are very cold and the children lack winter clothes. The shortage school books etc. has led many mothers to think that it would be better to keep the children at home altogether. They say that children learn very little and might fall ill sitting in unheated classrooms inadequately dressed. hhh 6. Attitude towards the Allies</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d25188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">The anti-Russian attitude of the Western Berlin population is pre­ponderant though the Western Powers do not escape criticism. The attitude of the French has caused great displeasure. Many Berliners see the cold hatred of Germany in the political course that French has taken, and they believe that such feelings ore quite out of place in view of the present European situation. It is very widely believed that French policy towards Germany has the following aims:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d35188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">1. Occupation for a prolonged period</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d45188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">2. Control and exploitation of the Ruhr</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d55188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">3. Restriction of German industry and the standard of German living.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d65188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">The Anglo-American attitude in Berlin is regarded as slack and conciliatory. It is also believed that during the present emergency in Berlin the Occupying Powers should share more fully the difficulties and hardships. Berliners feel that they are not to blame for the blockade and its consequences. They complain that premises occupied by the Allies are well lit and heated, when the German population must, suffer cold and darkness. British and American buses, which are mostly empty, continue to cause criticism when they pass overcrowded trams.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d75188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">It is expected that the Western Powers will take energetic and effective counter-measures against the latest Soviet instructions (identity cards, S-Bahn traffic regulations etc.). The population of the French Sector finds it difficult to understand that Coal barges are allowed to pass the water ways of the French Sector to and from the Soviet Sector.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d85188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">Postal communications to and from the Western Zones are also criticized. Many Berliners cannot understand why postal packages often remain at Tempelhof airfield for days, although it is said that the majority of air-lift aircrafts fly back empty to the Western Zones. The announcement that the weight of parcels allowed into Berlin is restricted to 50 grams and is disappointing to many Berliners especially those who expected Christmas parcels from the Western Zones and abroad. hhh 7. Economic Problems</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d95188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">The acute shortage of money, particularly Western Marks, as well as the difficulties with electricity, coal, raw materials and transport have hit a great number of Berlin factories. There is a shortage of goods, and unemployment figures are steadily rising.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-da5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">Pensions, annuities, unemployment benefits are paid irregularly, as a result of which a considerable number of Berliners are living in poverty.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-db5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">The introduction of Western marks as sole legal tender in the West Sectors of Berlin, as requested by the Magistrat, is supported by most Berliners, although the difficulties that this could entail are appreciated.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">Those who work in the Russian Sector, but live in the West, feel especially concerned with this problem, and claim that a reasonable and satisfactory solution must be found for them.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">Many Berliners believe that the sole use of the Western currency in the Western Sectors of the city would result in a rise of prices, but say they would prefer this to the present intolerable situation of two curren­cies of unequal value. hhh 8. Black Market</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">The cutting-off of Berlin, which has made foraging trips of any kind almost impossible, and the onset of winter have resulted in an, increase in the price of potatoes (1 cwt. 40 West Marks or 150 Eastmarks, 1 cubic metre of wood 70 Westmarks end 1 cwt of coal 25 Westmarks).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df5188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">Additional ration cards for the November ration increase could be bought on the Black Market for 25 Westmarks. A strong offer of American cocoa, for 25 Westmarks per lb is particularly noteworthy.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e05188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">So-called free shops opened in the Eastern Sector and the Eastern one are regarded as legalisation of the Black Market, and the prices demanded in these shops (for instance 33 DM(East) for 1 lb of Sugar, 5 DM(East) for a piece of cake and. 0.80 DM(East) for 1 Russian cigarette, etc.) are said to be impertin­ent and out of the question for the working classes.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e15188b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">3.12.48. N.F.</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>