<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Report on Berlin Morale No. 29 - second half of September 1948</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-61eeb3f9-039d-4ee9-9333-db3d85703fd9</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-18573d8b-6b71-4f83-940d-7197ca030d4a</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-155388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">CONFIDENTIAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-165388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="2">Public Opinion Research Office,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-175388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">Political Division,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-185388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="4">York House,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-195388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="5">HQ CCG (BE),</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1a5388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="6">Berlin, BAOR 2.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1b5388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="7">Report on Berlin Morale No.29 second half of September 1948 hhh General Atmosphere</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1c5388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">With regard to a speedy and peaceful solution of the Berlin crisis which would satisfy all sides, the pessimism of most Berliners remains unchanged. The decision to put the matter before the Security Council of U.N. is expected to be without success. In the opinion of the Berliner, Russia will either veto the discussion of the Berlin Problem, or not take part in it, and then declare null and void any majority-resolutions carried in her absence and would not recognise them. Altogether, Berliners are very sceptical in their views on the U.N.O. Meeting. In their eyes the assassina­tion of Count Bernadotte, whose death is widely and sincerely mourned, the fighting in Greece, Palestine, China and India are no recommendations for the work U.N.O. has done so far. Nor do they think that there is much prospect of a speedy improvement in the general world situation so long as Communism is striving for world domination. It is generally believed that there is hardly a chance of a peaceful and satisfactory solution of the Berlin crisis, as the tension between East and West had become so aggravated in the three post-war years that an armed conflict sooner or later would become inevitable. Next spring is expected to be critical, and thus an "Air-Lift" winter is predicted for Berlin. hhh The Food Situation</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1d5388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">The food situation remains serious. For the first time since the blockade, difficulties in the distribution of allocated foodstuffs have become noticeable. Fats and sugar, for instance, were distributed several days late. This delay immediately gave rise to the rumour that there were not sufficient food stocks in Berlin, and that the city was living "from hand to mouth". Berliners continue to express the desire to have good quality foodstuffs delivered, (particularly with regard to cereals, fats and meat).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1e5388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">A great deal has been written and said about gifts from Western Germany and foreign countries, but no special allocation of foodstuffs had so far taken place. Doubts have arisen as to what has become of these goods, people ask "Were they brought to Berlin at all?" In this connection Berliners were particularly annoyed about a report that several Volkswagens had been brought in by air for the Police. Volkswagens not considered so very important at present, as there are already enough motorcars in Berlin; it would have been much better to use the freight-space for really important items such as food, coal, etc.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1f5388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">Recently some foodstuffs which are no longer rationed in the Western Zones, such as spices, fruit juices, tomato and rhubarb preserves, childrens' cereals, vinegar and tinned fish have come off the ration in Berlin as well. But all these items are very expensive and as they must nearly always be paid for in Western currency they are out of reach for most Berliners and therefore do not bring relief to the situation. Coal Supplies</note>
				<note xml:id="q-205388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">The first night-frosts have given the Berliners a fore-taste of the coming winter and have made the fuel problem seem more acute. So far, no domestic fuel allocation has been made, though it has been announced that families with two children under 10 years of age would receive a hundred­weight of coal in October; coal which had been flown to Berlin specially on American Air Force Day. Thus, the Berliners face the cold period without any stocks of domestic fuel, and have few illusions about receiving any considerable allocation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-215388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">As a result of the gas and electricity cuts, insufficient quotas, and the total lack of wood and coal, many Berlin families are said to be unable to prepare one warm meal a day for themselves. There is a general demand that at least between six and eight a.m. and after six p.m. a minimum of one hour of electricity supply be granted in all districts simultaneously, as these were the hours when it was most needed. The depressing effect of the electricity cuts and of having to spend every evening in the dark must not be underestimated. For weeks many Berliners have been unable to listen to the wireless, or do any work at home, as electric supplies are mostly available during office hours and therefore of no use to the working popula­tion. As the season progresses and with the end of summer time on October 3rd, these difficulties will become considerable.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-225388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">Transport problems are a special source of worry to the Berliner. The S-Bahn runs irregularly and suffers daily break-downs; in the evening it is barely lit. The trams and Underground trains are invariably over-crowded and close down at approximately six p.m. The few omnibuses run infrequently and bring little appreciable easing of the transport problem. hhh Political Anxieties</note>
				<note xml:id="q-235388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">The administrative "partition" of Berlin has made further progress. Several SPD members of the Eastern Sector Administration of Districts have been dismissed and there is a considerable demand that in return, SED members should be excluded from the administration in the Western Sectors. hhh Accommodation Worries</note>
				<note xml:id="q-245388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">The turn of the weather has also re-awakened the fear of having to face another winter in damaged flats. Summer has again passed with few repairs having been carried out. Because of the lack of materials and money, the general bad condition of Berlin houses has hardly changed. hhh Currency - Economic Problems - Black Market.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-255388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">The chaotic currency position of Berlin, continues and entails severe hardships for many Berliners.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-265388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">Because of the blockade the economic life of the city is much impeded and there is a danger of a rise in unemployment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-275388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">In spite of raids and boundary controls the Black Market continues almost unchanged. Of late there has been many offers of Bulgarian cigar­ettes, which can be obtained for 0.25 Western Marks or 0.90 Eastern Marks. hhh The Berlin Radio Station (Rundfunkhaus)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-285388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">In the opinion of many Berliners it is an impossible state of affairs that the Russian controlled Berlin Radio Station remains in the British Sector. The British authorities are expected at long last to adopt a firm attitude in this matter. hhh School Reform</note>
				<note xml:id="q-295388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">The liquidation of private schools and the closing of religious educational institutions which was ordered, and the establishment of the "Einheitsschule" (standard-school), which many parents regard pre­mature, is sharply criticised. The people are not convinced that, under present circumstances and with the shortage of teachers, etc., the standard-school can guarantee a good standard of education. hhh Rumours</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a5388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">a) 50% of the aircraft carrying goods to Berlin are said to bring arms and ammunition.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b5388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">b) In Frohnau (French Sector) a new air field is said to be planned, after the one in Tegel is completed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2c5388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">c) The evacuation of sick and aged Berliners and of children means that the danger of war is imminent.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d5388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">d) 130,000 Germans are said to have been organised and uniformed as a ''German Legion" in the British Zone.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e5388b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">S.B. 28.9.48.</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>