<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Home Intelligence Weekly Report - No. 158 - 2 September 1943</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-440f0893-b350-4ddd-b61c-4a97ea45c664</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-1aca3b3f-20b0-44dd-9874-556650ff6fa9</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-5d4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5e4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5f4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="3">HOME INTELLIGENCE WEEKLY REPORT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-604a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="4">No. 152</note>
				<note xml:id="q-614a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="5">2nd September, 1943</note>
				<note xml:id="q-624a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">(Covering period from 24th to 31st August, 1943</note>
				<note xml:id="q-634a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="7">I. GENERAL COMMENTS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-644a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">(No reports have been received since the Prime Minister's speech of August 31) hhh 1. General state of confidence and reaction to news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-654a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">Confidence remains high as a result of the Russian successes, the air offensive - particularly on Berlin, and the evidence of unrest in occupied countries. In spite of the good news, however, there appears to have been a slight drop in spirits since last week, showing itself in:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-664a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">(a) Widespread uneasiness over British and U.S. relations with Russia; this has increased since last week.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-674a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">(b) Impatience at Allied inactivity, both not invading the Continent "to give more concrete help to the Russians", and in "riot driving Italy out of the war".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-684a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">At the same time, there continues to be good deal of expectation that "something big is brewing", though speculation is less than a week ago. Although there are still many optimists who think the war will be over by Christmas, there is an increasing tendency to put back the date of final victory to next year, and a minority say that "the war is only beginning now".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-694a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">Home Front. The hope that this will be the last winter of the war appears to be reducing dread of the black-out, but dislike of it is very strong; people are asking whether black-out conditions could be modified and whether -.cycle and torch batteries Will be in reasonable supply this year. The greatest home front worry still appears to be footwear.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6a4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.10.11.13. 17 passim. No report from Region 9 this week.) hhh 2. Russia and the other Allies</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6b4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">Suspicion and anxiety that all is not well between Russia and the English-speaking Allies, already' widespread 1st week, have increased.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6c4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">Russia's apparent lack of appreciation of our effort and our help to her, the recall of MM. Maisky and Litvinov, and, above all, the absence of any Russian representative at Quebec, are "linked as evidence that friction exists between Russia on the one hand and U.S.A. and ourselves on the other". Talk of the possibility of Russia making a separate peace with Germany is reported from six Regions. On the causes of disagreement, two main viewpoints are apparent (agar from minority who blame both sides or neither) :</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6d4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">(a) Those who consider that Russia has every reason to be dissatisfied, because:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6e4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">(i) We have not started a large-scale Continental landing to relieve German pressure. Even many who arc "far from friendly to Russia" say we have had ample time to build up and plan a major offensive, and that "to offer Sicily as our contribu­tion is an affront to Russia and dishonour to ourselves", They add that "if we don't do something big soon to divert Axis forces from Russia, we shall have only ourselves to blame if she takes the view that we are hoping to win the war at her expense, finishing up fresh and powerful while she is exhausted and weak".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6f4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">(ii) There is little sympathy with Russia among "highly placed officials and influential people", and still loss apprecia­tion of what she has done. This view is held by workers especially. There are "rumours of a whispering campaign against Russia", and it is feared that "the reluctance of the high-ups - but not Mr. Churchill - to work with Russia will lead to a breach and actual war with her later on". In Orkney, "it is firmly believed that the defenses being con­structed there are designed for future conflict with Russia rather than Germany".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-704a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">(b) Those who, while appreciating all Russia is doing, fool that she is unreasonable, because:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-714a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">(i) The Russians have not given enough credit to the other Allies for their help - by providing supplies, sometimes to our own disadvantage, by our heavy bombing policy, and by holding troops in the west to meet the invasion throat. People particularly fool that the Russians don't understand naval power, or "the difficulty of transporting troops and material by sea".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-724a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">(ii) Stalin is "cynically indifferent to everything but Russian ambitions". It is pointed cut that Russia left us alone in 1940 while she had a pact with Germany, and is still at peace with Japan while we have to fight her,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-734a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">Whatever reasons are suggested to account for lack of co-operation, its possibility is almost universally deplored. It is widely hoped that:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-744a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">(a) A conference between the three powers can be arranged to take place at an early date, to bring about "open and friendly co-operation and ensure peaceful European settlement hereafter". (Nine Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-754a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">(b) Mr. Churchill would throw some light on the subject in his speech (Five Regions), and make it clear that we are really one with Russia in the present struggle".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-764a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">(1.2.3.4.5.5SR.6.7.8.10.11.13) hhh 3. The Russian offensive</note>
				<note xml:id="q-774a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">General pleasure is reported at the capture of Taganrog, following on that of Kharkov. Admiration for the Red Army already great, is said to be increasing, and there is gratitude for "all she is saving us" and "restlessness that we are doing so little to help".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-784a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">Many expect further advances; some think "the Ukraine may be 'Captured by the end of the summer campaign", even that, "during the next few months, the Russians may be able to free most of their country".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-794a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">There is also speculation as to what Russia will do then. Some think she may stop at her borders and negotiate a separate peace, others that she will march through Poland into Germany; it is asked "what will happen in this country .if Russia gets to Berlin first?"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7a4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">(1.2.3.4.5.5SR.6.7.8.10.11.13. 17 two provincial P.Cs.) hhh 4. The next moves</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7b4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">Expectation that an Allied invasion of the Continent is imminent continues, but there appears to be less certainty about it this week and, in view of Russia's need, more impatience.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7c4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">Discussion is, however, not quite as widespread as it was, but the majority still find plenty of evidence to support their belief that it will take place before long, many thinking that "the balloon will go up when the Prime Minister returns".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7d4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">There is considerable disappointment that "we have reached September without any large European front being opened". People are impatient that "the Sicilian success was not followed_ by a quick attack on Italy", and fear that our delay is allowing the enemy to strengthen his defenses. There is impatience at the apparent lull after each new move we make. Some suspect that the U.S.A. is more interested in the Far Eastern than the European war, and may "insist on the second front being against the Japanese".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7e4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">At the same time, most people, whether confident or disappointed, seem "content to leave it to our leaders", fooling that "further preparations are worth waiting for if those are essential to a more complete success'. Speculation as to "whore" is on exactly the same lines as last week.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7f4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.10.11.15. 17 two provincial P.Cs.) hhh 5. The Allied are offensive</note>
				<note xml:id="q-804a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">(No reports have been received since the 'Berlin raid of August 31/September 1.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-814a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">Satisfaction with our massive raids" on enemy territory continues, and so does praise for, and pride in, the men of the R.A.F. It is felt that our "terrific rounding" of Germany must by having its effect on German morale, and it is thought that "signs of demoralisation and defeatism are already beginning to appear''. Demands for harder and heavier blows are again reported, and people are particularly anxious to see Italy "hammered into submission". Some believe that the R.A.F. blows, particularly on Southern Italy and the French aerodromes, are a prelude to invasion. (Four Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-824a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">The Berlin raid (August 23/24) was greeted with great satisfaction (Eight Regions), though pleasure was modified at first by surprise and regret at the high losses". However, it is felt, they were probably not disproportionate to the numbers of planes involved or "the effect achieved, and insignificant compared with those of a land offensive". Demands for more and heavier bombing of Berlin continue... them go night after night give am we've got'.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-834a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">U.S.A.L.F.: Comparison is made between the bomber losses of the U.S.A.L.F., their claims of fighters shot down, and our own losses. People doubt if our own bombers are as well defended, and there are demands for their better equipment (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-844a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">Rome: The general view is still that we should reject the proposal to make Rome an open city, and that we should put no faith in Italian claims. "Badoglio cannot be relied on to clear out military objectives." People would like to see the bombing continued; and the Pope is criticised for his "squeamishness" about possible damage to religious buildings. It is again pointed out that "he did not appeal to the Germans to refrain from bombing London churches".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-854a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.10.11.13. 17 three provincial P.Cs.) hhh 7. Germany's difficulties</note>
				<note xml:id="q-864a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">Although a few people are "reluctant to be optimistic about it", many consider Himmler's app ointment as "a clear indication that German morale is getting shaky". Some go so far as to hope that the bad news from the war fronts and our terrible air onslaught "may break it more suddenly then appearances suggest".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-874a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">The unrest "all over occupied Europe" - "which must be increasing Germany's difficulties" - is watched with interest; as is also "the changing attitude of neutral countries". All this is felt to show that "confidence in, and fear of, Germany were fading". Specific reference is made to:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-884a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">(a) Denmark: There is admiration for the courage of the Danes in revolting against Nazi oppression, and people hope that "we may be able to help thorn very soon". There is a tendency to interpret trouble hero as a sign either we intend to invade Denmark or that the Germans fear we will do so.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-894a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">(b) Death of King Boris: Little is known Balkan politics and people cannot toll whether "his removal will improve matters or not". Thor is no sympathy for King Boris, but a good deal of speculation about how he died: "'Most people. are convinced it was not a natural death."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8a4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">(1.2,3.4.5.5SE.7.3.13.13) hhh 8. The Conference</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8b4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">Speculation and comment about the Quebec. Conference are less this week; some people are describes "indifferent". Decline in interest is variously attributed to lack of information, to people being "tired of talk" and anxious for action, and to disappointment that the war against Japan was the principle subject of discussion. Nevertheless many welcomed the conference as "foreshadowing a more active West Front offensive" are "hoping for big announcements".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8c4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">'The lack of Russian representation continues to be the cause of widespread re Fret and much anxiety (See Section 2).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8d4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">Mrs. and Miss Churchill: Comment continues (Six Regions and Postal Censorship).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">The Prime Minister's speech (to which no pubic reactions have yet been received) eagerly awaited by most people, many of whom hoped it would shed light on the various questions that are exercising their minds Its postponement caused disappointment, and much speculation as to the reason. Some thought it indicated "political awkwardness" and a failure to "make up their minds but most people thought it implied some new development, as the end of Italian resistance, which Mr. Churchill was to announce.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">President Roosevelt's speech at Ottawa (August 25) is said to have aroused some "mildly favourable" comment not a great deal of interest.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-904a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">The revelations about Hess have been criticised (Five Regions) on two grounds:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-914a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">(a) Scouts and their parents are indignant, in spite of the explanation. As a Welshman observes: "We take great news in a matter of fact way, while one remark out of place causes, widespread discussion - we truly are a mad.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-924a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">(b) "The answer to the Hess mystery" was "refused to the House of Commons", but was given in Canada.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-934a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">The press handling of the Conference is criticised (Two Regions). It is thought to have been "singularly contradictory and confusing' and is also blamed for giving prominence to "the holiday atmosphere at a time when people are anxious about Russia and want decisive action".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-944a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.10.11. 13. 17 one Special, five provincial P.Cs.) hhh 9. Italy</note>
				<note xml:id="q-954a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">There is less talk this week about the political situation. A growing conviction that "only military pressure will drive Italy into submission" is allied to restlessness at our delay in invading it. People wonder whether this delay is "yet another example of' our being too kind to the Wops" - "like the mistake we made laying off giving it to them when Musso fell".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-964a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">While the majority arc in favour of 'nothing but unconditional surrender", a minority feel "such severe terms are likely to make them fight on".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-974a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">British Prisoners of War: Anxiety continues at reports of their transfer from Italian to German hands.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-984a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.10.11. 17 one Special, seven provincial P.Cs. hhh 10. Spain</note>
				<note xml:id="q-994a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">There continues to be some speculation about the reasons for the Hoare-Franco talks: "Does it mean better relations with Spain, or has Franco been acting on behalf of Italy?"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">(2.4.6.7.13) hhh 11. Amgot</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">Some distrust of Amgot continues to be reported. It is described as "an undemocratic body"; people wonder why it is necessary, and where in the future "the exiled Allied Governments and their peoples will come in".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">(5.5SE.6.11) hhh 12. The French Committee for National Liberation</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9d4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">There has boon satisfaction but very little comment at the recognition of the French Committee for National Liberation: "There is not much interest in the French at present."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9e4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">"The luke-warm declaration by America" has caused comment, and she is also blamed for having caused the delay in giving this recognition. hhh 13. Far East</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9f4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">There continues to be little interest in the Far East, although some people wonder whether "there is to be a new offensive there as a result of the Quebec Conference".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a04a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">The appointment of Lord Louis Mountbatten to the post of Supreme Commander in South-East is generally thought a good one (Four Regions): "People expect fireworks when he gets going". A minority doubt his being the right man for the post, however. (Two Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a14a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">The appointment has been taken to show that we may be about to make a definite move possibly towards the recovery of Burma and Malaya. Some "puzzled" comment is recorded, however, that "such leaders are needed against Germany, before bothering with the Far East".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a24a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">China: Sympathy for China and the desire to help her are reported from six Regions this week.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a34a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">Prisoners of War in Japanese hands: names of missing relatives continue to be welcomed but it is asked whether "Geneva cannot do more to get information?" Gratitude is expressed for the broad­cast about prisoners of war in the Far East given on August 24th.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a44a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.10.11) hhh 14. War at Sea.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a54a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">There is again little comment on this subject, but satisfaction and pleasure continue at the successes against the U-boat menace.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a64a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">The fine work of the Royal Navy, especially during the Sicilian campaign, is praised and there is great confidence "in its ability to deal with any situation".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a74a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">(1.3.5.5SE.7.10) hhh 15. Holidays</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a84a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">There is loss talk of holidays this week. People' continue to believe in "the necessity of holiday travel"; they feel that those workers who have gone away have been wise to do so. "Those who did not go away, wish they had." Some criticism of the "Government's weakness and lack of foresight" end of the policy of holidays at home is again reported on familiar lines.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a94a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8) hhh 16. The coastal area ban</note>
				<note xml:id="q-aa4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">Interest and speculation continue as to, the significance of the ban imposed on the South and South 'East coast. It is still believed that preparations for Invasion are being made in the area (Seven Regions). It is again suggested that it may be a bluff designed to cover activity elsewhere or even a double bluff.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ab4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">Uncertainty as to the exact areas banned to visitors has been the cause of much telegraphing and telephoning. In the Southern Region; it is said that "the restriction notices are so worded as to be incomprehensible to the general public".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ac4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">Rumours of troop movements come from the Regions involved in the ban.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ad4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">(2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.10) hhh 17. Broadcasting and presentation of news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ae4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">Satisfaction with news presentation by the B.B.C. and in the press is reported from four Regions. "People appear content to accept such official news as can be given at the moment."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-af4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">Sensational press headlines are criticised in two Regions. Although qualified by the following news paragraphs, "they remain in the reader's mind" thus conveying the wrong impression. People are, however, said to be "on guard against press misrepresentation".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b04a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">The B.B.C. is again criticised for the repetition of news (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b14a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">European News Service: Praise is again reported (Two Regions): "It is given with more colour than the Homo News".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b24a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">Praise this week for: Commander Kimmmins' postscript on the King's visit to the Fleet. August 22 (Three Regions); the Russian commentary by Alexander Werth, August 21 (Two Regions); the "Into Battle" series (Two Regions); War Commentaries (Two-Regions); The talk describing the construction of Mosquito pianos, August 24 (One Region)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b34a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">Dr. J.J. Mallon's postscript (August 29) is criticised in three regional reports. It is though we been an ''irritating pro-American advertisement" and "too sloppy". In one Region however, it is thought "likely to arouse real interest in American troops here".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b44a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="88">II. SPECIAL COMMENTS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b54a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">WEEKLY SUMMARY hhh 18. Menpower</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b64a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">The proposed registration of women (Eight Regions): There is a further decrease in comment, but opposition is still said to be very strong and on the lines previously reported:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b74a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">(a) It would be unnecessary "if manpower were not (Seven Regions and Postal Censorship). Specifically mentioned are the many young people, particularly girls:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b84a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">(i) With little or nothing to do in the Civil Service ­including Labour Exchanges and Food Offices - factories, large businesses, and H.M. Forces.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b94a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">(ii) Doing jobs which older women could do.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ba4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">(iii) "Who wriggle out of doing anything at all."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bb4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">(b) Their call-1m will serve no purpose (Five Regions and Postal Censorship because:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bc4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">(i) "They won't be able to stand factory work." Labour, it is suggested, should be recruited from those physically more fit such as men and women discharged from the Forces, retired men in good health, and "the many men on the dole".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bd4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">(ii) "All the older ones who are good for anything did not need calling up and have boon doing their bit for ages."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-be4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">(iii) "What will happen to the voluntary work they are doing" Many have been looking after their grandchildren, thus free­ing younger women for the factory. Also, "who's going to get the men's food and stand in queues for it?" Some of the work of the voluntary services, the W.V.S. and National Savings movement in particular, "will have to be curtailed".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bf4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">(c) "Women are carrying more than share of the burdens of war." (Two Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c04a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">Recruitment to the Women's Auxiliary Services and: Land Army (Four Regions) : There is some disappointment among girls that no more recruits are wanted for the Forces and that "they now have to go into munitions".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c14a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">In Dorset, farmers are said to be "very perturbed- at the restriction on recruiting for the Women's Land Army, especially as some of their male workers have only a short reservation".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c24a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">Changes of priority in men's call-up (Three Regions): Little comment is reported except in some mining areas where miners "object to unskilled men being allowed to 'opt' for mines when it requires years of training to become a, useful worker".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c34a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">(1.2.3.5.5SE.6.7.10. 17 one Special, five provincial P.Cs.) hhh 19. Clothing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c44a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">Clothing continues the subject of much concern - footwear problems, in particular, in view of the coming winter months.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c54a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">Increased coupon values for leather-soled shoes: (No reactions have been received to the announcement of extra coupons for children with big feet.) During the past two weeks there has been widespread criticism and resentment at the increased coupon Values for loather-soled shoes (Thirteen Regions). Parents of growing children who take adult sizes, and who are not tall enough to qualify for extra coupons, are especially upset (Six Regions): "Boy's size 5 only require three coupons, but size 5 1/2 now require nine coupons".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c64a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">People are said to have felt that even the old number was too high in view of the poor wearing qualities of present day shoes. It is claimed that a reduction rather than an increase in the coupon value of adult leather-soled shoes should have been made. (Three Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c74a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11.13. 17 four provincial P.Cs.) hhh 20. Food</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c84a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="108">Satisfaction with the food situation continues, although there is again some grumbling about the distribution and prices of certain commodities. The shortage of fruit (Six Regions) and of tomatoes (Three Regions) and the high prices of vegetables (Three Regions) and of fruit (Two Regions) are particularly criticised. People are asking "where is the bumper crop of plums".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c94a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="109">From Scotland, it is reported that "public anger is strong concerning the dumping of herrings at Clydeside ports last week. Press reports of conferences on the subject only increase the anger. 'It's a pure scandal' is one of the milder comments on the situation People are talking about this everywhere." From Co. Durham it is also reported: "There is a glut of fish, but here we have a famine".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ca4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="110">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.10.11. 17 nine provincial P.Cs.) hhh 21. Agriculture</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cb4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="111">The bumper harvest is praised this week in three Regional reports and Postal Censorship. In Wales, Devon and Cornwall, farmers complain that "the weather has been against them".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cc4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="112">Though some farmers still report shortage of labour, others speak of voluntary help "willingly and enthusiastically given".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cd4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="113">(1.3.5SE.7.8.10. 17 four provincial P.Cs.) hhh 22. America</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ce4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="114">During the last four weeks, increasing appreciation for "the great effort made by our American ally" in providing us "with the food, the weapons, and the man" has been noted - though "Russia's effort still overshadows them".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cf4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="115">"Doubts" still reported about America are as follows:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d04a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="116">(a) America desires to dominate the world after the war Some (Four Regions) people ask "how much of the Empire has already been ceded to America, and will we ever get it back?"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d14a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="117">(b) There is some resentment end distrust of American claims of losses inflicted on the enemy (Three Regions). "The Americans are assuming all the credit for present victories."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d24a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="118">American troops in this country: There has been little comment on American troops during the last four weeks. Some praise their "niceness"; but the following familiar criticisms continue to be reported:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d34a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="119">(a) Their behaviour with women and especially with young (Three Regions). "Due to their efforts children of fourteen and fifteen are with child"; it is thought that "American troops arc amenable only to American law". The girls themselves are, however, much blamed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d44a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="120">(b) Their high pay (Three Regions) - as a result of which they are accused of ostentation, and of "buying up" everything available including labour. The "palatial premises!' and "lavish provision" provided for them are also criticised.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d54a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="121">(c) Their waste of food and of petrol., their dangerous driving, rowdy behaviour, and excessive drinking (One Region each). In London, people are puzzled about the ribbons worn by American troops in this country.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d64a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="122">(2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.10.17)</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>