<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Morale Half Yearly Report, 26 March 48</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-ec0899eb-554a-4580-ae7d-5b62cf87fbd9</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-5ca34be9-14db-4078-8b1c-4e727f7cfee1</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-60557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="1">Subject: Morale Half Yearly Report.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-61557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">WCG/43/Details.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-62557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="3">26 Mar. 48.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-63557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="4">Garrison Commander,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-64557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">Bad Oeynhausen Garrison.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-65557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">Ref. "A" Branch 7 Armd Div (Static) letter 211/1/22/A dated 19 Feb. 47. Hereunder half yearly report in respect of this Unit : hhh 1. MORALE.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-66557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">Morale is definitely sound and keeps good, based mainly it is considered on the fact that each man has a reasonable idea when he can anticipate release from the service, although most men appear to be quite happy during the time that they are in the Army and would not really have missed the experience.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-67557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">As has been explained in previous reports men in this Unit have specific duties which can be divided into two classes - those who are drivers and who are constantly on the road, and who travel and see most parts of Germany, a thing they could never have afforded to see at their own expense and those who are employed in offices. Here again each with specific tasks and appreciating he is a cog in the machine that is responsible for the arrest and trial of war criminals who in the past have murdered and inflicted so much suffering on relatives, friends and countrymen.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-68557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">Men are not except in exceptional circumstances, employed on general duties, except as a form of punishment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-69557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">The attitude towards the civilians is not that of friendship, but of those who do associate with Germans they appear to do so solely to satisfy their own desires and would not in any way be to help them out of their present plight.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6a557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">Confidence in Military and Political Leaders - very little politics is talked about in the unit, although whenever a bye-election occurs in U.K. there is speculation as to whether or not there will be any change in the representation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6b557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">Little criticism is heard of members of the Government, although opinion has been expressed that many would like to see Churchill with a more prominent position</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6c557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">With regard to Military leaders there is little or no comment, but there is certain speculation as to what changes, if any, will arise with the arrival of the new Army Commander in April.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6d557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">It is generally agreed that England's back is against the wall and many consider that they are better off in the Army than they would be in civilian life at the present time. Several have expressed the opinion that they do not feel they can settle down in England when released from the Service and have intimated their intention of possibly trying to emigrate to one of the Dominions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6e557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">Others through their service in the Army have decided that an outdoor life is far more preferable to working in a factory or in similar employment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6f557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">Many persons are worried as to the nature of the employment they will undertake on their discharge as prospects for unskilled workers are not so good as for those who have a definite trade. However, although direction is in force in England, personnel appear to be satisfied that it is not being pressed and on release will, except in exceptional circumstances, not again be subject to direction and discipline. hhh 2. DISCIPLINE.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-70557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">Discipline on the whole is quite good although its standard is definitely below that obtaining in the Army during and before the war. This is doubtlessly due to the fact that the Army at the present time consists of so many young soldiers and NCOs, and in practically all cases senior NCOs have comparatively little service compared with their equivalent ranks 10 years ago.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-71557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">In many cases NCOs do not appear to realise that their duty is not only to do their specific job within their unit, office, branch, etc. but also to set an example and to lead those junior to them.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-72557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">No particularly serious crime has been reported in this Unit during the period and disciplinary offences within the Unit relate usually to matters of dress, lateness on parade, traffic accidents or overstaying a pass.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-73557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">There is a growing tendency amongst young soldiers to wilfully damage the quarters in which they are accommodated and this results in frequent assessments of barrack damages. It is understood that the disappearance of door handles, electric light bulbs and tearing of electric fittings from the walls is prevalent throughout the Garrison and that these items have a high black market value. However, to date no perpetrators of such destruction have been caught. Petty thefts from billets occur at frequent intervals usually involving an odd item of clothing, cigarettes, chocolate, etc. and although the Germans are blamed, it is fairly certain that some of the thefts are the work of British soldiers. Thefts appear to occur during office hours and of course shortage of personnel prevents billet orderlies being detailed for each billet during that period.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-74557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">Until such time as only military personnel are allowed to wear the Khaki battle dress only then will it be possible to get good discipline in manner of turn out and bearing, as at the present time the uniform is worn by so many organisations with and without titles thereon, that it is impossible to differentiate between the soldier and members of such organisations. hhh 3. Relations between all ranks, and with ether services and Allied Forces.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-75557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">Relations between all ranks are good and during the period on several occasions all ether ranks of the Unit have been addressed by Officers, Chaplains and Medical Officers on various subjects and they have always been only too eager to ask questions and it has been interesting to note that even when talks have been held in their own time they were only too willing to carry on with the questions long after the proposed time for closing of the meeting.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-76557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">Officers and other ranks working in the American zone on practically every occasion have to seek accn and messing in American Transient Messes or Units and little but praise is heard for the hospitality they receive, the different type of food which they eat and the benefits of the Post Exchange Stores.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-77557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">A great deal has been said about our Allies, the Russians and it is generally considered that it is impossible for the army to co-operate satisfactorily with our opposite numbers in the Russian Forces. An incident involving the Russians in Berlin was reported to you under cover of my WCG/90/Details of 25 Mar. 48. hhh 4. Morale of special categories.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-78557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">Within this Group which is composed in the main of non-Regular Officers now that the future policy regarding War Crimes is practically settled and each individual officer has a good idea as to his own future, morale has improved. In the past non-Regular Officers have not known whether their service within this Group would terminate within a matter of months or whether it would go on for some considerable time and in consequence morale possibly suffered.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-79557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">No recruits are received direct in this Unit, all reinforcements haring received their basic preliminary and corps training. However, the majority of reinforcements received during the period under review have only had a matter of two or three months service ahead of them on arrival here and in consequence have never really settled down and it must be admitted that they are in many instances "group happy" and do not have interest in their work.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7a557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">Numbers of reinforcements have settled down well, but just as they are becoming an asset to the Unit their release date approaches and their services are lost.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7b557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">The reinforcement situation appears to be very acute especially with regard to tradesmen and clerks, and a serious situation has arisen in this Unit like many others of an E.R.E. nature, in that it has been forced to promote young soldiers of little experience to the rank of Senior NCDs where really a man of more substance is required in order to keep morale and discipline on a high level. hhh 5. Operation of Python Scheme and Leave Scheme.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7c557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">Personnel due for Python have often declined to take same and only in a few isolated instances has a man elected his return to U. K. However, being in BAOR with its Leave Scheme Python now would appear to be rather inappropriate especially in the case of non-regulars. Of course it is appreciated that this side of Python will die a natural death with the end of the year.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7d557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">With regard to the Leave Scheme, it is still felt that leave should be taken in three shorter periods as opposed to the present two in the leave year. From the work angle and the running of an office it is certain that this would be far more satisfactory arrangement as to replace a man for well over three weeks twice a year is far more difficult than in the old days when it was necessary to replace him three times but for a very much shorter period.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7e557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">Considerable feeling exists over the ruling given in GRO 224 (4170) Appendix "C" that no officer or other rank may, except in exceptional circumstances laid down therein take leave in a continental country. This decision appears to be unsound as there would appear to be no objection whatsoever for the same individual proceeding to U.K. and then proceeding to the continental country on a civilian passport, irrespective of currency.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7f557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">However, with the introduction of a certain amount of foreign exchange for specified countries as from 1 May, 1948 it is to be hoped that the above quoted GRO will be revised in the light of the circumstances. hhh 6. Living Conditions including accn, Messing and Canteens.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-80557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">Living conditions on the whole are quite satisfactory. D.C.R.E. appears to have carried out far more re-decoration programme in the last 6 months than was carried out in the preceding two years after the end of the War.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-81557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">The equipping of billets to synopsis schedule whether it be for officers or other ranks is now nearing completion, practically all indents having been met.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-82557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">Heating and minor repair services have been quite satisfactory throughout the winter and the delay from time D.C.R.E. work is demanded to its execution is now comparatively short.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-83557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">Messing on the whole is average, but a terrific monotony in diet exists. Meat issues would appear to be mainly beef and green vegetables are definitely lacking in the menu, there being too much carrot and swede in ration issues.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-84557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">The recent increased allocation of fish, especially for breakfast, has not been welcomed as in the majority of cases it is served boiled due undoubtedly to the lack of sufficient quantities of fat. It would therefore appear that if the fish issue is to continue on the present scale extra fat should be allocated to permit deep frying.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-85557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">Canteens within the Garrison are adequate although it is considered that firmer steps should be taken to obviate rowdyism and fights which are too prevalent nightly.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-86557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">With regard to the NAAFI Canteen in Herforder Strasse it has been for some time the wish of this Unit that it should be exclusively for members of the Unit.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-87557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">Recreation facilities within the Garrison are definitely adequate, but the main interest appears to be in Soccer, and within the Group but little interest can be stimulated in Rugger or Hockey.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-88557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">News services are satisfactory especially the BFN programmes which are well prepared and London dailies usually reach us on the day of publication. hhh 8. Mail.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-89557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">Considerable feeling has been expressed regarding the mail on the sea route to U.K. wef 1 Apr. The private soldier in BAOR who was at one time definitely better off than his opposite number in U.K. is now worse off financially. The only benefits he now gets for his overseas service being duty free cigarettes and these on a strictly rationed basis. Even his cinema costs him more than it would do in U.K. for better entertainment. These films are not even up-to-date and often ore repeated twice in the Garrison within a short period. There is feeling on the failure of the A.K.C. to acquire new films and although the American film position is appreciated, there are dozens of good modern English films which could be doubtlessly procured and shown in this theatre. hhh 9. Family affairs</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8a557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">Very little has been heard regarding family affairs. Any man who has any troubles whatsoever at home is invited to have a personal talk with an officer about it and if necessary the advice of SSAFR is sought in normal domestic cases and if the reasons are compassionate enough the local police have usually supplied the true position within a matter of 24 hrs. hhh 10. Education</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8b557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">Within Bad Ocynhausen Garrison educational facilities are first class but very few appear to take advantage of these facilities. Any man who has requested time off for extra studying or any benefits from the Education Centre has been given the fullest co-operation here. hhh 11. Operation of Release and Re-settlement scheme.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8c557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">Great disappointment was felt when the Government announced the differential release scheme. Men would not appreciate that it was an acceleration of certain arms of service and expressed the opinion that it was a retarding of the release of specific groups and despite talks to the men they were not completely satisfied with the reason. hhh 12. Health.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8d557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">During the period there have been no high scale sick parades and health on the whole is good. The number reporting sick daily being generally within the recognised figure of 2.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">With regard to V.D. during the half year figures are definitely diminishing and this may, it is thought, be possibly due to the feet that some men are doubtlessly contracting V.D. and seeking attendance from German MOs to avoid the normal disciplinary proceedings which result for failing to use the PAC.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">Efforts have been made to rind evidence of such attendances but to date nothing has come to light.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-90557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">It is possible that the decrease may be due to the average ago of those now present in the unit being lower and also due to the effect of the film "Sex-Hygiene" which had an awakening effect on all those who saw it.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-91557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">Men have been frequently addressed concerning V.D. by Regimental Officers, Medical Officer and also the Padre.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-92557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">It is however interesting to note that men who have gone absent for two or three days whilst in BAOR usually return to the Unit and subsequently report sick and V.D. is diagnosed. hhh 13. Finance and Allowances.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-93557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">The present star system is by many considered unsatisfactory, especially with regard to the star gradings given to personnel employed in clerical trades.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-94557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">It is extremely difficult for a clerk except by service and being a Class II Tradesmen to get above a one star soldier unless he has other qualifications and those are not normally present amongst R.A.B.C. personnel, as opposed to Infantrymen who have subsequently taken clerical courses.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-95557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">Qualifications required for a three star soldier are seldom found amongst the average private soldier; a soldier with these qualifications would doubtlessly be an N.C.O.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-96557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">Now allowances are taxable married men complain they are worse off than they were prior to the introduction of the new pay code.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-97557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">As said above men in BAOR have usually more expenses than a man in U.K. as a man at home usually finds some friends with whom to spend the evening whereas in Germany, entertainment always costs money and the only saving would now appear to be on cigarettes.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-98557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">Considerable difficulty is caused by bad documentation in mens' AB 64s Pt. II and with new arrivals here it is seldom possible to ascertain the state of their accounts and AFN 1483s forwarded to the Regimental Paymaster often take several weeks before return and in many cases are not returned at all.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-99557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">Furthermore on these 1483s that are returned large numbers of errors are found due to the delay between the publication of the casualty in the unit, the publication of the Pt. II Order be 2nd. Echelon and subsequent receipt by Regtl Paymaster concerned.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">Cannot a copy of the casualty be sent direct to the appropriate Regimental Paymaster at the same time so that he could provisionally act on the casualty and confirm his action upon receipt of Pt. II Order, in the same manner as is applicable in the case of officers? Furthermore it has been suggested that confirmation of crediting of ration allowance published on AFO 1865 should be made to the unit in exactly the same way as the receipt of P.1954 charges. It is appreciated that the P1954 copy acts as a voucher to the ledger, but particularly in the case of members of this Unit who often have American Zone subsistence allowance notified for payment, it is never confirmed except on specific request to the Paymaster whether or not such allowance is ever credited. hhh 14. Miscellaneous.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">It is suggested that the question of the quality of the A.K.C. films and in fact the working of the whole organisation should be reviewed with the object of firstly to decrease the price of seats or alternatively to improve the quality of the entertainment provided.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">Personnel who have deferred until general demobilization have often expressed the desire to know when they can anticipate release to within a week or so and it is felt that although a stagger system has been announced it might well be possible to announce the programne in detail as well as the programme for remaining Age and Service Groups - the National service man who enlisted after 1 Jan. 47 knows his date of release far more accurately than a man who enlisted prior to that date.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9d557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">With regard to the announcement that all cigarettes taken to U.K. by personnel proceeding leave are liable to customs duty this came somewhat as a surprise and now even the soldier's cheapest enjoyment is being subjected to tax. Cannot this concession be re-granted?</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9e557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">(for) Group captain Officer i/o</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9f557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">War Crimes Group (NWE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a0557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">MAJOR A.W.STONE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a1557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="66">Ext: 2246</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a2557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="67">Adm. Section</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a3557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="68">War Crimes Group (NWE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a4557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="69">HQ British Army of the Rhine,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a5557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="70">BAOR 1.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a6557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">AWS/GW</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>