<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Monthly Report on Morale and Public Opinion - September 1947</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-4d74ed6c-baf7-483e-97f1-5cbfe757dec7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-d9689101-bc81-4551-8bea-e317d672a07e</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-594e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="1">Copy to: The Inspector General,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="2">E.C. Nottingham Esq. M.C.,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">Deputy Inspector General,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="4">BERLIN.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5d4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="5">The Regional Governmental Officer.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5e4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="6">The Regional Intelligence Officer.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5f4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="7">J. R.Mite, Esq.,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-604e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="8">Public Opinion Research Office,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-614e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="9">Governmental Sub- Commission,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-624e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="10">67 HQ C.C.G.,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-634e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="11">BIELEFELD, BAOR.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-644e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-654e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="13">Tele: .34 10 00</note>
				<note xml:id="q-664e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="14">Ext 8500</note>
				<note xml:id="q-674e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="15">609/23/S/12/7</note>
				<note xml:id="q-684e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="16">Public Safety</note>
				<note xml:id="q-694e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="17">HQ Hansestadt HAMBURG</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6a4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="18">609 He CCG (BE) BAOR 330</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6b4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="19">30 September 1947</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6c4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="20">Subject:- Monthly Report on Morale and Public Opinion - September</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6d4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="21">The Regional Commissioner</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6e4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="22">HQ Hensestadt HAMBURG</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6f4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="23">609 HQ COG (BE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-704e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="24">BAOR 3 hhh 1. GENERAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-714e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">The coming winter is being faced with forebodings that it will severely test such reserves of physical and moral energy as remain. There is no con­fidence that one last supreme effort will put the nightmare of the last years into the background once and for all. Present grim realities have replaced earlier optimism with a cynical apathy which is now rapidly turning to aggres­sive resentment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-724e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">Blame for existing conditions is placed with the British more than with the Germans themselves and it is the steady progression in this direction which lends significance to a development which will determine relations be­tween the two and the ultimate effects of British occupation on the future course of German politics. Apart from a number who are governed by conviction and/or self-interest or caution, the majority make no attempt to disguise their growing hostility and attribute their present situation to the incompe­tence, selfishness and greed of the British who preach democracy and human morality while they choke the remaining life out of Germany and willfully bar her way to the free exercise of her talents and energies. Such beliefs, however blind, unreasonable and uninformed, foster attitudes and. prejudices from which the former Germany drew her undeniable and menacing strength, while none can help being aware of Germany's present physical weakness, map' are again becoming conscious of the roots of her former greatness. German nationalism, which is beginning to overcome the shock of its defeat and humiliation, appears to be flexing its enfeebled muscles, and makes up in venom what it lacks in substance. Its spokesmen have no reason to be dissatisfied with the popular echo they find. Agitation against the British serves to alienate the people from any new resolves they may have had when the old order came to an unprecedented end and a considerable number, totally ignoring the true cause of the obtaining situation, affirming their nationalism in vicious anti-British terms. This trend gains strength from Britain's economic plight, which to the German is synonymous with weakness, and by the failure of leading Germans to consolidate public opinion in a manner which would prevent a return to the errors of the past by conditioning the public mind to the acceptance of existing harsh facts not entirely bereft of hope. As it is, there are few leading Germans in Hamburg ready to do more than to pay nominal tribute to the incontestable fact of our presence here.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-734e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">It appears that the problem of the control of a population whose self-restraint is likely to be tested severely during the coming winter, may require extraordinary and special measures.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-744e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">The prospects of a coming war are being more actively discussed than ever before. Impetus has been given by the prophecy of Lt. General Eaker of the United States Army (Air Force) that another war was drawing near the remark of Colonel Tulpanow of the Red Army to the effect that those who interfere with the Oder boundary will bring about another war; and the announcement of President Truman that the United States is remaining armed. The extreme tension of the present international political situation has also added weight to the opinion that another war is imminent. The less responsible elements of the population and persons who are on principle opposed to democracy are turning popular fears in this respect to their awn profit and the furtherance of their aims. hhh 2. FOOD</note>
				<note xml:id="q-754e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">During the last rationing period the supply of milk, meat and vegetables remained scanty and irregular. The supply of fish ceased altogether for about three weeks at the height of the fishing season. Popular opinion has it that this was caused by the inability of the Authorities to supply fishing vessels with fuel, in consequence of which catches were unloaded at Cuxhaven instead of Hamburg. Bread, potatoes, fats, sugar and cereals were supplied as scheduled The announced reduction in the allotment of winter potatoes from two cwts to one cwt per head, coupled with the low field in cabbages and turnips has increased public anxiety in respect of the food position for the coming winter. It is generally appreciated that the world harvest of all principal crops has fallen short of expectations and fears for a repetition of the deplorable con­ditions of last winter are approaching near panic. As a result, thousands of people are trekking to the country for the purpose of acquiring potatoes and other food stocks. General resentment is growing against the farmers who, it is felt, are withholding produce from regular channels of distribution.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-764e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">Criticism against Schlange-Schoningen is growing and is no longer confined to the Left. The principal charge at the moment is that he assessed German grain requirements too low and the German harvest too high.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-774e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">The early harvesting of potatoes (with its consequent decrease in size and yield) entailed early distribution with the result that winter supplies will probably have been used up before the winter sets in. hhh 3. FUEL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-784e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">The fuel position is being viewed with great optimism. Present efforts and successes in supplying a certain amount of fuel has established a measure of confidence that those supplies may be sustained during the whole of the winter. This impression has been strengthened by the recent announcement that the supply of gas will no longer be curtailed after the 1st October now that all damaged gas mains have been repaired. hhh 4. PUBLIC HEALTH</note>
				<note xml:id="q-794e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">The rate of tuberculosis continues to give concern and the recent wave of infantile paralysis has caused grave fears; it being generally recognised that both physical stamina and medical facilities are below the standard required to successfully cope with any large scale epidemic.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7a4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">There are many complaints that it is practically impossible to obtain either frames or lenses for spectacles. Opticians apparently have no means of replenishing their stocks as the greater part of Germany's optimal industry lies in the Russian Zone.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7b4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">Of the 45 municipal and private baths in Hamburg functioning before the war, only 22 private and 3 municipal baths remain in operation. Added to the inability to keep domestic baths in private houses going and the fact that private baths nay, as a rule, only be used on a doctor's prescription; this state of affairs is widely considered as detrimental to public health and hygiene. hhh 5. HOUSING AND BUILDING</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7c4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">There has been little or no talk of new requisitionings of office or living accommodation by the Occupational Authorities. A few houses are said to have been evacuated and returned to the German Welfare. German malice claims that there is no danger of a house being requisitioned for a second time as the British would not again requisition a building which had deteriorated due to their previous occupation and from which all objects of value had long since been relieved.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7d4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">The Hamburg building authorities are generally rated as the most incompetent in any Department of the German Administration. They are charged with building and repairing many non-essential restaurants, bars and other places of entertain­ment while achieving little towards the building or restoration of living accom­modation. It is claimed that individual initiative in this respect is hindered by the inability or unwillingness of the appropriate authorities to lend assist­ance Opinion also persists that much building material is leaving Hamburg and that the authorities are failing entirely in checking the flow. Officially all building materials remain in short supply. hhh 6. CLOTHING</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7e4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">The position in respect of clothing remains unchanged if it has not actually worsened. Only limited numbers of coupons are issued, many of which cannot be redeemed because the required articles are not available here or are arbitrarily withheld by shopkeepers who are not interested in transactions on a cash basis. Consequently, the ever-increasing shortage of clothing and especially of woollen garments and footwear, in view of the coming winter is causing great unrest.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7f4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">Ex-POWS in particular complain that insufficient provision has been made to equip them with clothing and footwear and that it has been impossible to get even the minimum required from official sources.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-804e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">The same plight exists in respect of household articles; damaged or lost items cannot be replaced and most families live under conditions Lore reminiscent of tramp life than of a no real civilised household.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-814e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">The general lack of electric light bulbs is acquiring greater importance now that the hours of daylight are getting shorter. This has effect not only on morale but on efficiency in offices and factories, eta. hhh 7. BLACK MARKET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-824e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">At the moment the Black Market appears to be dominated by trading in solid fuels (wood, peat, coal, eta.). There has been a definite slump in the supply of foodstuffs, especially fats, It is generally believed that food is being hoarded and that a considerable volume will be released on the Black Market during the winter when it is most in demand. Money remains scarce. The over-all price level has risen slightly, in particular, much higher prices are being asked for footwear and textiles.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-834e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">Counterfeit butter and sugar coupons are reaching the Black Market in some quantities. Investigations by the Police have so far involved 7 small Hamburg printing establishments. To date 37 arrests have been made. The majority of the forgeries (which consisted of coupons for over 2,000 kilos of food) were on a fair imitation of the new forgery proof paper. One roll of genuine paper, obviously stolen, was found in one of the printing offices referred to above. Investigations are continuing.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-844e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">There is talk of a brisker trade in narcotics which it is claimed can be obtained without much difficulty in most Black Market centres. However, there is no real evidence to substantiate this. The belief may have originated from the discovery by the Police of 51 boxes containing 205 kilos of narcotic drugs (Dolantin, Eucodal. Cebiom, Cardiazol,.Parachinin, etc.) in the possession of a Hamburg chemist who had invested his money in these drugs during the early days of the Occupation and stored them with a view to eventual resale or barter.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-854e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">There appears to be an increasing demand for petrol. Popular opinion claims that the high prices charged for transporting goods comparatively short distances are due to removal vans being, in the main, operated on Black Market petrol. hhh 8. MILITARY GOVERNMENT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-864e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">Criticism of Military Government policy was rampant during the last month. Practically every aspect of public life received its share of censure. Two events received specially severe comment, Firstly, the disembarkation of Jews in Hamburg and secondly, the military occupation of the Homag Works in Kiel.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-874e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">In respect of the first, the majority of the population condemned the forced disembarkation for a variety of reasons, among which, purely humanitarian aspects were overshadowed by the desire to ward off possible further encroachments on German resources and. to identify the British with measures and policies for which the Gamin nation has been condemned and made to suffer. There was no general revival of anti-Semitic feeling but the affair was widely if subconsciously used to soothe a guilt complex in respect of former German activities against the Jews. This tendency received emphasis from the growing antagonism to any British measure.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-884e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">In the economic sphere recent happenings at the Homag Works in Kiel have served to underline the widely held. belief that British punitive measures will extend to any sphere which shows signs of an economic revival. "Britain is in­sistent on strangling any attempt on the part of Germany to resurrect her industrial life" is frequently heard. The Hannover Nesse has acquired the popular name of "Demontage Nesse" and it is cynically observed that producers should exercise care in exhibiting their products if they wish to avoid having their factories closed down under the guise of reparations because of the com­petition they may give to British factories.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-894e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">Sentences passed by Military Government Courts for theft from British premises are generally considered too severe. It is held that provision should be made for a scale of punishment which takes into account the urgency of im­mediate need (as in German Law).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8a4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">It is claimed that train loads of oil products are passing through Harburg en route to Buchholz where huge quantities of allegedly unusable oils are destroyed by fire. It is understood that the oil was originally meant for use in flame throwers, for which purpose it is no longer considered suitable. public opinion is convinced that German industry could fine ways and means of utilising these oils but that the British would rather destroy it than put it at their disposal. hhh 9. DENAZIFICATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8b4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">As an item of topical interest denazification has been forced into the background by more immediate concerns. Two years of denazification have disillusioned those who hoped for a cleansing of the political and social atmos­phere. Much of their original enthusiasm has given way to cynicism and dis­trust and the belief is general that former Nazis as a group have done far better than they could have expected_ Individual cases of apparent injustice have fostered these beliefs and it is felt that many guilty and. responsible Nazis are going soot free whilst great numbers of nominal Nazis continue to pay the full price for their inability to evade the consequences of our Denazi­fication policy. While a minority still hope that the authentic purpose of denazification nay yet be achieved when the process passes wholly into German hands, the majority favour the natural death of a policy which has already been irrevocably compromised by greed, self-interest and other forms of subjective and. objective corruption. Many look upon denazification as nothing more than an unconscious part of their daily life which has long since lost any indepen­dent purpose or significance. hhh 10. SUBVERSIVE ACTIVITIES</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8c4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">While there is no tangible evidence of subversive organisations having mushroomed during recent weeks, there is no doubt that there is a growing and general antagonism towards the British. This antagonism is accentuated in those who have waited for this general trend to come about and who are now leading ending to it a touch of aggression and challenge. This is noticeable principally the greater readiness and frankness with which groups of people band together and avow their dislike and scorn both of the British and Germans promin­ent in public affairs who are striving to guide Germany along democratic lines. This greater freedom of expression often assumes a provocative character which meets with the passive approval of many. It appears that many of the younger elements consider the time ripe for a show of unmistakable defiance and that they are meeting with a great measure of support in their "daring" attempts to test the limits of British tolerance and forbearance. It is considered that this tendency will have to be carefully watched and active occurrences firmly handled lest they infect the maw passive sympathisers into active co-operation. hhh 11. PRISONERS OF WAR</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8d4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">German impatience is growing in respect of the return of German POWs to Germany. Criticism, which was most commonly applied to Russia is now also extended to the British and, in greater measure, to the French. It is reasoned that the retention of POWs two years after the cessation of hostili­ties is in violation of International Law and. constitutes a modern form of slavery. Although the Americans have shipped back all POWs from U.S. it is remembered that many were handed over to the British and French.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">Treatment of POWs in the U.K. is considered good. but it is claimed that Garman prisoners in the Middle East have many justifiable complaints and that in some cases former Nazis have been favoured over anti-Nazis as regards treat­ment and final release. It is frequently heard that the POWs in France are very badly off and frequently subjected to maltreatment and that the large intakes of former German POWs into the French Foreign Legion, in which Germans are now said to number 80%, have resulted from a cloture of persuasion and the desire to escape further brutalities. There is strong feeling that the time has come for the early return of all POWs even in the face of the existing shortage of clothing, housing and other necessities. hhh 12. ESCAPEES FROM THE RUSSIAN ZONE</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">While public opinion in Hamburg is fully informed of the growing number of Germans who illegally enter the British Zone from the East, it is convinced that the British and American Authorities are causing their arrest for illegal entry and deportation to the Russian Zone without trial. There are a considerable number of Germane who suspect that many persons entering the British Zone have been delegated with special tasks and orders by the Russians. hhh 13. ECONOMY</note>
				<note xml:id="q-904e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">The hopes raised in business circles by the Marshall Plan have given way to skepticism concerning the desire of Britain to further economic recovery in Germany. The intention of re-establishing German production to the 1936 level is rejected in the absence of even elementary progress. Many people believe that the Hannover Fair has served the hidden purpose of gauging the recovery potential of German industry and that the necessary freedom of action consistent with real progress will not be forthcoming. It is generally accepted that suf­ficient coal is being produced now to get German factories going again but that British bad faith and muddle combine to deprive Germany of this essential ingredient of industrial life.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-914e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">While the Holmag case holds pride of place in most discussions, en analo­gous case is cited which concerns a comb factory in Braunschweig. It is said that this factory, which was never used for any kind of war production, was recently occupied by British troops solely to help a British competitor. Simi­lar conditions are made to have obtained in the case of a factory producing fountain pens.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-924e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">A recent rise in shares of the Deutsche Werft and Gutehoffnungshdate, which are closely connected, is reported to be due to the Deutsche Werft having received an American order for the construction of two 10,000 ton tankers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-934e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">Complaints continue that Hansamuhle is being prevented by Military Govern-seat from producing substitute foodstuffs (for which it is excellently equipped) by having to eke out a precarious existence by filling tar from tank trains into barrels.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-944e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">It is reported that several highly qualified foremen and technicians from the Howaldswerft, Hamburg, have left Hamburg for Berlin without collecting their work papers or pay. It is believed that these workmen were under orders to go to Berlin from where they would be sent to Yugoslavia for employment in Fiume or Pole- Employers fear that other Hamburg shipyards may suffer similar losses, especially as a number of top personnel have been enquiring as to conditions under which they could take up employment elsewhere. hhh 14. RUMOURS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-954e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">Among the many rumours dealing with threatened war, the following persist:- That the former German General Ramcke is in the U.S.A. training paratroopers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-964e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">That a ship carrying 3,000 Germans in British Army uniforms has left a British Zone port for Greece.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-974e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">That a great number of ships have recently docked in Bremen carrying vast consignments of uniforms and other military equipment and that these are then loaded on to trains and taken to Hanau-on-Main.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-984e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">That former German naval officers are being assembled at Neuengamme C.I.C. where they are held for a week and questioned concerning their former politics and present sympathies; that they are requested to state their preference between Greece and Turkey, given a physical examination and informed that the British have been forced to adopt this course in view of similar action having been taken by the Russians in the Eastern Zone. It is claimed that weekly batches have been arriving in Neuenganme over the last six weeks.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-994e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">That the Russians have considerably widened and. deepened the tank ditches along the Russian/British frontier, particularly in the Province of Mechlenburg.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">Other rumours are:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">German fishermen have been forced to transport part of their catch to England.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">That farmers have been requested. to give up a number of their turkeys alive allegedly because of feeding difficulties but that in fact they are earmarked for Christens consumption in Britain.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9d4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">That farmers in the district of Stade have been refusing fruit to the Germans on the pretext that they have been forbidden to do so by the British who wanted it for themselves.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9e4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">That the former Field Marshal Paulus is in Berlin organising a new party for the Eastern Zone whose task it will be to adopt policies more moderate than those of the S .D . An official denial issued from Berlin has met with general scepticism</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9f4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">That the Americans have charged Dr. Schacht with working out a new financial system and it is only a matter of time until he returns to public life to trans­late his theories into practice.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a04e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">That a rumour is rampant in the Russian Zone that statements made to British authorities by escapees from the Russian Zone are being forwarded to Russian agencies. miscellaneous</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a14e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">German expert opinion is again busy claiming that the lone dry spell is a direct result of the large scale deforestation which has taken place. Next Year's prospects are bleak in view of the shortages of young trees which makes it impossible to renew large scale planting. Large districts will therefore suffer a reduction in soil fertility and great tracts will be turning into steppe or desert land.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a24e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">Much irritation is caused by the Allied refusal to allow German participa­tion in whaling and Atlantic fishing operations. It is considered that to permit this would not involve the Allies in any expense and would, at the same time do much to assist the food position.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a34e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">The Deutscher Pressedienst is believed to have an unduly large number of former naval officers on its staff. Some speak of the office as the 'Brawn House" because the possession of a militarist attitude is thought to be more important than the necessary professional qualifications.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a44e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="76">Deputy Inspector General</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a54e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="77">Public Safety</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a64e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="78">JT/SL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a74e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="79">Copy to: The Inspector General.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a84e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="80">The Regional Governmental Officer.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a94e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="81">The Regional Intelligence Officer.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-aa4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="82">J.R. White, Esq.,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ab4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="83">Public Opinion Research Office,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ac4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="84">Governmental Sub-Commission,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ad4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="85">67 HQ C.C.G.,BIELEFELD</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ae4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="86">BAOR.</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>