<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Monthly Report on Morale and Public Opinion - December 1947</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-33235f79-6f90-4476-b568-6abf58f10bb7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-7add1cdc-96ca-42f0-8917-d4653b38125e</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-144e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="1">Tele: 34 10 00</note>
				<note xml:id="q-154e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="2">Ext 8500</note>
				<note xml:id="q-164e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">Public Safety HQ Hansestadt HAMBURG</note>
				<note xml:id="q-174e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="4">609 HQ CCG (HE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-184e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="5">BAOR 3</note>
				<note xml:id="q-194e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="6">609/PS/S/12/7</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1a4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="7">30 December 1947</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1b4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="8">Subject: - Monthly Report on Morale and Public Opinion - December</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1c4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="9">The Regional Commissioner</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1d4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="10">HQ Hansestadt HAMBURG</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1e4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="11">609 HQ CCG (BE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1f4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="12">BAOR 3 hhh General</note>
				<note xml:id="q-204e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">1. During the last four weeks public opinion and morale, already very low owing to past physical and psychological strains, was most decisive­ly influenced by the various stages through which the London Conference of Foreign Ministers passed to its jarring and sobering finale. Now that the many disturbing and threatening implications of its failure are beginning to sink in, the population is abandoning itself to a climactic sense of despair and foreboding hitherto unreached. Prayer and cynicism together with a bitter awareness of dependence and impotence marked the opening of the Conference and accompanied it along its agonised and frustrated way to a burial with little hope of resurrection. To-day it is appreciated that the end of Germany's bitter road is not yet in sight and that it is entering a new and difficult year poorer in physical strength and moral resistance, in national and social purposes and in faith and hope.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-214e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">2. Few view the outcome of the Conference otherwise than as the begin­ning of a series of trials which are unpredictable both as to direction and ultimate result. No one doubts, however, that the slow and painful beginning made, principally by the Anglo-Saxon powers, to recast Germany in a new democratic Europe will be halted, and perhaps completely nulli­fied, by the march of events.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-224e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">3. In the field of immediate concerns it is realised that the break-down of the Conference spells the end of earlier hopes for a unified Germany under a Central Government - a Germany whose economic and social needs might have been better served without the restricting effects of conflicting Zonal directions in the field of industry and agriculture, finance and exports and on recovery in every sphere of national, social and moral health. Hopes for the miraculous restoration of Germany's eastern provinces have now entirely faded in the face of present develop­ments which have even put to question the efficacy of the Marshall Plan to bring stability to an uneasy Western Europe.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-234e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">4. In fact, few believe the Western Allies to be in a position to enforce and sustain, if necessary in precarious balance, policies and decisions which would not only safeguard German interests in Western Europe but from which a gradual shift to more favourable balance might be expected. It is felt that the main strength of power and resolve must come from the U.S.A., that Britain, even in conjunction with her European Allies, could not hope to answer single-handed and successfully a determined challenge. The U.S A. is remote, the U.S.S.R. in close proximity. These facts, plus German appreciation of Russian strength and concentration of purpose, of her material, human and political resources and the subversive potential which flows from them, are the principal factors activating German fears.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-244e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">5. There can be little doubt that the people of Hamburg are badly frightened by the prospects of a development which it is felt may in its consequences surpass the experiences of the past two and a half years. A small minority which, even against instinct and painful realisation, had had visions of a new and democratic Germany, now see their broader hopes endangered. The majority exhaust their desperate anxiety which often borders on silent panic, in an inarticulate and morale destroying concern for the future.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-254e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">6. In this crisis, few are inclined to weigh anew whether conviction and/or expediency do not demand a strengthening of ties to the Occupying Power whose natural affinities with Western Germany remain, or should have remained, unaffected by the criticism and distrust with which many of its single measures have been met. But the great majority have sunk to a state where lack of hope, and cynicism, the bitter fruits of frustra­tion, have long since convinced then that every nation's interests and purposes are essentially selfish and that democracy, if not an outright sham, is only for those who can afford it.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-264e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">7. Consciousness of their dependence in every sphere, hating their role as an object in this conflict and in general, the German feel abandoned and ostracized. Irrespective of developments in other fields, this alone constitutes a grave danger. hhh FOOD</note>
				<note xml:id="q-274e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">8. The food position in Hamburg has progressively worsened during the last six weeks; resulting hardships are accentuated by thoughts of other Christmasses in happier times. The situation is further aggravated by growing difficulties in obtaining such rations as are available. As always, the general morale is vitally affected by conditions in this respect and is, in consequence, extremely low.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-284e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">9. The growing bitterness and distrust of the population in respect of the food situation is mainly directed to the farmers and shopkeepers. The farmer is accused of contributing heavily to the Black Market and therefore being unable and unwilling to deliver his quota. The shop­keeper is charged with becoming more and more inconsiderate of the popu­lation generally and with being involved in Black Market practices and the giving of preferential treatment for his own selfish ends.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-294e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">10. Principal complaints centre on the insufficient provision of fats, the entire absence of potatoes for the last six or eight weeks and failure to provide substitutes or equivalents for these two vital food­stuffs. There is also a great deal of discontent because the issue of milk powder and egg powder for which the population registered four weeks ago, have not yet materialised. The situation is aggravated by the fact that many shops have been stocked with milk powder for approximately one month. Rumour has it that supplies of milk powder from, U.S.A have already deteriorated to such an extent that they are now only fit for the production of margarine. While the remainder of rationed food­stuffs have more or less been constantly available, further shortages in addition to the present principal ones are anticipated. This applies particularly to the meat ration which it is though will be endangered when the supply from recent peak slaughterings is exhausted arid the provision of cereals which, it is believed, will be seriously affected by coal shortages.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">11. Generally, it is felt that Hamburg as a declared emergency area is being mocked by an array of facts which contradict her status and widen the discrepancy between conditions prevailing within the Hansestadt and those outside her immediate boundaries.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">12. A special feature of the present position is that the first time since they were issued, this month's heavy workers rations were often unavailable. hhh FUEL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2c4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">13. In contrast to the food position, there has been a marked improve­ment in the supply of fuel to private households as compared with last winter. This is due both to better supplies and the less severe weather. However, complaints continue in respect of the frequent and irregular interruptions in electricity supplies.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">14. In consequence of the leak of fuel, many laundries are refusing to take work. In view of the shortage of soap and the rationing and fre­quent unavailability of electricity and gas, this poses a special problem for the much harassed housewife.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">15. Hamburg opticians who require regulated room temperature for the carrying out of certain processes are complaining that they are receiv­ing no fuel. They point out that many email industries producing un­essential items such as ashtrays, etc., are receiving fuel while their profession, which serves in the interests of public health, is left without. hhh PUBLIC HEALTH</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">16. Continuous and long term malnutrition, deplorable housing conditions, shortages of clothing, soap and hot water, etc., is causing great concern to the Public Health Authorities. It has been feared for some time that T.B. has reached frightening dimensions from which permanent damage will result. It is known that the number of active T.B. cases and deaths at­tributable to T.B. continue to rise. It is doubted whether the total number of persons who are so far only slightly infected with T.B. is known. Hamburg Public Health Authorities have made considerable efforts to detect T.B. in its early stages by X-raying whole groups of the popu­lation. It is claimed, however, that these activities are seriously hampered by shortages of X-ray films and fuel for those places in which T.B. examinations take place.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-304e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">17. Similar anxieties are entertained with regard to venereal diseases. It is thought that cases of syphilis are on the increase. However, the number of cases of gonorrhea is declining and this is popularly attri­buted to regular and growing supplies of penicillin. hhh HOUSING AND REQUISITIONING</note>
				<note xml:id="q-314e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">18. The recent announcement that further living accommodation was being requisitioned in Othmarschen, Hochkamp and Rahlstedt has caused such comment. There is still a widespread belief that many houses and flats requisitioned a considerable time ago have never been put to use. In­stances cited concern one house in Othiearschen, Hagedornstrasse 6, (uninhabited since August 1946); 17 three-roomed flats in Kochmannstr. uninhabited since February 1947; 10 eight-roomed flats in Oderfelderstr. uninhabited since May 1947. further uninhabited living accommodation is said to be located. in Badestrasse and Innocentiastrasse. It is observed that requisitionings continue in spite of Burgermeister BRAUER's request for Military Government to refrain from requisitioning new premises be­fore the available accommodation has been fully occupied. The announcement has also served to keep alive complaints that only a fraction of the Four Seasons Hotel is being utilized. hhh BUILDING</note>
				<note xml:id="q-324e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">19. While old and oft-reiterated complaints as to the state of building and repairs in Hamburg live on, repeated attention has been drawn lately to the to the fact that many houses (especially emergency accommodation, are still without window-panes, whereas cinemas, theatres, restaurants and shop windows have largely been restored. It is also complained that a number of vacant houses and new buildings have been fully glazed in spite of the fact that few old people and children have been living in houses which are inadequately provided with glass. This has been taken as a further indication that German Local Authorities are either without a plan or governed by instructions which ignore the public welfare. hhh CLOTHING</note>
				<note xml:id="q-334e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">20. Next to food and fuel, clothing and household articles are of principal concern. The existing situation where the few available goods appear to go to the highest bidder remains unchanged. As old stocks wear out, the clamour for better supplies of everyday commodi­ties swells. It appears that much of its force is no longer exclusively directed against Military Government but that the German Authorities are coming in for an ever-growing share of criticism.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-344e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">21. With the advent of winter, the footwear situation has been worsened. The shoe repair shops are unable to cope with public requirements and still less able to adhere to prices fixed for the carrying out of repairs. Materials can often only be acquired on the Black Market and prices are raised accordingly. Promised fuel for the heating of repair shops has so far failed to materialize and if fuel is purchased on the Black Market; the customer has to foot the bill.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-354e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">22. The fish and affiliated industries are suffering from a shortage of rubber footwear and waterproof garments. It is claimed that the Hamburg firm of ELSNER recently offered certain quantities of rubbers and wooden shoes to a number of firms but the firms in question were unable to persuade the Landeswirtschaftsamt to issue the required number of coupons. This attitude is not understood by the general public. A great measure of public opinion, not unsupported by various Landeswirtschaftsdmter, favours the removal of controls on kettles, buckets, saucepans, bowls, frying pans, cutlery, stoves, electric heaters, wooden bedsteads, radio valves, perambulators, clocks, razor blades, shoe laces, etc. This feeling is based on the argument that these goods are either available in sufficient quantities or in such short supply that the expense of administering their control is economically unjustified.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-364e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">23. The paper shortage continues to have an adverse effect on education in that the demand for school manuals and exercise book's remains far in excess of supply. Paper shortages are also said to be responsible for the fact that the Largest of the six match factories in the British Zone is working to only 50% of its capacity. hhh BLACK MARKET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-374e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">24. Complaints continue that it is possible to obtain the best of food, wines and spirits in the Hamburg restaurants at Black Market prices. Prices are said to range from RM 20 for a cup of coffee to brandy at RM350 per bottle.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-384e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">25. In general a good deal of talk has been heard to the effect that black marketeers have over-estimated the buying power of the population and that many are finding it difficult to dispose of their goods at current high prices.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-394e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">26. The finger of suspicion has been frequently pointed to the German Courts where, it is believed, black marketeers are not only leniently treated but find the kind of assistance which implies corruption of judges and court officials.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3a4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">27. The dinner given by the trade unions to the Chamber of Commerce a few weeks ago, at which several courses of excellent quality and quantity together with fine old wines were served, has caused some curiosity as to the origin of these supplies. It is said that the dinner took place at the Hauptbahnhof restaurant which was well-known in peacetime for the excellence of its cuisine. Some believe that the food and wines were made available by the Hamburg Co-operative Society.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3b4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">28. Wage and salary earners continue to complain that travel to and from work is made difficult by the number of persons undertaking non­essential journeys. It frequently has been suggested that Railway Com­panies should run trains with special coaches or compartments reserved for season ticket holders. The consensus of opinion seems to be that the Occupational Authorities are deliberately trying to curb rail traf­fic by keeping trains as uncomfortable and train schedules as inconveni­ent as possible. hhh MILITARY GOVERNMENT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3c4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">29. Following the trial of the former Hamburg Oberlandesgerichts President, Kurt ROTHENBERGER, at Nuremberg, considerable attention has been given to the clearing of Nazi traces and influences from the German legal world. The consensus of opinion is that military Government has been badly advised in these matters and true to its maxim "Control not Government" should have left it to the Germans to take the necessary action.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3d4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">30. As an example, the case of the former Hamburger General Staatsanwalt HAACK is cited. Many Hamburgers expected to see HAACK on trial at Nurem­berg instead of which he was interned for a short time and was, it is claimed, then confirmed by Military Government as legal adviser in Neuengamme to internees appearing before the Spruchkammer at Bergedorf. Further, that owing to German pressure this confirmation was later withdrawn. Nevertheless, a point is made that HAACK, who must have enjoyed the special confidence of the Nazi regime to have been entrusted with clearing up the murder of HEYDRICH in the former German Protectorate of Bohemia, was sufficiently and clearly "compromised' to such a degree as to preclude him from any possible consideration by Military Government.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3e4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">31. A recent order that all cigars and cigarettes and all coffee over one kilo in weight sent to Germans from abroad will be confiscated is meeting with violent reaction. A number of tense confiscations have already taken place and those who are left with a Military Government receipt in place of the tobacco or coffee feel that they nave additional cause for being critical, if not openly hostile to Military Government. hhh LOCAL AUTHORITIES</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3f4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">32. Complaints and criticism of German local Authorities are increasing rather than decreasing. The Landeswirtschaftsamt remain the principal target and is often contemptuously spoken of as "hiding behind Minden or the British". It is also accused of being the special preserve for func­tionaries of the S.P.D. and Herr BORGENER's statement that it would be impossible to distribute American relief supplies by Christmas has cer­tainly not lessened public distrust.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-404e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">33. Lack of bicycle tyres, of which more are thought to reach the Black Market than the free market, has been singled out as a further proof of the inefficiency and/or corruption prevalent in many German agencies. The Phonix Works at Harburg are frequently mentioned in this connection.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-414e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">34. Burgermeister BRAUER's pointed reference to the over-staffed administrative machinery of the Hansestadt (50,000 persons working for the Hansestadt - 50,000 for Military Government) in a recent speech to an S.P D. meeting was well received, as it gave support to the belief that a dominating bureaucracy has installed itself in civic affairs to the detriment of the common wea1d</note>
				<note xml:id="q-424e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">35. A measure of public hope and confidence is attached to the return of Dt. WOHLWILL from his London exile and it is anticipated that he will be able to restore the Hamburg legal administration to a semblance of its former high reputation. hhh DENAZIFICATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-434e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">36. In the field of denazification growing numbers of the population either show a complete lack of interest provided, they can afford it, or view its gymnastics with increasing cynicism and distrust. Many Denazification Panel members appear to share this general weariness mainly for the reason that their decisions and recommendations are nullified or ignored by decisions on appeal to Review Boards. It is claimed that Review Boards are susceptible to considerations which defeat the whole purpose of Denazification and that the presence of legally qualified. persons acting as judges or defending counsel make hearings the occasion for legal exercise at the expense of their proper political and social functions. The best legal talent is enlisted in cases where the property or wealth of former Nazis is involved and no expense is spared in these cases where there is a reasonable hope of safeguarding or recovering the principal part of the value at stake.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-444e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">37. Criticism is also directed at Spruchkammern whose sentences are either thought to be too lenient or too easily reduced on an appeal supported by the best legal minds. It is often commented that many solicitors of whom not a few are former "nominal" members of the N.S.D.A.P. are very busy attempting to rehabilitate former active Nazis and not in-frequently give written testimonials in their favour. All this under­lines a tendency which has been known to exist for a long time that not inconsiderable numbers of the population are by no means adverse to restoring former Nazis to their full social status and desire to be on good terms with them. hhh SUBVERSIVE ACTIVITIES</note>
				<note xml:id="q-454e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">38. Nothing has come to notice which would point to an increase in organised subversive activities on the part of former Nazis. Opinion which is concerned with this danger inclines to the view that such circles of Nazis that remain intact have called for a moratorium in view of the present international situation. It is felt that this abstention is conditioned in the belief that critical issues are imminent and that it is preferable to conserve all energies for a later date. hhh REFUGEES AND EXPELLEES</note>
				<note xml:id="q-464e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">39. It is generally believed that the breakdown of the London Confer­ence will result in the British and American Zones being swamped by large numbers of refugees from the Russian zone. If this occurs it is unlikely that these people will meet with much sympathy from an indigent population which has been hardened to a point of insensibility to the distress of others by the may personal difficulties and frustrations of the last few years.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-474e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">40. Meanwhile, former residents of the German eastern provinces complain that German banks in Hamburg are refusing to honour claims to funds deposited in their branch banks located in these territories. The hardship is undeniable, the clamour understandable. hhh ECONOMY</note>
				<note xml:id="q-484e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">41. The state of business and the morale of businessmen are equally affected by the present impasse and the political developments of the past few weeks. Hopes for an economic recovery are being threatened by the possibility of a new conflagration which many fearfully prophesy. Meanwhile most businessmen live from hand to mouth and almost all current business activity is characterised by practices and conditions which an ordered economy would not tolerate.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-494e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">42. Note is being taken of an increase of advertisements offering good positions to German technicians and other skilled workers particularly in South America. Most of these advertisements appear under box numbers and it appears that serious consideration is being given to the taking up of such employment especially by young men and women, graduates from universities', technical institutes, etc., who, under present conditions, have little faith in making a future for themselves in Germany.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4a4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">43. Hamburg exporters claim that the bureaucratic confusion within the Joint Export Import Agency is so great that contacts made with business­men abroad fail to produce results as most foreign businessmen refuse to be hamstrung by the J.E.I.A.S. exasperating methods.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">44. Businessman also condemn the special consideration given to Co-operative Societies in the allocation of supplies (allegedly as means of rehabilitating their business) and the levying of taxes. They hold that all business has been hard-hit by the war and its aftermath and that the practice of favouring socialized enterprises is a denial of democracy and the principles of free economy alike. hhh POLICE</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">45. There has been surprisingly little attention paid to the handing over of control of the Hamburg Police. This may be due to the fact that the population in general are not yet sufficiently aware or proud of the Police as a Hamburg institution to follow their development with much interest. Criticism of the Police continues to the effect that many of its members are too young and inexperienced to guide and help a "jittery" population and that the Force still contains many in its ranks who are open to graft and corruption. A number have remarked that the brusque attitude of officers towards the other ranks which formerly characterised the German police is again becoming apparent and that the relationship between higher and lower officials is deteriorating as a result.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">46. Many rumours continue to circulate to the effect that the lack of security in the streets at night is so considerable that many citizens either do not leave their houses after dark or traverse the streets armed with sticks, clubs, etc. The number of robberies is probably considerably less than is popularly imagined. The public believes that they are carried out mainly with the object of obtaining clothing. hhh EDUCATION AND YOUTH</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">47. Senator LANDAHL, Head of the Hamburg Schulverwaltung, is the target for a good deal of criticism. A great many leading educationalists including the head of the Volkshochschul, VOGT, and Professor MERCK, have violently clashed with LANDAHL. It is generally believed that LANDAHL would not have obtained his present position if he had not joined the S.P.D. He is charged with autocratic and overbearing conduct and appears to antagonise many of his subordinates by his vanity and reluctance to delegate responsibility.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">48. Mention has been made of young students, especially of the technical sciences, who are unable to chart their way after taking their final examinations. Most of them have no chance of obtaining the type of employment for which they have prepared and are forced to work either as artisans or labourers to qualify for rations. It is thought that good conditions of employment are being offered to those who are prepared to emigrate to the Russian Zone. Up to now few have done so. hhh PRESS AND WIRELESS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-504e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">49. While it is generally acknowledged that the press of the British Zone enjoys a measure of freedom in reporting and commenting on news, it is felt that the total number of copies of newspapers is insufficient and that the restricted size of newspapers prohibits full coverage being given to news, etc. This perpetuates the question as to whether the quantity of paper available to the British Zone is allocated in a manner which helps to serve primary interests and concerns before secondary ones. It is often said that more and larger newspapers and more and better literature could be made available if less paper were wasted in publishing fashion magazines, popular lyrics and crossword puzzles, etc. which appear to be available in unlimited quantities.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-514e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">50. Suggestions continue to be made to the effect that "Die Brucke", which is widely considered a useful and worthwhile instrument in the furtherance of German understanding of foreign and international problems, should have a number of branches established throughout the Hansestadt. This military Government experiment is one of the few which has met with the wholehearted approval of the Germans. hhh RUMOURS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-524e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">51. Lately, there has been a dearth of rumours and this fact has not remained unnoticed in Hamburg. The absence of rumours has been attributed to general apathy and the prevailing state of resignation. It is also taken as a sign of the prevalence of a form of exhaustion in which rumour and humour alike no longer play their part as a means of relief. hhh MISCELLANEOUS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-534e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">52. Comment continues that many former Nazis and professional soldiers are succumbing to concentrated French efforts to recruit them into the Foreign Legion. It is frequently said that decent Germans are finding it difficult to go abroad while German war criminals are offered refuge putting them outside the reach of German justice.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-544e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">53. A rumour to the effect that the Waiting Room at Altona Station which is now being used as a canteen for troops and other allied personnel is being returned to the Germans shortly, has found a sympathetic ear. It is believed that the present canteen is being moved to the Café HIRTE which as at present being run by an old National Socialist and profiteer of the Hitler regime.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-554e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">54. A number of unusually well-informed people claim to know that approximately three months ago, 35 former U-boat commanders were moved to No. 6 C.I.C Neuengamme. Soon after their arrival, they learned through the camp grapevine that they would be asked whether they were prepared to serve a foreign power in the event of war; and oath of silence on the matter would be imposed on them. Before the interview a meeting was held in the Camp in which a Nazi leader enjoined them to answer the question in the negative. It is said that this advice was accepted and that as a result they were subjected to a torrent of abuse from the British Camp Sergeant.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-564e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="67">J.D.Stewart</note>
				<note xml:id="q-574e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="68">Deputy Inspector General</note>
				<note xml:id="q-584e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="69">Public Safety</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>