<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Home Intelligence Weekly Report - No. 212 - 26 October 1944</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-9935f3e1-21b0-48a4-a818-680eef23f296</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-cd5de499-73d1-421b-9911-35e4afc65371</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-cd497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ce497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cf497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="3">HOME INTELLIGENGE WEEKLY REPORT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d0497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="4">No.212.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d1497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="5">26th October, 1944:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d2497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">Covering period from 17th to 24th October, 1944</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d3497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="7">I. GENERAL COMMENTS hhh 1. General</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d4497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">Confidence and determination remain firm, but optimism has yet further receded. Only a very few still hope for a "pre-Christmas miracle" in the form of a sudden German collapse; the great majority do not expect peace in Europe till spring or early summer.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d5497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">The familiar list of sobering factors now includes the weather, which is regarded both as depressing at home and helpful to the enemy in the Low Countries and Italy. War weariness and tiredness arer eported.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d6497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">Home Front subjects appear to be more talked about than war events and there is still much discussion of the mining and fuel situations, housing and employment prospects, Italian prisoners of war and clothing. The promise of extra foods for Christmas has, however, given great pleasure. hhh 2. The battle for Germany</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d7497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">Although there is still disappointment at the slower progress, and come are surprised at the toughness Of German resistance, there is now a general realisation of difficulties, and great admiration and sympathy for our men; and although people expect a big attach soon, they also anticipate very severe fighting.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d8497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">Reasons for present and anticipated difficulties are thought to be:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d9497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">(a) The bad weather - "Hitler's most successful weapon".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-da497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">(b) The difference between progress in friendly and hostile country.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-db497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">(c) Supply problems.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">There is discussion also of the possibility of guerrilla fight­ing developing in parts of Germany which have been captured; tackling this will, it is thought, be a big job.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">Holland: Sympathy and anxiety continue. There is some disappointment that progress, especially in the Scheldt area, is not faster.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">Aachen: The fall of Aachen was welcomed, though with no excitement. Many say the war is by no means over, if all German towns are going to hold out in this Way. Some criticism of the truce continues, though people were pleased with the devastation which followed, because "it will show we mean business" and, it is hoped, will affect the Germans' will to resist.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">The bombing of Germany: Widespread approval of the speed-up. People think it must affect</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e0497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">German morale and will shorten the war. Some are amazed at the way the Germans stand up to bombing; a few are sympathetic.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e1497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">Arnhem: Considerable comment and regret on familiar lines.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e2497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">Formation of German Home Guard: People think this is a sign of German desperation - but also of their determination to fight to the bitter end. It is not thought the new organisation will be of more than minor military value.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e3497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">H.H. the King's visit to the battle areas: Pleasure and admiration are reported.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e4497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">Prefabricated harbours: Interest and amazement.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e5497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">Dunkirk: A few people ask why there is so little news about progress hero and what is the reason for the delay.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e6497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">British casualties: A few express relief at the Comparatively light casualties up to the end of August.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e7497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13) hhh 2a. Attitude to Germany and the Germans</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e8497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">The usual comment continues unabated; the only new reaction being approval (Seven Regions) of the resolutions on this question of the Trades Union Congress (October 18).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e9497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">1.2.3.4.6.7.8.9.10.11.13) hhh 2b. Conditions in liberated countries</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ea497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">Resentment and bewilderment continue. People would like more accurate first-hand information about the true position. Meanwhile they remain bitter, thinking, that supplies of food and clothing "which we need" are being sent to the French and Belgians, who are believed to have been better off than us.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-eb497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">Women will not knit garments for children on the Continent because they say the need of children here is greater; they angrily add that wool of the quality supplied for this purpose is quite unobtainable in the shops. There is similar comment about the making of toys for French children by Women's Institutes.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ec497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">Stories and pictures of fashion parades and race. meetings in Paris continue to irritate.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ed497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">A rumour that silk stockings and "beautiful lingerie" are being sent from this country to the Balkans and France is reported from two Regions; it is felt to be most unfair.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ee497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">Some think supplies are really needed in. Europe - at any rate in Greece.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ef497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11) hhh 2c. France</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f0497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">Preliminary reactions to the recognition of General de Gaulle's administration on October 23rd are of pleasure.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f1497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">However, General de Gaulle's broadcast (October 14) caused irritation and anxiety (Seven Regions), though a few people accuse the press of giving garbled- versions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f2497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">Some distrust of, and antagonism to, France arc reported (Three Regions), chiefly on grounds of ingratitude and lack of help to the Allies.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f3497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">(1.2.5.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12) hhh 3. The Moscow talks</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f4497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">Reactions are very similar to last week's. There is, however, increased comment to the effect that Hr. Churchill always has to do the running about and that it is high time "the others came here" ­as the Prime Minister's many journeys involve a risk both to his health and to British prestige. At the same time there is great admiration for his "boundless energy" and appreciation for his efforts to promote good understanding among the Allies. People note the warm reception the Prime Minister received, the apparently cordial relations between him and Marshal Stalin and the letter's tribute to Allied achievements on the western front; and they hope that Anglo-Russian relations will have been improved by the meeting.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f5497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">The Russo-Polish dispute is generally thought to be the-Main reason for the conference. There is a widespread hope that an amicable settlement will result; great faith is placed in the Prime Minister's intervention as helping to provide a solution. A good many, however, are doubtful, fearing either that the question has not been settled or that only a surface settlement has been reached.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f6497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">The whole issue between Russia and Poland is one about which people arc bewildered and uneasy. Opinion is very mixed: on the one hand, sympathy for the Poles, distrust of Russia and a conviction that she could have prevented "the dreadful slaughter in Warsaw"; on the other, deep admiration for the Russians (particularly from the Protestant working class) , criticism of the Polish government in London and a tendency to be ".fed up with all Poles".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f7497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13) hhh 3a. Russia</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f8497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">The Russian drive into East Prussia has greatly pleased and cheered people - the more so as some had feared the Russians would rest content with the recovery of their own frontiers, while others had begun to think that they were holding back for political reasons.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f9497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">The Balkans: The liberation, of Belgrade is acclaimed, though there is some confusion about the fighting in the Balkans and better maps are wanted.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fa497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">Hungary: People are far from clear about the situation in Hungary, but the general impression is that the present "chaotic position" is more favourable to the than to the Germans. There is said to be little sympathy for the Hungarians.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fb497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.6.9.10.11.12.13) hhh 4. Greece</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fc497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">Widespread relief and pleasure continue at the landing in Greece and the liberation of Athens. People are pleased we have at last been able to do something for the Greek people, and that the liberation has been an "all-British" one.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fd497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">There is warm sympathy for the Greeks, and it is hoped that food and medical supplies will not be long in reaching them.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fe497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">Political: The political situation continues to cause uneasiness and bewilderment; people hope the internal differences will soon be settled. Some distrust of the King of the Hellenes is reported.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ff497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13) hhh 5. Italy</note>
				<note xml:id="q-004a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">Military Comment is again limited. Disappointment about slow progress and commiseration over the "frightful weather conditions" continue. At the same time, people realise that the campaign is holding down enemy divisions which otherwise might be used profit­ably elsewhere.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-014a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">The attitude of the Government towards "our former enemies" continues to be watched with suspicion. Comment is on familiar lines. hhh (1.2.3.4.5.7.8.9.10.11.12)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-024a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">5a. Italian prisoners of war</note>
				<note xml:id="q-034a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">Resentment at the "pampering" and "preferential treatment" of Italian prisoners is fairly widespread, and in two Regions is thought to be increasing. Some say there is strong feeling among our fighting men and repatriated prisoners.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-044a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">The chief complaints are again of: (i) too much liberty generally, including freedom to go to dances and cinemas; (ii) luxury travel facilities as compared with "queuing, overcrowding and the dirty vehicles to which civilians are condemned"; (iii) good house accommodation, when so many bombed-out people are putting up with temporary billets, leaky roofs, etc.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-054a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">People continue to say the Italians should be sent to help in the liberation of their own country..."If they are allies they should be fighting; if not, they should be prisoners".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-064a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">The Italians themselves are criticised for their behaviour with girls - though the girls themselves are censured - and for their laziness and "swanky" attitude.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-074a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">Appreciation of the help given to farmers is, however, reported (Two Regions), though it is also suggested they should be made to work harder on' the potato and beet harvest.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-084a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">(1.2.5.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12) hhh 6. Flying bombs</note>
				<note xml:id="q-094a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">Though comment has again declined, concern continues. It is thought that since the missiles are now launched from aircraft, there is no reason why the Germans should not attack any part of Eastern Britain between Aberdeen and London.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0a4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">Criticism continues of Mr. Duncan Sandys' speech.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0b4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">Reactions from target areas</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0c4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">Eastern Region: Uneasiness and weariness continue. People fear the attacks may go on for a long time yet. While many take them philosophically, some nervousness is apparent; this is attributed both to war weariness and to the shattering of people's belief - encouraged by official statements - that the menace was past. Some people still get up at night during the alerts, and children arrive at school very tired.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0d4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">Where flying bombs have fallen, there has been surprise at the few casualties caused. There is great pleasure that so many have been shot down.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0e4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">London Region: The continuance of raids appears to be accepted philosophically now; most people are sleeping in their beds again. A number are, however, disappointed and some are anxious. It is wondered how long the attacks will last....."until Holland is cleared", or longer still.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0f4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">Criticism is made of the publication of details of flaws in the flying bomb, as it is thought this may be of considerable value to the Germans.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-104a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">South Eastern Region: While some people are taking the renewal of the raids calmly, others show some uneasiness. Critical comment is made on the Government's "over optimistic statement" about raids.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-114a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12) hhh 6a. Flying bomb damage repairs.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-124a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">London: Although some feel that everything possible is being done to effect speedy home repairs, others, while appreciating that there: is a shortage of labour and materials, are critical of the slowness of the authorities, and it is thought by some that the best use is not made of available men and material.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-134a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">Critical comment is made on the idleness of the labourers employed, and also on the repairing of a cinema.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-144a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">South Eastern Region: he delay in repair work is frequently mentioned and priority for this type of work is advocated. Slackness among repair gangs is commented on. A grievance is caused by building operatives being directed to London from areas in the South East, when it is felt they should be available for the local builders first.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-154a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">(5.12) hhh 6b. Explosions</note>
				<note xml:id="q-164a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">Eastern Region: Rumours and speculation continue. The official secrecy about the "bolts from the blue" is accepted as reasonable, and with some amusement. Some think that stories about rockets are wild rumours.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-174a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">In places where explosions have been heard some perturbation is reported, although it is felt they cause less damage than flying bombs. Bone think we shall soon capture the launching sites.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-184a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">London Region: Rumours "so fantastic as to be amusing" continue to circulate. A few ask for an official statement, but many consider the Government wise to be silent. A few are concerned about the lack of warning, and fear the scale of attack may increase.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-194a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">The rest of the country: Rumours of rocket bombs and mysterious explosions continue widespread - with some requests that the truth should be told.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1a4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">(2.4.5.7.8.9.12) hhh 6c. Evacuation</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1b4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">Evacuees continue to return to London. Reasons they give are the relaxation of the black-out, official optimism, and dislike of the idea of their husbands "jogging, along at home" without them, particularly during the winter; those returning from the Eastern counties to London add chat there is as much danger there as in London. (5)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1c4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">6d. Return of evacuees from abroad</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1d4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">Relatives of children returning to Scotland from Canada describe themselves as "almost over-awed" by the great changes in them; they seem to have been cared for by people in a bettor social class than their parents, and it is feared the children will be discontented with their humbler circumstances.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1e4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">(11) hhh 7. Far East</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1f4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">(No reactions yet received to the news of the naval battle off the Philippines)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-204a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">There is a noticeable increase in interest this week, both in the Pacific theatre and the Burma campaign.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-214a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">The American landing in the Philippines and the excellent progress made have given great satisfaction. Still heavier blows are expected, especially when the big British fleet sent out to the Pacific links up with the American naval forces there. There is increased admiration for the fighting qualities of the American forces.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-224a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">The air attacks on Formosa have also given much satisfaction. Admiration continues for our men in Burma. Too little publicity is still thought to be given them, though the B.B.C's efforts in this direction are approved. Concern about the dreadful conditions under which our men are fighting, especially as regards their health, continues.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-234a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">There is some speculation as to the possibility of Russia declaring war on Japan when Germany is defeated.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-244a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">Prisoners of war: Satisfaction continues that prisoners may send a cable home; relatives are anxiously awaiting their-receipt. Anxiety about the treatment of prisoners in Japanese hands continues aggravated by rumours that there were 1,000 prisoners on board the Sunk Japanese transport.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-254a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">China: There is concern over events in China and a desire for more information.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-264a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13) hhh 8. The Town and Country Planning Bill</note>
				<note xml:id="q-274a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">Discussion has declined this week. Some, however, were awaiting Wednesday's debate with interest. People continue anxious for the Bill to go through as quickly as possible but are fearful that "sectional interests" will prevent it. Workers continue to criticise the suggestion to postpone the compensation part of the Bill.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-284a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">There is considerable confusion about the compensation clauses; where they are understood, opinion is divided as to whether 1939 values are adequate or not.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-294a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">(1.2.3.5.7.9.11.12) hhh 9. Party politics and the next general election</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">People are watching "the re-emergence of political parties", wondering when the general election will take place and how much longer the coalition will stand the strain. Some think the time has come for ending the coalition, "especially income the Town and Country Planning Bill debate"; but :more think the general election should not take place till the European war is over, and deprecate the "party leaders' return to party politics".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">Sir William Beveridge, M.P. Pleasure at his election. It is also asked: "Will it stimulate interest in a revival of the Liberal Party?"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2c4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">(2.5.6.7.9.10.15) hhh 10. Dumbarton Oaks proposals</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">Little comment. The main reactions are - hope that the new plan will be' more successful than the old League, and agreement that armed force is necessary to implement decisions. A few are sceptical as to whether the great powers will be willing to sacrifice their sovereignty.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">(1.3.9) hhh 11. News presentation and 'broadcasting</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">People continue approving of news presentation, especially by the B.B.C. The press is again accused of over-optimistic and otherwise misleading statements...."The public is told that the Gorman armies are now composed of convalescents, old men, etc, etc, and yet after bitter fighting we advance only 600 yards against then".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-304a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">Particular praise is accorded to (a) War Reports; (b) war commentaries.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-314a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">There is widespread enthusiasm for the introduction by the B.B.C. of discussions on controversial and topical subjects. People want "more and more" of them. Those particularly liked have been (a) the series on what to do with Germany; (b) the Bevan-Hogg debate; (c) "To Start you Talking".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-324a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">(1.2.5.5.6.7.0.9.10.11.12.13)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-334a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="103">II. SPECIAL COMMENTS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-344a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">BRIEF WEEKLY REVIEW hhh 12. Extra Christmas food</note>
				<note xml:id="q-354a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">Colonel Llewellin's announcement (October 18) has been greeted with almost unanimous pleasure; housewives are especially delighted. People are particularly pleased about the tea for old people and sweets for children. Some, however, think people of 65 or even 60 should get the extra tea ration.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-364a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">Oranges: The prospect is most welcome (Three Regions). hhh 13. Coal output</note>
				<note xml:id="q-374a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">Anxiety about coal output and winter fuel supplies remains widespread. The high price of coal also continues to be deplored ­particularly in view of its poor quality.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-384a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="108">The miners are increasingly criticised for the present position (Nine Regions). People think any threat of strikes on their part "little less than sabotage", particularly since they have "only recently received wage increases", and, in any case, possess adequate machinery for settling disputes. They are also strongly criticised for absenteeism.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-394a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="109">A few, however, still sympathise with the miners. They think they have had a "raw deal" in the past, and that most of the present troubles are attributable to this. Miners themselves very much resent being blamed for reduced output. They say they are "absolutely worn out" and incapable of greater effort. Some think coal disputes are given too much publicity.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3a4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="110">The Ministry of Fuel and Power and the Government also continue to be criticised (Eight Regions) - in some cases even more than the miners,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3b4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="111">Nationalization continues to be urged - particularly by the miners.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3c4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="112">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12) hhh 14. White Paper on Social Insurance</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3d4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="113">Widespread approval continues; the plan is again described as a great step forward. Minorities, however, are said to be fearful that increased regimentation will result, if it is put into operation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3e4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="114">More detailed explanation of the plan continues to be asked for.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3f4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="115">Comment is on familiar lines:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-404a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="116">Implementation of the plan (Seven Regions). People continue to fear it will be "whittled away" by opposition from "interested parties". Some continue to think it only a 'vote catching stunt" (Four Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-414a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="117">Paying for the scheme (Seven Regions). Business people, particularly, are fearful as to whether we can afford such a scheme and still compete with other countries.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-424a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="118">The possible effects on people's characters (Seven Regions). Some - the "old school" particularly - fear it will "put a premium" on idleness and rob people of personal initiative. It is asked if more emphasis cannot be put on the contributory nature of the scheme to prevent it being thought that people "will be getting something for nothing".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-434a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="119">Superannuation schemes and private insurance policies (Three Regions). Anxiety continues as to what will, happen to contributions already paid. Approved</note>
				<note xml:id="q-444a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="120">Societies and insurance companies (Three Regions). The future of these continues to cause speculation. Elderly employees are said to be particularly anxious about their prospects.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-454a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="121">Contributions (Two Regions) continue to be thought too high - particularly small businesses.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-464a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="122">Comment about specific provisions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-474a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="123">Family allowances (Six Regions). People continue to think the cash allowance inadequate. It is pointed out that children under school age will not get free meals and milk as "payment in kind".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-484a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="124">Some continue to think the first child should have an allowance, and that the allowance should be payable to the mother (Two Regions each).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-494a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="125">Benefits (Five Regions). It is again said that these do not give "freedom from want" - particularly since they do not allow for any rise in the cost of living</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4a4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="126">(1.2.3.4.5.6.A.6.9.10.11.12) hhh 15. Demobilization</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="127">The plan continues to be approved. There are familiar reserva­tions, however, that (a) points should be added for overseas service (Four Regions) and that (b) various classes such as teachers, builders, miners, and students and others with only partial training - or with none - should be given priority (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="128">People continue very fearful that there will not be jobs for the men when they are demobilized.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="129">(1.4.5.7.8.9.10.12.13) hhh 16. Army leave</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="130">There is reported to be a strong feeling that troops on foreign service, particularly in the Far East, are away too long without home leave, and a three years' maximum is urged. Relatives of servicemen who have been abroad for several years are said to be extremely indignant, especially those with "boys serving in the Far East whose health is probably suffering as a result of the climate". It is also asked, "Why do Army men have a much longer period of foreign service than the R.A.F.?"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="131">Compassionate leave to start a family: Very little comment, but there is some indignation at "the idea that women are being questioned about their private lives", and sonic disapproval at what is thought to "smack of the Fascist stud farm".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-504a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="132">(1.3.5.8.10) hhh 17. Home Guard and Civil Defence uniforms</note>
				<note xml:id="q-514a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="133">Home Guard: The permission to retain uniforms continues to give great satisfaction. Farm labourer members of the H.G. are very pleased they are to keep their greatcoats.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-524a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="134">Civil Defence: There still seems to be some confusion as to what must be surrendered and what may be retained, but those who under­stand arc pleased.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-534a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="135">(2.3.6.7.8.9.10.12)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-544a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="136">III. PERIODICAL REVIEW hhh 18. U.S. troops in this country</note>
				<note xml:id="q-554a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="137">During the past four weeks comment on U.S. troops has continued to decline and has again been on familiar lines. Relations between the troops and the public continue to be thought good where the men have been known individually they have been particularly liked. People also continue to praise the fighting qualities of the Americans in France and to be grateful for the help they have given with flying bomb incidents.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-564a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="138">There have been familiar criticisms, however, on the following lines:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-574a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="139">Relations with women and girls (Eleven Regions). People are particu­larly worried My very young girls associating with coloured troops while the women themselves arc held very largely to blame, the troops are criticised for "public" love-making. People hope increased street lighting will help to remedy matters.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-584a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="140">High pay (Eight Regions). People think this partly accounts for the Americans' attraction for women. It is also blamed for shortages- of beer and other commodities.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-594a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="141">Receiving better treatment than our men (Six Regions). Disparity in pay (Four Regions) and better treatment as regards food, clothing and entertainment are all complained of. Some again say this makes British troops very reluctant to "chum up" with the Americans Alleged waste at American camps (Four Regions). This is considered it to our rationed people".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="142">Transport (Four Regions). U.S. troops are blamed for careless driving Regions (Three Regions), and for wasting petrol driving to and from dances and other entertainments. On the other hand, in. one Region, the speed and efficiency of Americans convoys are praised.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="143">General behaviour (Three Regions). There continue to be a few complaints of "slovenly" appearance, boasting, and heavy drinking.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="144">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13)</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>