<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Home Intelligence Weekly Report - No. 166 - 9 December 1943</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-6f145d6a-d9c6-42be-b92c-c3e67c8b1a04</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-dc124b86-7e2b-4327-bebf-e525befe8d56</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-2e5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">Wt 39944. 10M 11/43. W.R.R. &amp; S. Ltd. GP 38. (14).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-305f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="3">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-315f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="4">HOME INTELLIGENCE WEEKLY REPORT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-325f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">No. 166, 9th</note>
				<note xml:id="q-335f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="6">December 1943</note>
				<note xml:id="q-345f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">(covering period from 30th November to 7th December, 1943)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-355f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="8">I. GENERAL COMMENTS hhh 1. General</note>
				<note xml:id="q-365f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">Public satisfaction with war events has increased this week, thanks to the new offensive in Italy, the raids on Germany, Russian advances and the meeting at Teheran "between the three great men".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-375f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">Nevertheless spirits have risen only a little: the flu epidemic is the chief topic for most people, and general tiredness, ill-health and the black-out are the cause of some depression.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-385f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">The release of the Mosleys continues to be widely discussed, but with less vehemence - though much resentment is still simmering.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-395f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">The ballot scheme for securing labour for the mines has had a mixed, but on the whole favourable reception.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3a5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">Domestic Front: Much talk of Christmas, chiefly about the prospects of getting a turkey, and the price and quality of toys. Post-war prospects, housing and footwear continue to be anxiously discussed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3b5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11.13. 17 and 18 passim) hhh 2. The Allied Conferences</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3c5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">The news of the two conferences has given much satisfaction, but so far there has been only limited comment. This is thought to be because people are waiting for more precise information before expressing opinions, because the news did not come as a complete surprise, and because there is some impatience with so many conferences which talk of the final assault.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3d5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">The Cairo Conference: The first reactions were surprise and pleasure at the presence of General Chiang Kai-Shek, end disappoint­ment at the absence of Marshal Stalin. This disappointment largely disappeared with the news of the Teheran conference, though there was still some regret and failure to understand why the Russian and Chinese leaders can never meet. Most people are glad to have China once more "in the picture" - as with many, workers especially, she comes second in popularity only to Russia - end there is great satisfaction et the comprehensive plans for fighting the Japanese.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3e5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">The declaration of punishment to be meted out to Japan went further them some had expected, but has met with very wide approval Nine Regions). There is, however, minority criticism from a) those who are tired of "fist-shaking" and want to see words translated into action, (b) those who feel that the problem of Japan's expanding population will still have to be solved, (c) those who fear threats will only stiffen her resistance and may provoke her to atrocities.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3f5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">The Teheran Conference: Only preliminary reports have been received so far, but people appear to be far more interested in this than in the Cairo Conference. There is great satisfaction - and some enthusiasm - that at last the three great leaders have come together; though Marshal Stalin has been criticised for "only going 60 miles out of his own country", while the other two had to go so far. People hope that all misunderstandings between the western democracies and Russia have now been smoothed away, that the future of Poland has been satisfactorily settled, and all arrangements made for the final assault on Germany. Meanwhile they are pleased at the apparent friendliness of the proceedings and eagerly await further information.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-405f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">There is so far little comment on the joint declaration, but, according to the Scottish report, "the fact that Stalin's signature appears on it gives evidence to many - especially workers - that the document will be honoured. Greater faith is placed in Stalin's word than in any ether statesman's."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-415f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">The release of news: Criticism of "the mishandling of publicity" is mentioned in reports from eight Regions, two of which, however, suggest that it comes largely from press circles or the "more informed". Nevertheless many people seem annoyed that other countries, and especially the U.S.A., should have heard the news before we did; and the fact that the Cairo conference to some extent "fell flat" is thought to be because news came through first from enemy and neutral sources.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-425f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11.13. 18 passim) hhh 3. The Hosleys' release</note>
				<note xml:id="q-435f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">Excitement has subsided considerably, and many are now speaking of "a storm in a tea-cup", and asking: "Why all the fuss?" But there are still many particularly working people who feel strong that the Hosleys should not have been released. There is no change in the arguments they use:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-445f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">(i) One law for the rich and another for the poor. Mosley would not have got out had he not been a rich men.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-455f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">(ii) Phlebitis is no excuse. Holloway is ideal for its treatment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-465f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">(iii) It is a compromise with fascism</note>
				<note xml:id="q-475f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">Among the growing number who approve the Home Secretary's action are some who nevertheless think that the timing was inappropriate.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-485f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">Mr. Morrison is now fairly widely praised for acting courageously according to his convictions in the face of popular clamour, and for his skilful speech in the Debate. There is more comment that opposition was deliberately whipped up to spite the Home Secretary</note>
				<note xml:id="q-495f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">In the East End, there are fears of recrudescence of facism and rumours that the British Union of Fascists has taken an old hall in Paddington for meetings. 18B is again criticised, though the, majority appear to have no understanding of it.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4a5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11.13. 17 twelve provincial P.Cs. 18 passim) hhh 4. Italy</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">The news that we are again moving forward is generally described as heartening. It is thought we still have a stiff job on hand, end the most optimists hope for is Rome by Christmas. There is much sympathy for the troops, and it is feared casualties may be heavy. More details of conditions under which fighting is going on arc asked for.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">The political situation is little mentioned. There is disgust at stories of Italians being allowed to fleece our men.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11.13. 17. 18 passim) hhh 5. Allied air offensive</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">There is again great interest in the raids en German territory, especially Berlin. They are looked on as a "gruesome necessity" to make future land operations less costly. There is much specula­tion .s to their effect on German morale. Though there is some sympathy for civilians, people generally are thought to display "neither tenderness nor exultation" over the victims; any tendency to "gloat" over their sufferings is disliked.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">Concern is, reported over the number of bombers lost, especially in the raid of December 2nd.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-505f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">(1.2.5.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.13. 17 ten provincial P.Cs. 18 passim) hhh 6. Reprisals end Secret Weapons</note>
				<note xml:id="q-515f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">In London it appears that a majority are now giving some thought to the possibility of a retaliatory secret weapon. Indeed, many are anxious about it, though there are still a large number who laugh at the idea. "Frightening tales" are repented "on good authority". It is rumoured that rockets have already fallen on London - in. Park Lane, the Borough High Street, and somewhere in the West End, There appears to be some confusion between rockets of British and German origin; thus, pockets are said to have been fired at Civil Defence practices. It is also rumoured that the Government is expecting large-scale gas attacks, and huge stocks of bleach powder are-said to have been delivered at decontamination centres. Evening theatre end cinema attendances are thought to have declined.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-525f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">In the rest of the country, there is a good deal of discussion about reprisals, though much less anxiety and more skepticism. Secret weapons are less discussed, though a large-scale gas attack on London is thought conceivable. Anything much anywhere else is not expected.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-535f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">(1.2.3.5.SE.6.7.8.10.13. 18 twelve P.D.Rs.) hhh 7. Raids on this country</note>
				<note xml:id="q-545f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">The recent raid on Plymouth is still producing comment on the lack of defences.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-555f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">In Deal, it is said that people have noticed with dismay the removal of A.A. defences from the town) and in. view of threatened reprisals would feel much happier if they could be returned.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-565f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">(5SE.7) hhh 8. General Smuts' address (November 25)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-575f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">This has provoked much thought and discussion. On the whole it has been very highly praised, especially for its candour and realism though a number of people have been disturbed and feel this is not the moment to throw explosives about.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-585f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">Disapproving comment is more detailed, than approving, and has particularly centred round his references to:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-595f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">France (Eight Regions): Though the realism of his references to post-war France is praised, they have caused some surprise and regret, and arc thought to be rather ill-timed and a "rich plum" for German propaganda. It is thought that the ardour of the French whether Fighting or otherwise - will be damped.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">Russia, "the Colossus" (Five Regions): This, too, was considered ill-timed by some, and likely to pave the way for still more distrust of Russia.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">"Britain will be poor" (Four Regions) : Some anxiety and failure to understand the reason for this. A few ask what is to cone of the "grandiose" post-war schemes, if we are to be so poor.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">Splitting up the Empire into zones (Two Regions): Some suspect an attempt to secure native territories of South Africa for the Union, and consider that coloured peoples are likely to be less well treated under the Dutch or South African flag than under the British.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5d5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">(1.2.3.5.5SE.7.8.13) hhh 9. Russia</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5e5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">Administration of the Russian successes and her continued progress continues, though the slight withdrawals caused some anxiety. The feeling is again expressed that the Russians are winning the war for us and it is time we relieved them.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5f5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.13. 17 six P.Cs. 18 passim) hhh 10. The Lebanon</note>
				<note xml:id="q-605f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">Comment continues on familiar lines and has decreased.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-615f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.10. 17 two provincial P.Cs. 18 nineteen P.D.Rs.) hhh 11. Leros</note>
				<note xml:id="q-625f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">Comment continues on familiar lines and has decreased.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-635f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">(1.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.10. 7 three provincial P.Cs. 18 passim) hhh 12. Turkey</note>
				<note xml:id="q-645f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">(No reports since the news of the second Cairo Conference) Speculation as to Turkey's possible entry into the war has recurred - in London it was recently rumoured that she had come in, with resulting intense satisfaction.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-655f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">There is still some feeling, however, that our loss of the Dodecanese islands has prejudiced the possibility of Turkey becoming our ally.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-665f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">(1.4.5.6.10. 18 five P.D.Rs.) hhh 13. War at Sea</note>
				<note xml:id="q-675f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">During the past four weeks general satisfaction with our successes against the U-boats has been reported. The figures of U-boat losses have acted "as a tonic".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-685f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">(1.2.3.6.7.8.9.10.13.) hhh 14. Broadcasting and presentation of news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-695f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">Apart from references to the release of news of the Allied Conferences (q.v.) there is little comment on news presentation; but there is still some complaint of inaccuracy and repetition, Some people feel that the B.B.C. bulletins have been "soft-pedalling" on Russian withdrawals.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6a5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">Programmes: The improved standard of drama productions is appre­ciated and more plays are asked for. More light music is wanted and people are thought to tune in to foreign stations to get it. There is comment on the poor quality of variety programmes.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6b5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">Sir Norman Angell's postscript November 28 (Eight Regions) was appreciated. It was thought to be "brilliant, logical, and needing to be said".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6c5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">General: Praise for Major Hastings' war commentary, December 2. (Four Regions); "The Air is our Concern" (Three Regions); Brains' Trust, St. Andrews's night (Two Regions); Theodor Brach's post­script December 5 (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6d5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="64">II. SPECIAL COMMENTS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6e5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">FULL MONTHLY REVIEW hhh 15. Post-war</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6f5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">During the past four weeks comment on post-war matters has continued widespread. Uneasiness seems to be deepening; in some cases anxiety has become pessimism. The appointment of a Minister for Reconstruction, the Prime-Minister's promise of "food, work and homes for all", and the emphasis on post-war matters in the King's speech, although serving temporarily to raise hopes, have had no appreciable lasting effect.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-705f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">Cynicism about the possibilities of a "better and brighter" world after the war is increasing, The "shelving" of the Beveridge and other Reports and White Papers, the "lack of definite proposals" and the "nebulousness" of promises are criticised, and are taken as evidence that the Government is really little interested in post-war matters..."All this talk is merely window-dressing". "Definite action" is called for and is considered by many to be the only likelihood of reassuring people.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-715f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">Increasingly pessimistic comparison is being math, with "what happened last time".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-725f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">Housing: Post-war housing continues to arouse widespread concern, particularly among those married since the war and so far dependent on relatives, or living in furnished rooms. A "wild scramble" when the war ends is feared to be likely.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-735f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">The delay in announcing plans for housing is strongly criticised, Apart from impatience that building is being held up, it is feared that lack of guiding policy will result in "jerry-building coming into its own again", in speculation in land, and "the same shameful exploitation which took place after the last war". The buying up of land and premises "more or less surreptitiously going on at present" is already causing some concern.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-745f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">There is little detailed comment on the kind of home wanted, though women are becoming increasingly interested and arc demand in more say in the planning of houses. The preference for small houses rather than flats is mentioned.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-755f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">Employment: Fears of post-war unemployment are widespread, par­ticularly, it is said, in the Forces. "Flooding" of the labour market after the war is dreaded and there is much discussion of the prospects of those in the Forces and armament industries; and of women.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-765f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">In the mining, cotton heavy industries generally there is acute anxiety about another "slump". ''Prospects of a return to normal conditions mean to the people in the coalfield, and in heavy industry generally, a return to unemployment and the dole." In the Northern Region, the introduction of light industries into the district is demanded, to ease the employment problem after the war.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-775f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">Education: Discussion of educational reform has continued and has become rather more general; though still chiefly limited to those professionally interested. The raising the school-leaving age - which it is hoped will help to lesson unemployment - the need for educational apprenticeship, and the "religious side" all arouse interest.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-785f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">Opposition to the White Paper from religious bodies is criticised, and it is hoped "The Government will be ruthless in its determination to make no concession". Some-minority fears are entertained, however, that "under the cloak of improving education, plans are afoot to educate all in a common mould".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-795f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">Post-war Controls: Post-war controls continue to arouse discussion though on a reduced scale. The public are prepared to admit that some controls will be needed after the war, and in some cases urge them as a means of preventing speculation and "racketeering". Nevertheless they are tired of "continual interference and form-filling", and "there will be trouble if this is not kept within reasonable bounds".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7a5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">It is felt that some definite, official statements should be made about post-war control, because at present it is not clear if the utterances of Ministers are expressions of the Government's views.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7b5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">Agriculture: Anxiety about post-war farming continues. Farmers and labourers are said to be equally concerned about the Govern­ment's future attitude. Better wages and housing for agricultural labourers are urged as means of keeping men on the land.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7c5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">Local authorities: The future of Local authorities is the subject of some discussion (Two Regions). There is said to be some uneasiness about Whitehall's "increasing control" over local affairs.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7d5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11. 17. 18 fifteen P.D.Rs.) hhh 16. Housing and billeting</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7e5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">During the past four weeks the shortage of all kinds of housing accommodation has continued to be the cause of considerable anxiety. In many cases it has become "one of the most immediate and pressing problems on the Home Front". The Government's delay in "getting a move on" is criticised and it is feared that a chaotic position would result if the war were to end soon.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7f5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">Particular reference is made to the difficulties experienced by:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-805f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">(a) War brides (Five Regions). Many of them who have remained at home with their parents already have children, and are becoming increasingly anxious to set up homes of their own.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-815f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">(b) Families of servicemen (Two Regions). There are again complaints that landlords will not let to them for fear of "bad debts".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-825f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">(c) Couples with children, and</note>
				<note xml:id="q-835f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">(d) Old people (One Region each).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-845f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">The high rents of houses, flats and rooms- furnished and unfurnished- continue to excite bitter comment (Seven Regions). It is again urged that rents for furnished rooms should be controlled.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-855f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">The "ramp" in the buying and selling of houses at exorbitant prices is also criticised (Four Regions). A "ceiling" on the price of houses, based on pre-war values, is urged.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-865f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">Repairs: Difficulties in getting repairs done are complained of (Four Regions). Even where repairs have been carried out they are said not to stand up at all well to the rain. In London there are also complaints of the delay in repairing bomb-damaged houses "until an investigation has been made by the Council".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-875f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">Local Authorities' requisitioning powers: Disappointment continues to be expressed (Two Regions). "Either there is nothing to re­quisition, or all talk and no do" results.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-885f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">Agricultural housing: The delay in the building of the agricultural cottages continues to arouse comment (Four Regions). Billeting: In the Eastern and Southern Regions billeting diffi­culties are said to remain a source of dissatisfaction. In the Southern Region particularly, it is felt that the housewife is sufficiently harassed without having people billeted on her and that after four years of war, hostels should by now have boon pro­vided.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-895f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">In the South Western Region and in there have been some complaints at the-thought of having to billet American troops.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8a5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.13. 17. 18 one P.D.R.) hhh 17. Miners and mining The ballot system: Comment has been considerable and reactions have been as follows:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8b5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">Approval: The majority among both miners and the general public think it is a good idea because they feel it will be fair to all (Ten Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8c5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">Disapproval: An appreciable minority disapprove or qualify their acceptance, because they believe:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8d5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">(a) There will be "loopholes" by which the rich will gain exemption (Four Regions), e.g. by reason of their "education".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">(b) It would be better to withdraw trained miners from the Forces. Miners, in particular, feel that "green" labour will be of little use for many months (Four Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">There is some sympathy for those who are chosen and parents are said to be "aghast". It is reported that young men in the Northern Region say they would rather go to gaol than down a mine; they are said to be volunteering for air crews end the Navy.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-905f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">Nothing but disapproval is reported from the Midland Region, where it is thought that it will only result in more square pegs in round holes. Simpler folk wonder how they will get all the names into one hat.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-915f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">During the past four weeks concern about the coal mining situation has continued.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-925f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">The following are thought chiefly to account for trouble and difficulties:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-935f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">(a) Unpopularity of Government man-power measures (Five Regions), in particular:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-945f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">(i) The introduction of "green labour", which miners in particular fool will increase accidents.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-955f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">(ii) The direction of young boys to the mines and their prosecution for absenteeism. (Since the announcement of the ballot system there has been less criticism on these lines).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-965f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">(b) Miners' remembrance of the way they were treated after the lost war and their concern about future of the industry (Four Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-975f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">(c) Conditions of work in general, and particularly the lack of up-to-date machinery in some mince (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-985f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">(d) Disparity of wages between mining and other industries (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-995f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="108">(e) "Subversive influences" in the coal-fields (One Region).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="109">Remedies: Many feel that nationalisation is the only solution (Five Regions). Extra food rations and a shorter working week are other suggestions (Two Regions each).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="110">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11. 17. 18 twelve P.D.Rs.) hhh 18. Domestic fuel</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="111">Supplies of cool: People in. the Northern, North Eastern, North Midland and London Regions wonder how they will manage on the coal allowance this winter. Supply difficulties ore reported from Norfolk.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9d5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="112">Economy campaign: There is little interest in the campaign. Opinion is divided as to the effort being made to economise. There is some feeling that people resent exhortations and feel rather that firmer action against strikers and greater economy in large organizations is needed (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9e5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="113">Waste of full is alleged in London stores, offices - especially American promises, and Fun Fairs (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9f5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="114">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.7.9.10. 17. 18 seven P.D.Rs.) hhh 19. Industry</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a05f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="115">Press accounts of the action taken by Ministry of Labour against Desoutters, for ignoring a direction, has heartened work-people, who think that "at last" the Essential Work Order is being used impartially.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a15f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="116">During the past four weeks comment has been mainly en the following topics:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a25f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="117">(a) Tiredness among workers, especially the young (Eight Regions) - thought by the majority to be duo to excessively long hours.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a35f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="118">(b) Enforced idleness and overstaffing (Seven Regions). There are a number of complaints of idle and wasted time in war factories, particularly in the Northern Region. Complaints are also made of needless work (e.g. building a wall and pulling it down again), due, according to workers, to the employers' desire to swell costs and thus obtain the added percentage of profit.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a45f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="119">(c) Slackness of workers and absenteeism (Seven Regions). This causes some concern and is thought, in part, to be due to illness and the lack of the stimulant of intense military activity; though also to indifference, particularly among youths.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a55f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="120">(d) Disparities in wages (Six Regions): Again this month particular mention is made of the disparity between skilled and unskilled workers' wages. It is said that skilled workers in the North Midland Region try for this reason to get work en unskilled operations.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a65f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="121">(e) High wades (Six Regions): Complaints are mostly of the high wages paid to factory workers compared with the Forces and workers still on peace-time salaries.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a75f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="122">(e) Dismissal of workers and unemployment (Five Regions): There is a considerable amount of talk of the dismissal of war workers and of unemployment, particularly in the Northern and Midland Regions and Wales. Rumours are also reported of the closing down of war factories.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a85f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="123">(g) Changes in production (Five Regions): Reports speak of pre­paration for post-war production already being made and of fears among workers of a "return to soulless industrial competition". Even where the change-over is to work in preparation for relief in occupied countries, workers are said to lose their feeling of urgency and to feel they are no longer needed to win the war.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a95f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="124">(h) Transfer of women (Five Regions): This causes complaints and is considered a sign of bad management of labour.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-aa5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="125">(i) Over-production (Four Regions): Some believe that output has exceeded requirements in many directions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ab5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="126">(1.2.5.4.5.5SE.6.7.8. 9.10.11.13. 17) hhh 20. Strikes</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ac5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="127">A slight decrease in comment this week: (Nine Regions) thought the great majority continue to condemn strikes in wartime; a small number still feel that workers have no other means of improving conditions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ad5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="128">During the past four weeks various suggestions as to the cause of strikes have been made:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ae5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="129">(a) Lack of firm action on the part of the Government (Eight Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-af5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="130">(b) Failings on the part of employers (Four Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b05f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="131">(c) Tiredness and war weariness (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b15f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="132">(d) Inability of Trades Unions to control their members (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b25f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="133">(e) The inefficient functioning of negotiating machinery (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b35f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="134">(f) Paid agitators and Fifth Columnists (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b45f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="135">(g) Communists and "Trotskyites" (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b55f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="136">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11.13. 17.18 nine P.D.Rs.) hhh 21. Man-power</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b65f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="137">During the past four weeks comment has decreased. However, the main topics have been:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b75f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="138">(a) The registration of older women (Seven Regions): Some criticism has again been reported (Six Regions) but on a very reduced scale, dying away to nothing the last week.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b85f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="139">The chief ground of criticism was that many young people are not yet fully employed. It is also believed by a few that some factories have idle time; aloe that the women's health will be affected. Others complain of the tactless manner of Ministry of Labour interviewers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b95f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="140">Women in the South-East are reported on the whole to have welcomed the registration and to be impatient with the attitude of some male M.Ps.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ba5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="141">(b) Misuse of labour (Five Regions): The view persists that labour is still not being used to the best advantage and reference is again made to:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bb5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="142">(i) Young unmarried men still not combed out; this is thought unfair to the older men, especially those with one-man businesses or with families (Three Regions),</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bc5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="143">(ii) Overstaffing, especially in the Civil Service (Two Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bd5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="144">(c) Evasion of cell-up by some women, especially young marrieds (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-be5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="145">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.8.9) hhh 22. Domestic help</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bf5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="146">During the past four weeks there have been continued references to the shortage of domestic help (Nine Regions). The difficulties of 'elderly people, invalids, mothers with several young children, farmers' wives, and doctors, are particularly mentioned. The flu epidemic is said to have brought the question of domestic help to a head. Men are said to have had to stay away from their work when their wives have been ill.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c05f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="147">There has been some criticism of Mr. Bevin's "Now Deal for domestic servants" (Four Regions). It is feared that many middle-class homes will be quite incapable of paying his rates.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c15f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="148">(1.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.9.10) hhh 23. Agriculture</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c25f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="149">This week much concern is reported at the revised farm prices announced by the Minister of Agriculture (Five Regions). Farmers feel these will not meet the increased wage charges and that the Ministry is guilty of a breach of faith. Some are said now to be becoming apprehensive about the future and to compare the present action with the repeal of the Corn Production Act after the last war, when- the first step was made towards sending the industry in­to a state of depression.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c35f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="150">During the past four necks the main topics have been:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c45f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="151">Land cultivation (Five Regions): Farmers are beginning to fear for the continued fertility of the soil under the present policy of intensive culture. They fool the peak has been reached and that it is useless to grow further cereal crops unless the land has been rested. Some consider the loss of fertility is already apparent.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c55f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="152">It is thought also that suitability of land and climatic con­ditions should be carefully considered when extra cultivation demands arc made. Grain matures so late in the North that much is wasted, and some farmers think they have ploughed to the limit and that the time has come for concentration on milk, and cattle for meat.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c65f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="153">Labour and wages (Five Regions): Concern is reported at the serious shortage of skilled labour, particularly cow-men and dairy hands. Farmers say that since their employees now pay income tax they are not so keen on working overtime, and it is also very difficult to get men to work on Sundays. A case is reported of one farm being forced to close down its dairy section on that account. Some fooling is reported that the new minimum wages rate of £3. 5. 0 compares unfavourably with wages paid on local aero­drome sites and causes discontent among the workers. At the same time there is praise for the land workers and appreciation of their "long hours and no indulgence in unpatriotic strikes".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c75f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="154">Concern is reported also at the shortage of rural craftsmen, such as thatchers (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c85f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="155">War Agricultural Executive Committees (Four Regions) : Some feel these Committees tend to become composed of "groups of men all in with each other", and there is criticism of mismanagement and the dictatorial attitude of some junior officials. It is reported from the Southern Region that "although no publicity is given to the methods of ejection of 'bad husbandmen by the Hants W.A.E.C., their activities arc causing a little alarm and 'their apparently unlimited powers arc considered to savour of the Gestapo". On the other hand, in the Eastern Region, "the work of these Committees is, in the main, appreciated".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c95f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="156">Housing (Three Regions): Hardships over tied cottages and the shortage of agricultural cottages continue to lee reported, and there is complaint that farm workers' cottages are being made of poor materials, e.g. cardboard door panels.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ca5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="157">Women's Land Army (Two Regions): The vital work which the women are doing for the country is praised, but there is comment on the proposed rise in wages by 3/- a week. Some employers consider the beginning of the winter an inopportune time for this and fear it may lead to some land girls being paid off.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cb5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="158">(1.3.4.5SE.6.7.8. 18 two P.D.Rs.) hhh 24. Health</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cc5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="159">During the past four weeks there have been increasing references to the epidemic of colds and flu, which this week is said to be a widespread topic of discussion (Twelve "Regions, several more than once). The epidemic is attributed mainly- to lowered powers of resistance duo to lack of vitamins in the national diet (Six Regions). Other causes mentioned are:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cd5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="160">(a) The poor quality of leather shoe solos (Four Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ce5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="161">(b) War weariness (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cf5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="162">(c) Germs dropped by the enemy (One Region).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d05f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="163">(d) A germ rumoured to have been brought back by members of the Eight Army (One Region).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d15f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="164">There is a desire that some simple precautionary measures should be issued by the Ministry of Health, and there' is some discussion about Patulin (Three Regions). Some anxiety is reported among those who remember the flu epidemic of the last war (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d25f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="165">General health: There have again this month been several references to war weariness and strain (Eight Regions). This continues to be attributed to long hours of work, wartime food and lack of holidays.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d35f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="166">Government statements about the good health of the nation continue to meet with criticism (Six Regions). In the Southern "Region it is pointed out that statistics cannot take into account the number of people who, although not fit, are conscientiously at work, whereas under normal conditions they would be away under doctors' orders.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d45f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="167">Tuberculosis (Six Regions): Concern continues at the increase in tuberculosis. It is thought that the exclusion of chronic T.B. sufferers from the Government allowance will cause hardship and that it is "a blot on a civilised country".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d55f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="168">Shortage of hospital accommodation (Four Regions): Concern continues, especially at the lack of maternity beds in hospitals.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d65f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="169">Shortage of doctors (Four Regions): Doctors are reported to be over worked and to have too many patients to be able to watch each one carefully. It is thought too many doctors have been called</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d75f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="170">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11. 17 five provincial P.Cs. 18 seventeen P.D.Rs. hhh 25. Venereal diseases campaign</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d85f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="171">During the vast four weeks approval for the campaign has continued. The posters and publicity are praised, though it is thought that even stronger measures are needed. More lectures and films on the subject would be welcomed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d95f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="172">The increased amount of drinking, especially among young girls, is deplored as it is thought to pave the way for V.D. It is again suggested that the "no treating order" should be reintro­duced,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-da5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="173">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.10. 18 six P.D.R.s.) hhh 26. Clothing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-db5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="174">There has been some appreciative comment in Northern Ireland and the South Eastern District on the reduction in coupon value of wooden-soled shoes (November 22) and cheaper shoes (November 25). In four other Regions, however, opinion is more critical: "Two pairs of rotten ones at ten coupons not worth one good pair'''. It is suggested this was done to enable manufacturers to get rid of shoddy goods; also, that wooden-soled shoes are "simply a flop" because they wear out too quickly.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="175">During the last four weeks the following, familiar topics have boon reported (See also Constant Topics, Nos, 2.5.16.22):</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="176">(a) Footwear (Eleven Regions). "Most people's greatest clothing worry". The main complaints are: -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="177">(i) Poor quality of shoes on sale (Eleven Regions), particularly children's. "Even in new shoes children have wet feet thin fifteen minutes of leaving home." Mothers say they will have to keep the children away from school.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="178">(ii) Repair difficulties (Eleven Regions). Reference is made to: The very long time repairs take; The poor quality of leather used for repairs - 'compressed cardboard is not suitable for mending shoes"; The poor quality of the repairs -patching of soles is no good"; The lack of leather for home repairs.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e05f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="179">iii) Shortage of footwear (Eight Regions). Specifically mentioned are: Hob-nailed boots for farmers; Workers heavy nailed boots; Children's shoes, sizes 7 to 13 Northern Region; Men's shoes, size 8 1/2 (London)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e15f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="180">(iv) Lack of rubber boots (Six Regions) for country people, particularly children. To quote from Postal Censorship: "Ronald has a cold just now, his feet got wet going to school and we can't get rubber boots for him",</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e25f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="181">(v) The number of coupons required (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e35f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="182">(vi) High price (Three Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e45f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="183">(b) Insufficient clothing coupons (Eleven Regions). It is said clothes cannot be replaced; and that some people "cannot keep even reasonably warm". Specifically mentioned as suffering from insufficient coupons are:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e55f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="184">(i) Outdoor manual workers (Six Regions), particularly agriculture workers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e65f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="185">(ii) Industrial workers Regions). Blast furnacemen and workers in heavy chemicals feel their coupon expenditure on working clothes is not sufficiently allowed for.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e75f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="186">(iii) Children (Four Regions). Many, it is suggested in one Region, "are without warm underwear in order to keep them tidy in top clothes".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e85f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="187">(iv) People needing uniforms (Three Regions), such as Scouts, Guides, members of the G.T.C. and children at schools where uniforms arc worn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e95f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="188">(v) Expectant mothers (Two Regions) Some complaint is report (One Region) about Mrs. Edwards' reference in her broadcast (November. 27) to a baby needing only a dozen or a dozen and a half napkins. "It is generally assumed that two or three dozen is a minimum, and according sixty coupons do not go far."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ea5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="189">(c) The surrender of personal coupons for towels, curtains, etc. (Eight Regions). The demand for a. special household allowance is said to be greater now that stocks are getting depleted.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-eb5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="190">(d) Shortage and poor quality of clothing generally (Seven Regions), particularly women's stockings (Five Regions). It is suggested in one Region that' "far too much labour is expended en cheap shoddy goods".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ec5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="191">(e) High price of clothing (Six Regions), particularly hats (Four Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ed5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="192">(f) Delay in issuing workers' supplementary coupons (Six Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ee5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="193">(g) Time taken by laundries (Three Regions). It is suggested they have been told "nothing matters but the soldiers; don't concern yourselves about civilians".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ef5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="194">Shortage of black-out material (Four Regions) "People think it unfair they should be prosecuted for black-out offences when it is impossible to buy sufficient material in the shops."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f05f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="195">Board of Trade publicity: Make Do and Mend classes continue to be popular, particularly in the South Western Region; they are also creating a great deal of interest in South Eastern villages. The Domestic Front Exhibition is spoken of appreciatively in Swindon. (l.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.l3. 17, 18 eighteen hhh 27. Toys</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f15f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="196">Strong complaints continue of high prices and often very poor quality of toys. Some people are disappointed that there was not a greater number of toys available following the announcement of the lifting of the quota restrictions (December 1). Fantastic prices of secondhand toys arc bitterly criticised; £10 or more for a doll's pram is thought ridiculous,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f25f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="197">(1.3.5.6.7.9. 13 passim) hhh 28. Alarm clocks</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f35f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="198">During the last four weeks there have again been complaints of the shortage of alarm clocks, and requests for permits from many workers not entitled to receive them.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f45f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="199">This week it is reported from Wales that many workers are pleased with the new regulation concerning the issue of alarm clocks, as they will now be eligible to receive them.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f55f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="200">(1.2.3.5.6.8.9) hhh 29. Furniture</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f65f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="201">During the past four weeks there have again been complaints of excessive prices demanded for both new and second hand furniture Utility furniture is also thought to be expensive.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f75f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="202">(2.3.4.7.8.10) 30. Food hhh General satisfaction with the food situation is tempered by comment on the particular items sot out below and in Constant Topics (Nos. 4.12.18.21.26). There is, too, growing feeling that wartime food is not sufficiently nourishing to give the necessary resistance to illness and tiredness (Six Regions), and some people connect the flu epidemic with the quality of the present food.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f85f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="203">Christmas fare is again a subject of much interest and some anxiety, and many people are worrying about what they are likely to eat for Christmas (Nine Regions) and drink on New Year's Eve (Two Regions including Scotland). People on the whole do not seem very hopeful of getting a turkey -"we shall be lucky if we get rabbit" - and some ore resentful and suspect that the matter is not being fairly dealt with. It is suggested that turkeys could be cut up and sold in portions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f95f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="204">The shortage of dried fruit is greatly deplored (Seven Regions) so is absence of suet (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fa5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="205">During the past four weeks there has been comment on:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fb5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="206">Milk: There have been continuous complaints of the smallness of the present ration (Eleven Regions). Particular sufferers are:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fc5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="207">(a) Smell households (Five Regions), who complain of the arbitrary imposition of days. Some one person households have only two deliveries o week, owing to milkmen refusing to deliver half pints.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fd5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="208">(b) Elderly people and invalids (Five Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fe5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="209">(c) Children of 5 -14 (Two Regions). "What happens to all the school milk during the holidays?"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ff5f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="210">(d) Those who never get a meal away from home (One Region).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-006088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="211">There are also complaints of distribution (Si:: Regions), and there is a persistent belief that "other places" - whether the next street or a different locality - hove plenty, or at least a bit over the ration.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-016088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="212">Oranges: Distribution has been criticised (Six Regions) on two grounds:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-026088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="213">(a)They should be made available to more people, particularly</note>
				<note xml:id="q-036088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="214">(i) Children over five (Four Regions repeatedly) - "as the sixes and seven long for them when the little ones get them";</note>
				<note xml:id="q-046088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="215">(ii) The sick and aged (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-056088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="216">(b) The: aren't always fairly distributed (Four Regions). Some children failed to get any of the last allocation and there is a feeling that oranges sometimes go to favoured customers instead. One report mentions people with time to queue getting oranges from two or three different shops. It is suggested that they should be distributed through schools and clinics that shops should be collpelled to display notices when an allocation is available.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-066088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="217">The inadequacy of the cooking ration (Six Regions), particularly at Christmas time.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-076088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="218">Canadian apples have boon looked forward to with pleasure (Five Regions); and there is some impatience at their non-appearance, particularly in the Northern Region where it is asked: "Why should they so to the south they have plenty of English apples and can grow their own?" Supplies were greatly appreciated in Scotland, but "control of sole would have been welcomed, as supplies often went to shop-crawlers before workers could get them".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-086088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="219">The difficulty of getting invalid foods (Three Regions): Ovaltine is particularly mentioned and so is whiskey which, oven when ordered by the doctor, is often unobtainable for other than regular customers. Thu "nastiness" of wartime cakes (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-096088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="220">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9. 10.11.13. 17 and 18 passim). hhh 31. Shopping difficulties and food queues</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0a6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="221">During the past four weeks complaints have been fewer (Eight Regions), hut on familiar lines, and very strong in the London Region where shopping is described as "a nightmare for the working woman" (See Constant Topics, No.6). The lunch-time and earlier winter closing of shops still seems to be the greatest cause of difficulties, and workers are still the section of the public to suffer most. People grumble that shopping is very tiring and wastes so much time.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0b6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="222">There are again complaints of:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0c6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="223">(a) The quota system whereby goods in short supply are put on sale at 10 a.m. or later and are sold out before lunch time.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0d6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="224">(b) The comparatively poor stock of food in rural shops, which involves rural housewives in travelling to the nearest town, where they often find that goods on points or in short supply have already been sold.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0e6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="225">(c) The ordering of goods by telephone, to the detriment of personal shoppers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0f6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="226">(2.4.5.5SE.8.9.10.11) hhh 32. Old Age Pensions</note>
				<note xml:id="q-106088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="227">The improved standard of supplementary pensions, which will come into force on January 17 if approved by Parliament, has boon welcomed (Three Regions), though many people feel that en increase in the basic pension is needed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-116088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="228">During the past four weeks there have been repeated references to the inadequacy of old age pensions, in view of the increased cost of living, and to the wish for their increase (Seven Regions 'Sec Constant Topics, No.7). Some feel that, in ­addition to an increase, there should be en extra food allowance - especially mill - and "less probing into the most intimate conditions of a pensioner".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-126088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="229">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.8.9.10) hhh 33. Income tax</note>
				<note xml:id="q-136088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="230">During the past four weeks approval for the "pay-as-you-earn" scheme has continued (Five Regions). There are still many people who would like a clear and simple explanation of it, end a broad­cast on the subject (December 3) was praised.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-146088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="231">Managements continue to complain of the extra amount of work for their staff that will be involved, and some fear they will have to engage extra accountants. Those not concerned with operating the scheme, however, hope it will not be shelved because of the extra labour needed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-156088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="232">Post-war credits: Some people fear that post-war credits will merely be credited to them against income tax, and not paid in cash.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-166088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="233">Irish workers: Bitter comment is reported about Irish workers who return to Eire after six months, without paying tax (North Midland Region).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-176088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="234">Slacking to avoid paying tax is still reported. The case is mentioned of a nurse who said she was obliged to take far longer holidays than she used to, as otherwise she would be liable for tax.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-186088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="235">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.9) hhh 34. Servicemen's pensions and dependants' allowances</note>
				<note xml:id="q-196088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="236">During the past four weeks, there have again been complaints of the inadequacy of Service pensions - whether for dependants or for the men themselves (Four Regions), and of dependants' allowances (Three Regions, See Constant Topics, No.13).. There is, however, some feeling that the general treatment of cases has improved and there is praise for the work of the Pensions Appeals Tribunals; it is thought that more publicity about them might do good. There is, too, appreciation of the grant to widows for rent.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1a6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="237">Specific complaints mentioned (One Region each) are:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1b6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="238">(a) Employers arc discouraged from making up the pay of their employees who join up, because the amount allowed by the firm will be deducted' from the War Service Grant.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1c6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="239">(b) The hardship incurred, due to the time lag between the re­duction of a woman's War Service Grant and the increased allotment made to her husband.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1d6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="240">(c) The reduction in a dependant's allowance if she takes paid employment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1e6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="241">(d) The inclusion of a widow's Service pension for income tax.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1f6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="242">(3.4.5.7.9.11) hhh 35. Home Guard, fire-watching and Civil Defence</note>
				<note xml:id="q-206088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="243">Fire watching duties: During the past two weeks criticism has continued on lines previously reported, though the recent announce­ment of some alleviation of duty in areas where this can safely be made has given satisfaction. There is disappointment in some districts where no release is possible. One report states "the present increase in illness has brought fresh grumbles, and in industrial areas there is strong evidence of the deplorable effect of fire-watching on miners, heavy workers and housewives".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-216088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="244">Home Guard: Complaints have continued of the amount of duty required, particularly from workers already employed for long hours and those who have already trained for many Months. But keen members of the Home Guard again criticise it Walter Citrine's speech as implying a doubt of the value of their services and providing wavering members with an exclusive for shirking. They advocate a greater insistence on attendances. It is thought that the "browned-off" feeling persists probably because it no longer seems evident that the Home Guard has a function to perform, One report suggests that what is wanted is not a cutting down of the Home Guard but more time off, and that one 3unday n month would have a tremendous effect.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-226088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="245">Civil Defence: It is suggested in one report, that full-time C.D. personnel could, be detailed for work in shops and offices near their Headquarters.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-236088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="246">(1.2.3.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11. 18 six P.D.Rs.) hhh 36. Black-out</note>
				<note xml:id="q-246088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="247">During the past four weeks there has again been a comment on the depressing effect of the black-out, which some think might now be modified, especially in inland areas. Some people ask why side roads cannot have star-lighting like main roads. In London it is thought that grumbles have died down sharply since the raid on Putney.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-256088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="248">On the other hand laxity of black-out is criticised in some quarters and it is thought that torches used by people living buildings must show up more than scattered lights. Pedestrians, motorists and cyclists, all complain of the dangerous flashing of torches, and of the blinding effect of headlights with badly adjusted masks. Drivers who adhere to regulations are often at a disadvantage.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-266088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="249">(2.3.5.5SE.8.9.10. 18 nine P.D.Rs.) hhh 37. Transport difficulties</note>
				<note xml:id="q-276088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="250">During the past four weeks transport difficulties have continued 'to be widely reported, on familiar lines:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-286088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="251">(a) Inadequate rural bus services (Seven Regions). In some areas bus services are almost ''non-existent"..."buses only twice a week".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-296088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="252">(b) The early evening bus curfew (Seven Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="253">Workers complain they have no chance for recreation. The difficulties of people arriving by train after the last bus has gone are also mentioned.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="254">(c) Overcrowding (Six Regions), Excessive overloading is said to cause tiredness and irritation to workers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2c6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="255">(d) Long waits in bus queues (Five Regions). Workers complain that busses arrive in groups with long intervals in between.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="256">(e) Buses failing to stop and pick up passengers (Three Regions) Bus drivers are said to pass "request" stops and to put on a spurt if they see people running to catch the bus.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="257">(f) Incivility of transport employees (Three Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="258">(g) Withdrawal of return bus fares (Two Regions). This continues to cause indignation in the Northern and North Eastern Regions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-306088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="259">(h) Busses pulling away from stops before passengers are ready (Two Regions). There is said to have been increase in minor accidents in the North Western Region due to conductresses ringing the bus off before the passengers are ready.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-316088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="260">Holiday travel (Two Regions): Some people in the South Western Region are said to be intending to travel over Christmas heavy holiday traffic is also expected between Northern Ireland and Eire.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-326088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="261">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.13. 18 ton P.D.Rs.) hhh 38. Petrol</note>
				<note xml:id="q-336088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="262">During the past four weeks there have been several complaints of waste and misuse of petrol (Seven Regions). Unequal distri­bution of petrol is alleged and it is asked where private car owners get their petrol (Three Regions). Complaints are chiefly of petrol wasted by:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-346088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="263">(a) W.V.S. (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-356088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="264">(b) Civil Defence (Three Regions), particularly the N.F.S.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-366088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="265">(c) Taxis used for pleasure purposes (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-376088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="266">(d) The Forces (Two Regions).'</note>
				<note xml:id="q-386088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="267">(e) Farmers, Government officials, Home Guard (One Region each).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-396088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="268">The restoration of the basic petrol ration rumour has reappeared this week in reports from the North Eastern and North Western Regions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3a6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="269">(1.2.3.4.7.8.9.10. 18 two P.D.Rs.) hhh 39. Salvage</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3b6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="270">During the past four weeks, inadequate collection of salvage has been reported from four Regions. This, coupled with the alleged waste of paper' by (a) Government departments in sending out circulars, and (b) the display of commercial adver­tisements, is considered to be the reason for the falling off of public interest in salvage.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3c6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="271">(2.3.7.8.10)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3d6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="272">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3e6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="273">Copy No. 287</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3f6088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="274">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-406088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="275">HOME INTELLIGENCE WEEKLY REPORT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-416088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="276">The aim of this Report is to present an impartial assessment of public feeling about the war and the war effort. It is not a record of fact, except in so far as public opinion is itself a fact. The public is sometimes ill-informed, prejudiced, or inconsistent. The recording of such feelings without comment implies no endorsement of them.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-426088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="277">The public is more prone to criticise than to praise. Good work or efficiency is usually taken for granted in accurate record of expressed feeling will, therefore, tend to be critical rather than laudatory. Though this Report must inevitably represent mainly articulate opinion, it has been found in practice that the views of the less articulate do not substantially differ, though their range is smaller.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-436088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="278">The method of compiling the Report is such that the amount of space devoted to each subject, and the order in which subjects are placed, are roughly indicative of the amount of public interest each is arousing. The omission of a subject from the Report means that it is not a matter of widespread comment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-446088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="279">In assessing the state of public feeling there are no absolutes. Findings can only be comparative. Each Issue of this Report must therefore be road as part of a con­tinuous series. Unless the series is seen as a whole, the significance of fluctuations in feeling cannot be appreciated.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-456088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="280">The figures in brackets at the end of each section refer to sources of information, a list of which is given on the next page. The weekly reports from Regional Information Officers (R.I.Os.) are compiled by their Regional Intelligence Officers from a large number of sources. Details of the methods of compilation and cross-checking are contained in paper on "Hew the Home Intelligence Weekly Report is made." This will be supplied on request to the Homo Intelligence Division of the Ministry of Information.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-466088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="281">P.T.O.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-476088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="282">37138-1 hhh REFERENCES</note>
				<note xml:id="q-486088b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="283">1. Northern Region (Newcastle)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a4487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="284">2. North Eastern Region (Leeds)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a5487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="285">3. North Midland Region (Nottingham)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a6487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="286">4. Eastern Region (Cambridge)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a7487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="287">5. London Region (London)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a8487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="288">5SE. South Eastern District Office, London Region (Tunbridgo)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a9487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="289">6. Southern Region (Reading)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-aa487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="290">7. South Western Region (Bristol)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ab487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="291">8. Wales (Cardiff)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ac487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="292">9. Midland (Birmingham)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ad487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="293">10. North Western Region (Manchester)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ae487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="294">11. Scotland (Edinburgh)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-af487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="295">12. See 5SE.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b0487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="296">13. Northern Ireland (Belfast)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b1487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="297">14. Special Reports from R.I.Os.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b2487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="298">15. Regions Adviser's Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b3487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="299">16. M.O.I. Speakers Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b4487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="300">17. Postal Censorship</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b5487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="301">18. Police Duty Room Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b6487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="302">19. Wartime Social Survey Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b7487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="303">20. B.B.C. Listener Research Papers</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b8487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="304">21. B.B.C. Special Papers</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b9487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="305">22. Scottish Unionist Whips' Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ba487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="306">23. Liberal Party's Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bb487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="307">24. Primary Sources</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bc487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="308">1-13 are Weekly Reports from R.T.Os.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bd487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="309">D 37138-1 10,000 6/43 R P W</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>