<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Morale Report - February 1942, Based on reports from District and Divisional Commanders at Home</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-6ebca804-5bab-4f55-8269-e113ef9d9f60</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-93713359-e175-48e6-b425-111fe2577238</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-5d547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">SECRET.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5e547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="2">MORALE REPORT- FEBRUARY, 1942.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5f547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="3">(Based on reports from District and Divisional Commanders at Home in Feb. 1942 and Censorship Reports received at War Office, Mid-December 1941 to end of January, 1942. )</note>
				<note xml:id="q-60547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="4">PART I. UNITED KINGDOM. • hhh OFFENCES UNDER THE ARMY ACT.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-61547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">1. Absence without leave is still the predominant offence. There is little change in the numbers, An improvement in the situation is reported in some units due to officers taking an interest in the home life of their men and judicious handling of compassionate cases. Apart from absence there is very little "crime" in the Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-62547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">2. The causes of absence remain fundamentally the same. hhh CONFIDENCE.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-63547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">3. The will to win remains strong. There is a general desire to "get at" the enemy. The troops are puzzled by events in Libya. The Far East is looked upon as a long way off and reverses there were regarded as inevitable. Confidence in ultimate victory is unchanged.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-64547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">4. Confidence in arms and equipment remains high in general. Apprehension is, however, expressed in units in which there is a shortage of arms or equipment which they find difficult to reconcile with Lord Beaverbrook's statements on the supply situation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-65547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">8th Armoured Division reports that the R.E. have felt keenly the superiority of German R.E. equipment as revealed by "Know your Enemy" pamphlets. The issue of mobilization scales of equipment has done much to combat this, but there is still the feeling that our R.E. are inadequately supplied with bridging equipment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-66547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">Reports from A.A. Command show that the reduction in the number of Bofors in Light A.A. units causes some disquiet and that it is difficult to keep up confidence in the A.A. Lewis Gun.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-67547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">5. Criticism of the Press and the B.B. C. is general. It is felt that the cheap Press do not assist morale by their constant charges of inefficiency against the Government and by their frequent references to Colonel Blimp. Recent attacks on the Prime Minister are resented by the troops but they feel that all is not well with the rest of the Government.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-68547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">The troops, however, dislike to feel that they are not told the whole truth by either the Press or the B. B. C. when things go wrong and there is criticism that attempts are made to conceal reverses by giving undue prominence to minor successes; They feel the country should be trusted to stand being told the true story.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-69547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">Their respect for their leaders does not suffer by frank admissions. The reputation of General Wavell was enhanced by his admissions that he was "caught out" by the Axis attack on Libya.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6a547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">6. All Commanders speak well of the effect of A. B. C. A. talks. The effect of Russian successes and our own reverses has been to make men take an increased interest in the Russian system of discipline and Government.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6b547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">7. Unfavourable criticism of the loss of aerodromes continues and apprehension is expressed as regards the adequacy of measures for the defence of aerodromes at home.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6c547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">8. It is represented that Infantry Commanding Officers, especially of regular battalions, are becoming increasingly concerned about the indifferent type of man now in infantry battalions. The ever increasing tendency to remove from the infantry all who show any intelligence is felt to have reached the danger point. This remark is applied not only to other ranks but to the continual drain of the best officers. The new intake is said to be excellent material but as lists of potential tradesmen have already been called for, the anticipation is that few good men will be left after basic training. The opinion is expressed that every infantry battalion should have an establishment of D.S.P. tested men of Grade 1 - 3. Without this, there is no satisfactory source for future N.C.Os.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6d547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">9. The drafting of men from Field Force formations to units overseas has caused unsettlement and the idea that they are being used as depots has had some adverse effect on morale.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6e547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">10. The value of the work done by chaplains in those units which have their own chaplains is highly spoken of and there is regret that there are not enough chaplains for all units. As a chaplain can effect little good unless he gets to know men well, it is felt that where the services of civilian clergy are made use of they should be encouraged to spend more time in the unit's lines. hhh CONTENMENT.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6f547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">11. Interest in training and operations. This remains keen. There is e marked improvement where the men are properly informed as to what is happening during the training and their role fully explained by their officers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-70547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">12. Living conditions and surroundings.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-71547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">(a) Quarters. These are again reported as generally satisfactory but Eastern Command states that the provision of adequate accommodation still remains a most serious problem. The effect of the reorganisation of the Command under the recommendations of the Gale Committee carried out as from 1st January, 1942, and the consequent decentralisation of administrative responsibility, is leading to a better grip of this problem by "Q" staffs of the Formations concerned. Progress is however, still handicapped by the delay in implementing the recommendations of the King report on the reorganisation of the Works Services. Effect has only been given to these recommendations in a piecemeal manner, and the delegation of financial powers to Corps District and District Comds., and their Engineer advisors is still awaited.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-72547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">A.A. Command again report that bad lighting in huts still exists and is having a depressing effect.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-73547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">(b) Messing. Good throughout the Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-74547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">c ) N. A. A. F. I. Female staffs still come in for praise and are preferred to men staffs.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-75547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">Some comparisons are again made to better supplies available for R.A.F.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-76547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">The reports generally are quite satisfactory.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-77547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">(d) Recreation and Amusements. Generally satisfactory. Censorship reports show that efforts by officers to keep men interested and occupied in their leisure hours are widely appreciated.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-78547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">Some criticism of E.N.S.A. concerts which have a low tone. Mobile cinemas would be greatly appreciated at isolated sites,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-79547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">(e) Mail Services. Generally satisfactory. Some complaints at delays due to censorship in report from Northern Ireland.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7a547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">(f) Leave Generally satisfactory throughout all Commands. Troops in Shetland Islands complain of waste of time in transit.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7b547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">53rd Division say that men who exercised their option to take 14 days leave are envious of men who took 7 days now going on leave a second time. Discontinuance of option of 14 days is recommended.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7c547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">13. Finances and Pay.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7d547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">(a) The disparity between Army Pay and Civilian wages is the subject of universal and increasing complaint.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7e547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">(b) Adverse criticism is made as to the reward given by the Amy to skilled tradesmen and some unfavourable comparisons are made to the pay given to such men in the R.A.F.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7f547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">(c) Opinions are again expressed that the pay of junior officers is inadequate. The withdrawal of Field Allowance is the subject some unfavourable comment. 8th Amoured Division regards this as "A piece of unabashed chicanery and no amount of fair treatment in other respects counter- balances this grievance."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-80547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">(d) 3rd Divisional Commander reports as follows:- When names of volunteers from officers arc requested for service abroad, the instructions usually state that officers will proceed in their substantive, or war-substantive, ranks, with the object of being regranted their acting or temporary ranks on arrival at destination, but that no absolute guarantee of this can be given.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-81547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">Officers (other than subalterns) who are suitable and recommended for service abroad are almost invariably holding acting, or temporary rank higher than their substantive or war substantive rank. There is a feeling that it is not quite fair that officers should have to drop acting etc. rank and take their chance of again proving their worth on arrival overseas. Furthermore, should they die through enemy action during the voyage, any pension granted to the officer's widow would be paid on his substantive rank only.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-82547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">It is generally agreed that money should be saved whenever possible but there is apt to be a suspicion in officers' minds that the financial aspect is allowed to loom so large that reason and humanity do not receive full weight. (This question is now under consideration in the War Office.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-83547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">14. Conditions affecting families.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-84547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">(a) Men still prefer their womenfolk to go to factories rather than into the Womens' Services.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-85547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">(b) The men still allude unfavourably to the financial aspects. There has been insufficient time for the new Allowances granted by Parliament to have taken effect end consequently there was little, if any, reference to these.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-86547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">15. Relations between Officers, N.C.Os and men. These are good. There is, however, a general opinion that junior officers are weak in man management Few start with any appreciation of their responsibility of looking after their men and the constant change of officers makes it difficult to ensure that they acquire it. Platoon Commanders stay with their platoons such a short time that men rely on their Platoon Sergeants rather than their Platoon Commanders. This is bad for the officers, the sergeants and the men,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-87547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">16. Relations with A. T, S. and other Allied Services &amp; Dominion Forces.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-88547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">(a) The relations with the Navy continue to be uniformly good.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-89547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">(b) Relations with the R.A.F. are somewhat mixed. Those with the fighting personnel are good and the men admire them. Those with the ground staff are not so good. There is a feeling that they unduly take on themselves the reflected glory of the Fighting Staff, they live in comfortable quarters and generally speaking have a good life. There is further the feeling that the R. A. F. are better fed as they receive a large part of their rations in the form of a cash allowance which allows greater variety.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8a547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">(c) Relations with the A.T.S. are uniformly reported as good.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8b547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">(d) Relations with Dominions Forces uniformly satisfactory. The majority of Canadians writing home allude to the good relations with the local population. There are however, some adverse comments on the hostility and unfriendly attitude of the British. The natural British "Reserve" is misunderstood by the Canadians, They do however, resent the tendency to attribute to all the misbehaviour of a few "bad eggs".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8c547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">Relation between British and Canadian Troops on the whole is good. Attachment of Canadians to British Units and vice versa has been very successful in improving relations.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8d547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">(e) Allied Forces. H. Q., B. T. N. I. report as regards the AMERICANS.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">The arrival of American Troops has been well received. Any adverse comment comes mainly from those who have met no American Troops. Americans so far are not throwing their weight about, they seen to be well behaved, quiet and anxious to learn. (We try to let the initiative for demonstrations etc. cone from them). I think the greatest danger is an "attempt to patronize by our very much better trained troops."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">Relations with the Poles are now very satisfactory. Other Allied Forces are not referred to. hhh EFFICIENCY.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-90547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">17. High standard of fitness and discipline has been maintained.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-91547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="53">PART II. OVERSEAS.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-92547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">The following is a summary of the censorship reports which have been received :- hhh GENERAL.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-93547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">16. "Operations in M/E have had a tonic effect in that Command. The morale of all troops is high, and the inspiring effect of adequate air support is most noticeable.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-94547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">The stiffness of the task ahead is fully appreciated, but confidence is not thereby impaired. Great annoyance has been expressed against the B. B. C. and the Press for their over-exuberance and hankering for quick results, which, it is felt, does not do justice to the difficulties and magnitude of the task.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-95547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">There is evidence of a certain physical weariness, but confidence and determination are as strong as ever. Perhaps the situation is best summed up in the following extract: "The life is grand, it's good to see the Nazis getting a taste of their own medicine. Physically I have never been fitter . . . . . it's the roughest possible life, absolutely no comfort at all except for plenty of tobacco and rum. In spite of this I would far rather be out here than skulking in England". hhh PARTICULAR AREAS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-96547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">19. Iceland (C). (26. Nov. 1941. - 26. Jan. 1942.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-97547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">Morale and fighting spirit is good and no serious complaints about conditions. Welfare arrangements improved.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-98547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">References to improvement in food and entertainments and amusements.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-99547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">Relations with civilians improving.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">Good relations with U.S. Marines has not been so good with troops of other Arms of U.S. Army who have now arrived.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">20. Middle East Force. (12. Nov. 1941. - 13. Jan. 1942.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">(a) British Troops in Egypt. Libyan Campaign is the main topic. Skill and toughness of enemy appreciated by the Troops which they feel has been under-rated by Press. Troops in forward areas know General Rommel's Army had not been reduced to the sorry plight described by the Press. There is confidence and optimism amongst the British Troops.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9d547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">Complaints and praise for the Postal Service appear in equal doses. Conditions in hospitals receive very favourable comments from all. Writers continue to urge their women-folk not to join the A.T.S., or to volunteer for service overseas. Some concern is expressed over the behaviour of Dominion Forces in the United Kingdom, and rumours of immorality by Canadians appear to be gaining ground. It would appear that correspondents from hone refer to the subject a good deal.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9e547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">(b) Palestine and Syria Widespread optimism from offensive in Libya though most realise the campaign will be hard. Praise and complaint of mail about equal.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9f547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">(c) Sudan. Enthusiasm over fate of Gondar and British and Russian offensive. Morale is good.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a0547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">(d) New Zealand Expeditionary Force. At the beginning of the period morale was of the highest order, although it was admitted that the fighting has been bitter and the casualties heavy. The extent of air support has been freely commented on, and favourably compared with Greece and Crete. While still good, morale has been appreciably lowered by events in the Pacific. The majority of the troops wish to be returned home, now that operations against Bardia have been successfully completed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a1547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">(e) Union Defence Force. This mail is healthy and cheerful, and displays grim determination, and a desire to avenge the men who fell in the battle of Sidi Rezegh. Confidence in the outcome of the campaign is in no way diminished. Much pride was expressed for the South African's part in the operations against Bardia. There was much praise for the efficiency of the Postal Services during the operations. All feel that the situation as regards food and water must be accepted in the circumstances, and a veteran of the last war remarks "This is a different army everything possible is done for the troops, surely they won't give us medals for this".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a2547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">(f) Australian Imperial Force. Anxiety to be in action is again displayed, and some show annoyance at being kept out of Libya, which they regard as their own particular hunting ground. The work of the R.H.A. in Tobruk is praised and relations with then appear to have boon cordial.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a3547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">Since the developments in the Far East, morale continues to be excellent. At first there were many demands to be returned hone but these have become noticeably fewer. The advance in Libya, the successes in Russia, the slowing up of the Japanese advance and General Wavell's appointment all added to their confidence.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a4547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">Rumours of U.S. troops being sent to Australia have gained credence and are not popular.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a5547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">There are few complains beyond the scarcity of tobacco and cigarettes, and profiteering in local shops.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a6547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">Conscription of munition workers in Australia is advocated, on news being received of strikes; some saying it is not good for morale to have to fight for "scum" who want money, while the troops lack equipment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a7547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">(g) Polish Force. Morale is excellent, and many references are made to the good relations existing with the British troops whom they call "their best friends", and talk of their "best memories" being while serving with them. Polish troops who took part in operations at Tobrut and Gazala speak with pride of the Brigade's fine showing. There were frequent references to General Sikorski's visit which it is felt will have beneficial results.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a8547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">(h) Free French Force.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a9547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">Dis-union existing in Free French possessions, and among Free Frenchmen abroad, was mentioned by several writers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-aa547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">(i) Greek and Cypriot Mail,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ab547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">The morale of the Royal Greek Army remains high. They are patriotic and grateful to England and appreciate their reception and treatment in Rhodesia. An improvement is noticed in the tone of the Cypriot mail, though delays and pilfering of mails and lack of leave to Cyprus continue to cause dissatisfaction. The morale of those in the fighting zone is high, this should produce an excellent effect in Cyprus.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ac547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">(j) India Personnel.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ad547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">(i) Egypt and Syria. Morale high, Entire confidence in victory in Libya. Increase in discouragement to relatives at home to enlist. Discouraging news from Bengal. Population stated to be panic-stricken.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ae547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">(ii) Sudan and Eritrea. Morale high.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-af547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">(k) Palestinians The tone of the mail is generally one of revenge against the Germans. They resent the good work done by Jews not being distinguished from the work of Arab recruits, pointing out that, with a Jewish population one third that of the Arabs, they have produced 10,000 men against 1,500 Arabs.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b0547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">They look forward to adequate rewards after the war, not "white papers".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b1547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">More adequate allowances for families, in view of the cost of living are demanded.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b2547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">The enlistment of women in Palestine has evoked much comment, but the earlier favourable impression has not been sustained. The women's response is satisfactory but the men discourage their women-folk from joining - for economic, social and moral reasons.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b3547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">The usual praise of rations and billets is noticed, but troops and civilians alike blame the authorities for their inability to stamp out profiteering in the shops.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b4547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">(l) Maltese (in Egypt and Palestine), The Maltese appear to be homesick and complain bitterly of postal delays.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b5547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">Concern is expressed at the continuous enemy air activity over the island, and writers express a desire to participate in the defence of Malta.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b6547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">(m) East Africa.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b7547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">(i) Admiration expressed for Russian resistance. Few comments on Libyan Campaign but the men realise the campaign will not be easy. v(ii) Morale of S. African Troops good, due to evacuation of details to the Union, Fighting spirit good. Chief complaints are:- boredom, postal delays and not being returned to the Union,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b8547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">21. West Africa</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b9547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">Morale good and troops on friendly terms with natives. There is a good deal of boredom and anxiety in being far from home.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ba547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">Factors which may sap morale in time are :-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bb547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">(i) Ill health (chiefly Malaria);</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bc547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">(ii) The climate and the flies:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bd547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">(iii) Monotony and boredom in the evenings, especially when the cinema breaks down;</note>
				<note xml:id="q-be547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">(iv) Postal delays. Resentment is shown at post offices in the U.K. accepting letters, When it is alleged no air mail service exists.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bf547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">(v) Having to take leave in South Africa instead of in the U.K. (as a rule); those that come home on leave very much resent having to revert to their substantive rank.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c0547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">(vi) The welfare officers appear to be a somewhat mixed bag.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c1547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">22. Gibraltar.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c2547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">Morale satisfactory.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c3547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">23. Faroe Islands.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c4547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">Morale and fighting spirits good. Weather causes depression.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c5547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">More could be done in the matter of recreations and amusements during long winter evenings.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c6547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">24. Aruba and Curacoa,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c7547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">Morale good. Certain boredom at lack of "action". Recreation and sport ample. Food and accommodation good.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c8547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="108">25. British Mission in Russia.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c9547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="109">Well treated, well fed, well housed and entertained. Russian troops praised for courage and hard work. Arrival of equipment etc. from Britain has strengthened Russian morale.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ca547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="110">Prevailing feeling seems to think that war between Russia and Germany will be over in the</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cb547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="111">Spring. The only complaints are- the apparent muddle over allowances and rates of exchange, long delay in mails, lack of reading material, and the high cost of everything in Russia.</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>