<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Monthly Report on Morale and Public Opinion - December 1946</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-397f312c-cc0a-4ece-b110-7acbfd24407d</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-19ea286d-5b60-4158-9831-858eeb04e019</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-4a4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="1">Tel: 447755</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="2">Ext: 8500</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">609/PS/S/10/16</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="4">Public Safety</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="5">HQ Military Government</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="6">Hansestadt Hamburg</note>
				<note xml:id="q-504f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="7">609 HQ CCG</note>
				<note xml:id="q-514f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="8">BAOR</note>
				<note xml:id="q-524f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="9">14 December, 1946</note>
				<note xml:id="q-534f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="10">Subject: Monthly report on Morale and Public Opinion</note>
				<note xml:id="q-544f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">Regional Governmental Officer</note>
				<note xml:id="q-554f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">There is forwarded herewith the above mentioned report for the month ending 10 December, 1946.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-564f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="13">Deputy inspector General, Public Safety</note>
				<note xml:id="q-574f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="14">HAMBURG MSO’R/MSG</note>
				<note xml:id="q-584f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">Secret</note>
				<note xml:id="q-594f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="16">Tel: 34 10 00</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="17">Ext: 8500</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="18">…./PS/S/10/16</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="19">Public Safety</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5d4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="20">HQ Military Government</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5e4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="21">Hansestadt Hamburg</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5f4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="22">609 HQ CCG</note>
				<note xml:id="q-604f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="23">BAOR</note>
				<note xml:id="q-614f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="24">13 December, 1946</note>
				<note xml:id="q-624f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="25">Subject: Monthly report on Morale and Public Opinion</note>
				<note xml:id="q-634f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="26">The Regional Commissioner,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-644f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="27">H.Q. Military Government,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-654f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="28">Hansestadt Hamburg</note>
				<note xml:id="q-664f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">1. In the past the average Hamburger was only abstractly conscious of the British; he had been taught to consider them as racially acceptable and as the two countries developed at a distance there was no ground for national enmity. Later, although German leaders began to instill the suspicion that the British were hampering German attempts at natural expansion both economically and politically, the first world war that followed nevertheless was fought without any special venom and more often than not with a sense of sentimental regret. Came the Nazis and the second world war again without any basic change in the German conception of the Britisher, in spite of the skilled and considerable efforts to poison those views. When the British took over the occupation of Hamburg, the average citizen remembered his basically friendly feelings and the much worse occupation alternatives he might have suffered. He hoped for a response inspired by a common interest and expected leniency, a measure of humanity, understanding and help. He did not then, and probably does not to-day realise how much he relied on the integrity of the British as a people in spite of his cynical admiration for their 'virtue'. At that time most were prepared to admit they had erred and many were ready to atone, provided political and moral recovery was aided by the prospect of a return to a life not entirely barren of hope, purpose and dignity.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-674f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">The closer view he has had during the last eighteen months of the British has not on the whole brought disappointment in any basic respect. Omitting these who give fiercely prejudiced allegiance to Germany, the Hamburger has found the British conform to his conception of them as a correct, kindly and often helpful people. There is little reason to dislike them personally and the best among them inspire respect and confidence. While their presence en masse acts as an irritant to national pride, there is no general animosity when British and German meet as an individuals and there is a sincere desire on the part of many for such meetings.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-684f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">The matter however is different in so far as Military Government is concerned. To the German it is the source and embodiment of all his difficulties and frustrations. In it he has found an impersonal entity on which he can fasten his rage and helplessness and can vent the bitterness and hostility which injury to self-respect, national pride and arrogance have left him. hhh 2. FOOD</note>
				<note xml:id="q-694f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">The general mass of the population continues to feed its animosity towards Mil. Gov. on the deplorable food situation which is viewed as going from bad to worse. Food remains the principal concern of everyone and the consensus of opinion is that early fears as to what the winter would bring have now been fully justified by existing realities. The approach of Christmas which has always been lavishly celebrated in Germany by rich and poor alike, is producing its special accent of bitterness.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6a4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">It is generally conceded that fats is the most severely missed item of the diet. Although the Germans have always been heavy meat eaters it is considered that the present ration is no meagre that its absence would scarcely be noticed if a better and more constant supply of staple foods were provided. Many complaints are made of the supply of potatoes and cereals. It is estimated that at least one third of the Hamburg population have not yet had their winter allotment of potatoes. Although weekly supplies of potatoes are again available the supply of cereals has not always been maintained and there is dissatisfaction respecting both the quality and quantity distributed, it is remembered that the cereal and fish ration were both reduced at the beginning of the last ration period, while Quarg (Cottage Cheese) was struck off the ration altogether and an additional pound of potatoes per week substituted. This juggling of calorific values in an attempt to maintain the official rate causes great concern, as it is considered this did not give a fair return in true food value.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6b4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">Public resentment in respect of food has two main targets: the British, who are accused of not doing enough to relieve an intolerate situation, and the German farmer who enriches himself at the expense of the urban population, while enjoying the tolerant protection of the Conservative elements entrenched in the Zentralamt fur Landwirtschaft. Charges of large scale hoarding with a view to securing higher prices or as a security measure in anticipation of another war, are also being levelled at other countries.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6c4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">The recent importation of turnips from Denmark met with much derision. Although it is generally conceded that they are of better quality than the native product, the popular mind tends to represent such imports as the best efforts the Allies are prepared to make on Germany's behalf.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6d4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">The recent British decision to kill 60% of all cattle and 33% of all pigs in the British Zone has been violently assailed on economic grounds. The official explanation that this measure was necessary to maintain the present meat ration finds no support in the popular mind which views this as economically destructive on one hand and further evidence of Allied reluctance to give real help on the other. hhh 3. Fuel</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6e4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">The small quantity of winter fuel distributed at the beginning of October remains the first and only issue. It can be assumed that this issue has now been used up as the recent reduction in gas made its use for cooking as well as heating purposes unavoidable. People consider themselves grimly fortunate in that the winter has been comparatively mild so far, but nevertheless appreciate the three coldest months lie ahead. It is remembered that it was the original intention to issue approximately 15 cwts to each family of four. Subsequent announcements that consumption of gas and electricity will be counted against this total have caused grave concern, especially in view of the fact that no official explanation has been given as to the method of calculation and the probable size of the resulting cut.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6f4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">Considerable hostility has been raised by the intention of Mil. Gov. to cut down the greater part of the remaining trees in Hamburg throughfares and parks. This measure, it is pointed out, would have yielded only five pounds of wood per head, and it is not yet known what effect the protests of the Landeswirtschaftsamt have had on this decision.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-704f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">Many opinions are being expressed as to the manner in which both British and German authorities are attempting to attract labour to the mines. British efforts to idealise the role and social function of the miner are openly derided as reminiscent of Dr. Ley's coaxing, when he "ennobled" the whole German working class and simultaneously lowered its living standards. The outcome of the Ruhr miners referendum seems to support the view that attempts at favourable discrimination are resented by miners and other alike in exercise of the common feeling that a sectional solution to present difficulties is wholly unacceptable. hhh 4. Public Health</note>
				<note xml:id="q-714f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">As a natural and inevitable result of the food situation the state of Public Health has declined and is a matter of increasing concern to the medical profession and laymen alike. There is scarcely an individual in Hamburg to whom the general decline in health within his own circle of relatives and friends is not obvious. Previous forecasts that 10% of the total population would contract T.B. now, are said to have been well-founded and probably on the conservative side. Physical resistance generally is at the point where even the most minor ailment invites serious consequences. It is this general susceptibility to diseases which constitutes the main danger in the public mind, while T.B. holds frightening first place. Much real concern is also expressed in respect of the increase in venereal diseases. The hospital situation is said to be critical. People in need of medical attention are required to queue for hours to the detriment of their health. Bed space in hospitals is totally inadequate and the suggestion is frequently made that the Barmbeck Krankenhaus should be released by Mil. Gov. to alleviate the position. It is asserted that only one quarter of this hospital's potential is at present in use. hhh 5. Black Market</note>
				<note xml:id="q-724f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">The decline in buying power continues. The approach of Christmas may in part explain the apparent shortage in the availability of cigarettes, coffee, tea and fats which continue to be most in demand. Fuel, especially coke and coal, is becoming more sought after daily.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-734f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">There remains of course a percentage of responsible people who appreciate that what remains of public decency and social virtue is becoming submerged in the struggle for life maintenance. It is this section of the population which is agitating for more effective measures of control although they feel that the Black Market will disappear only with the lessening of want and a return to normalcy.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-744f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">Police measures have received their share of criticism and the opinion remains prevalent that it is mainly owing to the supply of certain commodities from Allied sources that the Black Market retains its vitality. To many it follows logically that this constitutes a deliberate and insidious means of economic exploitation by the occupying power. hhh 6. Housing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-754f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">Though by no means comparable to the large scale eviction which began in July, the requisitioning of houses and flats during the latter half of November has met with an angry response. It is recalled with bitterness that Mr. Hynd had given assurance that confiscation of living space had come to an end. It is generally accepted that these recent evictions were not ordered by the Control Commission but were instituted by the Army authorities.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-764f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">It is alleged that less care and consideration in the providing of alternative accommodation is being exercised on the British side now than during the large scale operation carried out in July. Complaints are also being made that derequisitioned houses and flats are sometimes left in a state which does little credit to the nation whose representatives occupied them.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-774f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">The recent announcement that the requisitioning of living quarters has now definitely come to an end is not believed. It is hinted in some quarters that individual British Officers of conservative political leanings are more or less deliberately sabotaging the policy and decisions of the Labour Government in this respect.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-784f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">In the absence of an official announcement it is no longer believed that Hamburg is to be the Headquarters of the British Zonal Administration as was intended on the initiation of the Hamburg Project. In view of this there is an extra dose of venom in the allegation that many of the houses which were originally requisitioned for this purpose have neither been put to their intended use not derequisitioned.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-794f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">The housing strain in Hamburg is undoubtedly considerable and in conjunction with the health situation probably constitutes the main obstacle to a steady recovery in general morale and a lessening of the present tension.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7a4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">A considerable stir has been created by the announcement in last week's papers that Fallingbostel (near Luneburg) which can accommodate 30,000 people remains virtually uninhabited. Until recently this was a large centre for Polish DP's. It is complained that little effort has been made to use the facilities now available there to relieve overcrowding in other areas. hhh 7. Building</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7b4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">Much attention has been paid to an article by Prof. Martin Wagner in "Die Welt" of 12th November 1946 entitled "building which becomes us". Although not reaching the dimensions of a public controversy, a great deal of discussion is … around the problem of what, in view of the scarcity of building materials, should enjoy priority. Those who are housed in reasonable comfort by existing standards are inclined to the view that the repair of public buildings etc. should be given priority as one means of restoring a sense of civic normalcy, whereas other less well housed insist than an immediate measure of housing comfort should be the first consideration. As is usual the dividing line is largely determined by the sum of the people's most urgent requirements.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7c4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">There is much criticism of alleged malpractices and mismanagement in the civic administration dealing with repairs and construction. The Bauaufsichsamt is still the main target, it being said that its allocations lack any recognisable and ordered purpose, that many of its practices are corrupt, and that the priorities given cannot be justified by what is either necessary or useful. hhh 8. Clothing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7d4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">There has been no noticeable change in respect to such vitally needed items as shoes, stockings, underwear etc. in spite of repeated announcements in the press that the demand would shortly be relieved by the issue of clothing permits to the most urgent cases. In the meantime, general shabbiness of dress has become more and more obvious, clothing has been mended and recut time and time again until it is worn to shreds and scarcity of mending yarn and wool makes even repairs most difficult. Growing numbers of school children no longer possess footwear in which to attend school. Although much ingenuity has been shown in using clothing and footwear to the best possible advantage, resources are now coming to an end.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7e4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">Bitter comment has been caused by the announcement that farmers and farm workers would be given priority when the new and increased issue of clothing permits take place. The opinion is widespread that this class of person has parasitically enriched himself at the expense of the general population, is probably better fed and clothed than most and therefore should not be given special consideration. hhh 9. Electrical Supply</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7f4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">Despite the notice which appeared in the Press to the effect that as the electricity position had improved it was again possible to recommence day work in industrial and manufacturing enterprises, there are still many factories working late shifts. Absenteeism among night workers is on the increase, as the reasons which influence the workers concerned against the continuance of night work acquires new weight with the growth of fatigue and the promise of relief.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-804f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">Public opinion is strongly pressing for increases in street lighting particularly with the object of providing security against attacks by thieves and robbers. As night work has not ceased entirely and street lighting has not improved, complaints continue to be voiced that the British are wasting electricity by an excessive and irresponsible use of light and energy in every premises they occupy. hhh 10. Landeswirtschaftsamt</note>
				<note xml:id="q-814f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">There is great and widespread discontent with the Landeswirtschaftsamt both on the grounds of bureaucratic inefficiency and suspected corruption. The allocation and distribution of clothing permits is particularly criticised in that individuals with properly certified priorities find it a matter of pure chance as to whether or not they can obtain coupons. At some local Wirtschaftsamter queues begin to form at 4 and 5 o'clock in the morning in the hope that they will be able to obtain clothing coupons when the doors open. The impression persists that there are considerable stocks of clothing and footwear in Hamburg and this is borne out by reports of shop breakings in which considerable quantities of clothing, and particularly footwear are stolen. It is the discrepancy between what is thought to be available and the actual number of permits issued which is the main cause of discontent. On the whole it cannot be said that the Landeswirtschaftsamt enjoys any measure of confidence among the population, who believe that too many former Nazis are in responsible positions and many others are open to graft.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-824f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">At the moment a great deal of criticism centres on Dr. Heydorn mainly on the strength of his alleged membership of the NSDAP. Borgner (SPD) is also being criticised, it being the general belief that he furnished his office with furniture taken from the homes of former Nazis. hhh 11. Police</note>
				<note xml:id="q-834f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">A large bulk of the population consider that the Police are doing a fair to good job under the present difficult circumstances. Criticism is however directed against the Police in that the majority find little or no improvement in its attitude towards the public by comparison with the Hitler or pre-Hitler period and that there is much corruption in the force. Another unfavourable aspect is that many consider that there are far too many young men performing duties which bring into close and intimate contact with the public. A point which is repeatedly made is that the Hamburg Police will never enjoy full public confidence so long as many of its members are non-Hamburgers. A strong sense of civic pride obtains in Hamburg and the public will probably never be satisfied while its relationship with the Police lacks intimacy strongly flavoured with local habit and idiom.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-844f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">The traffic education week would have fallen on more fertile ground if it had not emphasised the deplorable situation in respect of overcrowding on trams, trains and buses, etc. Its purpose and potential value were not questioned but people who had to let five and six trams pass by found it intolerable to be politely pulled off the seventh.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-854f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">Some comment has been caused by the appearance of the Hamburg police in blue. It is thought that the police have been issued with large quantities of new clothing and that this is an excessive luxury in a time of general scarcity. It is not infrequently remarked that this cloth would have been better used for clothing refugees and other needy people. hhh 12. Denazification</note>
				<note xml:id="q-864f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">In general public reaction is one of weariness and the number of responsible voices clamouring for a speedy end to denazification is on the increase. A number of genuine anti-Nazis are expressing the opinion that denazification has been productive mostly of unjustifiable hardship and that it is materially contributing to the general process of demoralisation. Few responsible people believe that denazification is contributing to political, social or economic health and that the positive results are counter-balanced by the moral havoc it creates. Such righteous fervour, detached zeal and honest conviction as it originally commanded has long since been expended. It is difficult to find anyone capable or willing to advocate its desirability either in terms of immediate social usefulness or as being in harmonious accord with the political or economics ends to which popular feeling and conviction subscribe.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-874f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">It is difficult of course to estimate popular opinion accurately as there is scarcely a case where passion and self-interest do not intrude. The Wohnungsamt is a case in point. Such denazification as has taken place has certainly not resulted in inspiring confidence among the general population but it is obvious that little or no political principle is at stake here but only the desperate efforts of all to improve their housing at the expense of former Nazis. If there seems little doubt that the Wohnungsamt has laid itself wide open to charges of mismanagement, corruption and favouring of Nazis, it is not because Nazis have remained in office there but because former Nazis are successfully resisting the encroachment on their social interests by others whose best weapon is nothing more than a pseudo-political smoke screen. hhh 13. Deportation</note>
				<note xml:id="q-884f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">The first and violent general reaction which followed the announcement of Russian deportations of German workers and technicians to the USSR has now died down. This is by no means only due to the fact that no further reports have since appeared. The violence of the first reaction was largely conditioned by a general dislike for the Russians and the popular conception of conditions there, grounded in the aftertones of Nazis anti-Russian propaganda and supported by the recent experience of many who fought and, in some cases, were prisoners of war there. Public opinion has definitely sobered since as a consequence of a reassessment of the present position. Many view the future of Germany with such scepticism and hopelessness that the prospect of work, security and provision of the necessities of life irrespective of where these may be found has become a factor of such weight that traditional resistances, as they specially apply to USSR, have been or are being broken down. In this they are aided by the belief that the workers and technicians deported were need badly enough for this to act as a safeguard to those expectations which make their continued usefulness possible. hhh 14. Burgerschaft and Ober-Burgermeister Brauer</note>
				<note xml:id="q-894f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">On the whole the new Senate is given a fair chance of showing competence and efficiency in their administration. The circumstances attending its birth, however, have led to the not unpopular belief that the SPD showed signs of an authoritarian approach in the manner in which it conducted negotiations with the CDU. This belief is not confined to disappointed adherents of the CDU. Many in Hamburg had hoped for a more politically unbiased effort to achieve a four party coalition senate. It is especially regretted that failure to reach agreement with the CDU resulted in a loss to the Senate of Dr. Ketels, who is generally considered as the most competent expert available on economics.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8a4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">It is generally conceded that Oberburgermeister Brauer can be counted to side with the more conciliatory and responsible wing of his party. His personal integrity is unquestioned, he is well remembered for his services in Altona and it is thought that his long stay abroad has both broadened his sense of responsibility and widened his vision. There is scarcely a discordant note in respect of his nomination as Oberburgermeister. hhh 15. Press &amp; Wireless, etc.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8b4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">General disgust with the newspaper situation continues, it still being difficult for the average citizen to obtain a newspaper, and more particularly the newspaper he would prefer. While it is, in present circumstances, too early to assume which of the papers printed is the most popular, it can be said that the "Die Zeit" and "Die Welt" remain the two Hamburg papers which are read by preference, "Die Zeit" being viewed as conservative voice in political and cultural matters and being applauded for its scope and approach in dealing with social problems. "Die Welt" on the other hand receives praise for its attempt at objective and impartial reporting and although it is known that it is the "British" paper, criticism on these grounds is expressed only infrequently.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8c4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">The "Hamburger Allgemeine Zeitung" is colourless and badly edited, the "Freie Presse" strives to be fair and responsible, the "Hamburger Echo" (SPD) is widely read mainly on the strength of the viewpoint it represents, while the "Hamburger Volkszeitung" is generally derided as one sided by all but those who share its direction.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8d4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">All newspapers share public commiseration for having to project official announcements and officially inspired views mainly with regard to the calorific theme. It is thought that considerable progress has been made towards establishing the freedom of the Press to public articles and comment on all subjects of popular theme and discussion, with the exception of Mil. Gov.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">The Nordwestdeutsche Rundfunk seems far from having regained the position of attention and approval it enjoyed prior to 1933. While a few items on its present programme are applauded either for their cultural or entertainment value, it is generally thought that's its programme directorate underrates public taste and capacity for serious and worthwhile talks, etc. It is considered that many of its programmes are planned and produced on the assumption that levity and a certain cheapness are necessary requirements for an easing of the prevalent tension. There is general resentment to this patronising inference that lighthearted and shallow "aid" is preferable to an attempt to awaken or sustain the best in the needs and instincts of the people.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">The considerable demand for books, magazines and journals remains largely unfulfilled. At a recent auction of books, prints and graphs, sums were bid which made it practically impossible for the average person to acquire a single book however much he wanted it, unless he was one of the "nouveau riches" or fortified by backing from abroad. hhh 16. Economy</note>
				<note xml:id="q-904f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">The fear of widespread unemployment plus a sub-standard of life haunts many. Concern still centres on the non-agreement by the Occupying Powers as to the ways and means which will enable Germany to re-establish herself economically. The most humble man in the street sense that his life and hopes are vitally affected by the absence of decision which would regulate Germany's return to a self-functioning if supervised economy.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-914f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">Although some hopes have been raised by the recent announcement that less coal would be exported in future, it is appreciated that important as coal is to all economic activity there remain many other facros which require attention.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-924f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">The belief appears to be growing in the minds of the informed and uninformed alike that Britain and her allies are not only out to exploit all remaining German resources of material, labour and skill but equally to frustrate Germany's return as a competitor in international trade and industry. This may be taken as sign of growing "nationalism" and of implying to the Allies a far reaching fear of quality of German production and the diligence and resourcefulness of her traders.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-934f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">Superimposed on the general concern for Germany's economy is the struggle between two economic conceptions; the first adhering to the concept of private enterprise as the mainstay of all economic life, the second aiming at socialisation of all principal economic activities. Both are unanimous in the desire for an independent if supervised all-German economy. hhh 17. Rumours</note>
				<note xml:id="q-944f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">Much of the remaining warlike capacity in the Russian zone is working full blast for the Russians. Junkers Works in Dessau are producing jet fighters and the former German fighter Galland together with many former members of the Luftwaffe have been inducted into the Russian air force.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-954f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">A persistent rumour from Lubeck: a number of well-known naval officers have entered into Russian service and complete crews of German U-Boat personnel continue to serve under Russian command.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-964f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">The German Army of General v. Seydlitz, who was captured at Stalingrad together with General Paulus, is being trained and held in readiness for war. The conflict which is pending between East and West clearly focuses on Lubeck where many people are preparing to evacuate. The British are bring a noticeable number of new armoured units into Germany and tank ditches are being dug on the Russio-British boundary.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-974f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">Former members of the German Luftwaffe are being trained in Schleswig-Holstein.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-984f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">A recent report in the "Freie Presse" to the effect that a bottled message, pertaining to the fate Hitler is alleged to have suffered whilst on his way to the Argentine in a submarine, had been found near the Danish coast, has revised a good deal of popular speculation concerning both the manner and the likelihood of his death.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-994f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">The lenient treatment which Japan is receiving as compared to Germany is founded on American desire to have a jumping off place to the East. This rumour finds much credence as the USA and USSR are viewed as the principal antagonists in international power politics.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="81">HAMBURG</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="82">DEPUTY INSPECTOR GENERAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="83">PUBLIC SAFETY</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>