<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Weekly Report by Home Intelligence - No. 26 - 2 April 1941</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-a60f1d9f-23a8-4c04-8c0b-b690b4655a11</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-f6a95bfb-5da7-4a83-952a-4d8c5670da78</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-e75888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e85888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">Copy No 32</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e95888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="3">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ea5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="4">Weekly Report by Home Intelligence - No.26.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-eb5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">(From Wednesday 26th March, to Wednesday 2nd April, 1941)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ec5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">Note: The figures in brackets refer to sources of information, a list of which is given at the end of this report.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ed5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="7">I. GENERAL COMMENTS hhh 1. General state of confidence and reaction to news.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ee5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">This week, the decline in heavy raids and. the news from the Mediterranean, Yugo-Slavia, and Africa have combined to produce an atmosphere of optimism and cheerfulness about the war. The revolution in Yugo-Slavia was welcomed with surprise as a "sign that we have regained the diplomatic initiative", and as an indication that the neutral countries are at last realising which is going to be the winning side". The news has produced all the more effect because the great majority of people had previously regarded Yugo-Slavia as being as good as German.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ef5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">There are still a few who are anxious about the ability of Greece (and, indeed,Yugo-Slavia) to stand up to German attack without military assistance ,and if we do assist her, they fear another Dunkirk; but for the most part, people are well content to contemplate the present without speculating about the future.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f05888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">The advances in Africa and the Naval victory in the Mediterranean have led many people to expect that one or two more heavy blows will sec Italy definitely out of the war. Indeed, what is described as "the turn of the tide in our favour" is felt to be so obvious that optimists are predicting that the war will be over before the end of the year. The Naval successes were a particularly welcome tonic at Plymouth.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f15888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">It is reported that a considerable number of people trace a causal connection between the week's successes and the National Day of Prayer.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f25888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">In Glasgow, as an apparent result of the raids, there was much greater interest in, and enthusiasm about, the news than is usual. Another post-blitz change of sentiment in Glasgow is a new feeling of partnership with the English blitzed cities; "The people are now satisfied that they are bearing their full share of Britain's difficulties, and bearing it just as well". Disbelief in the official casualty figures has continued to be widespread, but no reports have been received since Mr. Morrison announced the revised figures **. A similar disbelief in the official figures is reported from Liverpool, Birkenhead, and Wallasey. In Wales, too, there are said to be doubts about the total figures for February, in view of the extent of the Cardiff and Swansea raids.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f35888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">** Mr. Morrison said that since the communique was issued on March 18 giving the figures of casualties in the two night raids on Clydeside on March 13 and 14, the numbers had risen and now amounted for the two nights combined to about 1,100 killed and 1000 seriously injured.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f45888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">He explained that it was impossible in the early stages to obtain definite figures.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f55888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">He felt it important to correct any impression that the original announcements were deliberately designed to minimise the seriousness of the damage sustained.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f65888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">In London, it is reported that, in the badly bombed boroughs, people soon to be taking longer to recover from the raids than they did last year; they are, however, very appreciative of the greatly improved social services for dealing with post-raid conditions (administrative centres, rest centres etc.); the only adverse comments reported are about insufficiency of staff to deal quickly with the applicants, and about delay in salvaging furniture.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f75888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">The government invasion instructions continue to be welcomed as "a sensible precaution". The main invasion problem now seems to be the method of distinguishing our own troops from Germans dressed in our uniforms, and special identification marks are being suggested by the public. But belief in the likelihood_ of invasion is now very low. The same attitude is reported towards the official advice about gas. "There is no undue perturbation", but several reports state that many people would welcome compulsory gas-mask carrying.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f85888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">The seriousness of the Battle of the Atlantic is fully realised, and as an apparent consequence, grumbles about food are few.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f95888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">The popularity of America is steadily rising. The mention of American aid at meetings and in cinemas is now often greeted with applause. One report suggests that a broadcast by "the ordinary American man in the street", on the lines of "In Town Tonight" would be much appreciated.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fa5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">The unpopularity of France (and there now appears to be less discrimination between the French people and the Vichy government) has also grown rapidly. From several regions, it is reported that there is strong feeling and "grave concern" about the passage of American food ships to France (to feed, it is suspected, Germany). Mr. Dalton's firm words about Admiral Darlan are welcomed, and it is hoped that these will be followed by equally firm action.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fb5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">(1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 5x, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 20 Special P.C.). hhh 2. Reprisals</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fc5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">Public feeling in favour of reprisals continues to be very strong, both in the blitzed towns and in the rest of the country. It follows much the same lines as those indicated last week. The moral aspects of the problem are now almost entirely discounted. Personal experience has made the inhabitants of the blitzed towns believe that attack on the centres of population is "a paying military proposition", and they demand that we should apply the lesson to Hamburg and Berlin. Our apparent reluctance to bomb the Roumanian oil wells is also once more being commented on. Air Minstry announcements that a town has been bombed 50 times (and is apparently still in existence) makes them consider that our raids must be "child's play" or "Woefully inaccurate". The recent official statements in the press and on the radio about our bombing "have made little impression, and people will want a lot of convincing that really heavy raids on civilian centres in Germany are not our most efficacious weapon". Further, every official statement about our increasing bombing and reserve strength leads to fresh questions as to whether we are yet exerting our power to the full, and the phrase "a small force of our bombers" in communiques is a particular cause of dubious comment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fd5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">(2, 5, 5x, 6, 7, 8, 9, 16 London, 20 Manchester P.C.) hhh 3. Rumours</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fe5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">This week, rumours have again been fairly numerous, but localised.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ff5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">1. Tales of exaggerated rid casualties, and a revival 126 of the stories of funeral services over entombed shelterers are reported from several regions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-005988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">2. Rumours of a connection between raids and events in this country are also prevalent:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-015988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">Bristol's last raid was attributed to a reference to that town in a recent speech by Mr. Bevin.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-025988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">Weston-Super-Mare is expecting a raid because because of its War Weapons' Week.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-035988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">The Filton Aeroplane works is said not yet to have suffcred severe attack because it is still supplying planes for foreign governments - etc. etc.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-045988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">3. From two regions, there are reports of a fairly wide­ spread rumour of incendiary bombs which release gas, thus preventing the efforts of fire-fighters. The more circumstantial Story adds that the ga :is colourless and odourless; that it rapidly produces depression and suicidal attempts, and that there have already been many victims, though this has been hushed up., The Manchester and Glasgow raids are named and another version suggests that the gas is merely tear-gas.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-055988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">4. In Nottingham, on March 30, the rumour was widely circulated that Mussolini was superseded or dead; at one cinema the performance was stopped, so that his assassination could be announced. This rumour apparently arose from press speculations.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-065988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">5. It is said that the Germans are landing raiding parties on our shores, as we are said to be doing on the coasts of France and Holland.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-075988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">(3, 5x, 6, 7, 12, 14 Northern, Special counter propaganda bureau report). hhh 4. Sunday Theatres and Music Halls.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-085988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">A report from the R.I.O. Scotland states that comparatively little interest has been aroused there by the proposal to open those entertainments on Sundays. On the whole, there has been less opposition to the idea than might have been expected. Both the press and the public are tolerant without being particularly enthusiastic. But it is felt that "any pressure from sabbatarian groups to bring the matter to a head" may arouse a strong reaction against them.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-095988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">A preliminary enquiry made in London last week showed that the great majority of those interviewed were in favour of Sunday opening. There are no reports yet on the reaction to the Parliamentary veto.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0a5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">(11, 23). hhh 5. Extremist Activities</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0b5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">Pacifism: The R.I.O. Northern Region reports that "A women's branch of the North Pacifists Advisory Bureau has just been formed to cover the Tyneside area. Its objects are: "To give advice and, if necessary, financial assistance to women who have consciencious objections to the registration and conscription of women to help in the war effort".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0c5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="38">II. SPECIAL COMENTS hhh 6. Food</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0d5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">The tone of this week's reports suggests that women are beginning to realise that primarily their food problems are unavoidable. Though fewer complaints have been reported, - shortages are causing some depression and anxiety, and in one town in the Midlands it is Said that lack of food is definitely weakening morale</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0e5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">Nevertheless, there is still a belief that many shortages are avoidable as they are caused by the failure to adjust distribution to cover local increases in population; it is also believed that there is still too much waste of food and that this is caused partly by the way it is allocated. Suggestions continue to be made that meals in canteens should be restricted. It is also said that some people are using tins of food for their cats and dogs.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0f5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">There has been a good deal of comment about the size of the cheese ration. Minors, on the other hand, are pleased with the increase in their allowance, and other categories of workers hope they will be similarly favoured.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-105988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">Most of this week's reports of queues, many of which are for eggs, are from the Midlands. The demand for "all round rationing" is encouraged by the reported "abuse of the queuing system", (this is particularly a subject of comment in Postal Censorship).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-115988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">It is reported from a reception area in Scotland that after a recent blitz the local inhabitants distributed their stocks of tinned food and "ready dinners" among evacuees sent into the district, and although the inhabitants more praised for their public spirited generosity, the Ministry of Food regretted that it was unable to replace the stocks which had been given away. This affair has been the cause of bitter complaints, and the local people are said to feel uncertain whether their humanitarianism would again get the better of their discretion if there were mother blitz.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-125988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">There is conflicting evidence about the success of communal feeding centres. Though many places have reported a growing demand for them, and that those already established are very popular, in some London districts they are not being used to their full capacity; it is felt that in these cases their popularity would be improved if they were given better publicity.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-135988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">(2, 3, 4, 5x, 9, 11, 12, 16 North Western, 13 Eastern, 20 Manchester P.C., 34). hhh 7. Labour.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-145988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">The registration of women is undoubtedly the most discussed labour topic of the week. In collaboration with the Ministry of Labour certain big stores have set up information bureaux to deal with enquiries on the subject. For further details see Appendix to this report.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-155988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">(1, 2, 3, 5x, 8, 9, 18 Midland, 20 Inverness P.C., 34). hhh 8. Trade</note>
				<note xml:id="q-165988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">Tobacco: Scarcity of tobacco and cigarettes is being reported with increasing frequency. In the North Eastern Region the shortage is said to be reaching "'famine proportions". The popular idea that N.A.A.F.I canteens are better supplied than retail tobacconists is "exasperating to war Workers" who have to go short. Supplies in London seem generally better than elsewhere.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-175988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">Shopping difficulties continue to be acute for working women</note>
				<note xml:id="q-185988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">(2, 5, 5x, 8, 34). hhh 9. Agriculture</note>
				<note xml:id="q-195988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">The Monkstown Branch of the Ulster Farmers Union have called upon their Executive Committee to take all steps possible to obtain from the Ministry of Food a promise that none of the 1941 harvest shall find its way to the brewers or distillers until the food supply of the people and the live-stock has been made secure". They have also demanded "that at least one-half of the brewers' and distillers' present stock grain shall be made available for the feeding of live-stock".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1a5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">(14 Northern Ireland). hhh 10. Evacuation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1b5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">A special report on the Gibraltar refugees living in hostels in London shows that they are homesick, and because they get little reliable news arc apt to be victims of doubt and rumour. They have not got used to English food, nor do they appreciate special war-time difficulties. Although some services provide certain recreational and other facilities, education is only supplied for some of the children, and the women have little to do. It is suggested that their morale could be improved by some sort of news service.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1c5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">There are 11,000 of those refugees (of whom 4,000 are children and they are housed in 20 hostels in various London districts.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1d5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">(5x).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1e5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">Home Intelligence.</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>