<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Monthly Report on Morale and Public Opinion - May 1947</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-1c2bc51f-867d-4157-9cd5-6448d2f83893</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-e2044873-5cb5-49b8-8118-6733ff204ed2</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-d24e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d34e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="2">Tele: 34 10 00</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d44e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">EXT 8500</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d54e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="4">60.../PS/S/12/1</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d64e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="5">Public Safety</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d74e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="6">HQ Military Government</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d84e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="7">Hansestadt HAMBURG</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d94e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="8">609 HQ COG</note>
				<note xml:id="q-da4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="9">BAOR.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-db4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="10">27 May 1947 hhh Subject:- Monthly Report on Morale and Public Opinion - May</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="11">The Regional Commissioner</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="12">HQ Military Government</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="13">Hansestadt HAMBURG hhh 1. GENERAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">In Hamburg to-day food alone holds the real interest of the people. The poorer classes are bordering on a state of desperation and should further feed cuts and disappointments have to be faced, a situation, such as arose with regard to coal stealing in the latter part of the bitter winter when all classes took part and theft was no longer regarded as criminal, night arise in the search for food. The difference would be that food in quantities would not be available and the population might well seek an outlet in other more desperate and dangerous ways.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e04e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">Those sections of the people who, through shortage of money, lack of anything to trade or for other reasons cannot deal in the blade market or go foraging outside the city and so have to live on what they can come by lawfully; are in a particularly hopeless state. Those sections, who number about one-third of the city's population, although bitter in the extreme yet behave generally in a very creditable and restrained manor. Their discipline is remarkable in the circumstances and not even the opportunities offered by the large sass meeting of some 80,000 on May Day and the still greater demonstration of some 120,000 to 150,000 on the 9th May produced one single breach of the peace or untoward event Nevertheless, discipline and restraint cannot be counted on if the food situation grows worse and with it bitterness and hatred of the Occupying Authorities increase. Con­fidence in their Trade Union loaders virtually alone holds together the people who are worst affected. Should those leaders fail a gravely dangerous situation may arise.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e14e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">It is not only with the handicap of desperate economic conditions that democracy as a political creed struggles to progress in Hamburg. It seems unable to loosen the stranglehold which old ideas and older leaders have on it; leaders who appear to have learnt nothing in the last fourteen years and to be concerned more with political gain than with producing progress and improvement. Regardless of the common misery, all parties, groups and interests, with very few exceptions, fight an intolerant, selfish battle against seek other. The result is that while they go through the motions of elections, freedom of speech, organisation and meetings, they are not getting one step nearer the practice of real democracy and the principle of peaceful and tolerant mutuality in the management of their affairs. Political democracy in Hamburg to-day has not conquered the imagination of the people. It fails to find for them any channel of escape from the past, from which they show so much decorous reluctance to escape or to provide any hope for their future. Old values, personal, social and national, have been destroyed, present circumstances are not conductive to the striking of new ones and, in the mass of remedies offered none sufficiently strong as expressed in political terms, has been found to lift the people out of the morass in which they are. They look as yet in vain for that leadership which would provide firmness of purpose in the face of so much ignorance, prejudice and desperation of living. hhh 2. FUEL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e24e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">While the problem of fuel for the coming winter has been pushed to the background by the more urgent concern of food the situation is regarded with grave concern as, it is felt, that little will be distributed. There is consequent bitterness that the "bulk" of Germany's coal production is being exported to France, England and elsewhere. hhh 3. CLOTHING, BOOTS AND HOUSEHOLD ARTICLES</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e34e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">The position in respect of these appears to grow progressively more hopeless and confused. Whereas recently goods were available but coupons could not be had, n coupons have been issued but goods cannot be purchased except irregularly. The German authorities, more than ever, are being criticised for lack of control of a situation which permits manufacturers to charge exorbitant prices beyond the range of the ordinary retailer and retailers to confine their sales in the main to the black market and hoard the wander in anticipation of a devaluation of the Reichmark. The various Wirtschaftamter are charged also with fobbing off applicants for supplies on the Jugendamt and charitable organisations which cannot hope to meet even a small proportion of what is demanded. hhh 4. PUBLIC HEALTH</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e44e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">Any mass assembly of the people of Hamburg to-day bears witness to the poor state of public health. Tired and apathetic: faces, slow movement and lack of vitality are the characteristics wherever great numbers of people congregate, especially of the working classes. For all that the majority ap­pears to have weathered the winter well, those bitter months have left their mark on the health of many. While the present warm and sunny weather pleases, it is significant that more frequently is it referred to as exhausting and railed against for the plague of Adele and flies which it has produced and the fear of disease in the prevailing state of sanitation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e54e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">Double summer time has come in for widespread criticism in that it seriously upsets day to day routine when people are in too low a state of health easily to adapt themselves to the change. They find it difficult to go to bed in the daylight, particularly in hot summer evenings and more difficult still to get up in the morning when still tired and listless. Dockworkers are amongst the worst affected as normally they got up at 4 but now have to rise at 2 a.m. This, it is said, produces a serious falling off in the output of their work. There is always, of course, the charge that the institution of double summer time is part of the plan of the Occupying Authorities to undermine still further the health and general resources of the German people.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e64e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">The situation in hospitals is said to have worsened if anything particularly so far as the old and the very young are concerned and it is that the tuberculosis rate for the age group 3 to 6, is steadily increasing. Lack of adequate dressings is much discussed particularly at the emergency hospital in Langenhorn where, it is said, that those which should be changed daily can now be changed only twice a week. hhh 5. HOUSING, CONFISCATIONS, ETC.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e74e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">Since no notable confiscations have taken place during the last month and the excellent weather permits so many to remain outside, little has been heard in this connection during the month. There is however, criticism that while the clearing of rubble is being pushed well ahead, there is no sign of any large scale building or repair to building, activity. Further overcrowding is feared later in consequence of the belief that more East Prussian refugees will flood into Hamburg once the Poles begin to expel the remainder of their German population.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e84e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">It is widely believed that German authorities are secretly disposing of the building materials which have been assembled for the Hamburg Project. This, it is said, is done without the knowledge of the Occupation Authorities, whose interests in this respect are being flouted by the heads of the building administration in the city. hhh 6. BLACK MARKET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e94e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">The Black Market continues to flourish in four out of every five homes and offices and almost every shop. The new laws have had a noticeable effect in reducing the number of trading centres in streets and public places but, so great has dependence grown on the Black Market that there is little reduction in the volume of illegal transactions. Courts are slow to begin hearing cases under the new Laws and the results of their action is still awaited. In the meantime, prices are rising although money is becoming shorter. Cigarettes, fats and bread are more difficult to get than they were and polio reports, before and over the Whitsun holiday, show a spate of illegal slaughterings of cattle. hhh 7. ECONOMY</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ea4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">A complaint becoming more bitter and widespread concerns the frustration of trade and production by the Occupation Authorities, who, it is said, will bring about a total collapse of all economic activity by their hostile atti­tude to German industrial initiative and their inability to organise recovery. A group of exporters claim there is plenty of opportunity to do business with foreign countries but that our economic policy prevents such owing to denying access to raw materials, use of foreign currency deriving from German exports, foreign loans and credits and proper communications.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-eb4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">Business circles are demanding that a stop should be put to Trade Union and Co-operative encroachment on business activities proper and that if further regulation and supervision is required, the State itself should undertake it.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ec4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">Much excitement has been caused by the report of impending dismantling of a further six industrial firms to meet a claim for reparations by Yugoslavia which is in direct violation of the Potsdam Treaty. The number of illicit exchanges of goods between the lectern and Russian Zones is reported to be increasing. The risk involved is appreciated but accepted, since in no other way can businesses be kept alive.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ed4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">Two matters which have aroused much anger are the requisitioning by the British authority of one-third of the total output of electric bulbs of which there is a rave industrial as well as domestic shortage and the fact that now, at the end of the fifth month, the steel quota for the second quarter has not been fixed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ee4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">Artisans, craftsmen, doctors and dentists are finding it more and more difficult to obtain the absolute essentials of their trades and professions. Purchases can only be made on the Black Market at exorbitant prices and usually have to be made by the customer himself. hhh 8. LOCAL AUTHORITIES</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ef4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">The sections of the Administration lately coming in for most criticism for corruption are the German rationing and food authorities and the Police. Both, it is said, permit the farming community to flout regulations while each in its own way selfishly profits by it.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f04e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">The Hamburg Courts and Prosecutions and in fact the whole legal system here, is the subject of increasing criticism for, what is referred to, as the high-handed exercise and frequent abuse of their powers. Apolitical cleanup is thought necessary together with the imposition of firmer control, either by the British authorities or l the German themselves. It has been suggested that many close associates of Schulz-Rishoff President of the Wohnungsamt, are ex-officers of the former Luftgaukommando XI.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f14e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">Criticises continue to be leveled against the administration of the Wirtechaftsamt and the manner in which it distributes posts and favours. Instances are quoted of former party members and persons of doubtful criminal history being promoted because of their S.P.D. membership, whereas others, who had not joined that party but are politically and criminally clear, as well as being better qualified professionally, have been reduced in appoint­ment. hhh 9. BORGERMEISTER DRAUER</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f24e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">The suitability of Max Brauer to hold his post has not waned during the month as a subject of discussion and he appears to be coming in for more criticism than previously. He is held to be too anglophile, too optimisti­cally American and that his stand for the rights of Germans is far from con­vincing. Nevertheless, he has a great following who hold he is doing his best in the face of grave difficulties. The story is gaining ground that shortly he will replace Ostrowsky as Oberburgermeister Berlin and, as a desirable successor, Senator Laudahl so far only has been mentioned. hhh 10. MILITARY GOVENRMENT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f34e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">There is little doubt, as the Daily Express in its issue of the 29th April stated, that Germans to-by consider the British as poor and weak, our military power as gone and with it most respect we commanded. A small minority only regard that fact with regret and concern for what it might invite Germany to become. There is scarcely any base intent with which Military Goverment is net charged, many of them being utterly fantastic. Greed and selfishness are supposed to be the principal motives behind most British actions and latterly hostility and contempt lack even that note of respect which is usually accorded any hated institution so long as it is believed powerful</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f44e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">Much outspoken criticism is heard of the exorbitant sums which are said to be spent in the rebuilding of Deutschlandhaus and the scale of luxury with which every feature of repair, decoration and equipment is undertaken. The criticism is all the more violent by reason of the difficulty met with in providing the minimum essential repairs for German housing. hhh 11. DENAZIFICATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f54e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">The process of denazification grows no more popular. Most people are heartily sick of the whole business and many believe that only those who have inducements to offer, have a reasonable expectation of having their oases dealt with without delay and that they have no difficulty in "buying " their passage. hhh 12. SUBVERSIVE ACTIVITIES</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f64e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">Nazi resistance movements hold no public interest and few believe that they operate on any significant scale. There is no doubt that the present hopeless situation produces some measure of unrest but neither on the extreme Left nor in the ranks of former Nazis are there any signs pointing to this being exploited in any manner other than political. On the other hand, how­ever, five centres of underground resistance are said to exist in Mecklenburg and Vorpommern, composed, it is claimed, of former members of the Wehrmachts principally members of the 2nd Division. hhh 13. MORALS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f74e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">Confidence in public morals grows steadily less not only as far as sex is concerned but also as regards honesty and straight business dealing. Everyone today in Hamburg, as a matter of course, is thought to be a potential rogue. hhh 14. YOUTH EDUCATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f84e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">Present conditions increase the tension within each family and result in circumstances where the proper upbringing of children is often frustrated, if not made impossible by the advanced irritability of parents. Children leaving school are encountering grave difficulties in choosing a profession or even getting a professional education of any kind. There is a lack of apprentice­ships in nearly every field as most manufacturing and commercial enterprises are unable to after or sustain such.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f94e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">Juveniles, who first stole coal as a necessity are increasingly turning to the theft of foodstuffs and other commodities. hhh 15. PRESS, WIRELESS ETC.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fa4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">Although there is no great evidence that the editorial direction of any Hamburg newspaper aims at enlarging the average German's understanding of cause and effect or helping him to realise that not all the world's ills are concentrated in his country, it is unfortunate that the present shortage of newsprint comes at a time when the people, more than ever, are in need of information to help them to appreciate Germany's role in future world affairs. Yost attempts by the wireless to counter rumours regarding the food position and the export of foodstuffs and other commodities abroad, particularly to Britain, are met with considerable doubt and frequently only serve to harden the belief that the wireless is being used as an instrument of official persuasion.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fb4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">The American film 'Going my way" now being shown in Hamburg is unanimously praised and favourably compared with the average British film.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fc4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">The reappearance of Alfred Kerr, noted Jewish literary and dramatic critic of pre Hitler days, who has recently written articles for "Die Welt", has aroused certain displeasure and indicates as did the appointment of Hellmer, manager of the Deutscher Schauspielhaus, also a Jew, the extent of latent anti-semitism in certain quarters in Hamburg. hhh 16. RUMOURS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fd4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">The following are current:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fe4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">The threat of war is so imminent that the U.S.A. are likely to present the Russians with an ultimatum during the coming Autumn; already our nightly air activity over Lubeck is considerable and we are resigned to the temporary loss of Hamburg and. Kiel to Russian invading forces.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ff4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">Grade "A" Getman seed potatoes are being shipped to England and a coarse variety of American potatoes is being imported in their place. (Very persistent) Grain ships from the U.S.A. destined for Germany were diverted to Portugal by the British authorities so as to acquire foreign currency. Schleswig-Holstein butter is still being sold in London ships and milk shortage is due to the fact that Gerson milk is condensed and tinned here before shipment to Britain.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-004f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">A number of Luftwaffe airfields round Hamburg with had not been ploughed under, are being restored for military use.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-014f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">The "Hamburg Project" was really abandoned in view of the possibility that the Russians might temporarily occupy Hamburg. hhh 17. MISCELLANEOUS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-024f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">A widespread impression exists that it is easy for moneyed people to purchase foreign nationality and that practically any foreign passport can be bought if the right people in are approached.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-034f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">The claim that more than 170,000 sheep have disappeared during the last months in the province of Schlesmis-Holstein is put down to alleged lack of control and supervision in the farming areas from which the Black Market derives its principal impulse.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-044f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">It is claimed that the ruthless deforestation which has taken place has resulted in the made area, in the thin layer of top soil being blown away by winds, seeds sown earlier have become exposed and young wheat shoots are buried by the drifting soil. This, together with the shortage of fertilisers and the bad state of farm machinery, it is feared will result in a steady reduction of agricultural yields</note>
				<note xml:id="q-054f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="52">Deputy Inspector General</note>
				<note xml:id="q-064f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="53">Public Safety</note>
				<note xml:id="q-074f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="54">MSO'R/SL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-084f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="55">Copy to: The Inspector General.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-094f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="56">The Regional Governmental Officer</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0a4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="57">The Regional Intelligence Officer</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0b4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="58">J.R.White, Esq.,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0c4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="59">Public Opinion Research Branch,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0d4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="60">Governmental Sub-Commission,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0e4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="61">c/o 70 HQ CCG (BE),</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0f4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="62">BAOR.</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>