<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Morale and Public Opinion Monthly Report - June 1948</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-31b90541-eb58-4b12-b9a7-2788d0968f6f</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-d2762048-ab94-46a0-8b4b-c9309b2833d6</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-2514e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="1">Ref: 609/PS/MR/3</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2614e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="contact" n="2">Tel: 34 10 00 Ext: 8537</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2714e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="3">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2814e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="contact" n="4">PUBLIC SAFETY BRANCH</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2914e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="contact" n="5">HQ Hansestadt Hamburg</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="contact" n="6">609 HQ CCG (BE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="contact" n="7">BAOR 3</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2c14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="date" n="8">30 June 1948</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="contact" n="9">To: Regional Commissioner&lt;br&gt;HQ Hansestadt Hamburg&lt;br&gt;609 HQ CCG (BE)&lt;br&gt;BAOR 3</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="contact" n="10">HQ Hansestadt Hamburg</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="contact" n="11">609 HQ CCG (BE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3014e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="contact" n="12">BAOR 3</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3114e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subject" n="13">Subject: MORALE &amp; PUBLIC OPINION MONTHLY REPORT - JUNE 1948</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3214e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="14">This report does not necessarily express the views or opinions of this Branch but is a reflection of the morale and opinions of the general public.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3314e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="15">GENERAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3414e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="16">1. Currency reform has been almost the only topic of general conversation. Prior to its inception on 20th June the people attempted by all possible means to get rid of their surplus Reichmarks, and black market prices rose to fantastic heights, e.g. coffee was quoted at RM. 2,800 per lb.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3514e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="17">2. Little business was carried out either legally or on the black market as those in possession of saleable goods withheld them as far as possible in order to obtain new currency as payment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3614e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="18">3. The reform generally has had a calming effect, especially on the lower salary grades who now feel that at long last their money will be worth something. The issue of 40 new marks to each person was praised as being fair to everyone, and the restricted amount has curtailed spending so that only the bare necessities are being purchased.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3714e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="19">4. Except at Banks and bakeries queues have almost disappeared and it would seem that the "buyers strike", which is being supported by the Trades Unions, is going to make itself felt on shopkeepers, especially those of them who have been withholding necessary house­hold goods. Cinemas, theatres and restaurants are also suffering to a certain extent.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3814e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="20">5. It is regretted, however, that the same currency was not introduced in all four Zones, and the separate currency of the Eastern Zone is believed to be the final blow in completing the split between East and West.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3914e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="21">6. Reaction to the decisions of the London Conference is generally unpleasant. The Allies are being accused of exploitation of Germany's industries, especially in the proposed Ruhr control.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3a14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="22">7. The result of the "Volksbegehren" is not accepted as being of any great consequence, as many people have declared that without trouble they signed their names a number of times.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3b14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="23">FOOD</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3c14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="24">8. Increased supplies, the issue of the long awaited fat ration, and prompt delivery of current groups of fresh vegetables have relieved much of the tension in the food situation, one notable feature being that more trust is placed in recent promises of increased rations.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3d14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="25">9. Great resentment is expressed, however, against the Cuban sugar and dates issued this month. It is claimed that Cuban sugar contains only a very small percentage of cane sugar and a large amount of dust and dirt. It is interesting to note that the Communists are holding "the American capitalists behind the Marshal Plan" responsible for dumping on the German market "this useless filth which will ruin the health of German children and for which Germany will later have to pay clearly in dollars".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3e14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="26">10. The amount of dates issued in the last one or two periods is said to be as great as Germany in normal times consumed in a year, the reason given being that Iraq could offer Britain and the United States no other commodity in return for the arms they deliver her to protect their oil interests in Iraq against Soviet intrusion.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3f14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="27">11. For a few days prior to Sunday, 20th June, difficulty was experienced by many in obtaining certain food supplies, particularly bread, because wholesalers and retailers withheld stocks in anticipation of currency reform. Some businesses even closed down for holidays of one or two weeks and thereby aroused great bitterness, especially among housewives. Prom Monday, 21st June, however, criticism was considerably tempered by the general relief that food stuffs were not only obtainable, vegetables being in such good supply as to be non-rationed, but that prices were remarkably low.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4014e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="28">FUEL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4114e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="29">12. There is a demand that the fuel question should now in the summer months be revised so that the people may be guaranteed heating for next winter, even at the expense of industry's coal requirements. A worker who has to spend all his free time stealing coal to warm his hone is neither contented nor productive. If this worry is removed from his daily life production will increase considerably in both quantity and quality.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4214e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="30">PUBLIC HEALTH</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4314e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="31">13. The usual fears have been expressed of the effect, especially on children, of the lack of wholesome food, good housing and foot-wear.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4414e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="32">CLOTHING/HOUSEHOLD</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4514e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="33">14. Sharp comment has been made about the shortage of soap and other washing materials, and the Occupation powers are accused of causing this shortage by:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4614e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="34">(a) refusing whaling rights to Germany,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4714e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="35">(b) dismantling soap producing factories, and</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4814e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="36">(c) curtailing certain productions the by-products of which would make soap.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4914e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="37">15. The return to shops of household goods as a result of currency reform has brought mixed feelings to housewives who, while glad that many of their domestic difficulties can at last be overcome, are annoyed that so many household goods have been withheld by shop-keepers, and there is a general demand that action should even now be taken against the defaulters.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4a14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="38">BLACK MARKET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="39">16. The general opinions is that although the black market will not be "killed" by currency reform it will be severely hit; that only luxury commodities which are really scarce will be traded, and those at prices not much above normal. The return on Monday, 21st June, to the legitimate market of many commodities hitherto unobtainable there is quoted in support of this contention.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="40">17. Early fears that in the first few days black marketeers would "corner" a major amount of the new currency were soon found to be groundless, as the Kopfgeld of DM 40 was not sufficient to allow anyone to buy much more than the bare necessities of life.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="41">MILITARY GOVERNMENT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="42">18. Severe criticism is made of the enormous Occupation costs to be borne by the Germans, and Mil Gov, over-staffed and under-worked, is alleged to have about the same number of employees as the Hamburg State. The last straw is that even housemaids have to be paid for by the Germans. It is frequently said that "it will suit the English very well to live at our expense for years to come. They will never live in such luxury again, so naturally they have no desire to leave Germany. They may tell us that we are being sustained by the British taxpayer, but surely his contribution is not comparable with that of the Hamburg taxpayer who alone to date has to pay DM 400,000,000."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="43">LOCAL AUTHORITIES</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5014e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="44">19. The people are now practically resigned to the fact that the resurrection of the Amtsschimmel and the over-staffed bureaucratic machine is now complete. They bow to the inevitable that the Beamte is once more a dictator.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5114e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="45">20. The personnel distributing new currency from Banks and other money exchange centres were praised for the patient and efficient manner with which they executed a difficult and trying task.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5214e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="46">21. The issue of ration cards, however, causes a general outcry against the inefficiency of the authorities. Firstly because the issue is started too late in the Lay, and secondly because of an apparent lack of planning. There are not sufficient distribution centres and the public to receive different cards must queue at separate counters. It is submitted that much time would be saved and good feeling towards the authorities restored if each person could receive his full entitlement at one counter.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5314e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="47">22. Senator DETTMANN and the Gesundheitsverwaltung are blamed for lack of action in the maintenance of ambulances. It is alleged that these have not been renewed since before 1933 and that their condition is so deplorable that patients being conveyed in them suffer not only great discomfort but unnecessary pain.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5414e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="48">TRAFFIC/TRANSPORT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5514e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="49">23. A distinct drop in the number of persons using trams, underground, etc., was noticeable after the currency reform, due no doubt to the fact that little business was being Lone in the first few days.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5614e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="50">24. Residents in Lokstedter Steinweg and vicinity complain bitterly that on 13th June the street mentioned was completely blocked from 12 o'clock by persons desirous of attending a Football hatch H.S.V. v. St. Pauli in Viktoria Sportplatz Hoheluft, and expressed the opinion that with a little planning by the police and transport authorities much annoyance could have been avoided.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5714e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="51">POLICE</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5814e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="52">25. During the exhibition of valuable Eastern collections in the Museum Fur Kunst und Gewerbe, two uniformed policemen were seen at all times patrolling, presumably to protect the collections. The public's reaction was first one of annoyance that they were not considered trustworthy, and secondly of surprise that the police authorities did not have the sense to place plain clothes officers on guard.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5914e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="53">26. The manner in which the police, with few exceptions, carried out their very important part in the currency reform has been very highly praised. In the majority of exchange centres they contrived to keep the crowds good-natured and friendly despite the facts that</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="54">(a) the police themselves performed very long hours of duty;</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="55">(b) the public had to stand in queues for many hours.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="56">ECONOMY</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5d14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="57">27. The Ordinance No.54 dealing with the direction of labour has caused a fair amount of unrest, e.g. a man in Altona already in steady employment with a private firm received an order to report for work with the building authorities. One paragraph of the Order stated that failure to comply would render him liable to punishment by a CCG court. Such action is likened to certain labour recruitment measures alleged to be carried out in the Soviet Zone. Direction, especially to hard physical labour, of black marketeers and other dodgers, would be welcome, but it is felt that under this Ordinance the local Labour Office is not only showing its own weakness and inefficiency but is hiding behind the skirts of the Occupation Powers in puerile attempts to carry out its own urgent responsibilities.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5e14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="58">28. Difficulty is being experienced in obtaining apprentices for some trades which make heavy demands on clothing, footwear, and cleaning materials, and which require a certain physical standard. In view of the present shortages many parents prefer their children to be "black-coated" workers. The only solution suggested is that special attractions in the form of increased wages and leave be offered for "dirty" trades.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5f14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="59">29. The 25% reduction in Marshal Aid has raised some doubts as to the sincerity of the U.S. desire to assist in Europe's economic reconstruction. Leftish elements proclaim the reduction to have been necessitated by the American rearmament programme, and frequently quote the old Nazi cry "Guns or Butter". They also warned the public against clutching at a straw in their present difficulties, that they will have no choice but to accept only inferior goods, and that they will have to pay dearly in future years for blind faith in American promises. It is generally expected, however, that the Marshal Plan will give genuine material assistance to Germany and do much to counteract Soviet propaganda.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6014e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="60">30. Despite current shortages, supplies of manufactured goods, particularly clothing, are not welcome, the overwhelming opinion being that Germany lacks neither plant nor labour and can gain infinitely more from the import of raw materials equivalent in dollar value to the manufactured goods which J.E.I.A. now forces her to accept.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6114e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="61">31. German Merchant Seamen "who have committed no war crimes and who today have nothing to lose and everything to gain" have been strongly supported by public opinion in their demands for an opportunity to resume their calling. Germany would thereby be saved the enormous freight charges paid to foreign Companies at present handling her imports and exports, and the reconstruction, maintenance, and manning of the Merchant Fleet would provide employment for thousands of idle shipbuilders and seamen.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6214e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="62">32. There is a distinct note of confidence in business circles that many of the fears expressed before the inception of currency reform are now proved groundless and that the new Mark will soon find a good value in the world market and be of infinite assistance in the restoration of German economy. It is felt, however, that the latter is to no small extent hindered by the fact that German initiative and industry are not alone responsible but have to labour under the many difficulties and hindrances imposed through the Joint Export &amp; Import Agency by large British and American business interests.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6314e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="63">DENAZIFICATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6414e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="64">33. The complete stoppage of work by the German Denazification Authorities in Hamburg and the resignation from Denazification bodies by S.P.D. members in North Rhine Westphalia are very popular because the general opinion is and always has been that</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6514e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="65">(a) the British alone should have carried out denazification in order that justice could be done;</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6614e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="66">(b) denazification has long outlived any useful purpose it may have served and has been nothing but a hindrance to Germany's peace of mind and general recovery.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6714e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="67">YOUTH/EDUCATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6814e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="68">34. The whole operation of currency reform afforded an excellent opportunity to the local authorities to rescue the many youths who are homeless, parentless, and until now have lived only through the black market. Their numbers are alleged to be very high, and their affect on the moral standards of future German admit life is expected to be very bad indeed unless strong action is taken immediately to educate and discipline them.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6914e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="69">PRESS/WIRELESS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6a14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="70">35. An article on the London Slums published in the HAMBURGER ECHO of 11th June 1948 has brought much sarcastic comment from the general public. This article described the filth, drunkenness, crime, prostitution, etc., in a particular quarter in London, and the general reaction has been that Britain is far behind Germany in matters of social welfare, that she was no doubt now attempting to drag Germany down to that level, and that she ought to clean up her own house before attempting to do anything in Germany.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6b14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="71">RUMOURS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6c14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="72">36. Tinned horseflesh, used during the war to feed Army dogs, is now being delivered for consumption by the German people.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6d14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="73">37. The salaries of the Burgermeister, Senators, and Senats-syndici are going to be increased despite the new value of the Mark under currency reform.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6e14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="74">38. There are many rumours that the British, Americans, and French are soon to withdraw from Berlin.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6f14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="75">39. A war between East and West is now unavoidable and will start before the end of the year.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7014e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="76">40. Troops and equipment are being massed all along the border and the first attacks will be made through Lubeck and the Harz Mountains.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7114e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="77">41. Russia is now mass-producing atom bombs.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7214e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="78">42. Russia is printing enormous numbers of the new Mark in use in the Western Zones, which will soon be flooded with these Marks so that both the currency and the Marshal Plan will be completely sabotaged.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7314e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="79">MISCELLANEOUS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7414e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="80">43. The reason given by the British authorities for returning to the Soviet sector of Berlin a Russian Colonel who had fled to Britain (namely that he wished voluntarily to be sent there), is treated with open disbelief and has greatly shaken public confidence in Britain's desire to maintain a firm stand against Soviet demands and impositions. It is now said that Britain would not hesitate to deliver to the Soviet authorities any fleeing German sought by them.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7514e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="81">44. The acquittal of PETERSON, BUSCH, and SCHULZ and others charged with crimes against humanity is quoted as yet another example of the unsatisfactory manner in which courts are handling such cases, and there is the usual criticism that the "big fish" are acquitted while the "small fry" are severely punished.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7614e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="82">45. Consequent on the publicity given to recent crimes in which armed Poles and Yugoslavs have been involved, there has been a general outcry that the time has come for these people, many of whom came to Germany of their own free will, either to be returned forcibly to their own countries or to have their many special privileges taken from them. Immediately after the capitulation, their armed robbery, murder, rape, etc., were an understandable reaction to the treatment they had suffered under the Nazis, but at this late date the Occupation Forces should take immediate action to curb these activities. France's campaign to recruit German workers in addition to the many thousands of prisoners of war which she still holds is discussed as a cunning method to rob an impoverished Germany 'of her few remaining skilled craftsmen and thus keep her indefinitely in subjection.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7714e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="83">46. The use of so much paper for forms and propaganda material in connection with "Volksbegehren" is deplored by a very large section of this paper-starved community.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7814e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="84">(A. S. Barnes, A.I.G.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7914e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="85">for Deputy Inspector General</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7a14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="86">Copy to: Inspector General, 62 HQ COG, BAOR 1</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7b14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="87">D.A.I.G., HQ CCG, York House, Berlin, BAOR 2</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7c14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="88">Reg. Governmental Officer, 609 HQ CCG, BAOR 3</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7d14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="89">Reg. Economic Officer, 609 HQ CCG, BAOR 3</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7e14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="90">Reg. Intelligence Officer, 609 HQ CCG (BE), BAOR 3</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7f14e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="91">J. R. WHITE, Esq., Public Opinion Research Officer, Bielefeld</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>