<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: 1st Armoured Division Morale Report for period 1 May - 30 Sep 47</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-4271737a-3980-4d04-8263-51b8c4d1330c</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-b45644af-8218-4a00-bfd7-fed36e8c01ee</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-db547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">1st ARMOURED DIVISION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="2">MORALE REPORT For period 1 May - 30 Sep 47 hhh 1.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="3">(a) Main Features</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="4">Since 1 May 47 the whole Division has been subject to much movement. May and June and part of July were spent in moving the greater part of the Division from ITALY to join the RA Group in EGYPT, end later to deploy in PALESTINE Despite many changes in plan and location - acme units have changed location two or three times in as many months - morale on the whole is good.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">The news of the impending dispersal of the Division came as a shook to everyone a</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e0547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">nd brought home to some the seriousness of the state of affairs at home. The feeling of uncertainty as regards the future affects the Regular Officer more than any other category and is an adverse factor towards morale.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e1547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">The recent talk by the DRAC (26 Sep) to the officers, warrant officers and senior NOOs of 2 Armd Bde, outlining the new proposals for the reorganisation of the JAC, had a very beneficial effect in this respect.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e2547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">(b) Attitude towards local inhabitants</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e3547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">In EGYPT the general attitude of the troops to the locals is one of tolerant contempt coupled with a feeling of suspicion towards the shopkeepers and contractors.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e4547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">In PALESTINE the Jews, depending on the prevailing state of dissident activity, are either distrusted or hated. The feelings aroused after the murder of Sgts MARTIN and PAICE have had time to die down A smell minority have a certain amount of sympathy for the Jewish cause.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e5547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">The attitude towards the Arab in PALESTINE is one of friendly tolerance.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e6547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">(c) Confidence in military and political leaders</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e7547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">(i) Military Apart from those who served in the war the average soldier has a distressingly smell knowledge of who the military lenders are, and displays very little interest in any commander above divisional level. Up to this level there is general confidence.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e8547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">The difficulties of the higher military leaders are appreciated by the majority of officers end senior other ranks. 'Though perhaps disturbed by a lack of published policy this factor does not have large adverse a feet on morale.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e9547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">In general confidence in military leaders is good.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ea547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">(ii) Political The young soldier of today takes very little interest in Political or home Affairs. The general attitude appears to be that the present Government is doing as well as any other could under the circumstances. Most men would back it again because they feel it is the 'Working Man's Party', and will continue to do so until such time as its failure should hit them personally.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-eb547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">The recent announcement concerning direction of labour was received with adverse comments by many soldiers, particularly those nearing release.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ec547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">(iii) General outlook regarding conditions at home and future prospects The minority have been shaken by the news of the financial crisis and the consequent further restrictions in food and clothing at home. The majority, on the other hand, take very little interest, and are not aware of the seriousness of the state of affairs. With very little thought for the future their target in life is to be released from the bondage of the Army and to get back to the freedom (sic) of English home life. There is little or no tendency to sign on or to defer release. hhh 2. Discipline</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ed547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">Has been mainly good. Whereas in ITALY the moat prevalent serious offence was stealing WD property, in PALESTINE it is sleeping on guard. In the many units who have managed to avoid cases of sleeping on guard there has been a refreshing absence of crime.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ee547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">The young men of today, whither he be officer, NCO or Private soldier, lacks to a large degree a sense of duty and self-discipline, This is undoubtedly due to the strange conditions of upbringing during the war years and will take time to eradicate.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ef547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">To get back to pre-war standards of discipline a unit needs a strong cadre of regular officers and NCOs. The young emergency commissioned officer, and the junior NCO (who is unavoidably young and inexperienced) appear to have difficulty in checking men without causing resentment, and they nuke their task more difficult by over familiarity with those whom it is their duty to control. Such regulars as there are do their beat, but they are far outnumbered by the host of unenthusiastic temporary soldiers who look forward to nothing but the day of their release.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f0547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">As usual, an enormous burden of responsibility rests on and is ably borne by the commanding officer. hhh 3. Relationship between all ranks, and with other services and Allied Forces</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f1547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">(a) All ranks The relationship between all ranks is good, but with the tendency as mentioned above to over familiarity between junior officers, NCOs and men.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f2547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">(b) Other services There has been no contact with the Royal Navy, and practically none with the RAP. There has been a certain amount of liaison with the PALESTINE Police, with whom relations are excellent.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f3547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">(c) Allied Forces In EGYPT the POLES are heartily disliked. In PALESTINE there has been little or no contact with Allied Forces. hhh 4. Morale of special categories</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f4547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">(a) Officers</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f5547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">On the whole good; but the uncertainty of what the future holds is more detrimental to the morale of the regular officer than to any other category. The fact that many, if not most, have been separated from their families for the greater part of their married lives can only be damaging to morale unfortunately in many uses there is still no indication of this situation being rectified.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f6547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">(b) Trained Men</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f7547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">Have settled down in their new surroundings quite well, but are only now beginning to learn to make themselves comfortable and organise their own recreation and hobbies.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f8547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">The senior and regular NCOs to a large extent have to 'carry' the others.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f9547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">The non-regular junior Irks end men in many cases are hypnotised by the thought of release.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fa547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">(c) Reinforcements</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fb547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">Few have been received since the Division arrived in ULF. Those that have arrived are on the whole cheerful and keen, but bewildered. Mot having been brought up in an atmosphere of family and they take time to understand the meaning and necessity of Army discipline. hhh 5. Operation of Python scheme and Leave Schemes</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fc547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">(a) Python Satisfactory.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fd547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">(b) LIAP Satisfactory. The cutting down of vacancies so that virtually only the Regular or short Services Regular is eligible is accepted as fair and sensible. Very few non-regulars would in any case have had enough service remaining before Release to have warranted the long trip home.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fe547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">(c) Local Leave There have been varied reports on CYPRUS. Some leave camps- particularly Golden Sands - are good and much appreciated. Others are bad and have resulted in justified unfavourable comments.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ff547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">The difficulties of setting up new leave camps within reasonable distance of troops in PALESTINE are appreciated, but under present conditions the need is paramount and the organisation Should be first class.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-00557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">The relief of being able to get away from the boredom of guard duties and the incessant carrying of arms is almost too obvious to mention. Local leave under current conditions is therefore an enormous factor in raising morale. hhh 6. Living conditions including accommodation, messing and canteens</note>
				<note xml:id="q-01557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">(a) accn</note>
				<note xml:id="q-02557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">On the whole is satisfactory, but the absence of electric light in the majority of man's tents is a serious defect. The standard issue of one hurricane lamp per tent is quite insufficient, particularly for the coming months.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-03557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">(b) Messing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-04557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">The ration scale, when compared with what is available at home, is good.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-05557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">As ever, the problem with messing is to find experienced master cooks and Messing officers very few cooks stay long enough to benefit their unite much after being sent on courses. Some were impressed into ACC early in their service and have little interest.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-06557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">Many units have tackled the problem with great energy end have produced good results. In one unit messing is excellent. In a few unite, where the lack of experienced personnel is more marked, the standard of messing is below average.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-07557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">(c) Canteens</note>
				<note xml:id="q-08557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">In EGYPT the canteens are good. In PALESTINE they are quite good, but the prices in NAAFI canteens are much too high, for the goods and service offered.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-09557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">The Div Amenity Centre and Camp Shopping centres are popular and well patronised, but again the prices are extremely high. hhh 7. Recreation and entertainment including news service.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0a557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">(a) Reaction There are plenty of football pitches which are always in use. Many unite have laid out their own athletic grounds and have held sports. Facilities for cricket are poor and far tennis non-existent.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0b557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">Sea bathing in liable to be hazardous, and the nearest swimming pool is a good hour's drive from the nearest units. On the whole, therefore, facilities are not good.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0c557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">(b) Entertainment Cinemas are sufficient in number and films have been reasonable. There have been a flaw good films and a number of old and poor ones. As ever the complaint is that the prime are too high for the entertainment offered.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0d557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">CSE live shows are popular, and some hews been first class. More live shows would always be acceptable.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0e557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">(c) The supply of local newspapers is sometimes erratic. There is a demand for more home newspapers and periodicals. The local Forces Broadcasting Station is appreciated. hhh 8. Mail</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0f557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">The arrival at mail is apt to be erratic at times. Parcels take longer than they should.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-10557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">Considerable disgust has been expressed concerning the new postal rates for people writing from home. hhh 9. Family Affairs</note>
				<note xml:id="q-11557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">Continued separation from families lovers morale even though it may not produce compassionate cases in this respect one unit - 1 BORDER have a legitimate grouse in that since the end of the war they have had families with the unit for only one month, end than only when the unit was in England.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-12557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">The number of compassionate cases has been small. Decisions of the GHQ Compassionate Committee are accepted as fair. Where application for the return of the soldier has emanated from the War Office repatriation has keen speedily dealt with.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-13557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">SSAFA continue to do excellent week. hhh 10. Education</note>
				<note xml:id="q-14557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">In spite of heavy is duties many units have managed to organise well run education courses.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-15557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">It in regretted that many soldiers look upon education within the unit as just another fatigue. Some look upon it as an escape from soldiering.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-16557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">There has been some disappointment that the Fun College has not been able on various occasions to after sufficient vacancies. hhh 11. Release and Resettlement</note>
				<note xml:id="q-17557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">Release has: been running smoothly, and the recent news of the speeding up at release was joyfully received by those effected.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-18557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">Pre-release and resettlement courses are popular. hhh 12. Health</note>
				<note xml:id="q-19557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">On the whole has been very good.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1a557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">Amongst tps in PALESTINE there have been 8 cases of Infantile Paralysis (2 fatal; 4 cases of Typhoid (1 fatal) end a small number of malaria cases. hhh 13. Finance, Pay and Alowance</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1b557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">(a) Officers There have been so many different instructions in the period that many officers are confused as to the method of drawing their pay and allowances.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1c557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">Many Officers accounts are not up to data. There are a number of cases of officers having received no local Overseas Allowances three or four months after arrival in MSLF. There are a few cases where officers are by Army Pay Office as opposed to by Agents of their having received no allowances or pay since arrival.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1d557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">In some cases the fault may have lain with the unit In that through ignorance of local instructions their method of rendering appropriate casualties was incorrect; but in many cases the time lag and the look of payment can only have been the fault of the Pay Offices</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1e557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">(b) Other Ranks The Star Classification Scheme is still in many cases difficult to interpret. There are still anomalies in certain arms - particularly R SIGS, RAMC and RACC. RRME in particular will find difficulty in recruiting Regulars because of the better pay in sinner trades in civilian life.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1f557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">Many units report delay in obtaining verification of eon's balances.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-20557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">One unit in particular - 662 Armd Tps Wksps - is greatly dissatisfied the CC states that he has lost faith in the Regimental Paymaster.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-21557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">(c) General For the single man the rate of pay and allowances is probably fair compared with the cost of living, For the married man separated from his family, life is extremely difficult. This formation has no experience of the cost of living for families in this theatre. hhh 14. Miscellaneous, including suggestions</note>
				<note xml:id="q-22557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">(a) The Infantry Group System The group system for infantry battalions does not appear to be functioning smoothly yet. There are still cases of Northerners being posted to southern groups, etc,.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-23557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">(b) Recreational Clothing There are occasions, even in PALESTINE, when the soldier desires to wear clothes other than what the Army provides. For instance, for lack of anything else, the average soldier has to play cricket in KD uniform. It is admitted that clothes are available locally, but at enormous cost.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-24557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">A standard issue of certain articles of clothing, available on repayment at reasonable prices, would be greatly appreciated.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-25557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">(c) Compassionate Cases Cases often occur of soldiers receiving telegrams from home saying, for example, 'Mother dangerously ill apply compassionate leave".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-26557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">It is felt that more publicity should be given at home - (eg,. in the newspapers or at the cinema) - as to what evidence and action is required in these cases. It is also felt that practically all cases could and should come via the War Office. If this were the case it would mean that the case had been investigated on the spot and War Office could signal the brief facts and authorise compassionate leave at the same time. dome cases do happen in this way. Many do not, and valuable and perhaps crucial time, is wasted. If this system were to be implemented it should be fairly simple to publicise the fact and to arrange a simple channel of communication eg:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-27557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">Civilian affected to Local Police Station.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-28557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">Police (after verification with doctor attending case) to War Office,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-29557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">War Office to Overseas Command.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">MESSAGE FORM</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="81">FROM :- 1 Armd Div 1311 50</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2c557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="82">TO (ACTION) :- 2 Armd Bde 61 Lor Inf Bde LG RA RE Sigs</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="83">ST Med Ord REME Pro 55 PS Sec HQ Son Div School 250 Fwd Del Son SCF Postal Pay</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="84">Welfare Edn</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="85">(INFM) :- 9 L 2 KRRC G (Ops) G (L) G (Int) A</note>
				<note xml:id="q-30557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">404 GSD (.) SECRET (.) personal from Div Comd to all COs (.) I have just hoard with profound regret that the acute manpower and financial crisis entails the dispersal of 1 Armd Div (.) this will start immediately with reduction to cadre of 2 Armd Bde less 2 KRRC (.) regimental cadres will consist of approx 38 offrs and 146 OR Primarily reg personnel (.) -choir object is to keep rot in being, until final plans are firm and provide basis for subsequent reconstitution with minimum delay (.) probable disposal of personnel NOT incl in cadres is as follows (.) rod; soldiers with loss than six months to serve abroad to UK (.) non regulars AS gps 58 and below to UK (.) AS gps both incl 59 to 65 to BAOR (.) AS fps 66 and over to RAC units in ITS (.) instrs for future of remaining units of Div are awaited from the War Office (.) we must all do everything in our power to maintain div standards and reputation up to the end (.) gist of the above may be 'communicated verbally to all ranks but official correspondence dealing with it will be treated as SECRET and it must NOT be communicated to the pross (.) all infm</note>
				<note xml:id="q-31557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">IN CIPHER 12 LIABLE TO INTERCEPTION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-32557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">PRIORITY IMMEDIATE</note>
				<note xml:id="q-33557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">Signed:</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>