<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Monthly Report on Morale and Public Opinion - January 1947</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-82c1d301-8ba6-486c-8a70-46057c4fc948</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-f0bfee0f-2a2e-49cb-86c6-4e37f74544be</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-104f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="1">Tel. 34 10 00</note>
				<note xml:id="q-114f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="2">Ext 8500</note>
				<note xml:id="q-124f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">609/PS/S/12/1</note>
				<note xml:id="q-134f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="4">Public Safety</note>
				<note xml:id="q-144f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="5">HQ Military Government</note>
				<note xml:id="q-154f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="6">Hanscstadt HAMBURG</note>
				<note xml:id="q-164f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="7">609 HQ CCG</note>
				<note xml:id="q-174f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="8">January, 1947</note>
				<note xml:id="q-184f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="9">Subject:- Monthly Report on Morale and Public Opinion</note>
				<note xml:id="q-194f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="10">The Regional Commissioner</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1a4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="11">HQ Military Government,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1b4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="12">Hansestadt HAMBURG hhh 1. GENERAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1c4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">The entry of the New Year found the morale of Hamburg at a lower point than had ever been reached either since the Occupation or during the memory of any of its people. The succession of blows of the last year had reduced them to a state where personal hygiene could scarcely be ensured, serious physical discomfort was general, food was insufficient and inadequately prepared, hous­ing conditions overcrowded and frequently miserable, lighting inadequate, warm clothing and bedding gravely lacking, queuing for food long and anxious and the least comfort desperately to be sought for. To these the New Year added a severity of cold not experienced for many years, a crisis arising out of fuel shortage and grave doubts as to the supply of to-morrow's bread. Despair reached a depth not previously equaled and brought the population nearly to breaking point. A few days of warmer weather broke the spell, revived hope and a dangerous crisis, which had been borne with great fortitude, passed. It has, however, left its mark both physical and psychological on the people.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1d4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">The few hopes they had that peace terms would better their position are dead. They anticipate only territorial amputation, a questionable sovereignty and a deliberately crippled economy. The distinction between humane victors and others is less clearly defined and there is developing an intense feeling of distrust and hostility to British occupation which is felt to have betrayed the confidence of most who had accepted British tutelage more readily than they would have accepted any other. As British prestige has ebbed, egotism and nationalism have grown and the Hamburger to-day is more German than at any time since the Occupation. He feels that he is witnessing economic and social dis­integration and inclines more and more to the view that this is the studied policy of the occupation regime. In this belief his sense of civic responsi­bility, never strong, is rapidly weakening. hhh 2. FOOD</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1e4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">The more miserable the conditions of cold the worse has been the food situa­tion for greater difficulty was found then in supplementing rations and many have been forced to make still deeper inroads into whatever stocks remained. Potato supplies expected to last until March are being exhausted in this manner and a great number are already without any. - The supply of meat, sugar, fats and cheese, however, has been generally maintained, as has also that of bread but many housewives have encountered difficulty in obtaining supplies owing to the number of bakeries closed through lack of fuel.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1f4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">Little fresh fish was seen during the month except herrings said to have been excessively salted so as to save them for human consumption. The vegetable supply is confined to cabbages and turnips, most of which reach the consumer in a frozen state. Vegetable Preserves promised months ago have not yet been dis­tributed. Except for dried milk, which is reported to be frantically sought after, the milk supply has been maintained Put cereal coupons have not been honoured for the first time since rationing was introduced in 1939.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-204f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">The daily diet of the average Hamburger for the last three weeks of each rationing, period is thought to be, three slices of dry bread in. the morning, a dish of cabbage or turnips boiled in water -with a few potatoes at midday and another three slices of dry bread at night. On Sunday, a small piece of meat provides a welcome addition.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-214f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">Such conditions of living have caused the people of Hamburg to be skeptical of any promise of more food and many people believe that it is the Allied policy to feed Germans no better than they are being fed at present. This belief is supported by the recent announcement of the intention to reduce livestock on farms. hhh 3. FUEL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-224f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">Whether hunger is worse than cold is a point frequently debated in Hamburg out no matter what is the consensus of opinion, there is no doubt as to the misery of both and little hope of relief from either, during what remains of the winter is held, The only general fuel distribution since October has been ½ cwt of wood originally intended for issue in September last. The recent press announcement of the distribution of 1 cwt of coal during January or February is given less credence than reports of a further spell of cold weather lasting from the end of January to the middle of February. Further cold spells are desperately feared by all but a very few lucky ones who still have some fuel left. There is little or no hope of finding any solid fuel on the flack Market; its supplies are all but exhausted and many are deliberately drawing on gas and electric supplies in excess of their due, fully realising they are inviting a complete cessation of heating.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-234f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">The consequences to public health of the cold weather are believed to be most serious. Unheated houses, damp walls and bed clothes are said to have resulted in widespread rheumatic ailments and afflictions of the heart and lungs. Scarcity of practically every kind of remedy, the impossibility of giving treatment to the more urgent cases, lack of hospital beds and equipment, the grave damage to chemists' stocks occasioned by the cold and by burst water pipes are topics widely discussed. It is not unnatural, therefore, that the figures of 30 deaths by freezing and 119 cases of frostbite are generally disbelieved in favour of figures ranging from 200 to 1500 deaths by cold.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-244f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">There is little sympathy among the general population for the attempt to increase coal production in the Ruhr by offering special inducements to miners. Miners are thought to receive too much coal already for their own use and that much of their surplus goes to the Black Market. It is claimed that material inducements will not suffice to produce more coal until miners are stimulated to greater efforts by assurances that German coal needs will first be met before exports continue. hhh 4. BLACK MARKET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-254f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">The Black Market still flourishes supported by all who can still continue to do so. As their numbers grow less so does the outcry against it and the criticism of the futility of Police increase. farmers are still held mostly to blame for food shortages and are believed in general to deliver up no more than 50% of their products but the proceeds of burglaries and housebreakings are also held to be a great source of supply. Black Market prices generally have remained stable for some time. Latterly there has been an increase in the cost of fats and cereals and prices for coal are now remarkably high. hhh 5. DENAZIFICATION.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-264f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">Although Denazification has not been prominent in discussion lately, there is a growing general feeling that nominal Nazis should suffer some financial penalty in the form of a tax or fine but otherwise should be left to pursue their ordinary activities which, however, should not provide opportunities of gaining political influence. Considerable note has been taken of the fact that nearly all Nazi doctors who were suspended are practicing again. No adverse comment on this has been made, probably due to the changed public attitude towards purely nominal members of the Party. The American amnesty for nominal Nazis has met with con­siderable approval in Hamburg and many feel that a similar amnesty should extend to the British Zone. Eighteen months of total denazification are thought to have done little to clarify the political situation or to produce social benefits and that attention should be concentrated on guilty and responsible Nazis. This atti­tude also extends to inmates of internment camps, who, it is widely felt should be punished where there is evidence of guilt, the remainder being released subject to necessary safeguards. hhh 6. PIONEERS OF WAR</note>
				<note xml:id="q-274f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">Many complaints are heard that returning prisoners of war meet with little assistance from the German authorities and that the Wohnungsamter and Arbeitsamter have made no provision for housing them or putting them to useful employment. Similar treatment was experienced by returning internees who spent most of the war years in Asia or Africa. While satisfaction is felt over the progressive return of prisoners of war from Britain, criticism is heard that very few have been repatriated from camps in North Africa. The disquiet over the ultimate fate of prisoners of war in Russia and, to a lesser extent, in France and the Balkans, is deepening and the reluctance of the powers concerned to release them in sub­stantial numbers creates acre than ordinary resentment. It has been noted that Communist organisations have given ready assistance to prisoners of war and, al­though the support has not been on a considerable scale, doubt is being expressed as to the means by which these organisations are enabled to provide assistance. hhh 7. LOCAL AUTHORITIES</note>
				<note xml:id="q-284f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">Confidence in Local Authorities appears to grow less. There is popular belief that they are incapable of running their Departments to the satisfaction of the public an-d much confused discussion centres on whom should be blamed, the British or German administration. On the one hand, Local Authorities are felt to be weak in their dealings with British Functional Officers and on the other, do not accord fair and just treatment to the individual. Complaints are many and the impression exists that not only is the bureaucratic machine top-heavy but that the majority of officials easily succumb to corruption. While practically every field of public administration is criticised, the Wirtschaftadmter, Wohnungsamter and Arbeitsamter in particular are attacked.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-294f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">There is much complaint that although goods are displayed in shop windows and an increased number of permits have been granted by the Wirtschaftsamter for the purchase of clothing, footwear, etc., such an seldom be bought at their actual retail value as shopkeepers require bribery in some form or other before they will part with their goods.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">An unspecified Wirtschaftadmter is reported to be conducting its own Black Market in sausage spices and pepper originally costing RM 1.60 per pound finds its way to the Black Market at RM 300 per pound. There is much criticism of control of stocks held by the Wirtschaftadmter and it is said that any check taking account of what was available in 1945 and what has been disposed of since through regular channels would reveal considerable discrepancies. It is further complained that official announcements by the Wirtschaftsamter are often misleading and that ration promises are not kept. An issue of 20 cigar­ettes to males at Christmas was said to be in excess of the normal ration and was followed by a delay of a fortnight in issuing the next ration; the effect of this was to cancel the Christmas ration. In other instances doubts have been expressed as to whether all food reductions are covered by legal provision. cases are quoted where old people over seventy who are receiving additional milk per day are compelled to return coupons for cereals, fat and meat. It is maintained that there has been no public announcement to justify this and that the Wirtschaftsamter in Blankenese and Gr. Flottbeck are proceeding arbitrarily.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">The Verkehrsamt is alleged to be busying itself circulating lists requiring registration of electric bulbs in garages. A British staff of fourteen is said to be kept busy on these lists, the purpose of which is to gain the permission of the electricity works to use the bulbs. Other complaints are heard that at the Wohningsanter residential permits can be obtained by small gifts and that a little influence does much to smooth the applicant's path.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2c4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">In small but well informed circles it is said that ex-Burgermeister Petersen is very active behind the scenes in an attempt to discredit his successor. Much of the adverse criticism in the "Hamburger Allgemeine Zeitung" is thought to be inspired by him in his desire to discredit the present as administration on the grounds of inefficiency and abuse of office for party purposes. Such criticism is generally resented, particularly from Petersen who is regarded as having used his office to further his personal business interests, While Burgermeister Brauer has avoided any charge of self-seeking, doubts are increasingly expressed as to whether he is of sufficient Political stature and possesses enough vision and foresight to remedy social evils. Many consider him too optimistic and others complain that the years he spent outside Germany have left him with a gap of understanding which he is not able to bridge. hhh 8. ECONOMY</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">The economic position of Germany is viewed with much pessimism which the fusion of the British and. American Zones has not relieved. Economic prospects are discussed with scepticism and it is increasingly felt that neither Britain nor America are seriously interested in restoring Germany's economy. Business men believe that many industrial concerns have been irrecoverably ruined and that the temporary expedients employed by the British and Americans will not restore them. There is great despair for complete recovery in the face of so much bad faith and economic self-interest as well as inadequate assistance.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">The continued export of timber to Britain is a lively topic among lumbermen and dock workers alike. Here again it is thought that German needs are complete­ly disregarded and that a policy of ruthless exploitation is being followed ir­respective of the ultimate consequences to German economy. The use of high grade timber for fuel to relieve the shortage of coal is considered the negation of sound economic planning.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">Against the background of the mere pressing problems of fuel and food is the question of impending monetary reforms. The recent announcement that such changes would take place simultaneously in the British and American Zones without awaiting Russian agreement has caused a rumour that reforms will be introduced on the 1st April. Certain consequent nervousness is felt and many believe that 70% of Bank and Savings Bank deposits will be confiscated, 20% will be blocked and only the remaining 10% left at the disposal of the depositor. Other measures are thought to be intended to depreciate the value of real estate. The upward trend of the value of stocks of industrial enterprises in the Russian Zone continues to cause surprise. Explanations for this are varied but some trace it to British press reports which have touched upon the possible return of Pomerania to Germany. A more readily accepted explanation is that there exists an amendment to the Potsdam Agreement whereby Thuringia and Mecklenburg are to be absorbed into the British Zone after two years occupation by the Russians. The majority, however, think it unlikely that the Russians will make any such territorial concession and will retain their hold on commercial enterprises in eastern Germany through special Soviet corporations. hhh 9. PRESS, WIRELESS, ETC.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-304f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">Astonishment is occasionally expressed at the wide measure of editorial freedom which the press enjoys in the British Zone. This is thought to be exemplified by an article, "The Atlantic Charter", which appeared in "Die Zeit" on 2.1.47. This freedom is not always regarded as liberal Kindedness and frequently is thought to be dictated by the need to provide Germans with a means of ventilating their grievances. Some satisfaction has been expressed at what is said to be the recently improved tone of the "Hamburer Allgemeine Zeitung" but this opinion seems to be confined to members of the CDU.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-314f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">Recent broadcasts which have been generally commended were: -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-324f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">(a) a talk by Nolting M.E.A. North Rhine, Westphalia, on coal production</note>
				<note xml:id="q-334f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">(b) a talk by Peter von Zahn on the uselessness of strikes and riots. -Whilst the talk has been praised, gaily listeners thought it inspired by the Li litany Government</note>
				<note xml:id="q-344f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">(c) The programme "Echo of the Day", a daily feature at 22.00 hours.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-354f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">Hamburg's principal theatre, the Schauspielhaus, is passing through a crisis mainly revolving around the person of its manager, Hellmer. His histrionic art is questioned by the actors of the theatre who consider it out of keeping with the times, in spite of the support recently given Hellmer in the Burgerschaft by the Borgerneister.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-364f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">Complaints continue to be heard that tickets to many theatres are unobtainable except when purchased by private arrangement. hhh 10. RUMOURS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-374f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">A rumour, believed to have originated in a fish canning factory in Altona, claims that herrings are being processed and exported to England. This is said to account for the low quality of the herrings issued to the Ha: burg population. The export of German butter to Belgium is on the increase.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-384f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">The greater part of shoe production in the British Zone is exported to Britain, while imports of footwear from Britain consists of badly repaired army boots and poor quality canvas shoes with wooden soles.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-394f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">In an unguarded moment a British Officer is said to have admitted that it was Britain's intention to reduce the German -population to 35,000,000 by privation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3a4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">The so-called "green frontier" between the Russian and British Zones, now patrolled by German policemen on the Russian side, is much more difficult to cross, firstly because of the greater knowledge of the Germans of the countryside and secondly because of the far greater brutality and corruption of German police</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3b4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">It is said that Prisoners of war in Russia who belonged to the S.S. are extremely well off and need not work.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3c4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">German sea captains and crews have been requested to volunteer for further sea service at a Baltic port, either Stettin or Swinemunde. None have volunteered but a number were pressed into service on ships on which only the wireless opera­tors were Russian. These ships, about twenty five in all, are said to have left the port for an unknown destination.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3d4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">The rumour that the Russians intend handing over certain parts of their Zone to British and Americans finds its counterpart in another alleging that western parts of the Russian Zone, previously evacuated, have been re-occupied in full strength in the last two months. In these districts Russian soldiers are behav­ing with that indiscipline which in the past had caused atrocities to be attri­buted to them. Public safety once again has ceased to exist as troops plunder what is left. hhh 11. MISCELLANEOUS.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3e4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">The employment of religious denominations to distribute charity parcels, which are arriving in increasing numbers, is generally regarded with favour, but there are nevertheless suggestions that the clergy are using this as a means of extending their influence. Many view this development with concern that churches once again my gain influence outside their purely spiritual sphere and that such charitable work should be left to non-religious organisations.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3f4f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">It is common belief that Germans in the French Zone are still worse off than those in the British Zone. Many train loads of German goods are believed to leave for France daily. This belief finds some support in the more widely held opinion that the French equal the Russians in ruthlessness and in the pursuit of economic self-interest.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-404f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">Internment camp guards at Heilbronn are reported to be recruited from former S.S. men and are said to enjoy the full backing of the Americans. The conduct of these guards is stated to be little different from what the world has come to expect of the S.S.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-414f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">Some malicious gossip has taken place concerning the removal of the Food Office from Hamburg to Stuttgart following upon the economical fusion of the British and American Zones. When the British staff of thirty as posted to Stuttgart the Americans returned twenty four to Hamburg as they themselves found six sufficient for their tasks. The story was at first treated. as a joke but to-day many seem convinced that the redundant staff returned to Hamburg to occupy housing accommodation that could more profitably be em­ployed for other purposes.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-424f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="51">Deputy Inspector</note>
				<note xml:id="q-434f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="52">Public Safety</note>
				<note xml:id="q-444f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="53">MSO'R/SL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-454f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="54">Copy to:- Inspector General,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-464f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="55">Public Safety _Branch,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-474f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="56">Bunde</note>
				<note xml:id="q-484f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="57">Regional Intelligence Officer,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-494f88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="58">16 (Hamburg) Intelligence Office.</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>