<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Report on Berlin Morale No. 28 - first half of September 1948</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-dc8046c9-cb3b-4747-8435-228f3d649129</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-7a3b4d40-36da-46ad-a1fd-e988f51a14bd</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-435488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="1">CONFIDENTIAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-445488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="2">Public Opinion Research Office</note>
				<note xml:id="q-455488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">Political Division</note>
				<note xml:id="q-465488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="4">York House</note>
				<note xml:id="q-475488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="5">HQ CCG (BE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-485488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="6">Berlin, BAOR 2.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-495488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="7">Report on Berlin Morale No.28.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4a5488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">(Covering Period 25th August to 10th September) hhh 1. General atmosphere</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b5488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">Rarely has the atmosphere in Berlin been more despondent, and to the Berliners the number of arguments justifying pessimism and anxiety are considerable. Even those who had not ventured to hope for a favourable issue of the Moscow discussions for Berlin, the Berlin talks were viewed as a clear proof of the Western Power's willingness to make concessions. Although originally there was talk of the lifting of the blockade being the proviso for the resumption of quadripartite talks sudden­ly no more mention was made of the matter and the 4 Commanders-in-Chief began their negotiations at the Control Council Building, followed by the Berliners with the keenest interest. These negotiations continue but so far no official statements have been made as to their progress. Therefore the most varied groups of opinion form themselves among the population.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c5488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">The majority of Berliners believe that both parties, chiefly the Western Powers, would be prepared to grant extensive concessions in the Berlin question as all concerned wish to avoid any further aggravation of the situation that leads to war and both sides wish to gain time. This attitude of forbearance on the part of the Western Powers has attributed to the following causes:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d5488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">1) In USA outcome of the Presidential elections is to be first awaited.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e5488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">2) Inner-political instability in France and her detached attitude towards Berlin make it increasingly difficult for the Western Powers to take united strong action, and</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f5488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">3) For the British and Americans, the air-bridge would in the long run, and especially during the winter become far too expensive.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-505488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">The most varied opinions concerning the presumed outcome of the Berlin negotiations have been formed. The following possibilities are considered:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-515488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">1) D-Mark (West) as sole legal tender.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-525488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">2) Both currencies operating on parallel lines.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-535488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">3) Creation of a special "Berlin Bear Mark". And</note>
				<note xml:id="q-545488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">4) D-Mark (East) as sole legal tender.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-555488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">The first is regarded as the first desirable by a large section of Western Berliners and has also been demanded by the SPD, CDU, LDP and UGO. Many, however, place little faith in this method as this would mean that the Western sectors would be entirely isolated and obliged to fall-back absolutely on an economic link with the West which could only be maintained by air and is therefore rather hopeless. The second, i.e. status quo, is in general regarded unfavourable. The third, i.e. the "Bear Mark", is in general considered to be the most favourable possibility of a quadripartite solution of currency difficulties for the whole of Berlin. However, this Bear Mark would have to be such that its ratio of 1:1 opposite D-Mark (West) and D-Mark (East) alike and thus form a sort of "Buffer-currency". In this manner it is hoped that Berlin could become a connecting and mediating link between the Western Zones and the Eastern Zone whereby its position as German Capital would be considerably strengthened. Pre-requisite hereto would be the re-opening of the roads from Berlin to the Western Zones (for which the Internationalisation of the permanent way and the Autobahn Berlin-Helmstedt is regarded as the ideal solution) and un-hampered goods and passenger traffic from Berlin into all the Zones.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-565488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">The solution making Eastern money the only legal tender is looked upon as the most unfavourable solution. Practical experience has shown that the D-Mark (West) was roughly three times the value of the East Mark. Should the East Mark become exclusive legal tender in Berlin this would imply that Berlin could only do business with the Eastern Zone or that threefold prices would have to be paid for goods from the West which would be impossible in practice. (Salaries and wages are expected to remain unchanged.) This would make the re-opening of land routes with the West more or less valueless, for it is foreseen that the entire passenger and goods traffic would be subject to Russian control.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-575488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">So the Berliner discusses all these possible solutions, and the wish is emphatically expressed in all quarters that the Western Powers remain firm and not give way to a "foul compromise". hhh 2. Food</note>
				<note xml:id="q-585488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">The critical food situation remains unchanged. Foodstuffs on ration cards are, however, being punctually supplied throughout. Many housewives complain that the proportion of dehydrated potatoes and potato powder which had been fixed at 1:5 for fresh potatoes is too low and the supply inadequate.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-595488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">Issue of 9 American cigarettes to every West Berliner and the issue of tea instead of coffee-Ersatz has been welcomed, at the same time the Berliner is grateful for any special allocation. These are regarded as a recognition by the Western Powers of the Berliner's bearing. hhh 3. Coal Supplies</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a5488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">The problem of domestic fuel supply for the coming winter as well as the power, gas and transport situation continue to cause anxiety which in view of the coming winter is increasing. Confidence in the "flying coal men" is not very great and allocations of coal via the air-bridge are not expected. hhh 4. Political Worries.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b5488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">The events at the Berlin Stadthaus are the topic of the day. As the Stadtverordneten meetings could not take place owing to communist demonstrations the delegates of the SED, CDU and LDP mowed from the Neue Stadthaus (Russian sector) to the Taberna Academica (British sector) where the meetings could be held in uneasy peace without the SED's participation. The resolution was passed to fix new elections for 14.11. Many Berliners view these incidents as a sure sign that the SMA does not intend to change its policy despite the present conferences of the four Commanders-in-Chief and continues to see its goal in either dominating the whole of Berlin or at least cutting the ground from under quadripartite administration and incorporating the Eastern sector into the Eastern Zone in a political and economic respect. The Russian licensed Press, however, asserts officially that the Stadtverordneten meetings had been trans­ferred to the Western sector according to a premediated plan in order to expe­dite the "split of Berlin".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c5488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">The sale of western licenced newspapers have been made increasingly diffi­cult in the Russian sector and the majority of newspaper vendors in the western sectors have resolved to boycott eastern licenced papers so that in practice only the correspondingly licenced papers are available in the individual Sectors.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5d5488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">The conferences of the Parliamentary Council in Bonn in general are re­ceiving little attention in view of local events. General Clay's instruction according to which the Berlin delegates are only granted advisory vote has been accepted most unfavourably. It is presumed that this instruction has been issued in consequence of the present policy of compromise of the Western Powers in order not to unnecessarily aggravate the Berlin crisis. hhh 5. Denazification</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5e5488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">The Schacht verdict has intensified the opinion of wide circles of the Berlin population that the "minor culprits are being hanged and the major ones are left to go scot free". It is considered high time to bring denazifications to a close. Such verdicts are held to lack all moral foundation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5f5488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">Summering reviewed, inclination towards Nazi-ideology manifests itself. Many people say that numerous mistakes and misdeeds for which the Nazis have been blamed are being repeated by the Allies themselves or at least are being tolerated by them. Compulsory Labour, restriction of free speech and expression of opinion, tolerating corruption or bribery and favouritism are all instances. hhh 6. Rumours</note>
				<note xml:id="q-605488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">Rumours that the French want to leave Berlin and that the French sector is to be attached to the British remain unchanged.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-615488b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">The Western Powers are said to have offered their rights in China to the Soviets in exchange for Eastern Germany and Berlin.</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>