<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Monthly Report on Morale and Public Opinion - January 1948</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-9f3ea16d-52bc-48a5-8d15-5c322ddbd234</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-f84ae438-6361-4bd1-b2d1-c017c2426f60</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-ce4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="1">Tel. 34 10 00</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cf4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="2">Ext 8500</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d04d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">609/PS/S/12/7</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d14d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="4">Public Safety</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d24d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="5">HQ Hansestadt HAMBURG</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d34d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="6">609 HQ COG (BE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d44d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="7">BAOR 3</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d54d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="8">29 January 1918</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d64d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="9">Subject:- Monthly Report on morale and Public Opinion - January</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d74d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="10">The Regional Commissioner</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d84d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="11">HQ Hansestadt HAMBURG</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d94d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="12">609 HQ COG (BE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-da4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="13">BAOR 3 hhh GENERAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-db4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">1. During the last month few Germans, however harassed their daily lives, could completely escape the feeling that they were living through momentous times. Cost of them fully realise that a stage has been reached in the re­lations between the Eastern and Western Allies of vital importance to them but which they have no power to influence. Most Hamburgers, whatever their leanings and political convictions, know that a state of harsh realities confronts them with what, to most, is a painful choice.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">2. The choice is painful principally because it involves what is strongly but generally considered an individual decision on the unity of Germany. It is true that the nationalism of many Hamburgers, as with Germans else­where, has been considerably overlaid by the pressure of immediate cares and the resultant state of exhaustion has progressively reduced their sense of national, social and moral values. But German nationalism could be and was kept in suspense as long as the Allied powers were resolved to treat Germany as a single entity.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">3. Germans reasoned that while these conditions prevailed, Allied pres­sure or relaxation would affect all Germany equally without disrupting her Physical unity and impairing German nationalist sentiment. Now most Hamburgers believe that conflict between the Allies, possibly resulting in the territorial dismemberment of Germany, will raise problems of loyalty which will disturb the German's instinctive affection for his country. The dilemma is common to all Germans, and no less in Hamburg with its traditions of liberalism in politics and economics. It is unfortunate that most Hamburgers feel that the British occupation has done insufficient during the last two years to compel confidence in what is regarded as inevitable.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">4. The present strain especially arising out of the bad food position, makes it difficult for the Hamburg population to feel assured that the Western Zones have a sounder economic future or that the course of events will justify their claim to have been the repository for German hopes for ultimate unity and independence.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">5. If the people of Hamburg could feel convinced of ultimately achieving this, they would find it easier to draw support for their choice from their abhorrence of the Communist alternative, which no amount of KPD or SED pro­paganda has so far been able to overcome. But the recent strike in the Hamburg port area has shown, as have strikes elsewhere in the Western Zones, that the representation of economic and social interests sometimes clouds the political lines along which it moves. If conditions in Hamburg were much more favourable than they are, self-interest and fear, together with what remains of old affinities with -Western thought and culture would plead earnestly for the course the Anglo-Saxon powers are charting for Germany. But even then there would remain a feeling of uneasiness, understandable in a people both proud and humble, who have borne the effects of defeat and social disintegration and who, demoralised though they may be, would still prefer to trust a past which is their own than an uncertain future under the tutelage of foreign powers which might conceivably embroil them in a new war. hhh FOOD</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e04d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">6. During the last four weeks, perhaps more than ever before, food has been the principal preoccupation of all Hamburgers. Very few pretend to be able to account for the violent slump in rations and it is incontestable that it is affecting all social activity and resulting in an extremely low state of public morale. Without early and marked relief in this respect, improvement in general morale in Hamburg is unlikely.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e14d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">7. The only foodstuffs generally and regularly available are bread, cereals and sugar. Apart from a small quantity of additional bread, which was issued in lieu of part of the potato ration, which has not been fully issued since November, no compensating issues of other foodstuffs were made.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e24d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">8. Fresh milk for adults has not been available for about two months and in the last three weeks the cheese ration, such as it is, has disappeared. There is also a shortage of fresh meat and complaints are frequently heard about the quality of the tinned meats which have been issued in its stead. For the first time, too, the fish ration shows signs of failing and none could be obtained for the first two weeks of the rationing period. The salted herrings available since then have generally been criticised as stale and unappetising. Other complaints are made but it is mainly with respect to the lack of fats that the situation is felt to be intolerable.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e34d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">9. Under these circumstances, it is not surprising that the population is either nonplussed or embittered by the apparent refusal of Military Govern­ment to ease the food situation from sources of supply considered available to them. In this connection, mention is made of quantities of copra which the U.S.A. is thought to have allocated to Germany but which lack of trans­port prevents being delivered to German ports. There is also difficulty in understanding the prohibition on German participation in whaling operations and why Germany should be treated differently from Japan in this respect. Parallel with these criticisms is the swelling clamour for Military Govern­ment to intervene and take determined steps to root out the selfish and. criminal activities of black marketeers whom Germans feel cannot be sup­pressed by their own corrupt German bureaucracy. hhh FUEL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e44d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">10. It is fortunate that so far the mild weather this winter has saved the population from a repetition of last winter's privations. Most Hamburgers fervently hope that the comparatively favourable weather will continue into spring aid make it unnecessary to close workshops and factories as was the case during the critical period last winter. Contrary to expectations there were no power cuts during the month and this brought a measure of general relief.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e54d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">11. It is common belief that large quantities of coal have accumulated in the Ruhr district during the last few months. Some estimates of the size of these stocks are very high and surprise is felt that no effort is made to barter part of them for food imports which, it is thought. a number of European countries would make available to Germany if paid in coal. hhh PUBLIC HEALTH</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e64d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">12. In spite of efforts to develop Public Health Services by the provision of medical supplies, doctors and additional hospital accommodation, public health continues to deteriorate.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e74d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">13. The war, and particularly its aftermath, has taken a frightful toll of the health of the population. The accumulated effects of undernourishment and mental strain are making tremendous inroads into constitutional reserves. This lack of vitality expresses itself in nervous irritability, lack of interest in all but the more important matters, loss of power of concentration and Door resistance to disease generally Its effects in the field of productivity are immeasurable and severely affects the will to recover. hhh CLOTHING - HOUSEHOLD</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e84d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">14. It is not only the shortage of all kinds of clothing which presses heavily on the population but also the difficulty of repairing what they have. The small quantities of soap and its substitutes issued monthly are not sufficient to allow more than cursory laundering.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e94d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">15. The shortage of footwear is appalling and there are many thousands in Hamburg who are either prevented from leaving their homes or expose them­selves to serious health risks during bad weather. Recent statements that more than 6,000,000 pairs of footwear were produced in the British Zone between July 1946 and June 1947 are met with astonishment. On the basis of this figure every fourth German living in the British Zone should have re­ceived one pair of boots or shoes, but there is a reluctance to accept the figure as authentic, especially as there have been so many who have been unable to buy footwear since the end of the war.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ea4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">16. Another matter causing great inconvenience in private households and industry is the shortage of electric bulbs, large quantities of which ap­pear to be available on the Black Market at the price of 1 R.M. per watt, a price which places the article beyond the means of the average working man. Allotments of electric bulbs to industry and public authorities are also insufficient and many questions are asked as to why a commodity which could be easily controlled is largely disposed of through irregular channels. hhh BLACK MARKET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-eb4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">17. Although a majority of people at some time or another participate in Black Market trading, it is by no means accepted philosophically by all. There is a growing realisation that it is a curse and more and more people are beginning to realise that it prevents the equitable distribution of available foodstuffs and other commodities. Recent speeches by high rank­ing Military Government officials and others have tended to focus attention on this social rumour and many believe that the German Authorities charged with enforcing controls would take more energetic steps in enforcing them if they were themselves free of any taint of suspicion. The strained food situation is driving prices higher and it is believed that all are influenced by those obtaining on the Black Market. hhh MILITARY GOVERNMENT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ec4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">18. Whilst there is no new-found confidence in Military Government many factors contribute to a rowing desire on the part of Hamburgers for a return to Military Government of some measure of control in those spheres where responsibility has devolved largely or exclusively upon the German Administration. This coincides with the increasing readiness of Germans to question the integrity of many of their officials and offices. The effect of this has been to deflect much of the criticism which is normally reserved for Military Government. This is probably more the product of inertia and cynicism than the development of an objective attitude towards Military Government. hhh LOCAL AUTHORITIES</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ed4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">19. Judged by the test that democracy implies confidence in and control over elected authority very few Hamburgers admit that their German Admini­stration is democratic in character or function. Without exception, the principal authorities of Hamburg have been criticised for overstaffing, inefficiency and indifference to public welfare and that in the attitude of officials, complacency and rudeness have been substituted for service and responsibility.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ee4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">20. A smug and hidebound bureaucracy is establishing its ascendancy over population too harassed, too timid, but above all, mostly too dependent, to assert itself. The Administration thus earns the opprobrium of the population, which is more conscious of its failure to administer than of any cause for rejoicing in its newly acquired freedom to manage its own affairs. hhh CORRUPTION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ef4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">21. The lack of confidence in the German Authorities is largely based on the many charges of corruption leveled against public officials. Recent disclosures concerning large scale irregularities with butter tend to con­firm these views but the public anger thus roused quickly subsides and gives way to a cynical belief that as in previous cases no punishment will be meted out to the offenders because of the danger of publicly discredit­ing politically eminent persons. Public opinion inclines to the view that Police and Courts are both directed by such overriding considerations and that there is nowhere scope for an impartial and searching investigation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f04d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">22. It is widely believed in Hamburg that the SIM has not only firmly en­trenched itself in all local Authorities but that it is practising nepotism on behalf of its adherents and that a reign of bureaucracy effectively stifles every voice of criticism within or without these Authorities.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f14d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">23. Meanwhile rumours continue that prominent Social Democrats and trade unionists still dine at the main station restaurant and other places in complete disregard of all restrictions on food and prices. hhh PRISONERS OF WAR</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f24d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">24. The question of German prisoners of war, estimated to number between one and a half and two millions, remaining in Allied hands, continues to agitate the public wind. It is regretted that after nearly three years there is still no German Central Authority to plead the cause of these prisoners, many of whom, it is felt, are being estranged from their country by their long absence.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f34d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">25. Whilst complaints concerning the treatment of German prisoners of war in French hands have been less frequent of late, there is a fairly wide­spread conviction that German prisoners of war in British hands in Africa are not only detained in captivity longer than is necessary but also are frequently exposed to inconsiderate treatment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f44d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">26. Prisoners of war returning from Russia refute Russian claims that priority of release is given to those who have excelled in labour. Re­leased prisoners claim that only a small fraction of former prisoners of war are physically fit and that the overwhelming majority are physical wrecks and often weigh less than 100 lbs. hhh ECONOMY</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f54d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">27. Recent rumours concerning impending currency reforms have yielded slightly to the belief that the Allies have recognised the futility of any such reforms before the great shortage of consumer goods and the necessities of life are relieved. The question of financial reform is coupled with the necessity of not only reducing the cost of a swollen German Administration but also the demands of the Occupying Power which is believed to be employing more than 32,000 Germans in the British Zone alone.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f64d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">28. To ease the shortage of hard currency, it is believed that the Mints of Berlin, Munich and Stuttgart have commenced minting 5 and 10 pfennig pieces and that as these are passed into circulation, a corresponding amount of paper money will be withdrawn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f74d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">29. Great satisfaction has been expressed in Hamburg shipping circles that German shipping and transport interests have been re-admitted to inter­national transit goods business, opportunities thereby being given to re­establish contact with former business connections abroad.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f84d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">30. Following the recent strike in the port area, it is claimed that the rate of loading and discharging ships has slowed down appreciably and all Hamburg shipyards, as well as any other industries, complain of the dif­ficulty of obtaining sufficient labour and facilities for training appren­tices.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f94d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">31. The Hamburg Stock Exchange is experiencing a brisk demand for any kind a industrial shares which are considered a better investment than cash or bank deposit however high they are quoted. Business acquaintances of brokers claim to know that in the Russian Zone two kinds of currency are to be introduced - an "Arbeitsmark" and a "Handelsmark" - the former to be used for the purchase of necessities and the payment of wages and salaries anti the latter for all other transactions. hhh DENAZIFICATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fa4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">32. While Denazification continues to be generally discredited, the con­viction is growing that former Nazis are the only ones who benefit from this development, cases being cited of the failure to purge effectively and reduce the possibility of former Nazis returning to positions of in­fluence before the new democracy is able to assimilate them. In medical circles much anger has been caused by the re-emergence into professional life of a doctor known as an arch Nazi and an important figure in the Medical Association during the Hitler regime. Anger at this man has been exacerbated. by his appointment as a panel doctor, whilst other Hamburg doctors who were anti-Nazis have waited a long time in vain for such professional appointments.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fb4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">33. It is thought by many that an investigation has shown 30 of the 35 Prosecutors at the Bielefeld Spruchkammer to be former members of the NSDAP or one of its affiliated organisations. In this connection, they point out that according to Ordinance No. 69 members of the NSDAP are barred from participating in trials connected with persons who belonged to Nazi organi­sations since declared criminal by the International Military Tribunal at Nuremberg. hhh YOUTH - EDUCATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fc4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">34. An SPD proposal to extend elementary education from four to six years has met with a good deal of opposition and is viewed as an attempt to sacri­fice gifted children to a standardized curriculum.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fd4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">35. Attempts by German Authorities, supported by Military Government, to increase the number of holiday homes for children are well-received. Those in existence are judged some of the most successful examples of co-operation between British and German Authorities. The Special food rations authorised for these institutions by Military Government and the interest shown in the homes by British and German Red Cross personnel has been widely welcomed. hhh PRESS, WIRELESS, ETC</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fe4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">36. Critics and other informed theatrical circles are curiously watching the reappearance of a man who in 1933 became the Theatre Director at Wuppertal and subsequently rose to considerable prominence as an outstand­ing producer of Nazi plays.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ff4d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">37. Hamburg newspaper publications have successfully concluded their dis­cussions with the Authorities for an increased allocation of newsprint. Papers which have hitherto appeared twice weekly may now be published three times and it is generally thought that "Die Welt", now a paper of restricted issues, will soon be published daily.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-004e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">38. It is rumoured that members of a resistance group former National Socialists, chartered and equipped a ship and sailed for Mexico with a considerable amount of money in dollars on board. The ship was inter­cepted in the vicinity of Jutland and escorted bank to Germany.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-014e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">39. A report is circulating that the move of a number of Russian and Russian controlled agencies from Berlin to Leipzig is about to take place. It is believed that this is promoted by a number of considerations but chiefly to permit Russian and SED policy to be implemented undiluted by Quadripartite influences and restraints. hhh Miscellaneous</note>
				<note xml:id="q-024e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">40. The possibility that the Eastern Zonal Frontier will be closed is widely discussed in Hamburg and in preparation of this, it is believed that a force of some 4,300 policemen has been sent to the border to seal it in case of need.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-034e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">41. Hamburg is experiencing a growing shortage of trial judges as a con­sequence of the return of many of them to the more lucrative living of practising solicitors or barristers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-044e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">42. It is thought in Hamburg that Germans employed in British Censorship Departments are using their offices and the information acquired by them in the course of their duties to sand pleas abroad principally to America, for gift parcels. A number of Hamburgers have received letters from rela­tives abroad reproaching them for having passed on their addresses It is also claimed that other Censorship employees have begged from or black-mailed Hamburg people thought to be recipients of gifts of food which were subsequently bartered or sold on the Black Market.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-054e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="56">(J.D. Stewart)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-064e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="57">Deputy Inspector General</note>
				<note xml:id="q-074e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="58">Public Safety</note>
				<note xml:id="q-084e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">FEH/SL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-094e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="60">Copy to: The Inspector General.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0a4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="61">E.G. Nottingham Esq., /LC.,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0b4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="62">Deputy Inspector General,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0c4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="63">BERLIN.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0d4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="64">The Regional Governmental Officer.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0e4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="65">The Regional Intelligence Officer.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0f4e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="66">J.R. White, Esq.,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-104e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="67">Public Opinion Research Office,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-114e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="68">Governmental Sub-Commission,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-124e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="69">67 HQ C.C.G.,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-134e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="70">BIELEFELD, BAOR.</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>