<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Ministry of Information Home Intelligence Division Weekly Report No. 77 - 25th March 1942</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-c15d6e2b-551a-47bb-9b4e-3a58732cfdb9</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-ae090926-7150-492e-9950-5fa233b4baad</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-625588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-635588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-645588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="3">Home Intelligence Division Weekly Report No, 77</note>
				<note xml:id="q-655588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="4">25th March, 1942</note>
				<note xml:id="q-665588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">(Covering the period from 16th to 23rd March, 1942) aa Note: The figures in brackets refer to sources of information, a list of which was issued with all reports up to and including No.66, 7th January, 1942. hhh I GENERAL COMMENTS hhh 1. General state of confidence and reaction to news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-675588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">No definite change appears to have taken place this week in the state of public confidence. Although Allied initiative in the Far East has contributed to "a certain brightening of the general scene", the prospect on the industrial and home fronts is still viewed with depression. It is stated that "the possibility of defeat" is openly discussed in some quarters, coupled with the question: "Do we deserve to win?" From several Regions, there are reports of "a certain reluctance to discuss the war"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-685588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">Ten R.I.O.s report a demand for strong, active and inspired Government leadership; an "almost pathetic gratitude" has been the main reaction to the new restrictions on clothing and fuel, both of which were regarded as real steps towards Total War. But "if the people's sacrifices are not capped by vigorous Government action, a swing towards defeatism or communism is thought likely"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-695588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">In five Regional reports reference is made to a sense of "frustration" and "fatalism". Such feelings, it, is suggested, arise from the desire for successful British military action, and for concrete evidence that we are really tackling war production. Dissatisfaction over production comes both from the direct experience of workers and the many stories of hold-ups and idleness which are in circulation, and also from. a "lack of information about what is already being done".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6a5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">In this connection, five R.I.O.s record appreciation of Lord Halifax's speech; "its impressive statement of our contribution to the war effort has won universal approval".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6b5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">(1,2, 3,4,5,6,7,8, 9,10,11,12,13, 21) hhh 2. The Far East</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6c5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">A more hopeful outlook is apparent in public feeling about the Far Eastern theatre of war. R.I.O.s are almost unanimous in ascribing this mainly to the appointment of General MacArthur as Supreme commander of the Allied Forces in the South Western pacific; "MacArthur's prestige stands higher than that of any general outside Russia". The heavy blows dealt to the Japanese Fleet are taken as evidence that "at last the Allies can hit and hurt the Japs". This news "has counteracted fatalistic depression caused by Allied losses in the Java Sea battle".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6d5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">Sir Stafford Cripps' mission to India: Sir Stafford Cripps has receded a little from the forefront of the political picture. "The magnitude of his task is appreciated, but most people appear to expect him to be successful - "the one man for the-job" is a typical comment. It is hoped he will not be away for long. It is stated that the main public interest at the moment in India is "strategic rather than political'; though there is a general feeling that "India should got her freedom'.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6e5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">Burma: Reduced interest in the Burma situation is reported, though "the news that Chinese troops are active in North Burma has been welcomed".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6f5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">Singapore: There has been a renewal of talk about the fall of Singapore; "it's the first time in history so many men have surrendered without a fight", and it is felt that "no adequate explanation has yet been given". Among those with missing relatives, it is stated that "sorrow seems to stifle criticism".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-705588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">Australia: Increasing interest in Australia is reported; the presence there of U.S. troops is welcomed, but there is speculation as to the real strength of these reinforcements. It is widely believed that Australia is "gravitating more and more" toward the United States, and that she is "as good as lost to us as a Dominion". Most people who comment thus do act regard it as a disaster, but rather as "a sound idea to have a permanent link between the two new countries". The public are said to be "bewildered" at the acrimonious exchange of messages about Hr. Casey's appointment. Some regard the episode as "childish and stupid, considering the plight we are in"; others blame one side or the other: - "Why move Casey if it upset the Australians and he was doing a good job in Washington?" or "Why are the Australians making such a fuss?"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-715588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">(1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12,13,21) hhh 3. Russia</note>
				<note xml:id="q-725588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">Admiration for Russian efforts continues, but doubts about the accuracy of their communiques grows. There is also increasing anxiety about the anticipated German Eastern offensive in the spring.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-735588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">(1,2,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12,21) hhh 4. Libya</note>
				<note xml:id="q-745588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">A slight increase of interest in Libya is reported, where it is thought that "another big effort by Rommel is imminent and inevitable".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-755588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">(2, 3, 7, 10) hhh 5. U.S.A.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-765588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">It is increasingly believed that the U.S.A. is at last "getting a move on". Particularly in Australia. The news reels of Pearl Harbour are said to have "brought home to people, how much was lost there, and what a handicap it has been".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-775588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">(2, 3, 6, 7, 8) hhh 6. The Daily Mirror The Home Secretary's warning to this paper has produced considerable comment. While most people seem to think it "deserves all it gets for making sensational capital out of our national dangers", they fail to see why the particular cartoon was picked on. Petrol wastage is thought to be a much greater crime than any committed by the Mirror, and few people appear to have interpreted the cartoon as the Home Secretary did. Four R.I.O.s report dissatisfaction with Mr. Morrison's action on the grounds that it assails 'Freedom of the press".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-785588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">(1,2,3,4,5,6,7,10,12) hhh 7. Invasion prospects</note>
				<note xml:id="q-795588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">There is some evidence that people are growing "more invasion conscious". In the South Western Region, there is said to be little reliance on "our methods of combating invasion". In the North Midland Region, "responsible officials are asking, for definite instructions so as to be able to organise the civil population. People particularly want to know if an area which is in danger of becoming a fighting zone will be officially evacuated. If not, it is asked, has the civilian a role to play, or does he remain passive?"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7a5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">(These reports were received before the Lord President's statement on 24th March).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7b5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">(3, 7, 15, 16) hhh 8. Inequality of Sacrifice</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7c5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">There is growing evidence of a feeling among certain sections of the public that "everything is not fair and equal and that therefore our sacrifices are not worthwhile". In particular, there is some belief that the rich are less hit by rationing than 'ordinary people" for the following reasons:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7d5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">(a) They can eat at expensive restaurants.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7e5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">(b) They can afford to buy high priced goods in short demand, such as salmon and game.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7f5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">(c) They can spend more on clothes and therefore use their coupons more advantageously.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-805588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">(d) They receive preferential treatment in shops, as "people giving large orders are favoured and the poorer people wanting 'little bits' are refused".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-815588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">(e) They receive preferential treatment as regards petrol rationing. To quote a Postal Censorship report: "we can see the Big Bugs riding in their posh cars and poor beggars can't get petrol for business".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-825588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">The feeling of "inequality off' sacrifice" between the Services and Civilians, frequently mentioned in these reports, continues. Ill-feeling between the two is said to be growing as tales of slacking in factories, high wages, and black markets increase the belief among Service men that civilians arc not pulling their weight.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-835588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">(3, 5, 9, 11, 21 special) hhh 9. Extremist feelings</note>
				<note xml:id="q-845588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">Communism: From two Regions there are reports that among "decent workers" feeling against the Government is being coupled with an increasing sympathy for Communism. The efforts of the communists in appealing for harder work and the increased use of women in industry are thought to be helpful, but their criticism of all in authority and their demands for a second front are thought to be undermining confidence in our leadership, "the more so as every reverse we suffer lends point to their story".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-855588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">Fascism: From two areas discussion is reported about "Quislings among our so-called leaders" with Fascist tendencies, who do not wish Russia to win, and do not "mean business" with Germany.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-865588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">These people, it is said, "wish to break the morale of the 'British public so that, when the spoils are shared, the common people will get only the bones".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-875588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">I.R.A.: The R.I.O. Northern Ireland. reports "sinister revelations in focal police courts" about the I.R.A. Members of this organisation are alleged to be "aiming at 'downing the British' at all costs and by all means - even to the extent of subverting British troops, using American troops as vehicles for obtaining military information, and doing Fifth Column work generally".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-885588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">(2, 3, 8, 10, 13, 14, Eastern and North Midland). hhh 10. Broadcasting and presentation of news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-895588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">Dissatisfaction with the presentation of news continues. The B.B.C. is accused of "plugging" the story of the sinking of the German E-boats, while incidentally mentioning that we had lost a destroyer. The quotation of "tainted foreign sources such as Stockholm" is criticised. There are again accusations against the Government of withholding bad news. Forgetful of previous complaints of "padding" of news bulletins, a minority of critics are now saying that "at this grave crisis in our history, news bulletins should not be so short".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8a5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">Sir John Anderson's postscript: Only two R.I.O.s refer to this postscript; it was described as "dull".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8b5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">Sir William Beveridge's "Times" article: More thoughtful people feel that this article "really put its finger on the weak spots in our production organisation", but they doubt if "vested interests" will permit the Government to put his views into effect.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8c5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">(2,3,4,5,8,9,10,11,13) hhh II SPECIAL COMMENTS hhh 11. Industry</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8d5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">Dissatisfaction with production is still widely reported on the same lines as in our last two reports. "Stories of labour wastage and idle time in factories continue to abound", according to five R.I.O.s; as the R.I.O., North Midland, says, "if they were all true it would seem that barely a single essential factory was working to capacity". People "seem to be little aware of the amount of material that is being out in factories, and mostly stress the rumours that they hear of idleness, dissatisfaction among workers, and dishonesty of management".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">The lack of mutual confidence between workers and managements, referred to last week, continues to be reported as 'becoming more and more marked, to the detriment of the war effort". In general, each accuses the other of being "purely mercenary minded", and thinking only of their own interests.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">The managements in particular are accused in connection with: -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-905588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">(a) Cost plus ten percent system,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-915588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">(b) Considering their post-war position,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-925588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">(c) Inefficiency,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-935588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">(d) Failure to explain to the workers the reasons for hold-ups.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-945588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">The workers are accused in connection with:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-955588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">(a) Absenteeism,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-965588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">(b) Piece work.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-975588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">Women's call-up: the demand continues for: -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-985588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">(a) Shopping facilities,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-995588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">(b) Day nurseries,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">(c) Part time work for married women near their homes.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">Irish labour: The R. I.O., North Midland, reports that labourers imported from Eire are the "terror of law-abiding citizens in the Leicestershire area, and that tales of drunkenness and assault are frequent, while several of these labourers have had to be put into mental hospitals". It is "generally supposed that the Ministry of Labour imports these men", and there is said to be "much bad feeling" locally; it is urged that there should be "some form of control, and' inspection".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">Dockyard workers: Allegations of slacking in shipyards and dockyards are made by sailors on leave, who say that "ships fail to be turned round quickly because of the deliberate slackness of some of the men in repairing and loading them". Dockers in Hull, however, are reported to be very critical of "those in authority and blame managerial incompetence for wastage of time and materials". Sir Roger Keyes' criticism is said to have "aroused fierce resentment". The transference of dockers to other ports is "resented as unnecessary, as frequently there is no work when they arrive at their new posts".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9d5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">(2,3,4,5,6,8,9,10,11,12) hhh 12. Income Tax</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9e5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">The "abnormally high rate of absenteeism in the mines" is alleged to 'be largely due to income tax according to one R.I.O.; "it is said to be customary now for the men to absent themselves on one day in the six".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9f5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">The complaints about income tax which continue, are in connection with: -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a05588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">(a) Tax on overtime.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a15588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">(b) Tax on married women's earnings.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a25588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">(c) The fact that workers who earn good money in the summer months have to pay tax on it during the winter, when they are earning less.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a35588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">(d) Post-war credit. There continues to be a demand for a card or booklet whereby workers could see the amount of Post-war credit due to them".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a45588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">(3, 5, 10, 12) hhh 13. Fuel rationing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a55588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">The proposal to ration fuel of all kinds appears to have excited little comment and, an general principles, no criticism; this is partly attributed to the recent improvement in the weather. In the Northern Region, however, "it is hoped that the scheme will take into account the fact that the warm weather comes much later in that Region than in the south, and that quite severe weather may be experienced in April or May".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a65588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">A "violent protest" is reported from the North Midland Region, "against the allocation of 3 cwt per month to each householder in that Region and 6 cwt to toe rest or England". It is pointed out that "the colliery districts are the worst hit as coal is used for heating and cooking, electricity being very little used and many houses having nothing but a coal range". Feeling is said to be "running very high".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a75588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">It is thought that there will be a great waste of transport in the case of outlying districts, if coal must be delivered monthly by the hundredweight instead of by the ten at longer intervals, as at present.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a85588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">(1, 2, 3, 5) hhh 14. Transport</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a95588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">The new Ministry of Transport Order whereby, after April 12th, queues must be formed for trams and buses in all parts of the country, has been welcomed as "extremely sensible"; people feel that "it will make life easier for them".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-aa5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">Workers' transport difficulties continue to be reported, particularly in the case of workers requiring to travel long distances who are crowded off the buses by shoppers travelling only a single stage. It is suggested that some means should be devised whereby long distance travelers take priority over those travelling short distances only.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ab5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">(2, 3, 12) hhh 15. War damage</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ac5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">From two Regions come reports of "dissatisfaction on account of delay in the settling of claims by the War Damage Commission. It is pointed out that small builders cannot afford to undertake further repairs to property while Previous expenditure is not refunded; as a result, housing property is deteriorating and many houses cannot, be let as they are unfit to live in". The case is quoted of one builder in the London Region who has put in six different claims since October, and has "not even received acknowledgements".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ad5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">(5, 10) hhh 16. Food</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ae5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">General: There are again few complaints about the food situation this week, and Postal Censorship reports that "satisfaction is still predominant". It is interesting to contrast this with Postal Censorship reports on incoming mail from Eire where the reverse is the case, and has been so for some time.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-af5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">Luxury meals: Criticism of expensive restaurants continues and there is some interest in the idea of limiting spending on restaurant meals. According to the R.I.O., North Midland Region, "luncheon clubs and 'official dinners are also coming to be regarded as in bad taste and it is thought they should be suspended for the duration of the war'. High prices of green vegetables: There is again mention of green vegetables being "wickedly dear'.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b05588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">(1, 2, 3, 5, 7, 8, 10, 12, 13, 21 Special) hhh 17. Clothes rationing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b15588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">General: On the whole the reduction of clothes coupons has been considered "no worse than was expected", and has been accepted calmly. There does, however, seem to be some anticipation of considerable difficulty in managing to be decently clothed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b25588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">Trade in coupons: Two R.I.O.s mention trade in clothes coupons: "old people particularly are said to sell theirs". Such trade is confirmed by Postal Censorship reports which refer to traffic in coupons, and quote the following example: "I've been black marketing for coupons; I managed to wangle 30 to-day; the woman I bought them from has no use for them; she'd sooner have the money".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b35588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">(2,3,4,5,6,7,10,13,21 Special) hhh 18. Rumours</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b45588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">The Queen Elizabeth is again reported to have been sunk, but this week this rumour comes from only one Region. From the Southern Region comes rumours of impending British offensives: -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b55588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">(a) On the Norwegian coast.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b65588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">(b) On the Low Countries and Schleswig-Holstein.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b75588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">15th April is mentioned in this Region as the date for the German invasion of Britain.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b85588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">London Region reports a rumour that certain members of the Government were planning to make a peace move, "which accounts for our lack of offensive action". In one version of this rumour a date was fixed for this peace move, but that date has passed. It is further suggested that it was because Churchill was aware of this "peace move" that he made the changes in the Government.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b95588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">A rumour said to have caused heavy withdrawals from Savings Banks in the Salford Dock area, is that "25% of all savings will be confiscated in the next budget".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ba5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">There are some rumours in Wales about the whereabouts of Mr. Churchill. He is said to be on his way to Russia.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bb5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">Other rumours reported are: -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bc5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">(a) That the coupon value of stockings is to be raised to four.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bd5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">(b) That the tax on tobacco is to be increased.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-be5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">(c) That cigarettes are to go up in price - the "10 for ninepenny" kind to be 10 for a shilling.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bf5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">(3,5,6,8,10 ) hhh 19. Constant topics and complaints</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c05588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">Complaints continue to be reported on the following subjects:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c15588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">(a) High price of goods in short supply.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c25588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">(b) Soap rationing: the delay in announcing the extra allowances, particularly for babies.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c35588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">(c) Inadequate transport facilities.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c45588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">(d) High wages of juveniles</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c55588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">(e) Non-collection of salvage.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c65588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">(f) "It is no use putting saucers on the market in Cardiff without cups".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c75588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">(1,2,3,5,7,8,9,10,12,21 Special P.C.)</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>