<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Morale Report for period 16 April to 22 April 1943</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-a4c96caa-9713-4f91-ad89-af3ea804de5e</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-c1895a8a-7ea3-4704-8ff4-6da2706d52a5</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-d74a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">RESTRICTED</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d84a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">Equals British CONFIDENTIAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d94a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">ALLIED FORCE HEADQUARTERS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-da4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="4">Censorship Branch (INC)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-db4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="5">A. P. O. 512 U. S. Army</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="6">26 April 1943.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">C/106/1</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">MEMO TO: G-1 Section A.F.H.Q.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">INC Section</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e04a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">Mr. Makins</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e14a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">Mr. W. Woollcombe Boyce</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e24a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">1. Attached hereto Report No. 11 From Censorship IBLO with Controles Techniques in respect of period 12 - 18 April 1943, forwarded for information.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e34a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="13">V.E. SCOTT BAILEY,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e44a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="14">Major, G. S.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e54a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="15">Chief Censor.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e64a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">Incl: 1</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e74a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">CONFIDENTIAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e84a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">(EQUALS BRITISH SECRET)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e94a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">OFFICE OF THE CURT' BASE CENSOR</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ea4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="20">Base Censorship Detachment No 1</note>
				<note xml:id="q-eb4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="21">APO 700, U.S. Army</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ec4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="22">22 April 1943</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ed4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="23">Subject: Morale report for period 16 April to 22 April 1943, inclusive.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ee4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">To: Commanding General, NATOUSA. (through channels) hhh 1. Health.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ef4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">Many comments noted frequently mentioned the writers good health and how living under field conditions in Africa have immunized them against common ills. The precautions against malaria are thought to be disagree­able but the benefits compensates the individual distaste. There is an indication that there is a contagious skin disease prevalent in this area. About 98% of all comments on health are favorable. The following were noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f04a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">"Very soon we have to start malarial precautions which means sleeping under nets and taking Adabrine twice a week until November. Hate to think of it but guess it's better than getting the disease, yes? We have now the transportation to take us to the beach several times a week and swimming is fine I have been told."--40th Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f14a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">"The whole building is set aside for contagious diseases except this one room. Most of the patients have Scages Dorsalis, a very contagious skin disease, but I haven't caught it yet."--10th Field Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f24a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">"We have been cold, hungry, homesick, dirty and even had bedbugs."-­52nd Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f34a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">"Yesterday finished a concrete floor for mess kitchen to keep rats away rats larger than sewer type in city."--Co. C, 242nd QM Battalion. hhh 2. Mall.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f44a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">Mail service to some units continues to be misdirected and delayed; it appears many writers blame the postal system in the States for this condition. It is noted that mail within North Africa is also delayed unnecessarily. The processing of V-mail in this theater has increased the volume of mail handled, writers are trying out the system for the 1st time. The receipt of micro-film from the States is looked upon as a means of receiving mail with more regularity. About 70% of all comments on mail service has been unfavorable. The following were noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f54a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">"It is a crime the way New York is horsing the mail of the 5th Base Post Office around. Just after I sent you a V-mail letter today telling you I received your letters of March 19, 20, 23, 25, 27, and 29 I received from England your letters properly addressed to me over here, dated March 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, and 9. Also one from … dated March 8. No wonder I didn't get any mail from you all during March to speak of and I was at a loss to understand the reason. It is no longer funny. We have been over here long enough for them to know where we are and to ship the mail correctly. My case is not the only one being sent in error over here but many others."-5th Base Post Office.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f64a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">"I would like to know what they do with the mail when it takes so long for it to get here. Perhaps it is put into storage until they get enough to send over in a big bunch. I don't know, but I do now know that all of this propaganda that you read about the efficient mail service that they have to the troops overseas is a lot of talk and does not belong to reality."--505th C.A.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f74a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">"Your letter of January 8 reached me yesterday-a mere 96 days in transit. It had been to good old U.S.A. I have wondered what you were doing and have asked about you many times but no one knew about it."--Hq. Fifth Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f84a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">"Have just learned that our mail has been misdirected to an area some 300 miles away which accounts for lack of mail for last few days. Hope all this mail is properly redirected."-10th Field Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f94a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">"I think I've written about two hundred letters since I left the States and I received about six."--509th Parachute Regt.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fa4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">"Sure have missed hearing from you. Just hope our mail catch up with us before long so far we haven't received any mail for 3 months."--APO 520.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fb4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">"The mail man just now brought me your letters of Feb. 1st and 22nd. Rather late eh? Of course I had already received those of Mar. 1st, 8th, and 29th-so know you were O.K."--12th AFSC.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fc4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">"I wrote a letter to the chief nurse of another station hospital 2 hours from here and it took her 8 days to get it so you can see what the mail situation is."--32nd Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fd4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">"Today I received your letter dated March 22 and I really couldn't understand what happened because I've been used to reading mail that was two or three months old. So imagine my surprise when all of a sudden out of a clear sky the mail orderly hands me four letters. They all are late letters from the 9th of March to the22nd."--Hqs. Det. Fifth Army Engineer Training Center.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fe4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">"Mail deliveries have been good- I can't complain. I have received nine letters from you so far since April lst."--345th Fighter Sq., 350th Fighter Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ff4a7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">"I got three letters from you yesterday. They were from the last pert of March. I got your Easter card today. The last few weeks the mail has been coming through good. Mine has all been getting here in between two to three weeks."--21st Signal Company, Service Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-004b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">Oh, say hon I hear we have some film in from the States. Maybe I will have one on the roll from you. I'm sure anxious for this to really get started, maybe we can have news from home just a week or so old instead of a month, ha."--Sianal Photo Mail Detachment. hhh 3. Training. Training has accelerated in this area during the past few weeks. It has been noted that complaints against strenuous training has lessened. Many realize what they lacked and are trying to pass this information back to military personnel in the States. Enlisted personnel are being trained to take over hospital duties, particularly for work in the G.O. Wards, surprise is usually expressed at their adaptability in replacing the nurses. About 75% of all comments on training emphasize the necessity of training and point out faults that have been found. The following were noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-014b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">"We have in this action trained a group of troops who are now well trained combat units. There are still many things which must be stressed. Communications in combat are vital. The communication must be up to the minute. The tempo of modern combat is so fast that unless your communication can keep up with the action. The leaders are fighting blind. Leader must do a leader job, planning and directing. They must not become involved in small details, such as acting as telephone orderly, or company clerk. Be sure that the men who are going to execute your plan, understand it. Make sure your instructions are clear and complete. Have them repeat it back to you. You will be surprised how much misunderstanding there is."--Hq. 5th Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-024b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">"I gave you this information before, since then lots happened as you know. This is not from personal experience, as the Lord knows, so far I have none, but from reading and hearing. If I had to train an outfit I would stress the following: Military courtesy and discipline, they harp on that plenty. Perhaps it has no place in action, but if outfits have it they will react quicker to orders; individual protection, get me in the habit of digging fox holes, at once, and deep enough for protection and let tanks run over them; give men rides in buttoned up tanks, so they know how much the tank crew can see; marksmanship (with all weapons) against tanks and planes; mine laying and removal, use of detectors, neutralizing mines and booby traps; night problems, moving into position at night, use of compass; scouting and patrolling; correct transmission of orders; endurance of all men and officers, ability to go a mile in 10 minutes with equipment; camouflage, individual and vehicles; road discipline with gas and air alarms; amity of outfit to function several days without much sleep and little food and water. These are a few hints that will help you to have a darn good outfit. Above all Colonel get rid of officers and key men who are out of place, don't wait until you go into action, it is then too late."--Hq. Fifth Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-034b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">"Training over here has greater reality, the hours are longer and the work more strenuous. The other day I visited an outfit and talked with the band leader for a while. He said the band in the past hadn't gone through the same strenuous training schedule as the rest of the troops because in combat they are used as couriers and litter bearers. But reports have come back from the front that soldiers who worked in headquarters and got little physical training and band personnel were suffering considerably up at the front. So now these band boys are taking their 25 mile hikes and going through the regular training schedule in addition to their playing."--19th Replacement Bn. APO 700.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-044b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">"In recent weeks, we have been having a diet of CPI's which I fear is a joy(?) you have yet to experience. There things can be run from your comfortable office in your home town, since they are skeletonized maneuvers without actual troops. However, we don't do things that way. The last one, over the week end, we bounced the entire forward echelon about 50 miles over the mountains, and have set up a complete command post in a pine woods." --Hq., VI Corps.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-054b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">"I spent the afternoon out on the rifle range undergoing recruit instructions on the proper method in which to shoot a pistol. You see several weeks ago the officer in command of our unit decided we should all shoot the pistol. Well, as usual, I missed the target most of the time and out of a possible two hundred I was successful in making thirty-five. This was so lousy that … decided I needed some recruit instructions, which is what I was doing this afternoon. Since I've at least been shown the correct way to hold and shoot the pistol, I believe I will better my old score by at least one hundred percent the next time I shoot. Would you believe that in the years I've been in the army, I have never had any instructions relative to rifle or pistol procedures? I was able to under­stand the causes of my poor shooting after the schooling, and I think most of my fault in the past has been my ignorance in knowing how to hold the weapon."--Hq. Co., VI Corps.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-064b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">"My ward men are trained well enough now so they do just as good work, generally speaking, as the nurses and the nature of G.U. service calls for the services of ward men more than that of nurses, no doubt; eventually I will have no nurses at all and all ward men to run my wards for me. The way they have taken to the care of sick is phenomenal. I would never have believed it had I not seen them work and worked with them. I have the greatest respect and admiration for them. They have done a swell job for me and I shall be eternally grateful to them."--12th General Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-074b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">"No other news particularly, flying like mad men. Navigators will fly on each and every flight, practice DR, celestial, and radio. The navigators are to be the BIG DOGS of the next campaign."--62nd Troop Carrier Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-084b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">"Boy, what a day, walked 34 miles today, and swam across a swamp with all our clothes on and a machine gun. Some fun!"--Company E, 7th Infantry. hhh 4. Equipment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-094b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">About 90% of all comments on equipment are favorable. Information is usually general as most writers comply with security regulations and don't reveal too much about their equipment. It has been noted in the past and again this week, that essential tools and supplies are lacking for necessary work. The following comment is typical:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0a4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">"Yesterday was so darn busy that I didn't have a minute. Spent all day at the Ordnance office trying to get some equipment. Even with full TBA supplies we are short tools to handle all the automotive work. However, it is trying to do the same amount of work with less than we have so I can't kick."--2012 Ordnance Company MM. hhh 5. Food.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0b4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">The supply system has improved greatly and the "C" ration in many cases has been supplemented with frequent additions of fresh meats and vegetables. Unit commanders, when they have the ingredients, contrive to supply ice cream to their unit. About 98% of all comments on food are favorable. The following were noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0c4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">"The supply situation is so much improved here that we are able to get just about everything we want; further our supply of food, especially fresh meat and vegetables is steadily increasing and such things as steaks and hamburger are now a common-place occurrence. Today for the first time in Africa we had of all things ice cream."--lst Bn. Hq. Co. 30th Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0d4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">"Chow is improving over here now with fresh meat twice and three times a week. Our cooks are learning to prepare this overseas ration better so we eat fairly well."--19th Replacement Bn., APO 700.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0e4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">"Just took a break in order to go to chow and now that I have eaten I feel great. Of course, I've reached the stage where all this G.I. good tastes alike. It seems to me that we're forever getting "C" rations and after a period of time they get somewhat boring. I'm now eating for the sake of nourishment and not the pleasure connected with it."--Company B, 8th Replacement Bn., 1st Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0f4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">"As for the food situation, we had a delicious meal of steak and potatoes, gravy and vegetables. You can see how that there is very little if any reason to worry. I dare say that the dough boys get more attention and better treatment than any other army or any civilian in the States. We are well taken care of."--21st Signal Company, Service Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-104b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">"In addition we are having ice cream with chocolate sauce for supper. It is the fourth time that I've had ice cream since leaving the States and I feel happy as a king. We have a place in town where we take the ingred­ients and they freeze it for us so we plan on having it twice each week as long as we're here."--181st Quartermaster Company (DS)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-114b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">"Over here, we really have very little to complain about. We are getting plenty to eat (I had nine large hot-cakes the other morning) and Uncle Sam is taking pretty good care to see that we get ample smokes, etc. We even are able to buy a few bars of candy a week, and two or three pack­ages of chewing gum, which is plenty for me."--286th Signal Company.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-124b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">"We had a poor supper tonight so I am lunching on fig cookies. We got some of them with our rations this week, and I have been saving them for a time like this."--21st Signal Company, Service Group. hhh 6. Entertainment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-134b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">Many comments have been noted, for and against the Red Cross organizations here. The majority complement them for setting up clubs for all around entertainment. Many units avail themselves of traveling shows and movies that are offered by the special services. Special mention is again noted for the excellence of programs offered by the American Radio Station here. The troops in this area appear to be about 95% content with the entertainment available to them. The following excerpts have been noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-144b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">"I should like to tell you that we now have a American Radio Station over here, and we get all the programs that we used to hear back home. They also attempt to have them the same time and day that they were on in the States. Of course, they are delayed broadcast (on records) but they sure do help a lot. Tonight, being Sunday, we will hear the American Tele­phone Hour, Jack Benny, and Charlie McCarthy. They also have the regular shows so we can pick just what we want for the evening's entertainment." - Det. 12th Weather &amp;renal-on.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-154b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">"Yesterday I had the most inspiring sight of my life-we played two shows. In the afternoon, the division in the mountains where we showed declared a half holiday and we had an audience of over 5000 men. They sat on a mountainside and we played in an improvised stage with two, two and a half ton trucks on either side as dressing rooms and two other trucks with their lights on for spot lights. To see these men who had had nothing in the way of entertainment for weeks enjoy our show was worth the hardships we encountered to get there. And when we finished and played the Marsielles, God Save the King and the Star Spangled Banner and see 5000 dirty tired but happy soldiers stand at salute, it gave me a thrill I'll never forget. I'M doing some actual good sweetie, I can see it and feel it. The men after the show came up to me, the officers and G.I.'s and shook hands and told me how much they appreciated me bringing the show to them. The haven't had a thing in the way of entertainment for weeks, some of them for months. We're a good trouping outfit-these French professionals I have are swell--take all kinds of hard living, traveling, bivouac tenting and kit eating with a smile and a laugh and say 'this is the least we can do'."--APO 512.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-164b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">"We had one of those Special Service travelling shows here last night. The first we have had; everyone enjoyed it very much." --D.T.C. APO 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-174b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">"We now have a motion picture nearly every night. We have our own projector now, and can get film as often as we wish. The one we had last night was 'George Washington Slept Here.' So far I have seen nearly all the pictures we have had here, but it still seems good to see them again." --Company A, 1st Bn. 301st Ordnance Regiment Base.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-184b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">"With the grand job the Red Cross is doing the boys are pretty well taken care of. Red Cross puts on free eats, movies, boxing, reading and game rooms and really the boys get plenty of enjoyment out of it all. So far they are the only ones here who are doing anything for the boys."- - 547th Army Postal Unit.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-194b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">"You remember how I felt about the Red Cross in the States, don't you? Well, I thought right, because they aren't doing much at all that the army couldn't do itself. They have books, ping-pong and that's about all. They give me a pain in the neck. I'll never give them a dime. When you do get something it's like trying to get two pair of pants in a suit from Old Abe Rubin." -.Patients Detachment, 12th General Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1a4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">"After dinner we went to the cinema and saw 'Goodbye Mr. Chips'. It is an excellent show, but not what a fellow needs over here. It is too serious. What we need is light musical comedy. We shouldn't kick though for we are very fortunate in having the entertainment we have."--Hq. &amp; Hq. Co. Fifth Army (Finance Section).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1b4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">"No movies tonight so I shall have to stay home whether I want to or not. After so many old ones, it doesn't make too much difference whether we have a show or not for I don't go to more than about a third of them and the rest Of the population here seems to be about the same. When they get a new movie here--you have to go about two hours before the show starts in order to get a place for chair--the bad movies--fifteen minutes will allow you ample time for a front row seat."--437th Bomb. Sq., 319th Bomb Gp. hhh 7. Sports.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1c4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">Information derived from this week's mail indicated continued improvement in sport activities. Warmer weather has induced many to go swimming and long for a golf club. All comments have been favorable. The following were noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1d4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">"Tonight we had a ball game and we lost. The temp we lost to invited us after the game to have some wine."--Company; 343rd Engineers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1e4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">"Lately we've been having a baseball game almost every night and that plus the good food and the good books makes it not unpleasant."--Hq.Co., 9th Bn., let Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1f4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">"Some of the fellows and I went to town on pass, today being Sunday, and there was a sports meet at the stadium here and we really had a swell afternoon there."--Company D, 2624 Sug Serv Regt.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-204b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">"It would like very much to have a golf course over here. The outlay of the land would be ideal. There are miles of flat plains and interrupted with rolling hills, etc. I will be glad when this thing is over. I hope I get a chance to play golf again."--52nd Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-214b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">"Had a very nice day today. First time I've had a few minutes to myself for a month or two. Went swimming on the beach. Nice, except water was pretty cold."--Hq. let Bn., 15th Infantry. hhh 8. Leave. Officers of some organizations have been granted leaves to attend rest camps which seems to be deeply appreciated. While on the other band no mention has been noted of enlisted personnel having the same opportunity. Some unit are being restricted on daily leaves or passes for various reasons. About 60% of all comments noted have been favorable. The following general comments were noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-224b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">"The big news is that I'm leaving in the morning for a rest camp for 5 days in French Morocco. It is awarded men and officers who have performed meritorious duty."--Hqs., 1st Tank Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-234b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">"Surprise-I'm at a rest camp. Isn't that something the headquarters organized a camp on the lowliest beach you ever saw, right on the Mediterranean. It is being operated to provide a rest as a special reward for officers and men. Don't know what I've done to deserve a special reward but anyhow, I got in on the first camp, and felt quite complimented. It started on the 15th and ends either the 19th or 20th. We have nothing to do except swim, play tennis, hike, or just loaf. I spent all day yesterday swimming and sunning myself, and overdid it a bit. I got beautifully sunburned, from the top of my head to the tips of my toes."--Hq. Fifth Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-244b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">"We get 5 day leaves and I am next going to try &amp; trip to Cairo, Egypt. I will do it or bust. Some of the drs. have gone already for the trip. Cairo they say is the New York of Africa."--11th ADG Hq.Sq., 12th AF</note>
				<note xml:id="q-254b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">"Did hear of your furlough and do envy you in that respect. I never have had one. Been in nine months."--57th Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-264b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">"There is one good thing about this place---you can sure build up a lot of furlough time. I am not sure if they are obtainable over here or not, but even if they are, it seems to me that it is just a waste of time that could be put to better advantage later on."--Hq.Det., Fifth Army Engineer Training Center.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-274b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">"Nothing. exciting going on. We are under restriction cause the rate of veneral disease among the men is too high. Instead of punishing those guilty the entire regiment has to suffer. It's bad enough not getting a day off but now we can't even go off in the evening."--Co. A, 92 Engr. Regt. hhh 9. Quarters. Lately comments have been favorable caused by better weather and the ingenuity of personnel in adapting themselves to their conditions. Many prefer living in tents in the open rather than in barracks. The living conditions of some units are indicative of their low morale. The following have been noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-284b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">"I managed to secure enough lumber to build a bed with a piece on one end to tie my barracks bags on and to build a shelf under the bed to put my shoes and some other small articles in a convenient place. We also built some shelves and a rack to hand our clothes on which all of the men in the tent share. The tent is rather crowded but we do have enough room to stand to dress and it is nice to have the things that we need close at hand rather than having to go to another pup tent and rummage in barracks bags for thirty minutes finding everything that you possess before you find the thing that you want. Our furniture is certainly not a work of art however as long as we are comfortable I guess that is the thing of most importance." net.12th Weather Squadron.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-294b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">"Well, we moved to a different location and now it's in tents and out in an almond grove. I like it better than in barracks for its healthier out in the fresh air."--1661 Ordnance (MM) Company.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">"We are living in tents again now but not pup tents. We have six in a tent, made our own bunks, have a wooden floor so you see it's really not bad at all. However, we have no lights so that gives us very little time for writing."--1661 Ordnance Company (MM). "Imagine being at war and living like I do. With my villa at the Mediterranean and the apartment in town I have far more comforts than I ever had at an American post."--340th Fighter Squadron.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">"We have to sleep on the ground and our tents are always wet. There isn't enough water for washing and we only can take a bath once a week. There is no writing paper available and we don't have enough cigarettes. Our morale is very low."--1st Replacement Depot. hhh 10. Politics. No comments. hhh 11. News and propaganda. All comments noted on this subject continue to express appreciation for both the American and German radio programs. News has increased in circulation to the troops in this theater, of conditions in Tunisia. Enemy propaganda is still enjoyed. Apparently the newly arrived officers from the States have not been informed as to the war news in this theater. The following remarks have been noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2c4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">"Last night we had to fall out for a night formation to hear a General speak. It's rather rough to fall out day and night but this was really worthwhile. He gave us at least a glimpse of the good and bad that's happening on the front and any news here is literally eaten up."--Co. B, 8th Bn., 1st Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">"We find increasing comfort on our radio. We have a government radio and we can get anything that is sent of any kind of etheric medium. Our best most popular propaganda is one that comes on every night at 8 p.m. It is devoted to the poor lonely boys in the Dark Continent, Africa. The sponsor is A. Hitler advertising the Third Reich. They specialize in arguments 'why we are in Africa' on the 'Communist Menace!. All this is interspersed with music calculated to mike us homesick. Every night we gather around and laugh like hell, we are trying to figure out just how we can send a few requests. Too bad that we don't have an American propaganda station we certainly could give some mighty fine answers to Mr. Sehickelgruber and his Heinigang."--438th Sq., 39th Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">"Talked to some officers of the new division which just landed here. These guys certainly have a thorough knowledge of the military events of this war. Most of them believe that French North Africa was entirely occupied by Germany before we landed here in November. It is certainly a sad picture to see that officers arriving in a theater of war don't know what is going on. I suppose too many people are still reading only the funnies and comics"--209th C.A. Regt.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">"Got hold of some French newspapers. The news are without any details and everything is so vague and it is very difficult to tell what is going on. Mostly syndicated articles but nothing new and all but inspiring. Not like American papers. The censorship apparently does not allow the news to filter through the people."--143rd Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-304b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">"The news of Tunisia is cheering. Recent developments there and in the European zone of action give me much hope for the realization of even my most optimistic 'predictions'. With American production and supply nearing capacity and the American army beginning to reach a stage of experience where it compares favorably in tactics and technique with even the Russians and Germane, things should soon be reaching a climax. However as I said, I cannot voice as much optimism concerning the war in the Pacific. A negotiated peace with the Japs would not surprise me too greatly."-- 22nd Replacement Bn., APO 700.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-314b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">"I am tremendously unhappy this evening. Last night Lord Haw Haw that bastardly bad news manufacturer reported for the third time in four months that my vessel had been sunk with thousands of troops. I pray to God that this news has not reached your ears but write now especially to let you know that as usual, he lies. We are all well, our cargo has been landed and our ship floats as proudly as she did on her maiden voyage so many years ago. I am confident that she will remain afloat long enough to out­live even this war, however long it may last."--N.A. Trading Corp. (Merchant Seaman). hhh 12. Religion. Frequent mention is noted of duties performed by chaplains for religious groups other than their own faith, thereby raising the morale of observant personnel. Religious church attendance is being encouraged by unit commanders. The following are typical comments:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-324b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">"Despite all these inconveniences, I find the men most faithful to their religious duties. Most of them go frequently to the sacraments and also the attendance at weekly or rather daily mass is most encouraging. Although very little is said yet I feel as though they all realize the dangers that are theirs as soldiers, and by far the vast majority are acting accordingly."--36th Engineers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-334b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">"Last Friday night we held our Jewish services with the aid of the Chaplain attached to the ship. We weren't many but I get a kick out of it because it shows that there are thoughts that are worth while and when a Catholic Chaplain can give his time to conduct Jewish Services, then the spirit of humanity still flourishes."--Hq. Co., 649th Engineers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-344b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">"I am really getting religious. Went to Church twice Sunday. I have never been to a more impressible service than the one Sunday night when the negro chaplain presided. Had a wonderful sermon and sang spirituals."-­1st Replacement Depot. hhh 13. Home Affairs. Interest still persists in the receipt of news from home regarding rationing. Information is arriving in this theater of reported rumored deaths of individuals who are in good health, this has caused consider­able concern to relatives and friends. Dissatisfaction is still prevalent against women joining auxiliary units of our armed forces. The family relations are still strained due to non-receipt of allotments. The following were noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-354b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">"I received the two Times-Star, V -mails three or four days ago, and was interested in all the local news. Sounds like the rationing is pretty tough these days, especially on meats. I suppose you'll be getting your V garden started before long--that should help fill in some of the gaps."-- Company A, 261st Med. Amph. Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-364b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">"Doc … had a letter from… the other day. They are mourning my death. According to the persistent story I am 'missing in action'. Heard the same rumor before. The report of my passing is highly exaggerated. Mrs… can vouch for that. Anyway I saw Bob about five days ago and he will swear that I am still alive (at least he saw me move)." --Hq.lst Bn., 92nd Engineers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-374b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">"Well, anyhow war isn't fun. So why mix the women up in it. They are involved in a vital but impersonal way as it is. Can't that be enough? Just because a policeman has to abbot a criminal that doesn't mean he wants his wife standing by in a Ladies Auxiliary uniform, does it? Please don't you get any of these so called patriotic ideas. Be a patriot and stay at home." - -346th Fighter Squadron, 350th Fighter Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-384b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">"Sorry you feel the way you do toward me about the allotment. Darling, I did all I could when I signed up for you to get the allotment and the government set the time to pay off and if they didn't there aren't anything I can do or my Commanding Officer for they pointedly tell us not to ask questions concerning it. They tell soldiers now I told you what to do in two letters which I hope you have now."--Co. A, 240th QM Bn. hhh 14. Relations with local inhabitants.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-394b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">About 75% of all comments on this subject indicate a favorable attitude on the part of our troops. The attitude of the inhabitants has been appreciated in that, they are lending moral and military support to our cause. They are still strongly criticized for their attempt to over-charge our personnel. The following are excerpts from letters:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3a4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">"In most instances the natives have welcomed our arrival and have not only offered us moral support but are contributing greatly to the cause in many ways. In addition they have mustered quite an army that is daily meeting the enemy with counting effects."--Finance Section, Base Hq., APO 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3b4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">"Life in Africa is still as dull as can possibly be, we don't have much entertainment other than going to the Red Cross. Some of the boys who are fortunate enough to know how to 'Parlez vous Francais' are doing fairly well. The people are more than glad to invite you over and share what little they have but under the conditions one is rather reluctant in accepting." - -Hq.Co., 2632 QM (Dep)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3c4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">"Prices in the shops have been hoisted to exorbitant levels for the Americans. Life gets quite expensive for us and we start to be more careful with spending our money." --19th Replacement Battalion.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3d4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">"I traded some empty tin cans to the native kids for green onions and egss. The French people try to hold us up, 74 cents for a dozen eggs. I think they realize the Americans make a little more money. I also asked how much for a rooster. $4.00 for a brown leghorn rooster. I said 'Shove it up your … I guess they think we're suckers."--Co. A, 845th Engineer Avn. Bn. hhh 15. Relations with Allied Troops. All comments are favorable. Praises of esteme for our Allies have numerous mention in letters examined. French Officers attached to our forces give ample proof of our cordial relationship with them in our common cause. This respect is gained by our morale, training, and equipment. The following are a few comments noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3e4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">"Things are going swell and we couldn't be fighting alongside of a greater army and bunch of men than those that the British have put in the field. They are experts, trained and efficient soldiers, that have become masters of the art of war through months of fighting and knowledge gained through many battles. Their Air Force is really great."--346th Fighter Sq.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3f4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">"Life with the Americans is for us quite a revelation. The food is entirely different from that to which we are used to in our army life, but we are getting used to it. We are amazed to see the Colonels and Majors eating the same food as the privates do. The uniform of the officers are not different then from the enlisted men. The way the officers treat their men is a real revelation to us. What a difference from our army. Work goes on during the whole week and there is no Sunday. I am very satisfied with the instructions we are getting and I think that pretty soon we will be able to handle the American vehicles."--French Officer on DS with U.S. Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-404b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">"I am very glad to tell you that we have three meals a day and that they are gigantic meals. These gentlemen certainly have to reason to complain and I am only sorry that we don't have such a good set-up because I am sure that a lot more work could be done. They are very nice and congenial fellows and we are getting along very fine. The training schedule is very strenuous and we are very busy the whole day and even sometimes during the night. The method of instructions we are getting is very satisfactory."--French Officer attached to the 804th Anti-Tank.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-414b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">"I am in an American training camp. It is very interesting. The Americans are really outstanding with their mechanized equipment. Their anti-tank guns are extremely efficient and powerful. We are very well treated and everybody is very congenial and friendly towards us."--.8th RCA attached to the U.S. Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-424b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="108">"Met a Frenchman last night who had come to Side-Bel-Abbes to work up a broadcast on the 'Foreign Legion'. … , a classmate of mine, and I were having a drink with a sergeant of the Foreign Legion, who had brought in one of our wounded soldiers while in Tunisia. This Frenchman could not get over the delightful fact that two American Colonels were having a drink with a Sergeant and practically wept with emotion at such proof of 'Bon Comardesl."--Hq., Fifth Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-434b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="109">"French people are telling me that they have no confidence in the high ranking French Officers. They claim that their feelings are not pro-allied and that the common French soldier does not trust his leaders. The best thing to do would be to discharge all professional soldiers and replace them by men of the young generation. According to their opinion it would give the French army a new spirit which with the American equipment would be a most valuable partner for the Allies."--19th Replacement Battalion. hhh 16. Censorship.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-444b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="110">Major violations intercepted during the past week consisted of a large percentage that revealed location of units and movement of military and naval forces. A total of 31 Form 912's were sent out, 20 were to officers and 11 were to enlisted personnel. Enlisted personnel continue to post their mail illicitly. Usually they have no violations in their mail if their unit censor checks it carefully. Boat mail examined continues to tell of the convoy movements and ports of embarkation and debarkation. All boat mail is not left at the Port but saved and sent into the APO several days later.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-454b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="111">Unit V-mail censorship procedure is very lax, causing extra handling and censorship, the cause is that they usually fail to place censor stamps and sign­atures where required, apparently they do not receive the information handed down through channels or do not care to be bothered to read every circular. V-mail has increased mail handled by this office by 100%.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-464b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="112">Many in this theater are returning to the States and upon their arrival disclosing information relative to location of units over here, the excerpt noted below is the general indication that this method of indirect evasion of censor­ship is being carried out. The following excerpts were noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-474b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="113">"One of our men (officer) has returned to the States. He said that he would write to you and tell you about things that I haven't been able to-so don't be surprised to get a letter."--21st General Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-484b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="114">"… finally got some letters from… today, a bundle of them. Someone must have swept the floor at APO 512. He also got one that has been in the hands of the censor for three weeks from (Censor please take note). It is too bad the system cannot be stream-lined a little. What with mail piling up in P.O.'s and censors offices I'd think they would get so damn snowed under that no one would get any mail. If we applied the same rules to win the war, I wonder how long it would take. Luck is very hot about it. He has been having a lot of censor trouble. Two of his letters were returned because he mentioned the name of an officers friend who used to be at Riley, and on the same day the newspaper published the order of battle on the front. I'll only use one side of this sheet cause it's hard to tell if censors can take it or not."--APO 3.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-494b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="115">"Boy, dad, after the last five days....I'm unit censor now and while I was away the mail sure stacked up on me to censor and I'm bleary eyed from reading so many letters and have still lots to go."--Cannon Company, 39th Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4a4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="116">"Right now it is censorship. I suppose it always will be after all I guess that part is essential when one really gets to thinking about it."-­Signal Photo Mail Detachment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="117">"Getting along fine but censorship regulations have been tightened to a point that I'm even permitted to say less in this than in my former letter which I trust you have received."--Co.C, 8th Bn., 1st Replacement Depot. hhh 17. General complaints.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="118">There has been a sharp increase in the number of complaints and are now contained in about 15% of all letters examined. There is still the general complaint on allotments not reaching dependents. The following are some of the subjects noted and deal with: promotions, supplies, safe arrival cards not sent home, assignment to duty not qualified for, morale of the 1st Replacement Depot, and complaints about the Red Cross. The following excerpts have been noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="119">"I have been wondering why you have not received the allotment money I applied for a long time ago. You haven't mentioned it lately and I was wondering what you were doing about it. I know that you can certainly Use the money that is why I am anxious to have you get it as soon as possible. As a matter of fact you should have gotten the first installment in November and I cannot understand why, in so many months you have not heard anything. I want you to start writing letters at once to find out just why you haven't received any, explanation or notification of what's happening. All the forms that are required have been filed on this end and it's about time you get some response. I am afraid if you don't start asking question pretty soon they will forget all about the whole thing. Some information you might need is as follows: My full military name(for identification purposes). The allotment was filed last June, 1942 and was effective June 1, 1942. The first $22.00 was taken out of my June earnings. This June 1st will mark the end of one year. I will have had a total of $220.00 deducted from my pay and you haven't received a penny of it. It certainly calls for an explanation and I suggest you do some demanding about that money. Actually you are entit­led to $500.00 counting the money the Government promised to add to my allotment. What you oughter find out is where the hell is the money?" You mentioned a report I was supposed to fill out. I filled that out in December and I'm sure it has reached the War Dept. by now. Don't let this matter wait any longer. You are entitled to this money and you should get it. Raise hell until you do."--AG Section, Base Headquarters, APO 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="120">"In the Air Force, we are also faced with the problem of establishment of separate supply establishments which in many cases the duplication of the dumps established by ground forces. It seems that we are not only fighting the Germans and Italians but also our ground forces. I don't know what the trouble is but I have actually had to drive sixty miles to draw rations far my men when I could have been issued the same rations from a ground force dump only a mile or so away. With transportation very scarce, this certainly seems to be a very poor arrangement."--82nd Fighter Control Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="121">"I think the greatest trouble is that there is too much attention given to the preparation of requisitions, reports, and records and all the other red tape connected therewith and too little attention given to the actual care and protection of the supplies received. The waste at the ports and in the zone of the interior is far too great."--82nd Ftr. Control 8q.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-504b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="122">"I caught a soldier drunk in our chow line a day or so ago and ordered his company commander to court martial him. A recruit in the States might react well to soft treatment. If you think you make any impression on a man who is over here, by talking to him-your nuts. I've been too easy on the assorted lieutenants and captains who as replacements are under my jurisdiction. I frequently get that stuff- 'Your' a swell Captain,'-but when the Major hollers, they step faster than they do for any of my milder toned orders. I'm about to conclude that officers enmass have got to be treated like enlisted men."--09th Bn., 1st Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-514b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="123">"Been listening to the boys gripe about promotion. There is none I guess-I have no gripe. I do feel sorry for some of these guys wounded and all fighting like hell and getting no promotions. They ship senior officers from the States-captains, majors and higher but I have made up my mind that I won't be in the army when it's over so it does not bother me."--9th Bn., 1st Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-524b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="124">"Still a corporal and holding down a sergeant's job. Sort of gets me mad at times but that's the army."--Company D, 301st Ordnance Regiment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-534b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="125">"I can't imagine why you didn't get a safe arrival card as it was made out back in December, unless they lost it."--111th Observation Squadron.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-544b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="126">"I've been aver here several months now and according to letters from home and Florence, the safe arrival card that is supposed to be sent by the War Dept. has not reached home yet (as of March 30th)....and mail normally takes about 18 days from here."--Hq. VI Corps.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-554b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="127">"At present we are detached to another outfit(not medics) doing every­thing a outfit like one isn't supposed to do. However, I've found since my induction, even a person trained in some specific capacity is very likely to be doing something entirely different. This may not last long (I hope) and eventually we may be doing what we were intended to do. Someone, some­where got off the proverbill ball and isn't quite certain how to resume."-­57th Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-564b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="128">"There are a lot of latrine grams here but practically all the officers mail is censored. The morale of the officers is very low. They just pray to get out of here. There is a very lost feeling being a casual."--Hq.Det., 9th Bn., 1st Replacement Depot. "Wish I could tell you some of the things that are going on around in these parts but will suffice it to say some of the most jealous throat-cutting among officers I ever heard of is being done and should not exist in times like this. I am out here where the Reclassification Board is so I see and hear many things."--.1st Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-574b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="129">"I see some funny things going on. Lots of high-ranking officers are up for re-classification. Of course you know where they come from, Res. and N.G. Too much politics and not enough Company opposition."--lst Repl. Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-584b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="130">"We are now on our fourth week here in North Africa and I am still in the same situation as I was when I left the States. And from the looks of things I will remain the same for quite some time. I know I shouldn't say it but this remaining here and not being assigned to anything is be­coming quite monotonous and I am growing quite stale on the things that I should be up on in order to perform the work that is expected of me. And to top everything off practically every other thing that they do around here is contrary to the things that we were taught and also the rules and regulations of the books. And I am not at all ashamed to say that I am quite fed up on everything. About the only thing that I think we are getting that I like is a lot of physical training and a lot of road marching. In fact we do 4 miles in 42 minutes. We double time for a half mile and quick time for a mile and so forth until we have completed 4 miles." -.Hq.Co., 6th Bn., 1st Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-594b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="131">"None of us can complain about the treatment we get as they do all they can to make it agreeable for us and all of the boys appreciate it. It is pretty hard for them to do anymore."--Company A, 2nd Conv. Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="132">"I don't know why they keep putting all of that stuff in the papers about the picnic the Red Cross is giving us all of the time over here. Personally. I think it is a lot of bull. We haven't done any more than see a Red Cross representative since getting over here. They sure have the newspapers shown up at home though. The closest I have gotten to the Red Cross is to donate two dollars to them a couple of days ago. Maybe the outfits who are stationed in the towns and cities are able to get the entertainment etc that the Red Cross puts out but not us."--8th Troop Carrier Sq., 62nd Troop Carrier Gp.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="133">18. General. About 98% of all mail examined indicates the continuation of high troop morale. Comments noted have been on subjects relating to: nationalism, the fighting quality of troops, complements for chaplains and the Red Cross as boosters of moral, military theory versus actuality, and 'black market' prices. The following excerpts were noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="134">"I can't shape the destines of the world, but I hope that when this mess is over there will be no Germany or no Japan. I only hope that coming gener­ations won't have to send their sons through the hell our boys are going through now. I'm with them and suffer with them, swear and curse with them and will go through hell with them, but it will all be worth it if those who follow us will be able to enjoy peace. I also hope our country will always be armed to the teeth so that we will not fail like France did."--183rd Inf., 36th Divison.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5d4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="135">"Greetings, bud. In the army a month now and still a private, eh? You're slipping, brother mine. All kidding aside, glad to have you with me. Glad to welcome you into the American Army-as a fellow soldier in the fight against the forces of Nazism, Fascism, tyranny, and darkness. And I'm sure that wherever you'll be, whatever you'll do, you'll give your best to the army, the government and to the people of the United States."--Company B, 6th Bn., 1st Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5e4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="136">"Although this type of living, eating, sleeping is extremely primitive, most of us are feeling fine. To be utterly truthful we can't say that we're actually enjoying it-but we'll get along. Everyone in the States should be required to live the way we're living low for about a week; ther'd be much less complaining about not having enough gas for pleasure driving, about sugar and meat rationing, and all the other details that seem to worry most Americans."--Company B, 111th Medical Battalion</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5f4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="137">"As for us here, everything we really need is procurable in some way or another. We have good food, have a bed to sleep in, a pup tent over us which is enough and naturally feel as though we are better off than most people back home. We have enough clothes to last us for a good while, our shoes to last a long time and underclothes may be procured without any rationing on our score."--36th Engineers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-604b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="138">"I was over to the hospital today to see one of the boys. His bed is next to a fellow that just got back from the front. It seems incredible, but I believe he is disappointed because he is not up there with his outfit giving the Jerries h... I was almost wishing I was up there when I got through talking to him."--2lst Signal Company Service Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-614b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="139">"Of one thing I feel certain--these happy-go-lucky cowboys are going to give a damn good account of themselves. They have the best morale that I have ever seen for the closer to the bullets we get the higher their spirits go."--36th Cavalry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-624b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="140">"The Chaplain of one regiment is, as the boys describe him, 'the tops'. Before and since we landed, he has been an inspiration to the regiment. Among the first to leave the ship, his first thoughts were for the welfare of the soldiers, both spiritually and physically. In my estimation the Chaplains go down as the unsung heroes of the war."--H &amp; S Co., 36th Engr.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-634b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="141">"I love it here. We work with American soldiers and I can say this.. Our army is grand. They can't be nicer to all of us than they are. The army men say 'Nothing too good for the Red Cross'. The boys like our snack bar very much but I think the most important thing is that they can talk to us. They usually say when they see us 'She looks American, she talks American, she is American". --American Red Cross.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-644b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="142">"And the girl in the Red Cross will shock you worse than a German 88 shell with their audocity in running coffee and donuts and good cheer right under the Jerry noses to some outpost where some of the boys get to losing hopes of ever seeing a woman's smile or hearing one laugh again as pure wishful thinking. Never will you hear any stories of their efforts and those of the 'Y' and other organizations, like came out of the last war. This is really 100% all-American."--Company I1, 47th Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-654b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="143">"Father you would be proud of the gifts the Red Cross gave us yesterday a cloth bag with cigs, soap, writing paper, a pocket edition book, sewing kit, pencil, chewing gum, shoe polishing cloth, etc-one to every man and would have done your heart good to have seen the expression on the men's faces reminded one of passing out Xmas gifts to the kiddies did our hearts and souls so much good."--143rd Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-664b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="144">"The Red Cross has been very good to us. They give cigarettes, candy which I cannot eat. They also give us stationary. I would like to have you draw about five dollars from the bank and give it to the Red Cross."-­Company C, 343rd Engineers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-674b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="145">"We have quite a few from Tank Destroyer outfits, but cannot write you any details about how things are. You know, seeing some of my students from Denver and their work away from school, one gets a little discouraged at what you thought were wonderful students. Of course, they do not always have the same equipment, and often times are aggressive enough. I have come to the conclusion that we are not a militaristic nation, and that England is. Those soldiers are plenty mean, with a high fighting morale, and a will to go right back and give them hell. I think with a few months of seasoning our men will develop too. The German soldier is aces, so all say, everyone has healthy respect for them. We get lots of stories here, direct from the front which probably would be beat to keep to yourself. War is an interesting thin, though tragic too--certainly brings out the best or the worst--there are no half way measures."--21st General Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-684b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="146">"Guess Morris got his discharge because he was or is over 38-from what I have seen of the older men in the army, I really think that, unless they are useful technicians, men of that age are of far more value in defense plants. I know that I'm still pretty far away from it, and I find many of the things we have to do pretty tough, physically until the army can devise some system where the older men don't have to take part in the strenuous action. I feel that they are serving a better purpose at home. Keeps more beds in the hospitals empty for those that really need care."--286th Signal Company.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-694b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="147">"One tip I can pass on is when in the open don't open your C ration when the sun shines. We found out the hard way. We would start to eat in the field and first thing over came the Messerschmitt's and raked us with MG fire. Next day we changed location and the time for chow but same thing we got it again. Finally after a few days I happened to talk with an Air Corps man and he said the lids and cans reflected the rays of the sun and sent up heliograph signals which Jerry waited for--and we got it. Needless to say we now open cans up in tents or bend over them and we live that much longer."--QM Section, Base Headquarters, APO 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6a4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="148">"Prices are extremely higher here than in the States. Everything is rationed here. The 'black market' is well known and doing a nice business. Since the influx of the American soldier, wine parlors have grown in numbers and doing the best business of any establishment in the towns. And some of the prices charged for the stuff is outrageous."--QM Section, Base Headquarters, APO 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6b4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="149">ERNST L. PELCHEN, Jr.,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6c4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="150">Captain, Infantry,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6d4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="151">Chief Base Censor.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6e4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="152">63 Inclosures:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6f4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="153">62 Form 912, Serial Nos.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-704b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="154">BCD 1-90 to BCD 1-20 incl, 2 copies each</note>
				<note xml:id="q-714b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="155">Statistical Report in Duplicate</note>
				<note xml:id="q-724b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="156">DISTRIBUTION:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-734b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="157">2 Commanding General, NATOUSA.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-744b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="158">1 Commanding Officer, MBS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-754b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="159">File</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>