<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Home Intelligence Weekly Report - No. 116 - 24 December 1942</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-936b4ba2-e474-4b1e-a4cb-0d570626869e</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-1e4b403b-c4b5-4e11-940e-c099ca0056fe</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-fe5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ff5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-005e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="3">HOME INTELLIGENCE WEEKLY REPORT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-015e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="4">No. 116. 24th</note>
				<note xml:id="q-025e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="5">December 1942</note>
				<note xml:id="q-035e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">(Covering the period 15th to 22nd December 1942)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-045e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="7">I. GENERAL COMMENTS hhh 1. General state of confidence and reaction to news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-055e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">Although the Russian offensive and the advance of the Eighth Army are said "to have given general satisfaction", spirits appear to remain everywhere much the same as last week. Confidence is on a high level, with the public convinced that "we are heading for victory", but without the elation which followed on Rommel's defeat at El Alamein and the Allied landings in French North Africa.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-065e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">Uneasiness about Darlan's position, though less than last week, is still considerable. Christmas is arousing a great deal of interest and discussion, and many people are said to be doing their best to make "this austerity Christmas as bright and cheerful as possible". hhh 2. North Africa.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-075e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">Confidence that the Axis forces will be driven out of North Africa is again widely reported this week.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-085e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">The Eighth Army: The progress of the Eighth Army has caused general pleasure, and confidence in our army and generals is high. Reports from two Regions, however, refer to "some uneasy talk about the lengthening of our supply lines".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-095e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">The encircling movement "which was stated to have cut Rommel's forces in two" was hailed as a victory by some people, who were therefore disappointed at "the get-away". According to reports from four Regions, there was some criticism of "the build-up" given to this news: it was regarded as "a return to the bad old days of the Cairo spokesman".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0a5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">The First army: Concern is expressed about</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0b5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">(a) 'The lack of news from Tunisia; people are said to be wondering what has happened: "Have we suffered some reverse?" (Six Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0c5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">(b) Events not having moved "as -quickly as was anticipated" (Three Regions): "Did we, as usual, underestimate the enemy?"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0d5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">(c) The initial shortage of air support: "Have we an adequate force at our disposal now?" (Two Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0e5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12) hhh 3. Admiral Darlan</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0f5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">Feeling is similar to that reported during the last four weeks, but there is a decrease in comment and criticism, and an increase in the number of people "inclined to accept the position".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-105e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">Darlan continues to be regarded with "the greatest suspicion which "his latest declarations (16th December) have done nothing to allay".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-115e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13. 16. 21 Aberdeen, Birmingham, Bristol, Cardiff, Carlisle, Edinburgh, Glasgow, Inverness, Manchester, Reading P.Cs.) hhh 4. Russia</note>
				<note xml:id="q-125e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">The Red Army's recent "amazing" successes are reported to have made "a great impression on the public", and the "possibility of a major Russian strategic victory is boding discussed".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-135e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">There appears, however, to be growing scepticism about the figures quoted by the Russians: (Six Regions as against four last week), and it is asked "How could the German Army continue as the tremendous force it is, if the Russian figures were true?"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-145e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">"Enthusiasm" for Russia continues to be reported, and she is said "to come very close to the feelings of the people". The organisers of an Aid to Russia week in Cheltenham are said to have been "staggered" at the generous response, "people of gill classes contributed; oven new coats and fur coats were given".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-155e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13. 21 Aberdeen, Birmingham, Bristol, Cambridge, Edinburgh, Glasgow, Inverness, Leeds, Manchester P.Cs.) hhh 5. The Beveridge Report</note>
				<note xml:id="q-165e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">Although again this week there is reported to be a slight decline in discussion, interest in the Report still appears to be considerable, but Christmas has evidently taken its place as the most talked of subject on the home front</note>
				<note xml:id="q-175e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">It is suggested that discussion May have decreased because:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-185e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">(i) "people are waiting to know what the Government is going about it", (Four Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-195e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">(ii) "People are waiting for further supplies of the abridged edition" (Three Regions). Approval for this edition is reported, "even though it is not very abridged." "Further elucidations of the scheme by radio and press" are asked for.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1a5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">Opinion seems to be equally divided as to whether the Report is "liable to divert attention from winning the war", or is "designed to raise the nation's hopes and keep it going."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1b5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">Opinions expressed, many of which are confirmed by Postal Censorship, differ little from those retorted last- week, and may be summarised thus:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1c5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">(a) General approval of the scheme. The belief that it is "all too good -;o be true", is again reported, particularly from "the power sections of the community," Two reports indicate that "earlier enthusiasm has to some extent-abated" and that "criticism seems to have become more vocal".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1d5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">(b) Skepticism or cynicism as to the likelihood of the plan being accepted. "So many amendments will be made, that the plan will be a wash out". Many people fear that it will be "delayed or even wrecked" by the Insurance Companies (Seven Regions) and/or "big business" (Five Regions). Reference is again made to the feeling that "if the Report is not adopted, there will be serious trouble in this country after the war".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1e5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">(c) Although approval is by far the most general reaction, the following objections appear to be fairly widespread:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1f5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">(i) "It is merely subsidizing laziness." (Six Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-205e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">(ii) "The question of unemployment must be settled first." (Five Regions) We ought to "abolish want, not poultice it".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-215e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">(iii) "Can we afford it?"- "Where is the money coming from?" (Five Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-225e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">(iv) "How will the scheme affect our export trade?" "How will the country be able to compete with other nations" - especially those "not having the same costly social services as this one?" (Five Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-235e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">(v) "It will discourage thrift." (Three Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-245e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">(vi) "The 4/3d, weekly contribution is too high" for workers (Three Regions) , particularly "when wages return to normal".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-255e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">(vii) "Twenty years is too long to wait" for the full retirement pensions. (Three Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-265e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.12. 21 Aberdeen, Birmingham, Cambridge, Glasgow, Inverness, Reading P.Cs.) hhh 6. Far East</note>
				<note xml:id="q-275e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">There is still little reported comment on the fighting in New Guinea and the Solomon Islands. Satisfaction is reported (Three Regions) at the recapture of Buna and Gona, and appreciation expressed for "the fighting qualities of the American and Australian troops in Now Guinea". People are said "to realize that the defeat of Japan will be a long business", but to be "confident of the result".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-285e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">Burma: The British advance into Burma seems to have aroused greater interest than events in the Pacific, - the public's interest in General Wavell is considered partly responsible for this. The move in Burma has produced "a favourable reaction" and "a general air of expectancy", and is welcomed both' for "lifting the Japanese threat to India" and as "an essential preliminary to re-opening the main supply route to China".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-295e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.12.13) hhh 7. R.A.F. offensive</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">The bombing of Germany: Raids on Germany, though giving satisfaction appear to be taken for granted, in spite of the fact that there had been some disappointment that "the recent bombing of Italy meant the complete cessation of night bombing of Germany".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">Concern is reported from three Regions at the number of bombers lost in these raids. The bombing of Italy is said to cause greater satisfaction than that of Germany. Press references to the possibility of Rome being declared an open town have aroused considerable feeling. Workers are said to be particularly indignant: "London, Malta and Canterbury have been bombed; why not Rome?"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2c5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">(1.2.3.4.5.6.8.9.10.11. 21 Bristol P.C. :52) hhh 8. German anti-Jewish atrocities in Poland</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">Widespread indignation, anger and disgust are reported as result of "the recent revelations of Nazi atrocities, particularly the disclosure of the policy for exterminating the Jews in Poland". They are said to have led to intensified hatred of the Germans - and also of Laval, for his anti-Jewish measures. The joint declaration of the nations that the perpetrators will be punished has "caused great satisfaction". It is hoped that no mercy will be shown when the time comes, and some believe that "retribution should be in the hands of the relatives of those who suffered". A minority think that the disclosures are exaggerated, or regard them as "hate propaganda", and as "seeming too horrible even for the Nazis".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">Anti-Semitism: Much of the feeling about the atrocities is, however, on the lines of: "I don't care for the Jews, but this is terrible", and no report specks of any increase of sympathy for Jewish people in this country. Anti-Jewish feeling is referred to in five reports, one of which suggests that this may be on the increase and that the atrocity propaganda has given rise to talk of Jews and black-markets after a period when it seemed to have decreased.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">(2.3.4.5.6.7.8.10.11.13). hhh 9. The unchaining of German prisoners</note>
				<note xml:id="q-305e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">"General relief and satisfaction" at our decision to unchain German prisoners are reported again this week. It is felt that "we have done the decent thing, and given the Germans the lead". Amongst relatives of prisoners there is some speculation and anxiety as to "the speed and nature of Germany's response".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-315e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">(2.4.5.6.7.8.12) hhh 10. The Prime Minister's statement on the Churchill tank.(15th December)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-325e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">There appears to have been little public interest in "the Parliamentary breeze" over tanks. The Prime Minister's popularity is high, and there is some disgust "among fair--minded and patriotic people at the carping criticism of lesser men". Opinion seems to be divided about "his comments to his critics"; some people welcomed them, others, it is suggested, thought them "unworthy of the Premier",</note>
				<note xml:id="q-335e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">There is some thankfulness that "Hitler did not come this way" when our troops had less than a hundred tanks.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-345e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">(2.4.7.8.10.11) hhh 11. Sir Stafford Cripps' postscript (20th December)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-355e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">Preliminary reports indicate that Sir Stafford Cripps' broad­cast was received with approval rather than enthusiasm. Some praised it highly as "the real Cripps speaking" and as having "put him back on the map": others thought it dull, or felt it could have been shorter.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-365e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">The majority, however, and workers especially, welcomed it as "a plain, straightforward talk", particular notice being taken to his reference to:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-375e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">(a) The managements: Sir Stafford's "dig at the bosses" is said to have gone down, particularly with workers, some of whom believed that the speech was "directed chiefly at the administration".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-385e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">(b) Absenteeism: Some people considered the postscript was "designed to stop absenteeism at Christmas".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-395e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">(c) The importance of post-war planning: This is said to have caused some people particular satisfaction, and Sir Stafford is thought to have "perked up considerably" when he came to this.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3a5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">(d) Joint Production Committees.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3b5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">(1.3.4.6.7.9.12) hhh 12. Broadcasting and Presentation of news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3c5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">Enthusiasm for listening to the news seem to have lessened somewhat, end criticism on familiar lines is reported. References to people switching off after the headlines have re-appeared and the suggestion is again made that the bulletin should begin with a brief note as to whether it contains any fresh news. There is further appreciation of the summary at the end of the news bulletin.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3d5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">Delay in the release of news is complained of in reports from five Re ions. "We are always behind the German bulletin", In spite of criticism, it is stated that the B.B.C. news is generally preferred to that riven in the Press. Complaint is made of sensational press headlines and of the same news being made to look so different in the various newspapers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3e5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">European News Service: Preference for the European news service is again mentioned in reports from two Regions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3f5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">Variety programmes: The poor quality of "home-produced" variety is commented on in reports from two Regions, but Tommy Handley's popularity is again referred top especially among children. (Three Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-405e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-415e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="68">II. SPECIAL COMMENTS hhh 13. Christmas</note>
				<note xml:id="q-425e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">Christmas is said to have become "the most frequently recurring item of talk", and considerable discussion is reported from most Regions. For many people this is thought to be "the happiest Christmas since war began, because of the Allied successes already achieved and the certainty of further victories to come". Apart from those who "welcome the holiday as a rest", and those "whose home life is broken and who are anxious over relations in .the services", most people appear to be trying to make it as much like a normal Christmas as conditions and shortages will allow. "In spite of the difficulties of shopping there is a certain amount of festivity in the air, especially where there are children", and a belief that "we'll all be together next Christmas" is said to make "the hardships of this austerity Christmas" easier to endure.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-435e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">Toys: From eleven Regions comp complaints of the "extortionate prices" charged for toys, disgust and anger being reported at "the excessive cost of poor quality toys, and the extreme pro- filtering which is going on in the trade". The Government is "frequently blamed for not coping with the whole matter reasonably, fairly and in plenty of time", and for having "made so little effort to make Christmas a happy season for children". According to one report "the release of further supplies of toys has caused some satisfaction", and is quoted as evidence that "public opinion is still listened to, by the Government", but some people consider it "farcical", and are said to be oven angrier because "not one extra toy has been seen".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-445e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">The position of Servicemen's families is mentioned in three reports. "What can our soldiers think when they come home and want to buy something for their children and then find that 6d. toys are being offered to them at 5/6d. or more?"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-455e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">Christmas presents: The "rubbishy quality of goods in shops" and the absence of anything "Worth buying, even useful things", are mentioned in two reports. Surprise has also been expressed at "the abundance of cards and calendars", which is described as "extraordinary if there really is a shortage of paper".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-465e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8 9.10.11.12. 21 Aberdeen P.C. 32.) hhh 14. Manpower</note>
				<note xml:id="q-475e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">Reports from eight Regions this week refer to the alleged waste of manpower. Criticism -follows familiar lines:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-485e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">(a) "Too many young men in civilian jobs," (Four Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-495e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">(b) Evasion of work by "wealthier women who are not being compelled to work in the same way as the less wealthy" (Four Regions): Officers' wives, childless married women, and women whose children under fourteen-do not live at home are specified.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4a5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">(c) "Lack of co-ordination in the transferring of workers: men taken off skilled work, and pub on to unskilled and less useful work". (One Region)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">(d) "Overlapping and duplicating of distribution services such as those of coal and milk". (One Region)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">(e) Factors which deter women from volunteering: - fear of six months' income tax still to pay when employment ceases, discouragement by husbands, and "the handling of women at labour exchanges". (One Region each)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">At the same time, some firms are said to be "anxious about the possibility of further demands on their already depleted staffs". The call-up of doctors is also said to be causing, some concern in the South Eastern Region, "especially Medical Officers of Health"; it is hoped "that not too many will be drawn from civilian life".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">(1.2.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12. 21 Glasgow, Manchester. P.Cs.) hhh 15. Production</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">Again little comment on this subject is reported this week, but it is suggested that production continues to be adversely affected by the following:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-505e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">(a) Women war workers' shopping difficulties and long hours of work "combined with domestic responsibilities". (Four Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-515e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">(b) The "uncooperative attitude of managements, and idle time, (Two Regions) In Wales, however, "a joint meeting' of management and workers at one factory is said to have speeded up production and to have encouraged similar activities in surrounding works and factories". hhh 16. Transport difficulties</note>
				<note xml:id="q-525e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">There are references from twelve Regions this week to transport difficulties which are said to continue to be "a burning question" and the subject of critical discussion.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-535e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">In the North Western Region some discussion is reported as to "what is a worker" and "who should have priority".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-545e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">There are again complaints on familiar lines of (a) Overcrowd­ing of buses by shoppers and by train travelers because of the abolition of cheap train fares; (b) Inadequacy of rural bus services; (c) Curtailment of evening and Sunday morning transport; (d) Buses running empty in mid-mornings and mid-afternoons; e) Special buses for workers, running, half empty.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-555e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">Christmas travel: People in the South Western Region "seem to be intending to stay quietly at home" for Christmas. In Scotland bitterness is reported towards those who have booked hotel accommodation and are travelling.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-565e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12. 21 Manchester P.C.) hhh 17. Venereal disease and Regulation 33B</note>
				<note xml:id="q-575e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">This week, reports from ten Regions (as against four last week) refer to public comment on this subject. The following points of view are expressed:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-585e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">(a) "More .far-reaching and stringent provisions than those laid down by the Government will have to be employed",. The public are said to be ahead of the Government and to feel that "the disease should be compulsorily notifiable". (Four Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-595e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">(b) Regulation 33B is "a definite first step towards dealing with the problem of venereal disease" (Three Regions). The public "do not understand the reason for the attack on it in Parliament".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">(c) There should be a vigorous publicity campaign, including the showing of films, to give the public full information about infection, symptoms, consequences - including "the dire effect on the next generation" - and treatment. (Three Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">(d) The disease "is a just punishment on those who contract it", (A minority in Scotland)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">(1.2.3.4.5.7.9.10.11.12) hhh 18. Batteries</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5d5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">Complaints about the shortage of batteries continue to be reported (Eight Regions). The Government is blamed for "failing to foresee and plan for this need": it is said that' "a. little concession would strengthen people's morale under the strain of winter and black-out".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5e5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">Cycle lamp batteries: The shortage of these, described as acute in some places is said to be causing "great hardship and incon­venience" and to be responsible for a great increase in riding without lights. It is considered to be "particularly unfortunate at a time when buses are overcrowded" and there is comment on the danger to life. Workers are said to find it very difficult, getting to work, and to be uncertain whether to "break the law by cycling without lights, or to stay away". Resentment is reported in "places where police action, with threats from some magistrates of heavier penalties, has followed the use of bicycles perforce unlighted".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5f5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">Torch batteries: The shortage of these is reported from five Regions, in three of which No. 8s are particularly mentioned,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-605e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">(3.4.5.6.7.8.9.12) hhh 19. Petrol</note>
				<note xml:id="q-615e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">From seven Regions this week come references to the waste and misuse of petrol. The distribution of petrol is thought to be unfair in two Regions, end some country people feel they should get a bigger allowance than townsfolk.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-625e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">There are again complaints of the misuse of petrol allowances, and of the waste of petrol by the army, U.S. troops, and farmers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-635e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">(1.3.4.7.8.10.11. 21 Carlisle, Glasgow P.Cs.) hhh 20. Food</note>
				<note xml:id="q-645e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">Satisfaction with the general food situation and praise for Lord Woolton are again reported, The announcement that there would be no increase in food supplies is said to have been received philosophically and people are reported to be reconciled to an "austerity Christmas". The following complaints are however reported:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-655e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">Fish: The zoning scheme is said not to have found favour yet, Complaints of the shortage of</note>
				<note xml:id="q-665e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">fish continue (Eleven Regions), though the feeling is reported to be increasing that the fish trade should be blamed for this rather than the Ministry of Food. Preferential treatment of customers by fishmongers is still alleged.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-675e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">Christmas fare: The shortage and unequal supply of the traditional Christmas fare is commented on in nine reports. Housewives who have been able to obtain these are said to be delighted, and talk of nothing else.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-685e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">Poultry: Dissatisfaction at the unequal distribution of poultry, and strong suspicions that there is black-marketing going on are reported. (Five Regions) Considerable feeling is said to have been aroused in one Region where American officers have been "touring the countryside buying up turkeys and poultry at fantastic prices".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-695e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="108">Porridge oats: The inclusion of rolled oats 'on the points ration is said to be viewed with concern by housewives. (Four Regions) It is pointed out that rolled oats use less fuel than oatmeal.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6a5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="109">Milk: The rationalisation of silk deliveries is alleged to be cousin,- much discontent in two Regions. The cut in the milk is reported to have aroused a good deal of comment and is thought to have been unnecessary (Three Regions) The hardship to old people end semi-invalids is mentioned, as for many of these milk was the staple diet. (Two Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6b5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="110">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13. 21 Aberdeen, Birmingham, Cambridge, Cardiff, Carlisle, Edinburgh, Glasgow, Inverness, Reading, York P.Cs.). hhh 21. Clothing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6c5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="111">Coupons: The demand for an issue of coupons for household linen continues. (Six Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6d5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="112">Children's Clothing: The shortage of children's clothing, especially footwear, is reported from five Regions. In the North Western Region it is alleged that in one area absence from school is due to shortage of shoes.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6e5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="113">Utility clothing: Criticism of the poor quality of utility stockings is again reported, and also of utility boots and shoes.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6f5e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="114">Sheets and towels: The high price and shortage of sheets and towels is complained of (Three Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-705e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="115">Rubber boots: Landworkers in the Eastern Region are said to be handicapped by the shortage of rubber boots and children in country districts are thought to be prevented from attending school in bad weather owing; to the shortage of Wellingtons.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-715e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="116">(2.3.4.5.6.7.8.10.12) hhh 22 Fuel Economy</note>
				<note xml:id="q-725e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="117">Although the Economy Campaign is said to be attracting less attention then formerly, people are thought to be exercising great economy. Some people, however, are reported to regard the Fuel Target as a purely voluntary matter and fuel economy as en idle phrase. In Wales it is said to be felt that if we manage to avoid coal rationing it will be due to economy by consumers and not to the coal industry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-735e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="118">The bed quality and shortage of coal is reported from five Regions. It is thought that those who could not afford to buy coal in bulk, or had no storage space, or neglected their opportunities in the summer are "in a bad way now" because of irregular deliveries.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-745e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="119">Difficulties due to shortage of paraffin are reported from the South Western Region.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-755e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="120">From the Northern Region it is reported that several complaints have been received from Batley where the local gas company are said to have removed meters from houses of customers who have not burned enough gas to incur a charge sufficient to cover the meter rent.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-765e88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="121">(2.3.4.7.8.10.11.13. 21 Inverness P.C.)</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>