<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Home Intelligence Weekly Report - No. 57 - 5 November 1941</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-25cfd217-e249-4407-8ba9-7c341e96e3f1</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-2501d3d1-6234-4279-bea8-05dfd10a934c</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-fc5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fd5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fe5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="3">HOME INTELLIGENCE WEEKLY REPORT NO. 57</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ff5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="4">NOVEMBER, 1941</note>
				<note xml:id="q-005b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">(Covering the period from 27th October to 3rd November, 1941) Note: - The figures in brackets refer to sources of information, a list of which is given at the end of this report.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-015b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="6">I. GENERAL COMMENTS 1. hhh 1. General state of confidence and reaction to news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-025b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">Though there appears to be no marked change in public feeling this week, there are signs that anxiety about Russia, particularly over the situation in the south has slightly increase. Bewilderment, frustration, depression and indifference are mentioned in various reports, but do not suggest any significant alteration in. the public's mood. Interest is still concerned mainly with the campaign in Russia, and with tie question: "Will Russia be able to hold out?" Increased confidence in Moscow's chances of successful resistance are somewhat outweighed by a deepening anxiety about the Crimean position and the threat to the Caucasus. Public apprehension is expressed on the following points:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-035b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">a) Russia's already immense industrial losses.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-045b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">b) The threat to the Rostov pipe-line</note>
				<note xml:id="q-055b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">c) The threat (at present anticipated only by a minority) to 'our' means of communication for the transport of war materials to Russia.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-065b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">But in spite of a growing realisation of the increased seriousness of the situation, confidence in Russia's continued resistance, is, on the whole, maintained, and there seems to be no fear of her suffering a sudden collapse.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-075b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">Factors which are regarded as comparatively cheering are:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-085b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">a) The continued defence of Moscow.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-095b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">b) The reported deterioration in the weather.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0a5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">c) Stalin's statement, quoted by Mr. Harry Hopkins, that "the battle line will remain west of Moscow."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0b5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">d) A belief in the, uselessness of the Nazi's gains, and that even if they over-run the whole of Russia, "their army will be reduced by a third, and their gains will be nothing but ruins."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0c5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">In Spite of the anxiety reflected in most reports, there are indication that "this country is still not sufficiently alive to the dangers of the present German drive", nor to the possibility that "nearer to Moscow means nearer to London." The past month is spoken of as a period of almost complete bewilderment, accompanied by a feeling of indifference. Complacency and-war weariness are again mentioned; those are partly due, it is suggested, "to the strain-of waiting, and of watching a struggle in which people feel they have no active part". This feeling is summed up by a writer in Postal Censorship who says: "It's time we were getting the war over, but we are not trying to get it finished - the public want to be getting at it, but the people in authority don't seem to be in a hurry".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0d5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">(Though confidence in the, Prime Minister is "as sturdy as ever", the usual criticisms are reported of Lord Halifax and Colonel Moore-Brabazon.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0e5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">Several reports speak of "apathy and lack of public interest" from parts of the country as widely separated as London, Bristol and Aberdeen. "So many people just don't seem to know the position of the war, at all they live from day to day with apparent unconcern. It is suggested that the recent agitation for a Western offensive arose as much from a desire to "give vent to their own restlessness and sense of frustration" as from the public's desire to help the Russians.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0f5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">Last week there were signs that the public were beginning to realise that an offensive in the West is not yet practicable. This tendency is now more 'generally reported, and appears to be considerably strengthened. The majority are said to be satisfied to leave the decision to "those in whom our war policy is vested", (There is, in some quarters, a persistent feeling that Government statements on the impracticability of Western land offensive are all bluff, and are intended to conceal that "more is going on than we are told about".) Several reports agree in placing the chief responsibility for this agitation on the press, and there is adverse criticism of some of the London newspapers on this account. There is also a feeling that the campaign was being "sponsored by certain political groups"; and the public are beginning to "suspect that their feelings are being worked upon for political ends". While it is generally admitted that the demand for an immediate invasion of the Continent has collapsed, "discontent with our apparent inactivity, finding no outlet", is said to be producing "a sullen resentment". The "role of arsenal does not appeal to the imagination".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-105b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">(1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12,13,20 Bristol, Manchester P.C. s, 29,32) hhh 2. The R.A.F. Offensive</note>
				<note xml:id="q-115b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">The systematic bombing of Naples and the successful raids on enemy shipping have caused very considerable satisfaction. There is, however, disappointment that our air offensive against Germany seems to have slackened. The public is said not to be "greatly impressed by what it regards as our routine bombing of Western Germany", or by daylight raids over. France. A raid on Berlin appears to arouse the greatest enthusiasm, and there is comment on the report that the Russians raided Berlin this week, whereas the R.A.F. have not been there for some time.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-125b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">People are recalling recent official statements that the raids on London would look like child's play compared with what our raids on Berlin would be; there is a feeling that now is the time to demoralise the' Germans while they are "enthusiastic over their "Disappointment 'and mistrust of official announcements" are said to have resulted from a recent 'semi-official article in the 'Manchester Guardian'." This is said to have been issued by the Air. Ministry and Ministry of Economic Warfare, and to have referred to Cologne's City Centre as "beginning to look like the centre of a badly-raided English town". It is pointed out that the public knows that Cologne has been raided over fifty times, often by our largest bombers, and the assumption is :-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-135b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">(a) "That our bombing must be poor stuff",</note>
				<note xml:id="q-145b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">(b) "That statements made by Sir Archibald Sinclair and the Prime Minister, to, the effect that our bombing is far heavier than German bombing", must be inaccurate.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-155b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">(2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 29). hhh 3. Invasion Prospect</note>
				<note xml:id="q-165b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">"Notwithstanding recent warnings by national leaders, expectations of a German invasion of Britain have definitely receded", according to five R.I.O.s, who refer to this subject as "rarely being mentioned by the public". There is a tendency to regard invasion warnings as a "stunt" to keep people alert. Efforts to increase gas-mask carrying are said to have met with negligible success.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-175b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">(5, 9, 11, 12, 13, 20 Bristol P.C.) hhh 4. The Communist Party of Great Britain</note>
				<note xml:id="q-185b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">There are reports of increased Communist Party activity, "under the cloak of discussion groups" such as "The Russia To-day Society", the "Daily Worker's Defence League", and the "Medical First-aid for, Russia Group"; in the North Western Region "prominent citizens are said to be acting as chairmen of these meetings".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-195b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">The public's attitude to the Communists is once more tending to become hostile, according to some reports. Their manoeuvres, and particularly their campaign and poster, "Strike now in the West", are regarded as Party tactic, and are either resented or ridiculed. The opinion has been expressed that "the Communists will work to save Russia, but not Britain".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1a5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">(4, 7, 10, 13, 21) hhh 5. America</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1b5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">Reports of public reaction to President Roosevelt's Navy Day speech, speak of it as having been enthusiastically received, as "the most satisfying of his speeches", and as "the most daring and bellicose he has yet made." Although one R.I.O says that "there has not been the usual criticism that it was just 'words', the 'man-in-the-street' (and particularly the soldier-in-the-train') tend to be more critical of America after the sinking of the 'Reuben James". "This type of uninformed criticism" sees the American attitude as a "firm determination to keep out of the war at all costs"; and there is some feeling that "she will come in at the end and claim all the credit for defeating the Nazis". "Informed opinion", on the other hand, is more doubtful of the value to us of active American participation, with Japan taking a hand, and "admires the President's handling of the situation".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1c5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">(4, 6, 10, 12, 13) hhh 6. News presentation and Broadcasting</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1d5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">Several reports again speak of increased respect on the part of the public for the reliability of German official communiques. The sequence; of events is said "to conform with amazing regularity to a given formula" : -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1e5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">1) Position is described as "confused".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1f5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">2) The Germans claim to have taken a certain position.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-205b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">3) This is neither confirmed nor denied.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-215b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">4) The place for the first time is mentioned without comment by the Russians.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-225b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">5) It is reported that the Russians have evacuated it. hhh The result of this is said to be that "our war news is considered to be less reliable than that of the Germans".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-235b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">Some people ask that the times and wavelengths of Russian broadcasts in English should be published, and also those of American news bulletins, "which would give a better balanced view of the war than the B.B.C. bulletins".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-245b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">The suggestion that broadcasting should be reduced has aroused little comment, but there seems to be general agreement that the 8 a.m. news should not be stopped.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-255b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">There has been more praise for Laskier's postscripts which are described, as "by far the most effective"; they are said to have "touched the public conscience more than any official appeal has done so far". hhh (2, 3, 5, 6, 7, 11, 29)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-265b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">7. Post-War hopes The R.I.O., North Western Region, reports. "There seems to be considerable depression about post-war jobs, though this is relieved to some extent by the hope that the Government will be compelled by pressure of public opinion to adopt some policy this time, by which idleness and shortage of necessities will not be experienced by unemployed millions". The idea of a charter for the home country "on much more specific lines than the Atlantic Charter", is being discussed in some quarters. It is said that "if the Government were committed, in the event of economic collapse, to the provision of certain essentials such as Shelter, food, clothing, education and a more adequately protected old age, it would certainly do much to remove some of the depression".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-275b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">(10, 20 Bristol, P.C.) hhh 8. Rumours</note>
				<note xml:id="q-285b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">There are various rumours, mostly attributed to press or Parliamentary gossip, about impending Cabinet changes. Among tales of secret military activities, are rumours that:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-295b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">"British forces have raided France and have even penetrated as far as Amiens";</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">"Parties of our men are invading the Continent, from Norway-- to S.W. France, overpowering and slaughtering Germans, and returning without loss to themselves".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">It is rumoured in Huddersfield that "Orders recently received by manufacturers for khaki overcoating cloth indicate that this may be needed for Russia".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2c5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">From Cardiff area comes a report- that. "French factories - are working to full capacity for the Germans".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">There are reports of the circulation of forged ten shilling and one pound notes; these are said to have been found in places as far separated as Salisbury and Edinburgh, "but North Country towns are the worst sufferers". (In this connection a N.B.B.S. broadcast to this effect will be recalled.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">The rumour that hats are to be rationed has been revived during the past week.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">(2, 6, 7, 8, 10, 11, 32)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-305b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="53">SPECIAL COMMENTS hhh 9. Industry</note>
				<note xml:id="q-315b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">The feeling that "we are not working anything like all out" persists, and is still backed up by individual stories of misdirection, slacking, etc. As recorded last week, it is the managements, more than the workers, who are now held responsible. A propos of this, it is reported by one R.I.O. that "Lord. Beaverbrook's recent telegram to factories to work night-shifts has caused adverse comment among those who are already doing do. It is said to have given the impression that the Ministry of Supply is out of touch with what is going on".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-325b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">Government Employment and Industry: Adverse comment on the Government's attitude towards industry falls under two headings this week:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-335b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">(a) That its appeals for greater drive by the workers are not backed up by an exacting standard in its own departments. A comb-out of Government departments is advocated, both of young men and young women, "many of whom, it is thought, would be more usefully employed in producing munitions."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-345b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">(b) That "a number of men closely connected-with big combines and financial interests hold positions of control in the Civil Service," It is feared that 'the interests of the small man may be sacrificed, giving the larger firms an advantage after the war, amounting almost to monopoly.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-355b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">Non-cooperation of Trades Unions: "Financial considerations and "lack of co-operation on a big scale" on the part of the trades unions are suspected of slowing down and hampering the war effort." They are criticised for maintaining situations whereby plumbers may only plumb, and a lorry driver must sit and wait rather than lend a hand in loading a lorry".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-365b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">Delay after training: Dissatisfaction has also been recorded at "the time lag which too often occurs between training in a Government centre, and absorption into industry." Certain cases are said to indicate "that week's spent on the dole after training have a demoralising effect on the persons in question and on their associates." It is suggested that trade pay should be given in the waiting period as "much bad feeling as well as material hardship is caused; especially if the worker was taken from lucrative employment for training."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-375b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">Registration of Women: The demand for the use of compulsion continues. 'There are still fears that women 'are being chivied into unsuitable jobs" and it is emphasised that the whole position of women who are called up should be made clearer, both as to their rights of appeal and the penalties they may expect if they refuse to co-operate.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-385b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">The lack of day-nurseries, and of part-time employment, and also the- difficulties of shopping, remain the chief deterrents to married women who would otherwise go into industry. Anxiety about shopping difficulties has been intensified by the proposal that shops should close earlier. (In this connection it has been suggested that 'the London Passenger Transport Board, who have been doing E survey of factory 'hours, to find out at What times the markers travel, should be asked to make the results available to shop-keepers, 'who could then stagger their hours accordingly.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-395b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">(1,2,3,4,5,6,7,9,10,11,12,13) hhh 10. A.T.S.recruiting</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3a5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">Recent publicity, emphasising the point "that Army Service is a hard and worth-while job", has received favourable comment, as an attempt, too long delayed, to appeal to the young women's better motives. It is felt that the stressing of good pay, and similar practical inducements, is inevitably a wasted effort in any recruiting campaign, as the girls are well aware that they can earn more by munition-making than in any of the Services. What is described as "the failure of the recent recruiting drive at Hinckley" is reported by the R.I.O. North Midland Region, to be partly, at least, due to local conditions: -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3b5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">(a) The girls are used to factory life and prefer the munition factories, whore they can earn £4 or a week, and contrive to live at home.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3c5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">(b) The existence of what is regarded as a comfortless barracks for the 4.T. S. in the district is thought to have deterred possible recruits.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3d5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">Those factors are mentioned because it is felt that some influences of a similar material kind are bound to operate against recruiting in almost all districts, and only if the appeal is raised to a somewhat higher plane can they be overcome.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3e5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">(3, 4, 5, 6, 7) hhh 11. Income Tax</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3f5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">From R. I. O. s, social workers, industrial managers and other contacts there is fresh evidence of what is called "the urgent need" to emphasise to 'first payers' the fact that payment of income tax 'is an important part of their war-effort. It is apparent that the problem of reconciling the workers to the tax is a double one. It is necessary:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-405b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">(a) To explain what .their money buys in the way of munitions, and particularly how much of it Will be refunded after the war-a point: on which'-there is-widespread ignorance.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-415b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">(b) To explain how income tax, by restricting spending, also helps the country to avoid inflation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-425b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">Cases of absenteeism, refusal of, over-time, and various .forms of slacking continue to be reported, in which the explanation is: What's the good of working to earn money when there's nothing much to buy with it? The Government only takes it away if I do.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-435b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">The General Manager of a factory engaged on war work writes: "The general reaction here (to the tax) has been bad, mainly, in our view, through lack of adequate explanation. The high assessments will inevitably produce grumbles, and there will be attempts by some to limit earnings. But so far as we can judge, there will be no serious opposition, provided the payers can be convinced that with the aid (in part) of their money, the war will be prosecuted vigorously. Here are some ideas which may seem absurd to the informed mind but they are seriously held by some our workers: -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-445b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">(a) Because tax is deducted in the office, the firm must have some interest in it, and perhaps gets a share in it.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-455b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">(b) Income tax is just another way of reducing wages.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-465b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">(c) Let's go and work for Smith &amp;. Co. up the road, because their workers don' t have to pay tax.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-475b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">(d) It would be better to work only four days a week and so pay less, tax or go slow and not earn a bonus.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-485b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">This contact also states that married women's income tax is so high that many of them, anxious to do war work, "simply cannot afford to take a job, even when-unencumbered by young children". By the time they had paid the incidental expenses, fares, meals out, someone to look after the house, etc, they would be out of pocket.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-495b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">(2, 5, 7, 15, 20 P.C. Bristol 32) hhh 12. Food</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4a5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">On the- whole, the food situation continues to give satisfaction. It has been pointed out that "there is little or no anxiety concerning food problems in the approaching winter - this compares very favourably with the apprehension felt by the public at this time last year". Lord Woolton's announcement of the rationing of tinned goods has been welcomed, as ensuring a "fairer deal for the hardworking woman, who cannot shop in her factory or business hours". For this reason the point system has been particularly praised. It is hoped that, as shoppers are not restricted to any particular store, "the element of competition between one retailer and another may restore to shopping some of the little civilities which, it is thought, have been discouraged by the rigid rationing system".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">Milk and Meals in Schools: Irritation is reported among householders "who are told that the reduction in their milk supply is for the benefit of children, as they know the supply to school-children is smaller now than in the days prior to the reduction". There appears to be "strong feeling, especially in small towns and country areas that the statements made in Parliament about milk and meals in schools show a complacency which is quite unjustified".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">Oranges: Five R.I.O.s mention "confusion" or "muddled distribution" in connection with the oranges-for-children scheme; in some areas the fruit is believed to have gone bad because retailers, uncertain of the legal position, dared not sell surplus oranges after they had supplied the children's demand.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">Salted Cod: The scarcity of other fish appears to have done nothing to popularise this import, which is generally disliked. "Fish-mongers are reported to be making a dead loss on it", partly because "people appear to recognise only one method of cooking - e.g. frying - which seems to be unsuitable for this kind of fish".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">Pig Clubs: It appears that "small pig clubs have been extremely disheartened by the new regulation that 50% of the meat must be sold to the Ministry. One such club in Lincolnshire sums up the feeling with a resolution: "That this club, having sixteen members and only five pigs, considers it impracticable to conform to the new Government Regulation, and if it is enforced, the club will have to be disbanded."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">Wastage of Potatoes. "Great concern" is felt at the large acreage of potato crops which, in spite of the lateness of the season and the severe weather, have not yet been lifted. Shortage of labour is understood to be responsible.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-505b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">Food Substitutes: There is general approval for the Government's stand against worthless food substitutes.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-515b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">(1,2,3,4,5,6,7,10, 13, 15, 20, Carlisle, Manchester P.C.s) hhh 13. "Waste Paper"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-525b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">It is said that "Lord Beaverbrook's speech on the subject of waste paper has created a veritable howl against the wastage of paper by Government departments in sending out documents couched in circumlocution and early Victorian language". References are made to the Prime Minister's statement, shortly after he assumed office that he had given instructions to Government 'departments that communications from them should be as short and concise as possible, "and the cry goes up, why don't the Government Departments take some notice"? The forms to be filled up by Servicemen's dependants in applying for the new grants, are instanced as being "very difficult for any uneducated person to understand". Whenever new ration books are issued, the same complaint is made.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-535b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">(3, 5, 32) hhh 14. Scrap Metal</note>
				<note xml:id="q-545b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">The discontent felt for some tine over the apparent neglect of scrap-metal dumps has received an impetus from surveys being made of iron railings. It is suspected that scrap iron merchants are exploiting the position for their own profit, and that railings may be purchase from such dealers for re-erection. In, some localities it appears that many people are somewhat alarmed, thinking that the collection of railings indicates a serious shortage of iron, ore". It is suggested that it should be explained to the public 'that scrap iron is needed to mix with pig iron in the manufacture of munitions".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-555b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">(3, 10) hhh 15. Clothes Rationing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-565b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">Coupons for footwear for elementary school children seem "likely to prove an important-problem", as even in normal times the excuse of "No boots" is given for absence from school. "Poorer classes", it is said, "buy cheap boots and get neither wear nor coupon value".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-575b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">One R.I.O. reports "there are serious complaints among workers in heavy industries that clothes and boots require continual replacement"; workers in welding and foundry, works especially "complain of inadequate provision for replacement of clothing and boots, either burned or rapidly deteriorated by excessive heat".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-585b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">Apparently men of the Merchant Navy are not told, before they quit their port of arrival to go on leave, that they must obtain a certificate from a Merchant Marine office in order to get new rig-outs coupon-free. The result of this is that men living inland have to waste part of their leave to visit a port where this certificate can be got.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-595b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">(3, 4, 8, 12) hhh 16. Constant Topics and Complaints</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">The early closing of shops is said to 'be "causing discontent among female employees", and revision of shopping hours is urged "to suit business and industrial women workers".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">Country people who have no other means of lighting are said to 'be "irritated and depressed by the acute shortage of paraffin". A shortage of coal is also reported from some areas.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">There are complaints about -the new system of supplementary allowances' for servicemen's dependants; these are said to involve "far too much- form-filling, and are likely to take months of application before any benefit is received". There is also a dislike of the 'hardship principle' - "wives feel they are put in the position of asking favours.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5d5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">Wastage of petrol in private cars is again rousing discontent; it is said that the postscript by Frank Laskier, the Merchant Seaman, "has had more effect than any appeal" in making people conscious of the price paid for petrol.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5e5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">Inadequate transport is still responsible for loss of production hours.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5f5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">There are renewed complaints of larger houses not receiving their due share of evacuees and war workers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-605b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">The fear of a shortage of sanitary towels "is proving as damaging as the actual shortage, which appears to 'be pretty general. The importance of the adequate supply of these articles to the morale of women cannot be too strongly stressed".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-615b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">The shortage of wireless batteries and valves continues, as does 'that of children's shoes, which is said to be serious in. some districts.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-625b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">Nine R.I.O.s mention the acute shortage of matches, other shortages are of lighters and flints, tobacco and cigarettes, gas lighters, electric bulbs, vinegar, and drawing pins.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-635b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">There is "some grumbling about milk", and five Regions report dissatisfaction over scarcity, quality and unequal distribution of eggs'</note>
				<note xml:id="q-645b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">(1, 2, 3, 5, 6, 7, 10, 11, 13) hhh REFERENCES</note>
				<note xml:id="q-655b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">1. Northern Region (Newcastle)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-665b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">2. North Eastern Region (Leeds)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-675b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="108">3. North Midland Region (Nottingham)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-685b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="109">4. Eastern Region (Cambridge)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-695b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="110">5. London Region (London)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6a5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="111">6. Southern Region (Reading)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6b5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="112">7. South Western Region (Bristol)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6c5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="113">8. Wales (Cardiff)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6d5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="114">9. Midland (Birmingham)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6e5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="115">10. North Western Region (Manchester)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6f5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="116">11. Scotland (Edinburgh)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-705b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="117">12. South Eastern Region (Tunbridge Wells)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-715b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="118">13. Northern Ireland (Belfast)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-725b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="119">14. Special Reports from R.I.O.'s</note>
				<note xml:id="q-735b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="120">15. Regions Adviser's Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-745b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="121">16. M.o.I. Speakers' Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-755b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="122">17. Local Information Committee Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-765b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="123">18. Home Press Summaries (M.O.I)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-775b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="124">19. Regional Press Summaries (M.O.I)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-785b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="125">20. Hansard</note>
				<note xml:id="q-795b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="126">21. Postal Censorship</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7a5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="127">22. Police Duty Room Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7b5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="128">23. Wartime Social Survey</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7c5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="129">24. B.B.C. Listener Research Papers</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7d5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="130">25. B.B.C. Special Papers</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7e5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="131">26. Citizens' Advice Bureau Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7f5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="132">27. W.V.S. Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-805b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="133">28. Scottish Unionist Whips' Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-815b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="134">29. Liberal Party's Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-825b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="135">30. Economic League's Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-835b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="136">31. War Office Post Bag Summaries</note>
				<note xml:id="q-845b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="137">32. Primary Sources Weekly Reports from</note>
				<note xml:id="q-855b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="138">1-13 are Weekly Reports from R.I.O.'s</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>