<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Ministry of Information Home Intelligence Division Weekly Report No. 78 - 1st April 1942</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-6398c09b-4ac7-485c-82ad-9ffb4e046a4e</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-b03a6741-ac69-4ecd-96ff-35d3095266cf</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-c85588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c95588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ca5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="3">Home Intelligence Division Weekly Report No.78</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cb5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="4">1st April, 1942</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cc5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">(Covering the period from 23rd to 30th March, 1942)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cd5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">Note: The figures in brackets refer to sources of information, a list of which was issued with all reports up to and including No.66, 7th January, 1942.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ce5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="7">I GENERAL COMMENTS hhh 1. General state of confidence and reaction to news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cf5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">There appears this week to be a slight though definite rise in confidence and public spirits: this is referred to by eight R.I.O.s. The reasons for this are not clear-cut; among those given are the Production debate, the heavy R.A.F. raids, the St Nazaire attack, the weather, and "a general Air of expectancy". But there are still reports of an unsettled, bewildered and critical" attitude. Two R.I.O.s again refer to "apathy", a contributory cause of which is said to be irritability with "the Government's lack of push in prosecuting the war". "Considerable sections of the public" are said to regard the war "as something remote, and to have lost a feeling of personal identification in the struggle". A marked disinclination to discuss it has again been noted in one Region; "particularly among young people": interest at the news of recent Allied actions being described as "spasmodic and short-lived".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d05588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">Signs that "inspiration and leadership and, above all, are urgently desired", come from the reports of five R.I.O. s. Welcome continues to be given to the Government promise of "a more intensive effort and more austere way of life, but there is a widespread fear that it may be only 'a little spurt', and that 'normal lethargic departmental machinery' will hold things up".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d15588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">The Prime Minister's speech at Caxton Hall: Moderate interest is reported in Mr. Churchill's speech. His reference to the worsening position in the Atlantic was chiefly noted, and there is some comment over his prediction of successes which, according to one R.I.O. "is thought to have been more optimistic than the tone expected from Mr. Churchill". It is still thought that he is "carrying too much on his own shoulders".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d25588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">(1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12,21) hhh 2. The Far East</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d35588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">The situation in the Far East appears on the whole to have been little discussed during the past week. There has been some criticism of "our policy of dispersal" and of defending untenable places with inadequate forces, which were reinforced only in time for the reinforcements to be lost too".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d45588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">Australia: Great confidence in General MacArthur is reported eight R. I. O. s ; his appointment is even described, as "one of the best Allied moves of the war". The public "do not think the Japs will be able to capture Australia"; on the other hand, Australia's growing ". Americanisation" is often commented on, without concern.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d55588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">Some resentment against Mr. Curtin and the Australian Press is again mentioned, but admiration for the all-out effort of the Commonwealth is also shown.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d65588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">(1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12,21,32) hhh 3. India: Considerable interest in the Indian situation is reported.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d75588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">Sir Stafford Cripps' mission is felt to have been prompted by "imaginative statesmanship". But the serious and delicate nature of his task seems to be appreciated only "by the very small section of the public with intimate knowledge of Indian affairs". The whole problem is said to be "far too complicated for the British working man to understand."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d85588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">Some feeling is also expressed that "as Dominion status was obviously indicated, it is a pity we couldn't have got a move on long ago".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d95588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">(2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12,16) hhh 4. Russia: Though admiration for the Russians seems undiminished, comment on, their activities' is declining. It is noted that German counter-attacks are increasing in strength and it is feared that as a result the Russians' difficulties will grow, and the continuation of their successes is now "hoped for rather than confidently expected".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-da5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">(1,2,5,8,9,10,12) hhh 5. Libya and the Mediterranean</note>
				<note xml:id="q-db5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">The slight increase of interest in this theatre of war, which was reported last week, appears to continue. Four R. I. O. s mention a belief that "Rommel will move first", and it is thought by some that the Allied leaders tend to under-estimate him. "It is felt that he has been able to obtain heavy reinforcements, and that there will be rapid developments in Libya, and possibly the Near East generally".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">Though there has been little comment, some satisfaction has been noted at Roar-Admiral Vian's action against the Italian fleet. The news is said to have been at first received "with some caution". One R. I. O. reports "shock that we had to send destroyers after battleships".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">(1,2,6,8,9,10) hhh 6. U. S. A.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">There is still some impatience with what is felt to be lack of effective action by the United States, but the realisation is expressed that U.S. and. British navies have "done well to get troops to Australia from the U. S. and the middle East". The recent attacks on Wake and Marcus Islands are said, 'by two R.I.O.s, to have inspired hope.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">(2,6,10) hhh 7. "Desire for a second front"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e05588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">M. Maisky's call to the Allies "to stake all this year" is said to be supported by the public's desire for offensive action "on all fronts". It is felt that "a purely defensive strategy is getting us nowhere, and that we have still got to do some attacking on Germans, as well as on Japanese". In this connection a feeling is reported from two Regions, that we intend "to do something in a big way", which is generally thought to mean "a grand scale invasion of the continent". This notion is supported by rumours of "fifteen divisions; and hundreds of invasion barges" concentrated on the South and East coasts. These stories are thought to be confirmed by "the more reassuring note" in leading articles in the Press, adding to the "general sense of expectancy".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e15588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">(3,4,5,6,7,8) hhh 8. Invasion</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e25588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">Sir John Anderson's recent statement on the role of civilians in the event of invasion is said to have had a mixed reception. While the "stand firm" policy is thought to be much more practical than the order to "stay put", there is some feeling, particularly amongst responsible people, that "the new instructions are far from sufficient". Some feeling is also reported that Civil Defence workers and the police should be armed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e35588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">At the same time, it appears that the majority of people do not think there is much possibility of invasion.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e45588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">Local Defence Committees; There seems to be some feeling that there has been much unnecessary delay in forming these Committees, due mostly to "jealousy in high places". From the South Western Region, where interest in invasion is said to have been stimulated by Mr. Denis Freeman's talks, the following criticisms are made of Local Defence Committees, "which have been in existence for six months",</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e55588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">(a) They keep things too much to themselves and would not have time to let the public know their plans in the event of invasion.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e65588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">(b) Lack of co-operation between these Committees and Military authorities.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e75588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">The role of women: The R.I.O. Scotland, reports that country women are constantly referring to the example of Russian women, and are anxious to take an active part in the event of invasion. It is pointed out that "a basket of hand grenades is no heavier than a basket of turnips". The feeling is mentioned that officialdom takes no cognizance of women as a potential force, but is governed by the old idea of "fighting to protect our womenfolk".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e85588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">(2,3,5,6,7,9,10,11,12,16,32) hhh 9. Broadcasting and Presentation of News</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e95588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">Seven R.I.O.s report continued dissatisfaction with the presentation of news, and there is still said to be "a cry for the whole truth". Reasons for suspecting that "straight news" is being withheld are beliefs in: -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ea5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">(a) The substitution of "confused news" for "bad news".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-eb5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">(b) The minimising of our losses.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ec5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">(c) The explaining away of our reverses; a particular instance quoted is the reference made to "shortening our lines in Burma" when "a withdrawal was probably meant".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ed5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">(d) The fact that "Lord Halifax has been able to tell America things it had not been right to tell us".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ee5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">(e) Alleged conflicting statements made by various official spokesmen.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ef5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">European News Service: Three R.I.O.s mention a preference for this "more cheerful and aggressive" service "which makes one sure we're winning, whereas the Home News service is so dreary it makes one think we're losing".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f05588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">(1,2,3,5,9,10,11,12,21 Manchester P.C.) hhh 10. Freedom of the Press</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f15588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">"A sharp division of opinion" over Mr.Morrison's warning to the Daily Mirror continues to be reported. The view is widely held that the Mirror is a "dirty little rag", but "the distinction drawn by the Government between legitimate criticism and subversive attacks upon the war effort" is thought by some people to be invalid.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f25588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">(2,3,5,6,7,9,10) hhh 11. The Services</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f35588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">The R. A. F.: The renewed R. A. F. offensive has been greeted with satisfaction, although two R. I. O. s report disappointment that "in spite of favourable weather conditions we have not been bombing Germany as heavily as our political and service leaders have led us to expect". Approval for the bombing of Lubeck is reported. This, it is thought, "must be a great help to the Russians". "The photographs of the results of the Cologne raids have done much to dispel a feeling that the actual results of our raids on industrial Germany have not been so effective as the undetailed communiques suggest".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f45588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">The Army: Satisfaction is reported by one R. I.O. at the formation of the Army Air Corps and the regiment of glider pilots. These innovations are said to give a feeling "that we are adapting ourselves to the conditions' necessary for modern war".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f55588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">(2,4,6,8,9,11) hhh 12. St. Nazaire Raid</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f65588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">So far, only four regional reports have been received. Three R. I. O. s report praise for what is described as "a very good job of work" which has "captured the public's imagination". Criticism has been made, however, of the delay in the release of the news and of its "patchy" presentation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f75588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">(5,8,11,14 North Western) hhh 13. Grantham By-election</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f85588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">This election is mentioned by three R.I.O.s as having been "watched with interest" by "thinking people". It is stated that its result "is taken by some as an indication of the shape of things to come". (4,5,6)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f95588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="50">II. SPECIAL COMMENTS hhh 14. Industry</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fa5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">Dissatisfaction with production appears to be less intense than it has been for the past month, though it is still reported in one form or another by 12 R.I.O.s.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fb5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">Debate on production: Two R.I.O.s mention Mr.Lyttelton's straightforward speech" as a cause of general satisfaction; according to the R.I.O., North Midland, "complaints about production have diminished considerably since the speech, as is always the case when a grievance is well aired in Parliament, and there are signs of action". Particular pleasure has been expressed at Mr. Lyttelton's statement that "his mind will be closed to no suggestions, however revolutionary", and there is said to be a "strong demand that wages, prices and profits should be stabilised - as is believed to have been done in Australia, Canada and the U.S.A. - as the first step towards total war on the Home Front".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fc5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">Lack of mutual confidence between workers and managements: "Loss of production is again blamed by men on managements, and by managements on men". As was mentioned in our last Report, the men are chiefly accused of absenteeism, while the managements are criticised on account of the cost plus ten per cent system, considering their post-war position, inefficiency and failure to explain to the workers the reasons for hold-ups.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fd5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">Absenteeism: The R.I.O., Scotland, write "The Government's new stringent measures against absenteeism are being badly received (according to preliminary reports); many workers believe that their presence or absence does not materially affect the war, owing to lack of materials or to bad organisa­tion inside the factories. It is thought that in most cases, disciplinary measures are poor remedies".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fe5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">The following factors are again mentioned by several R.I.O.s as being thought to cause absenteeism:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ff5588b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">(a) Transport difficulties</note>
				<note xml:id="q-005688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">(b) Shopping difficulties</note>
				<note xml:id="q-015688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">(c) Lack of day nurseries</note>
				<note xml:id="q-025688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">(d) High wages, making it unnecessary to do a full week's work.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-035688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">(e) Income Tax.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-045688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">Essential Work Order: Two R.I.O.s refer to some dissatisfaction with the working of this Order. In one case there is reported to be a "growing demand for heavier penalties for offences against the Order". At the same time it is pointed out that "no attempt should be made to tighten up discipline without parallel measures designed to bring managements under control. It is argued that workers will not greatly improve their efforts in war production until there has been a drastic reorganisation of relations between employers and workmen, bringing employers quite as obviously under control" as are workers under the Essential Work Order.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-055688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">Excess profits tax and coal production: There appears to be sonic belief that "Excess profits Tax is a very important factor in limiting output". It is believed, for instance, that "once a colliery has earned its pre-war standard of Profits, it is, in fact, presenting every additional ton of coal mined to the Government as a free gift and is stripping itself of its main asset".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-065688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">Wasted work: Two R.I.O.s and one Local Information Committee report disquiet on the part of workers at the scrapping of products after they have been manufactured in considerable quantities, particularly when no explanation is given to the workers as to why this is done. A case is also mentioned of workers in a Clydebank factory who complain that the shells they made nearly a year ago are still unfinished; they are "incredulous of the explanation that lack of materials has held up these shells so long".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-075688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">Women's call-up: Complaints arc reported from Wales that "women .conscripted for national service are not being absorbed as quickly as the occasion demands". In the Eastern Region surprise is reported at the announcement, that, in the middle of February, there were 62,000 unemployed women and girls in the country, though there is an acute shortage of domestic labour.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-085688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">Women steel workers: "The introduction of women in the iron and steel factories to have proved a great success", according to the R.I.O., North Midland Region. The staff manager at "one of the largest iron and steel works in the country" is quoted as saying that ,he "has yet to find a job which women could not do, and that they often prove bettor workers than men and the men have to 'buck up their ideas' to keep pace with them". It is also stated that the number of break-downs in the machinery had decreased since the women took them over, because of their lighter touch". Some men are still said to "resent the intrusion" (as mentioned in our Reports, 17th December, 1941, and 18th March, 1942), but the majority "sensibly regard them as necessary for the prosecution of the war".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-095688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">(2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,1O,11,12,13,16,17,32) hhh 15. Food</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0a5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">"Spontaneous Approval of the Ministry of Food and its work" is again reported this week, and there is little evidence of grumbling about the food situation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0b5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">Points rationing: The public seem; prepared for everything to be rationed, and are hoping that the points system, "which makes it fair for everybody", will be used.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0c5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">Four R.I.O.s mention complaints by women workers that women who are free all day can "scoop up unrationed foods". There is also some comment on the high prices of unrationed foods, which "only people with plenty of money can afford to buy".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0d5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">Luxury feeding: The impending reduction in rations in the home is said to be giving "a great impetus to the outcry against the meals still being served in hotels and restaurants to those who can pay for them". The R.I.O., Scotland reports that "drastic limitations of the amount that one may spend on a meal are being called for",</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0e5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">(2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,11,12,31 Carlisle, Nottingham P.C.) hhh 16. Fuel Rationing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0f5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">There are still few reported comments on the proposal to ration fuel, though there appears to be some feeling that "the coal business has been badly handled, if the only commodity we have abundance of in this country is in short supply". The following minority reactions are, however, mentioned:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-105688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">(a) In coal producing centres some anxiety is reported owing' to-the greater reliance on coal for heating and cooking. Protests about the "unfair allocation" of' coal continue to be reported from the North Midland Region, and particularly from the coal producing centres near the North Eastern Region (where the ration is higher).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-115688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">(b) It is felt that those who live in outlying villages and farms should be allowed to stack coal in readiness for the winter when communications may be cut for long periods, and also to save transport in frequent deliveries.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-125688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">(c) There is some criticism of the "wastage of electricity in official buildings, such as Town Halls and A.R.P. depots, where lights are left burning in rooms that are not being used". There is also reported to be a "growing demand that official action should be taken against shops which appear to be extravagant in 'display lighting'. This is most marked in connection with radio supply shops and the cheaper clothing shops".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-135688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">(1,3,5,6,8,9) hhh 17. Petrol restrictions</note>
				<note xml:id="q-145688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">Further reports indicate that "the public have accepted the abolition of the basic ration with good grace, regarding it as necessary". Some apprehension is, however, expressed by people living in rural districts who feel that the cut will fall more heavily on them, as "often shopping is relatively difficult without a car".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-155688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">At the same time, it is pointed out that, while civilians are willing to "do their bit in putting up with hardships and making sacrifices", great indignation is caused by instances such as that</note>
				<note xml:id="q-165688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">where "700 Civil Defence Workers from rural districts in Suffolk travelled by cars and buses to Framlingham for a film show which, in the end, did not take place". Dissatisfaction is also reported at alleged waste by the N.F.S. and the Services.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-175688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">(1, 3, 4, 5, 8) hhh 18. The Waste Paper Salvage Order</note>
				<note xml:id="q-185688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">In two Regions there is said to have been a good response to the waste paper order, and less paper is to be seen in the streets. The following points, however, are said to be causing a good deal of discussion:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-195688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">(a) Advertising waste: It is thought that "much paper is wasted on advertising space in the press. As many of the commodities advertised are unobtainable, much of this advertising is thought to indicate evasion of Excess Profits Tax".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1a5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">(b) Government waste: Three R.I.O.s report criticism of the Government for extravagance either in the size or the number of the forms which are issued to the public:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1b5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">(i) The Inland Revenue Authorities are criticised for sending 'sheaves of forms in different envelopes to the same address by the same post, with the added irritation of an 'economy notice' in each".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1c5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">(ii) The Ministry of Food is criticised for the size of the new form for milk supplies for children.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1d5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">(iii) The Ministry of Information is "castigated for Wasting paper on posters",</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1e5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">(1,2,3,8,9,10,15) hhh 19. Warship Weeks</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1f5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">"Reactions from several districts, particularly the East End, indicate that the processions in connection with London's Warship Week, have been much appreciated, and their heartening effect was considerable". A number of unfavourable reactions or questioning comments to Warship Weeks in general are, however, reported.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-205688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">(a) It is asked why the Government does not "conscript the wealth under the powers they possess", rather than "appeal so expensively to the public".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-215688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">(b) There is much criticism of the waste of petrol involved. "Tractors, lorries, bren-gun carriers, searchlight batteries, civil defence vehicles, all moving slowly in low gear may be propaganda, but must make heavy inroads on petrol supplies".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-225688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">(c) There is also criticism of the waste of time involved. "It is said that in some cases the already over-worked local authorities have co-operated only grudgingly, and wore glad to see the end of the week".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-235688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">(d) It is asked how much these "mammoth targets" really mean, and there is a growing public suspicion that "big firms just transfer shares to look patriotic and put up the figures".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-245688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">(e) "Concern is felt at the amount of paper necessary for the publicity".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-255688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">(f) It is said that "the maximum effect is not achieved owing to savers who have already attained the maximum of 500 War Savings Certificates being unwilling to invest in long-term bonds".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-265688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">(1, 5, 8, 32) hhh 20. Black markets and anti-Semitism</note>
				<note xml:id="q-275688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">The severe sentences now being passed on black marketeers seem to have met with approval. Action against them is thought to have led "to a keener desire on the part of the public to co-operate cheerfully in the rationing system".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-285688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">Three R.I.O.s refer to anti-semitism this week. It is attributed chiefly to "the number of Jews appearing before the Courts over black market dealings", and to "the presence of Jews in hotels and restaurants where expensive meals are to be bought".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-295688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">(8, 9, 10, 12) hhh 21. Rumours</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">Fewer rumours are reported this week. One from the North Midland Region is that the tax on beer and cigarettes is to be increased.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">From the London Region comes a rumour that between 1,700 and 1,800 men of the Rifle Brigade have been killed in Lybia.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2c5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">From Glasgow is reported the story of an invasion of the Isle of Wight in which some prisoners were said to have been taken.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">(3, 5, 11) hhh 22. Constant topics and complaints</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">There are continued complaints about the following subjects: -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f5688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">(a) Income Tax. Complaints continue on the same lines as those referred to in our last report.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-305688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">(b) The high price of essential articles in short supply such as kettles, pots and pans, crockery, towels, etc.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-315688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">(c) The shortage of day nurseries, which is said to act as a brake on married women taking up war work.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-325688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">(d) Non-collection, or careless collection, of salvage.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-335688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="108">(e) The "exorbitant" price of green vegetables.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-345688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="109">(f) Disparity of wages between agricultural and aerodrome workers, Servicemen and civilians, office and manual workers and youths and men.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-355688b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="110">(2,3,5,7,8,9,10,11,12,21 Nottingham P.C.)</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>