<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Home Intelligence Weekly Report - No. 142 - 24 June 1943</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-6b5cce63-1235-46f3-a427-94025a94df62</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-107f900b-8dec-4ee0-bcf2-d781c3518441</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-465c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-475c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-485c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="3">HOME INTELLIGENCE WEEKLY REPORT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-495c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="4">No. 142 24th (Covering period 15th to 22nd June, 1943)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4a5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="5">I. GENERAL COMMENTS hhh 1. General state of confidence and reaction to news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">For the seventh week in succession now - since the-final defeat of the Axis in Africa - public spirits remain on a high level. The, are maintained by:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">(a) Continued expectation that "the famous second front will come soon".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">(b) Our air offensive.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">(c) The King's "popular action" in visiting our For Africa and Malta.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">(d) The position in the Mediterranean: "We're right on Musso's doorstep now and he 'may pack up".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-505c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">(e) Confidence in our leadership, enhanced by the new Pantellaria technique of taking places with fee casualties",</note>
				<note xml:id="q-515c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">(f) The "increasing destruction" of U-boats.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-525c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">(g) The inference that Germany "is not strong enough" to attack Russia.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-535c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">(h) The appointment of Field Marshal Sir Archibald Wavell as Viceroy designate of India.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-545c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">On the other hand, the following, while not adversely affecting -confidence, are considered "flies in the ointment":</note>
				<note xml:id="q-555c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">(a) The delay in attacking Europe, The tension reported last week is said to be increasing, with a feeling of "I wish to heavens we could get on with it". (There is, however, general confidence in our leaders to choose the right time and place.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-565c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">(b) The de Gaulle - Giraud bickering.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-575c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">(c) The U.S. coal strike.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-585c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">Speculation continues about the length of the war in Europe, with opinion again divided between: "we've seen the last blackout" and "it'll drag on for some years yet". Some people fear that there is over-confidence and that this may lead to a slacking of effort - the superstitious think it may bring misfortune,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-595c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">Two reports mention the fact that it does not appear to be a great deal of talk about the war - "less than might be expected, consider­ing events".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">There is, on the other hand talk of holidays, not only Whitsun but future ones: "People's hearts are more than ever set on getting away", and it is suggested that "the Government should move heaven and earth to give people a break".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">Home Front grumbles are mainly about clothing (particularly footwear), the lack of fresh fruit, transport and shopping difficulties. All of these complaints are widespread.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11.15. 21 all provincial P.Cs. 22 Passim.) hhh 2. The King's visit to the Mediterranean People were surprised and excited to hear of the King's visit to North Africa. They are very pleased at this "splendid recogni­tion of what our troops have done" and feel "it will buck our boys up". Women with relatives serving-in North Africa are particularly appreciative- and are "honoured that the Queen will feel the same as us while he's away".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5d5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">Anxiety for His Majesty's safety is, however, very great; it was increased by his non-arrival in England after a press statement (June 19) that he had left Gibraltar for London by air. Many criticise the issuing of information about his movements before his return: "Neither he nor the Prime Minister should run such risks"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5e5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">Other reactions to the North African visit include:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5f5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">(a) Speculation about its significance, on the following lines:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-605c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">(i) "It's an eve of attack review." Old soldiers recall similar reviews in the last war.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-615c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">(ii) "It shows we cannot be attacking just yet, and it may be just bluff to deceive the enemy."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-625c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">(iii) "It's to help compose French squabbles."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-635c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">(b) Confidence in our mastery of the Mediterranean: "We must feel very sure of our ground over there to let him risk it".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-645c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">(c) A feeling that the visit will have good propaganda value in occupied and, neutral countries.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-655c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">(d) Belief that his personal decoration of General Eisenhower will be appreciated by the Americans.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-665c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">(e) Appreciation of his concern for his staff, and for press correspondents people are also very pleased about his visit to Malta, which they consider singularly appropriate.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-675c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11.13. 22 passim.) hhh 3. The new Viceroy of India</note>
				<note xml:id="q-685c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">Although the appointment of Field-Marshal Sir Archibald Wavell as Viceroy came as n complete surprise, it has been received with approval as a "wise and clever move" by the great majority. Field Marshal Wavell has great personal popularity, and it is believed ho has a "knowledge of India's problems" and is "unencumbered by political connections". Some people are anxious about "the waste of his great military talent", while others suggest that "he will not go down well with the Indian Nationalists". At the same time, it is generally felt "the defence of India must come first… and Wavell is the men to see that it does".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-695c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">Commander-in-Chief, India: The appointment of General Sir Claude Auchinleck as Commander-in-Chief, Indic, is also reported to be popular (Five Regions). "He had bad luck in Egypt, and deserves his new job." It. is thought that "a combination has been found which will assure the military strength of India"...."Every example of firm purpose in war policy is approved." (1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.6.9.11. 22 three P.D.Rs.) hhh 4. The next move</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6a5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">Widespread expectation continues that "we are building up for our assault, and any day now the big news may break". People are on the whole confident that our plan is well worked out, and that will strike when we are ready.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6b5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">Tension at the delay is, however, growing; a small minority are worried: "The campaigning months are passing....are we waiting too long?"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6c5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">Criticism of "restless" newspaper headlines and over-optimistic prophecies continues.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6d5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">Casualties: Many particularly relatives of servicemen, fear that the slaughter will be terrible. However, the capture of Pantellaria, with "the loss of only forty men, has encouraged some to think "'we may be able to save a lot of lives by preliminary air and naval actions before our forces land",</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6e5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">Italy: The capture of the islands is looked on as "a step towards the collapse of Italy"; it is hoped that the air bases they provide may make landings on the mainland unnecessary. Opinion varies as to how long Italy will hold out, but many think "she can be knocked out in the immediate future". A few feel "Germany will never allow her to give up". Some people continue to be irritated at "our being led to believe the Italians cannot fight". Reports from two Regions mention some pity for the "deluded Italians".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6f5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">Speculation as to where we shall strike continues, and many think it will be at several places at once.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-705c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">(a) The Mediterranean: Italy, with Sicily and Sardinia, is still first choice. The belief, however, that she may collapse without invasion and the closing of the Turko-Syrian frontier have this week stimulated discussion about possibilities in the Eastern Mediterranean. People are particularly wondering what part Turkey will play. Will she "get off the fence" and join the Allies now vie are winning, or at least let us use the Dardanelles and link up with Russia? The recall of the Turkish Ambassador in Vichy is taken by some as a sign that Turkey is "backing us".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-715c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">Whether Turkey helps or not, however, the Balkans are a favoured guess, with or without the Dodecanese and Crete.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-725c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">(b) Western Europe is not out of the running; while Holland and Norway are cited as possibles a strongly held view is that "if we go across the Straits of Dover we will have short lines of communication and a preponderance of air strength. It is also looked on as "the shortest cut to Berlin".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-735c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.3.9.10.11.15. 21 ten provincial P.Cs. 22 passim.) hhh 5. Allied air offensive</note>
				<note xml:id="q-745c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">Reactions differ little from those reported last week, though comment about "the twelve days lull" has now given way to satisfaction with the renewed heavy bombing of Gorman industries.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-755c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">Although still confined to a minority, there seems to be "a growing feeling that raids will end the war without much herd fighting". "People who were once dismayed that our lend forces were not speeding long ago to the relief of the Red army, are now speculating as to whether bombing may not be the quicker way."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-765c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">The increasing scale of American Fortress raids on Germany, end particularly their increased losses, are leading to a greater appreciation of the American efforts, and of Americans in general.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-775c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11.13. 21 eight provincial P.Cs.) hhh 6. Air Raids on this country</note>
				<note xml:id="q-785c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">There is "some anxiety about sneak raiders and fears that our casualties are worse than the public is allowed to know". People want to know what is meant by the "small number of fatal casualties" in the day to day communiques, and speculate on "the size of the monthly total".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-795c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">The Plymouth raid (June 13): Though "morale was good", the raid is described "as a shock to the city" after "a gap of two years, ­especially by comparison with the parade of air strength in the recent Wings for Victory week",</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7a5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">The Grimsby raid (June 14): Many people in the North Midland Region are "anxious about' the effect of the new anti-personnel bomb used in this raid. In view of the casualties caused by handling these bombs, more warnings end instructions are thought necessary. Some consider the-raid "a direct consequence of Mr. V. Alexander's speech during Wings for Victory week, in which he mentioned the splendid work done by the Grimsby trawlers in minesweeping, thus drawing attention to Grimsby".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7b5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">The London raids. (June 18): Many believe that the postal sorting office was picked out by the German raiders and wonder "what the balloons and other defences were doing". (2.3.5.6.7) hhh 7. Low flying planes</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7c5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">'Dislike of planes flying low over built-up areas, particularly at night, has been mentioned in reports from four regions during the past fortnight. Apart from the disturbance to people's sleep, it is said to make elderly people very nervous. Though most people take it for granted that the machines are ours, some imagine that "an odd sneak raider may be about".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7d5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">(2.3.6.7.) hhh 8. Poison gas</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7e5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">There has been "some increase in interest in poison gas, its possibilities as a weapon, and the likelihood of its use". A few fear the Germans may use it when we invade the continent; it is believed the Japanese are already using it against the Chinese.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7f5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">The majority do not expect gas attacks "as long as we have air superiority", and are not sufficiently concerned to see that their gas masks are in order. "Few of them even know where their respirators are to be found", according to one report.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-805c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">(1.2.3.5SE.10) hhh 9. North African Politics</note>
				<note xml:id="q-815c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">Exasperation with the "'continued squabbles" of the French leaders has increased; "Their heads should be knocked together to make them agree". The more disturbed fear that "the factors which caused the 1940 crack up in France are still in operation"..."it bodes ill for France when she is freed". For others the situation has become a joke.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-825c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">"Both Generals arc unpopular"; there is still some sympathy for General de Gaulle, though his stock has gone down considerably during the last few weeks. He is thought to be "difficult" and his uncompromising attitude is criticised. But against this is the feeling that "the French have compromised too much in the past", and that the "pro-Vichy elements" need ousting.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-835c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">General Giraud, "though less -unpopular than he was a few months ago", is criticised for too obstinately to the "Vichyites" in his entourage. He is described as "the nicer but the stupider of the two",</note>
				<note xml:id="q-845c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">Allied "guidance" in the crisis has been little commented on as yet. Preliminary reactions are that it is "evidence of Allied strength and realism in the political field". It is felt that France may need "strong Allied guidance" for a long time to come. (1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11.13. 21 two provincial P.Cs. 22 thirty-four P.D.Rs.) hhh 10. War at sea</note>
				<note xml:id="q-855c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">Relief and pleasure are reported at the recent news of successes against U-boats. The public are said to be "becoming more confident about the whole position at sea", and it is thought that "we are getting on top of this menace", thanks to the now methods and devices.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-865c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">(1.3.4.5.5SE.7.10.11.13. 22 twenty-one P.D.Rs.) hhh 11. The Far East</note>
				<note xml:id="q-875c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">The recent defeats inflicted on the Japanese Air Force at Guadalcanal, the attack on the Japanese camp at Kiska, and the support given by American bombers during the recent battles in China are "regarded as encouraging". Increased aid to China is urged, as people now feel that the "Chinese, with air support, have more than a fighting chance". Some think that "events are brewing up" for an offensive by the Americans.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-885c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">The growing confidence of Australian leaders about the diminished chances of invasion by Japan is looked on as reassuring (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-895c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">(1.2.3.4.8.10) hhh 12. Russia</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8a5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">The successful Russian bombing offensive and the "reappearance of the Orel bulge" have aroused appreciative interest this week, although Russian claims of air successes "still seem to be unreal". People are again speculating as to where and by whom the next move will be made. There is any migration and sympathy for the Russians and "optimism for the future"; a minority think Germany may be "holding beck her forces till she sees which way the cot jumps - from the West or the East".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8b5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.8.9.10.11. 21. 22 sixteen P.D.Rs.) hhh 13. U.S. Strikes</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8c5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">Adverse comment on the U.S. coal strikes continues (Six Regions). "The Americans haven't yet got the right attitude to the war", "this sort of thing doesn't help to promote good relations between our two countries".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8d5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">However, people from mining districts are reported to feel strongly sympathetic towards the U.S. miners - "they should pay them froth the time they reach the bottom of the pits; that's only fair and should go for us too".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">Reactions to the latest settlement have not yet boon received.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE .7.8.10.11. 21.) hhh 14. The Labour Party Conference</note>
				<note xml:id="q-905c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">The conference is reported to have caused "considerable public interest" in Scotland end the' North Eastern Region, but much less in other Regions. The points causing most comment were:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-915c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">The vote against the Communist Party's application for affiliation: Though one report says that opinion was divided about this, the general reaction is said to have boon satisfaction and relief. Some take it as "a most hopeful sign that communism will soon be finished and done with in this country".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-925c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">The upholding of the electoral truce was widely approved.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-935c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">The election of the Treasurer: The result -was a surprise to many.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-945c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">The post-war treatment of Germany: There is some, interest in the Conference's division of opinion on this question, but there seems to be fairly general agreement with the view that Germany must be completely disarmed after the war. "Little or no sympathy" is reported with the attitude of Mr. Aneurin Bevan and his associates in condemning "so-called Vansittartism within the Labour Party".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-955c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">The Labour Party's post-war plans are said to have "caused some disquiet in circles: who pay 10/- in the £1 in income 'tax and who fear that capital and savings will be confiscated".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-965c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">The B.B.C. and the Conference: Many liked the B.B.C. reports of the Conference, particularly the recording of parts of the actual speeches, though some thought it took up too much of the B.B.C.'s time.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-975c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">(2.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.13) hhh 15. Holidays</note>
				<note xml:id="q-985c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">Whitsun holidays: Reports from the South Western Region and indicate that there was a good deal of travelling over Whitsun. In Bristol, workers found difficulty in getting to their work, with restricted services and holiday crowds and residents of holiday resorts and rural villages complained of food and transport difficulties.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-995c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">Summer holidays: "A stronger desire than ever" to get (Away from home this year - particularly among women - is reported from five Regions this week. People feel that "holidays at home will have to be super-attractive to counter this urge "Weary war-workers" who feel that they deserve a holiday away, are saying "that the Govern­ment should either arrange to stagger holidays, or devise extra transport so that .we can get away".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">Factory workers are worried about the question of paid holidays and there are already rumours, from a London suburb, of a factory which does not intend to pay its employees for the holiday period; women workers are also anxious that their holidays shall coincide with their husbands' leave. Industrial workers want to know if the decision on these points rests with the employer or not.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">(2.3.5.7.8.9. 22 nine P.D.Rs.) hhh 16. Broadcasting and presentation of news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">Comment is again slight. "As news has been so good, people are less critical of its presentation".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9d5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">There are a few references to repetition in the news bulletins... 'The B.B.C. should be told net to weary tired people and expectant folk with dreary stories to fill in the news time". Two Regional reports mention that the news on the Empire and European Services is preferred to that on the Home Service, which is described as "dull and uninteresting".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9e5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">It is suggested that there is "too much playing up of tension over the forthcoming offensive in both Dress and radio". "Many people turn on their sets for each bulletin, expecting that any one my announce that invasion has begun."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9f5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">More photographs of R.A.F. raid damage are asked for.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a05c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">Praise is reported for Paul Winterton's postscript (June 6), and J. B. Priestley's broadcast (June 21). The broadcasts of the Oaks and Derby were much enjoyed in the North Eastern Region as "recaptur­ing for a few moments the pleasures of peace time".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a15c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">Criticism is reported of "The m a in the street". "His views are by no means the opinion of the man-in-the-street, and his voice and delivery arc not popular".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a25c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">(1.2.3.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11.13</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a35c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="94">II. GENERAL COMMENTS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a45c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">MONTHLY REVIEW hhh 7. Post-war conditions</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a55c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">Those who continue to disc post-war problems - and they are many - may he roughly divided into:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a65c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">(a) minority who "take the trouble to road about planning" or to join discussion groups; they would like more information on the subject, particularly wireless talks.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a75c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">(b) The groat majority who are in varying degrees apprehensive or "gloomy and cynical" about conditions after the war. (Among poorer people particularly, fears outweigh hopes.) Many believe that "the end of the war will moan the beginnin7 of our problems"; they fear that "the Government will side-track the Beveridge plan", that it is dominated by big business end monopoly concerns and that, in consequence, "we shell find our­selves at the end, of this war in the same position as we were in 1918....or even worse". The public "would be more content if they could ho told that definite schemes would come into action immediately hostilities cease".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a85c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">Matters of particular interest, and - for many people - concern are:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a95c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">(i) Employment: The worry and fear of unemployment continuo." People wonder "how all the men and women in the Forces will ever be absorbed into industry', what will be "the position of workers in the armament industries after the war", end "what will be done for women now taking men's places in industry". The small business man who has had to close down, or go into the Forces, is anxious about his chances of re-opening after the</note>
				<note xml:id="q-aa5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">(ii) Housing: "Present difficulties are coupled with a growing anxiety for the post-war provision of houses".... "There is a demand for more and better homes for men returning from the Forces, whose wives arc now living with parents," Apart from the question of shortage, people particularly Londoners - fear that "too many flats will be built, when people prefer the privacy of their own small houses", "Houses for families", it is felt, "should have at least three good bedrooms and space for pram accommodation, without needing to congested hall or parlour, laid-on water, gas and electricity" and, above all, indoor sanitation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ab5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">(iii) Health: A recent British Institute of Public Opinion result showed a considerable majority in favour of a State-run medical service. The chief reasons given for this view were that it would do away with preferential treat­ment for foe-paying patients, and that specialists would be available for all, Spontaneous comment indicates that there is some fear that "a state service would moan loss of choice of doctor"..."women, particularly, seem to dislike the thought of being obliged to accept any doctor alloca­ted to a district, instead of being able to choose their own". There is, too, some apprehension that a state service would "reduce everything to the level of the present panel".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ac5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">(iv) Regimentation: Some people fear that "post-war planning will mean dragooning, regimentation and loss of liberty to bureaucratic control". "The recent "ration book muddle" is said to have increased fears that "rules and regulations will govern our lives after the war". Nevertheless, these fears seem to be outweighed by the greater fear that "the whole matter will be left in the hands of private enterprise instead of being planned on' a national scale".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ad5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">Agriculture: There is some anxiety about the future of English farming after the war". The Government's agricultural policy is watched with interest, and it is hoped that "imports will not be allowed to force down home prices".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ae5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">A Special Postal Censorship report on Post-war Reconstruction states that two noticeable trends of opinion emerge from the examination of 791 extracts dealing with various angles of post-war world reconstruction:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-af5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">(i) "Insistence that members of the returning Forces, representing the younger generation, should play a force­ful part in coming internal and international affairs".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b05c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">(ii)A growing demand that women should be given a more responsible role, socially and politically, in post-war world administration." (This view is expressed more by women writers than by men.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b15c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="108">Other points noted include a diminished interest in Russia, a new interest in the possible advantages of emigration, some slight apprehension about state control, increased conjecture on post-war Europe, and a growing desire for retribution towards Germany.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b25c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="109">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11.13. 21 Special P.C.) hhh 18. Industry</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b35c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="110">Production: Over the past four weeks complaints of poor production have been reported from several Regions every week. Comment has been of a general nature, rather than criticism of specific firms. Workers are said to complain of "enforced idleness" and wasted time, and to feel in some cases "that their efforts are not put to the best use". Managements report slackness among workers, and com­plain of production held up by shortage of men and materials, or by lack of co-operation between Government Departments, Very few references are made to absenteeism. While the general public accept these complaints, they also feel that low production is due to bad relations between workers and management, to complacency on both sides, to the cost plus system, to income tax, and also to the following:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b45c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="111">(a) Tiredness of workers. Throughout the past four weeks there have been continual references to war strain, "edginess" and tiredness among workers. The chief causes are believed to be long; hours of work, coupled with Home Guard and fire-watching duties, and bad lighting and ventilation in some factories. The strain is thought to fall heavily on women - particularly older women - who have household responsibilities. In some cases women are believed to be doing work which is too heavy for them. There are reports of anemia and debility among women workers, and doctors are now said to be signing medical certificates for "industrial tiredness". The need for greater emphasis on the health of war workers is stressed in one report. Much illness and absenteeism, it is felt, would be avoided if it were made compulsory to produce a medical certificate of fitness on application for factory work.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b55c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="112">(b) Slacking or workers. People foul that where "clock watching" habits and "lack of a sense of urgency" exist among workers, they could be counteracted by more "frequent personal visits to factories of men who have been in action", and by explanations to workers of the uses to which their particular work will be put. While slacking is believed to be partly due to the general tiredness, a few references have been made to immorality, gambling and drunkenness in some factories.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b65c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="113">(c) Wages. Complaints of disparity in pay between skilled and unskilled workers, particularly in the engineering trade; and between workers in different factories doing similar jobs have been reported several times during the last four weeks. The high wages of unskilled workers are believed to be partly responsible for unrest among factory workers. High wages paid to some juveniles - and above all mentally defective juveniles are particularly deplored.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b75c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="114">Dissatisfaction among engineers at the results of the recent National Arbitration Tribunal Award was reported from several Regions at the beginning of the month, but no comments have been received during the past two weeks. Earlier in the month' there were two references to the low wages of railway workers, but, according to a report from one Region, the public are satisfied that an amicable settlement were made by the recent wages agreement between the railway employers and employees (announced in the press June 19).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b85c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="115">Strikes: Condemnation of strike action continues to be reported (Five Regions) and among non-industrial sections of the community there is a feeling that strikers "should be dealt with ruthlessly". Particular reference is made to:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b95c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="116">(a) Transport strikes: In Scotland the recent strike among the S.M.T. workers aroused resentment, and people were pleased that other arrangements were made for transporting workers to their place of work. In the Perth Eastern and 'North Midland Regions some anxiety exists among: the public, lest strike action be renewed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ba5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="117">(b) Swansea Valley coal strike: The recent strike of 4,000 miners in protest at the fines imposed on twenty-four colliers, is said to have aroused antagonism among non-mining sections of the community. "Young hot-heads" arc blamed for the trouble, and they are alleged to have "out-voted the older men" on the question of strike action, Employers and the non-mining public suggest conscription of the "young trouble-makers into the army".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bb5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="118">The Essential Work Order has been criticised both by managements who complain "of the arbitrary limitation of freedom", and by shipyard workers who believe that it "is used by officials to retard output". People fear that the restrictions imposed by the Order fall heavily on juveniles "who cannot change to more congenial work", and on married women (above the call-up ago) who wore working before the Order was introduced, and now find they cannot leave their work.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bc5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="119">Compensation to injured workers: Two references have been made to the difficulties of injured world men who have to wait a long time before they receive their final award. In many cases this imposes great hardship on their families. The maximum sum payable under the Workmen's Compensation Act is also considered inadequate in view of the present high cost of living and people ask why the Insurance Companies cannot pay more now, since their premiums are based on wages which have, on the whole, risen since the outbreak of war. Production in Northern Ireland: Reports from Northern Ireland stress the excellent results obtained from Sir Stafford Cripps' recent visit and tour of Northern Irish war production firms. Workers and management both appreciated his "goodwill and sincerity" and the general feeling appeared to be "that he is with everyone who puts war production first". His references to "the official tendency to shorten hours" and his stress on improving the technique of personnel management wore particularly appreciated.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bd5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="120">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.13. 21) hhh 19. Manpower</note>
				<note xml:id="q-be5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="121">During the past four weeks comment on the manpower situation has been chiefly concentrated on the call-up of older women, their difficulties, and their accusations against "young women dodgers", and on the "inexplicable and unnecessary transfer of labour". vEvasion of the call-up: Criticism, which is chiefly directed young married childless women and "select young ladies minimum of voluntary work" comes largely from women who fool that they should not be called on till all the younger "dodgers are rounded up". Complaints of evasion of the call-up by young men have decreased during the past four weeks.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bf5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="122">The transfer of labour: The purpose of transferring labour is still little understood. References to "this senseless merry-go-round" are still reported, and the Ministry of Labour is accused "of not minding who they send where, as long as they can show a transfer!" More specific comment is of:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c05c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="123">(a) Financial difficulties of workers transferred to loss remunerative work. Girls find "they cannot make both ends meet" living away from home, and wives with families find themselves in difficulties because they often do not get their money regularly from their menfolk.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c15c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="124">(b) Welfare facilities: Young girls are not properly supervised. In some towns, girls have to find their own billets, and more hostel accommodation is needed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c25c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="125">Call-up of married women: Some opposition to the direction of married women into industry has been reported from two or three Regions every weak, There is feeling that older Women, particularly "those in a critical period of their lives" and women with growing families should not be directed into factories.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c35c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="126">Women themselves complain that the Labour Exchanges do not provide adequate privacy for their interviews, that their "extenuating circumstances" arc not sufficiently taken into consideration, that the National Service Officer will not hoar their appeals and that "their lives have now become a slavery", with work and travelling time added to the burden of running a home. Married women are said to fear that "they will soon be directed into full-time work", and those without domestic responsibilities dread the possibility of "becoming mobile"; in a Fulham factory recently rumours were circulating that mothers with children of school age were about to be called up and directed into war work. It is suggested that some friction and disappointment would be eliminated if "the machinery of the call-up" were better understood. In some cases people are reported to be ignorant of the functions of the National Service Officer, the National Service Tribunals, and of their right of appeal against the call-up.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c45c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="127">During the past four weeks comment has also been reported on the following points: Shortage of domestic servants, particularly for old and infirm people.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c55c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="128">"Misdirection of labour": Allegations of men and women directed to "less suitable" and "less important" work have been reported, on a small scale.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c65c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="129">Shortage of Nursery accommodation has been reported from several areas. The need for more residential nursery accommodation and for night nurseries for mothers working on the night shift are particularly stressed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c75c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="130">Out-work: Demands for part-time work facilities have been received from villages in the Southern and South Western Regions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c85c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="131">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.3.9.10.11. 21) hhh 20. Miners and Mining</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c95c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="132">There has been considerable anxiety about the fuel position during the last four weeks, "discrepancies in official statements about coal supplies" having caused some bewilderment. "Major Lloyd George says it's O.K.; other speakers say we are facing a bad deficit." The possibility of a shortage next winter, "when we may not be so lucky with the weather", is feared.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ca5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="133">Criticism is directed at the miners. They are thought to be too much pampered. Some of the blame for low production is attributed to absenteeism and it is felt that "the Government should take action to make then work". In mining areas, however, it is felt that miners, particularly the older generation, are doing their share and "even being worked too hard".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cb5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="134">The practice of working only unproductive seems is also alleged. There is some belief that the mining industry is being mismanaged. "The whole situation badly needs cleaning up, and. any kind of exploitation on the part of miners or mine-owners stopped." A minority feeling is that only nationalisation will bring greater output. Others suggest that the "only practical remedy" is to comb the Services, and reserved occupations for experienced miners, and to direct more labour from other industries into mining. Miners, however, are against the practice of directing young men into the pits against their will. Carelessness results and men's lives consequently endangered.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cc5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="135">The miners themselves complain of the disparity in pay between them and munition workers. It is pointed out that men and boys are unlikely to work in the mines when they can get higher in more congenial jobs.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cd5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="136">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.7.8.9.10.11) hhh 21. Fuel and domestic coal There have been recurring complaints the bad distribution of coal. Coal merchants in some areas are said to have nothing sufficient stocks to meet legitimate demands, and, in view of Government exhortations to store coal for next winter, considerable dismay is being caused at the lack of supplies. There is some resentment that people who buy a bag at a tine are penalised by merchants; those buying in bulk usually receive their full allotment and are enabled to store up in preparation for the winter.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ce5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="137">The poor quality and high price of coal are also criticized. The poor quality is pit down to the owners closing the good seams until after the war.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cf5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="138">Fuel Rationing: From three Regions discussion on fuel rationing has been reported: "Quite a number of people are in favour of it if some fair method can be devised".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d05c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="139">In Wales, however, it is said that the South Wales public would be against fuel rationing. (1.2.3.4.5.7.8.9.10.13) hhh 22. Clothing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d15c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="140">There has been an increase during the past month in the Complaints of the inadequacy of clothing coupons. Women and growing children are said to be experiencing great difficulty. "The allocation is considered to cover too wide a range of commodities." Much resentment is still felt that household goods are on the personal ration, and the demand for a separate allowance of coupons remains fairly widespread.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d25c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="141">People are reported to "be looking forward to the new clothing period". "Many are praying for September 1." There is some speculation on the number and value of the new coupons. It is hoped that the position of children will be reviewed and a larger allo­cation made, especially in the case of "overgrown" children.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d35c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="142">Children's footwear: Complaints of the shortage and poor quality of children's footwear have increased. "The position is said to be acute and becoming a real anxiety to mothers." There is some criticism of the Board of Tradestatement (May 25) that three pairs of shoes are provided for each child a year. "Does anyone seriously think that growing children need only three pairs of shoes a year?"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d45c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="143">Shoe repairs: The difficulty in getting shoe repairs done and their poor quality arc fairly widespread. "Not only do people have to wait some time for the repairs but prices are high and workmanship bad." "The soles of repaired shoes are said to crack right across before being worn any length of time."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d55c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="144">Utility clothing: There are still some complaints of the poor wearing quality and high coupon value of utility stockings. They are said "to wear into holes in six hours". A few Regional reports refer to the shortage of non-utility corsets. Utility corsets are said to be of inferior quality and very ill-fitting. "Three pairs now have to be purchased in twelve months where one was sufficient in pre-mar days."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d65c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="145">Quotas: There have been a few references to ''quota systems" in shoe shops. Workers complain that they cannot possibly roach the shops before these quotas are sold. It is asked what the assistants do with their time when the shops are only open for an hour.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d75c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="146">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.3.9.10.11.13. 21. 22 eight P.D.Rs. 32) hhh 23. Food</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d85c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="147">Satisfaction with the food situation as a whole has been reported throughout the past month. Complaints of the fish shortage have declined in volume and the only widespread and per­sistent grumbles have been over the shortage and elusiveness of fresh fruit and tomatoes; these arc again reported this week, on almost exactly the same lines as last (Fresh fruit, cloven Regions; Tomatoes, eight Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d95c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="148">The scarcity of fresh fruit, however, now appears to have stimulated criticism of the "alleged full fruit standard jam" (Four Regions). There is much disappointment - particularly among those who have been taking sugar instead of jam - that most of the soft fruit is to go to the jam manufacturers, but even those who approve this policy "complain bitterly of the quality of jam now offered".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-da5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="149">During the past month the following have been the subject of repeated but not widespread comment:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-db5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="150">Oranges: There is said to be a growing feeling that "as the under fives get other priorities in the way of milk, eggs and fruit juices", the growing children ever five should get the oranges. Even if the under fives get the first chance, "a second period should be introduced for children between 5 - 12". There have also been complaints of "bad distributions": "adults are obtaining supplies, while school children have to go without". One report mentions "strong criticism of public houses getting oranges easily for slicing into drinks".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="151">The fat ration has been mentioned in reports from five Regions the last month. An increase would be welcomed (i) for sandwiches, "when workers nave no moans of feeding at a British Restaurant or canteen", and (ii) for home baking, to obviate queuing for-cakes.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="152">Packed lunches for workers: The difficulty in providing those has been reported from five Regions. The shortage of cheese, fats and cakes are all mentioned in this connection.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="153">Meat: There have been a number of complaints about what is described - incorrectly - as "meat zoning". Thus, in the Eastern Region, people complain of "eternal beef" or "eternal mutton", while in the London and North Eastern Regions they bemoan the long run of pork. Pork is thought to be unwholesome in hot weather, and expensive. (1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11.13. 21 all provincial P.Cs. 22 passim.) hhh 24. The Ration took distribution</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="154">Criticism of "the original chaos and confusion" is said to have subsided, and in most Regions distribution is reported to be proceeding smoothly.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e05c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="155">Complaints of travelling long distances arc only reported from rural areas in the Northern and Southern Regions this week, and the only complaints of queueing come from some districts in the North Midland Region.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e15c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="156">(1.2.3.5.5SE.6.7.10.21.22 twenty-three P.D.Rs.) hhh 25. Shopping difficulties</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e25c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="157">Shopping difficulties, particularly for workers, and shop­keepers' preferential treatment of certain customers have been reported steadily throughout the past month. Complaints on both scores appear to have been n stimulated by tie arrival of fresh fruit, tomatoes, and new potatoes in such quantities as to stimulate the longing without gratifying the taste.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e35c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="158">The two main sections of the population who feel that they are treated are:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e45c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="159">(a) Workers, who complain that: (i) "all the delicacies go to those who have time to queue for them" or, failing that, to the shop assistants; (ii) "shops are closed when needed, and open in hours when no one can get at them"; (iii) "all the best food has 'gone by Saturday afternoon"; (iv) "in many cases shop-­keepers will not allow workers' neighbours to eat their rations for them". Suggestions from the public are that: (i) there should be some staggering of mid-day shop closing; (ii) shops should stay open later, now that the evenings are lighter; (iii) rare foods of all kinds should be on points; (iv) "points goods should be released at 1.0 p.m. on Saturdays, instead of Mondays, so that workers cart have an equal chance of getting things that are scarce".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e55c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="160">(b) Residents in holiday resorts, who complain that the trippers buy up the limited supply of rationed goods.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e65c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="161">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.7.8.9.10.11) hhh 26. Servicemen, their pensions and dependants</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e75c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="162">The "whole problem of pensions in all its aspects, but particularly those relating to disability pensions for ex-service-men and women", has been widely discussed. The Government's "meanness" and "failure to tackle the problem boldly" have been very much criticised.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e85c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="163">The "meagerness" of ex-servicemen's pensions is deplored. They are considered "an example of how the men will be treated after the war". Feeling is particularly strong about men who are discharged without pensions on the grounds that their disability dates from pre-service days. "If four or five doctors can pass a man as A.1. then it is clear that his illness must be due to war service."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e95c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="164">Servicemen's dependants' pensions and allowances are also criticised. "The drastic reduction of income which often takes place when a serviceman's wife first receives a widow's pension" is considered particularly unjust. Servicemen themselves are said to be distressed at the thought of their dependants suffering in the event of their being incapacitated or killed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ea5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="165">The setting up of pensions appeal tribunals has been welcomed, though they are considered belated. It is also felt that the number contemplated is too small for the volume of work they will have to tackle.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-eb5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="166">Much interest is being taken in the Pensions Bill. One report says that it is, "exercising the public's mind more than anything else outside the war effort".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ec5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="167">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10. 21 one Special P.C.) hhh 27. Local Authorities and Service pay</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ed5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="168">Resentment at the making up of Service pay to peacetime salary rates in the case of local Government staffs, has been reported from the North Eastern and Worth Western Regions. wives "resent their rates being used for this, when their own husbands in the Forces do not got their pay made up".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ee5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="169">(2.10) hhh 28. Old Age Pensions</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ef5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="170">The inadequacy of Old Age Pensions has been widely criticised during the last four weeks. They are considered "totally inade­quate in view of the increased cost of living". Some Budget concessions, it is felt should have been made to old age pensioners. hhh 29. Transport and petrol</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f05c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="171">Complaints of the earl stomping of buses in the evening have increased slightly during a month. It is felt that "while double summer time is on, trains and buses might run an hour later in the evening".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f15c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="172">Overcrowding of buses is also the cause of some complaint. This is said to have been aggravated by the distribution of ration books. Crowding out of long distance travelers by short distance ones is again complained of. It is suggested that ld. and 1.5d. fares should be eliminated during peak periods.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f25c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="173">Petrol: During the past month there have been a few references to the waste and misuse of petrol. There are still thought to be too many large private cars on the road and taxis being misused. It is said that petrol has been wasted in "'Wings for Victory" weeks and parades, while business men cannot got enough for their work and are consequently disgruntled.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f35c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="174">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.9.10.11.13) hhh 30. Housing and Billeting</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f45c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="175">The shortage of housing accommodation continues to be a serious difficulty. Expectant mothers and families with children are mentioned as being particularly "heard hit". "Many, in desperation, take accommodation which is unsuitable and has a detrimental effect upon health." The high price of accommodation is complained of, and action is requested "to check the soaring prices of so-called furnished rooms".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f55c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="176">Billeting difficulties continue to be experienced in some Regions. There are complaints of wealthy people in large houses with rooms untouched by the billeting officer, whereas working-class people are forced to take billetees. In industrial areas, it is said, "the digs situation leaves much to be desired". In Slough the need for further hostel accommodation for war workers is urged.... "It is not uncommon for two men who are strangers to be asked to share a bed, although in the Army this is a crime".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f65c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="177">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.3.9.10.11) hhh 31. Agriculture</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f75c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="178">Government rural housing scheme: A good deal of critical comment has been reported from agricultural areas during the past four weeks on the-scheme for building farm cottages. People do not like the design and object to the use of concrete; but one report suggests that criticism springs from real ignorance of the design, and that the building of sample cottages would do much to counteract unfavourable comment. The delay in putting the scheme into operation is also criticised, in view of the urgent need of rural houses; in some areas: the allocation of sites is considered unsatisfactory. .The number proposed is thought to be inadequate, and people fear "a drift of newly-weds to the towns in the post-war era" if the shortage is still acute when peace comes. There are also complaints of high rents, and of the difference between the government subsidy and the building costs; it is asked "why the cost of building should be so high when the Government has a right to control building costs".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f85c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="179">The requisitioning of farmland for military purposes, afforestation and, in the Northern Region, for coal borings, has been criticised by farmers during the past month, It is felt that the military and civil authorities should show more consideration to the farmer, and endeavour not to take the more valuable land. In the North Western Region farmers complain that they cannot buy such good land as the farms which have been taken from them, and they say that they crop obliged to turn to dairy farming which yields them a smaller income.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f95c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="180">Wastage of crops: Two references have been Made to the non-collec­tion of cabbage and beet crops, and farmers appeal for better methods of collection next year.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fa5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="181">Harvest help: Farmers continue to express fears that labour will be short at harvest time-and suggest that labourers be released from Home Guard duties during this period, or that local troops should be made available to help. Some farmers are still said to be sceptical about "the Value of town helpers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fb5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="182">Arrangements for the holiday harvesting scheme are said to be going forward in the S. Western Region but in the Bournemouth and Surrey areas people complain that little progress is being made.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fc5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="183">Prospective helpers in the North Eastern Region still want more detailed information, and asks if the Citizen's Advice Bureau cannot be supplied with it. ''Other would-be helpers are worried about the low pay. Londoners would find the scheme more attractive if arrangements could be made for them to go away by twos or threes, or in families.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fd5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="184">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.) hhh 32. Salvage</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fe5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="185">Complaints of the non-collection or irregular collection of salvage have continued during-the last four weeks (Ten Regions). "Householders, are beginning to wonder if there is in fact a real demand for the material which they so carefully collect," Appeals in the press and on the radio are criticised; "the public are completely aware of the need for saving paper, books and rubber, but often find great difficulty in having them removed. It le local authorities who need to be Made salvage conscious - not the house­wife."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ff5c88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="186">Criticism is growing at the hundreds of dumps" lying around, some, it is said, for over two years. The public are also "shocked and amazed" at seeing everything "lumped together by the dustman".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-005d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="187">The removal of railings: There has been criticism and a good deal of dissatisfaction at the collection of railings from private property, particularly "since so many dumps of metal are seen to be left untouched over long periods (Eight Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-015d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="188">Particularly strong feeling exists where young children are left exposed to traffic dangers, The ban on the building of wooden gates adds to this feeling. The "official answer calling for 'parental control' is greeted contemptuously".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-025d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="189">In agricultural areas there is also criticism of the removal of railings "where herds of cattle and sheep are continually being driven", or where animals are loose at tight near houses.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-035d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="190">The "wanton damage" done by "the disgraceful methods of removal", is also criticised. There are complaints that the railings after remailer are lying in gardens for a long time, and that some merchants are hoarding ornamental ones till after the war.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-045d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="191">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.7.8.9.10.13. 21 one provincial P.C.) hhh 33. Health</note>
				<note xml:id="q-055d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="192">Complaints of physical and nervous fatigue have been reported frequently during the past month. Absenteeism and industrial unrest are attributed partly to the strain of long working hours combined with extra Civil Defence and household duties. Many feel the need of a "real holiday" women workers who are "carrying on a double job" being particularly mentioned.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-065d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="193">People are inclined to blame "vitamin deficiency in the war­time diet" for the prevalence of skin troubles, indigestion, colds and general debility and to feel some resentment of official statements that "the health of the nation is better than before the war".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-075d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="194">Tuberculosis: There is comment on the growing fear of an increase in tuberculosis. The distribution of dirty milk in Derby, reported earlier in the month, is still a cause for anxiety.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-085d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="195">Maternity cases: The shortage of accommodation for maternity cases is reported (three Regions). "Expectant mothers have sometimes to travel at least twenty-five miles for free hospital accommodation."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-095d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="196">Diphtheria: The British Anti-vaccination Society leaflet which is being circulated in parts of the North Midland Region has met with disapproval. (1. 2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9. 10.11) hhh 34. Venereal diseases campaign</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0a5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="197">The campaign continues to be approved, but there is increased demand for more lectures to young people on sex education, and for talks by competent people to older children before leaving school. It is thought that the present method tends to suggest that "V.D. is nothing to fear, provided treatment is promptly sought". Some people favour compulsory medical examination every year. There is also some demand for up-to-date statistics, and a query as to whether "the alleged increase is really an increase, or due to the fact that with so many people in the Services we are getting details of cases which would normally be unrecorded".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0b5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="198">(3.5.8.9.10) hhh 35. Income Tax</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0c5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="199">Dislike of the present method of paying income tax has been reported from five Regions during the last four weeks. Workers in munition factories particularly arc concerned at the arrears they might have to pay should war manufacture suddenly cease. The present system encounters "the strong working-class fear of running up debts".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0d5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="200">Trouble occasionally crises now when workers are transferred from one job to another at a lower rate of pay, or when overtime is out. The "urgency of a pay as you go system is considered proved, in view of the adoption of such a scheme in America".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0e5d88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="201">(1.2.4.5.9.)</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>