<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Letter dated 10 May 1944 from A J Hewling to Secretary of State</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-85ae026b-e22b-4722-85de-6c6b1edb6811</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-ec40effc-a482-4e42-85f6-33a47251d2e8</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-38547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">Register No.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-39547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">Minute Sheet No.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3a547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="3">CONFIDENTIAL.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3b547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="4">Secretary of State.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3c547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">You asked me for some thoughts on Army morale and the machinery in the War Office for assessing it.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3d547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">About the importance of morale in the Army there can be no two opinions. Unless we have an Army willing to fight, we shall not win this war, no matter how perfect our plans, organisation or equipment. To be willing to fight, the Army must believe in the cause in which it is fighting; this is the most important point: second in importance, the Army must believe that it is being given a reasonable chance to fight under the best possible conditions for a successful outcome.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3e547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">Fundamentally, therefore, the basis of good morale is belief in the cause. History teems with examples of a successful fight made in a good cause with inferior weapons, though as modern war gets more complex so does the triumph of the good cause depend increasingly on good weapons.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3f547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">It is not unprofitable from this angle to attempt to analyse the state of Army morale after Dunkirk in 1940. The 300,000 odd soldiers who came back from Dunkirk were not, by and large, in any way a defeated Army so far as their morale was concerned. An angry Army they were in many respects: angry with suspected defeatism and lack of fight in some portions of their Continental allies; angry with shortcomings in equipment, air support and with other partly-true and partly-imagined shortcomings of the British military machinery; but angry above all with the enemy, and determined to give him back blow for blow at the earliest opportunity. The German invasion of this country in 1940 might have succeeded through overwhelming superiority of armaments; there is no reason whatever to think it would have succeeded through the Army not fighting it out with the Germans a l'cutrance - what the R.A.F. did in the Battle of Britain does not in any way mean that they had a monopoly of the will to fight.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-40547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">On the equipment side the British Army has now at long last made up its deficiencies, and probably every member of 21 Army Group believes he will go into the coming battle as well armed or better than his foe. Further, the course of the war, revealing in ever darker colours the innate beastliness of the Boche has not in any way weakened the average British soldier's desire to exterminate the Nazi and all his works. But the longer the war goes on, the more does the soldier tend to give importance to his actual conditions of service, and the conditions of life of his family and dependants, matters which in the first flush of enthusiasm in the early stages of a war are relegated well to the background. It is, in a way, the soldier's manifestation of war weariness; it is a perfectly natural and inevitable development, and not in itself a matter far-undue blame.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-41547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">Equally, as the war goes on Army morale (and the same, of course, applies to the other Services and even the civilian population) becomes a more and more important factor, in its two-fold aspect of:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-42547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">(a) maintaining belief in the cause; and</note>
				<note xml:id="q-43547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">(b) maintaining the soldier in a contented frame of mind.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-44547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">Again, the nearer the war gets to its probable termination, the more the soldier's mind tends to leap over the closing stages of the war and pre­occupies itself with the problems of his re-absorption into civilian life and work. In other words, the latter part of any great war brings with it its own morale problems, largely different from those of the early stages of the war, requiring different solutions, and - this is the important point - calling for much more far-sighted diagnosis, fore-thought and planning.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-45547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">So much by way of preamble to the immediate problem.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-46547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">The member of Council responsible to you for the morale of the Army is A.G. Morale is so important a factor in the war-time Army that no Secretary of State could rest happy unless he received periodical assessments of the state of morale in the Army from the responsible Member of Council; and indeed, anything seriously wrong with Army morale very soon obtrudes itself on a Secretary of State's notice in the form of Parliamentary Questions, Press comment, correspondence, or many other less obvious ways.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-47547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">In order to (a) inform himself as to the state of Army morale and (b) submit from time to time reports to you on that question, A.G. may be expected to require some machinery, since he cannot himself cover more than a limited field by personal visits and tours, however important these may be. For good or ill the present A.G. has evolved a fairly detailed machinery for assessing the morale of the Army; different men use different methods, and if A.G. gets the kind of information he needs for fulfilling his own responsibility in the matter of morale, then presumably it is not for others to interfere.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-48547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">The real test is what A.G. produces to you as a result of his morale machinery, and whether experience shows that his machine enables him to make accurate diagnosis of the state of Army morale; and it is relevant that you are not without outside checks upon A.G's assessment of Army morale, in the form ­as mentioned above - of Parliamentary and Press re-actions, and your correspondence bag; no film star can hope to rival the fan-mail of a minister who really "puts his foot into it" in Service matters affecting the rank and file or their dependents.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-49547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">The real trouble with the presentation of Army morale by A.G's Department in the past seems only partly with the methods by which information about morale is obtained; it is rather with the screening and sifting of that information, the sorting out of the grains of gold from tons of rubbish, and the presentation to you of a sufficiently and "in proportion" view of the whole field of Army morale.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4a547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">You have rightly pointed out that recent Quarterly Morale Reports have consisted largely of recitals of grievances; in deference to your comment thereupon, A.G. has lately attempted some numerical assessment of the more prominent grievances to which he draws attention; but even so, grievances are only one (and perhaps the less important) aspect of morale, and that its negative aspect. A grievance may be felt by, say, a particular searchlight detachment in this country. One or two hundred searchlight detachments similarly placed in the U.K. may, to a greater or lesser extent, share that grievance. It will therefore figure in the reports of a considerable number of Commanders. But what one would expect A.G's. Department to do is to ascertain whether the grievance is a temporary difficulty or not; whether it is easily remediable or not; whether it is just one of those things which are part of the inevitable conditions of life of isolated searchlight detachments; or whether the grievance is shared by other kinds of troops and is evidence, therefore, of something wrong on a wide scale with a particular aspect of Army service. Only after some such careful process of quantitative and qualitative assessments should A.G. bring it to your notice as a matter requiring definite and positive action in the interests of Army morale. On the other hand, it is A.G's job to see whether even the more or less limited grievances can reasonably be put right, and to take up with other Members of Council as necessary, the problem of finding a remedy.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">This line of thought leads to the conclusion that the machinery which A.G. requires to assess the state of Army morale is largely a matter for his own determination. Different A.Gs. will work in different ways. But the reports on the general state of Army morale which A.Gs. make to you as S. of S. should be reports written with a due sense of proportion and perspective, with not too much detail to obscure the main outlines, i.e. the old question of the wood and the trees. The form which the short reports on the state of morale at home, produced in recent months by the Ministry of Information, has much to recommend it from this angle, whether those reports were good or not in substance. To put it another way: A.G. should present you with a picture of Army morale painted with the impressionistic brush of a Turner and not with microscopic detail of a Cenaletto: the details he can always supply on demand.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">Turning now to the attached B.M.: A.G. in minute 15 attempts to persuade you to concurrence in a continuance of the present morale machinery: for the reasons set out above, I think that is really a matter for A.G. himself to determine, within his responsibility to you for Army morale, provided that-he produces what you want in the way of morale information. At 16A he presents his latest Morale Report in a form which he hopes will commend itself to you: to the extent to which he has grouped difficulties and grievances under a few broad heads, and tried both to assess their substance and to indicate what is being done or is possible to do to remedy the matter, 16A appears a much more acceptable form of the Morale Report. You will have gathered from what is said above that this is not the form of report I think A.G. might be expected to put up to you, but that something on far broader lines and less a collection of (however real) grievances, is what is wanted.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">The other possible defect of the existing morale machinery is perhaps even more important, and certainly of increasing importance.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">The existing morale machinery probably ensures that no substantial grievances of the troops or hardship of their conditions of service goes unrecorded, and to that extent it covers one aspect of morale fairly thoroughly. But grievances are only a "spotty rash" upon the Army body which indicates a state of illness within that body-, and though very useful for diagnostic purposes, the more important thing is preventive hygiene for avoiding the spots coming out. The point I am trying to labour is that morale should not only be concerned with the "present discontents" .but should, to an even greater extent, .be looking ahead to foresee probable causes of trouble and enable anticipatory preventive action to be taken: the medical analogy, though obvious, is a very good one.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">This function of the morale machine is likely to be of the highest importance in the period which will follow the coming Continental battle. Assuming a reasonably short, however intense, campaign in Europe, the problem of Army morale, as I see it, will bear two main aspects. In the first place there will be the problem of keeping those in good heart who have to remain with the Colours to finish off the Japanese war; in the second place there will be the, perhaps even more difficult, task of ensuring reasonable contentment among the large number at home and overseas (particularly overseas) who are earmarked for release at the end of German hostilities, but who, by reason of the necessary time taken by the machinery of release and through shipping shortages, organisational problems, etc., can only be brought back to civil life over a period of months or even a year or more. Experience indicates that the latter aspect is likely to be by far the more troublesome one.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-50547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">The Army can claim credit for having been the prime mover in commencing a study of the problem of maintaining morale in the Armed Forces to fight the war with Japan, a problem which is now being actively studied by the Inter-Services Committee under the chairmanship of Brigadier O'Donnell. I understand this Committee is producing very soon an interim report, not by way of a blue print or the measures necessary for meeting this problem, but to give an early indication of the scope and nature of the problem. It has associated with it Ministry of Information representatives, and for the present purpose this aspect of the dual Morale problem can be regarded as covered by the future activities of O'Donnell's Committee.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-51547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">But no similar body has yet been charged with pulling together the manifold aspects of the problem of the "releasable" soldier. The War Office (in consultation with other departments) have made many plans which impinge upon this problem, for example the planning of education during the demobilization period, the many measures taken to facilitate the whole demobilization machinery and make it work quickly and smoothly, the plans for providing good civilian clothing for the released soldiers etc. etc. What seems, however, to be needed, is some committee or body to look at the problem of the "releasable" soldier as a whole, to see that all main foreseeable needs of the transition period from total mobilization to partial mobilization for the Japanese war are covered, and (not least) to ensure some sense of proportion among the many plans which relate to that period and which concern both "releasable" soldiers and the soldier retained for the Japanese war. Further, the problem is not solely a Service one; it largely also concerns the Minister of Labour., who has to co-operate in the vocational training of the "releasable" soldier and smooth his reception into the possibly not too friendly atmosphere of civilian employment; the Board of Education, which will be concerned with the special needs of the student and young professional class; the Colonial Office, India Office, etc. who will want to recruit promising men for "the white man's burden"; and many other departments for their special interests. The main problem, however, will be for the three Service Departments and the Ministry of Labour, and it seems that the nucleus of any committee or body which is to study this aspect of Army morale after German hostilities ought, as its nucleus, to comprise representatives of these four Departments.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-52547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">Clearly, both as concerns the Japanese war aspect and the demobilization aspect of morale after the end of the German war, the War Office should be far less concerned with tackling troubles as they arise than that of planning to avoid their arising. In an imperfect world the 100% foolproof and event-proof plan is not practice but, particularly in the light of the experience of 1919, many troubles will be avoidable by adequate forethought, and it is not too soon to begin the thinking process now.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-53547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">Attempting to sum up: what is suggested is:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-54547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">(a) A.G. is responsible to you for the morale of the Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-55547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">(b) In fulfilling this responsibility he should present you, from time to time, with a general picture of the state of Army morale at home and abroad; this general picture should not enter into such detail as results in difficulty in distinguishing the general shape of the wood from the shape of individual trees.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-56547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">(c) There is something to be said for the reversion to the practice of the early Morale Reports at the beginning of 1942, when the Quarterly Report was presented to the E.C.A.C. and discussed by them; such discussion could be a stage preceding any periodical report made to you by A.G., or alternatively the E.C.A.C. could, after discussion of the Morale Report, make a submission to you on any major "discontents" which represented a serious threat, present or potential, to the morale of the Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-57547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">(d) The morale machine should be concerned not only with assessment of "present discontents", but as much, and possibly in future even more, with future threats and the avoidance of foreseeable problems calculated to militate against the maintenance of a high morale in the Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-58547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">(e) Particularly after the German hostilities cease, the morale problem will be in the main two-fold: on the one side the morale problem of the Japanese war, now being explored by Brigadier O'Donnell's committee, and on the other side the problem of the "releasable" personnel for which some special machinery including Ministry of Labour representation, is desirable.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-59547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">(f) Further, Army morale and its problems are not confined within the bounds of A.G's. periodical reports or the reports from Commanders on which they are based; part and parcel of the morale problem is the education of the soldier, by A.B.C.A. and the B.W.P. pamphlets: the Parliamentary Questions which so often represent the first airing of an Army grievance; the War Office post-bag and particularly the Ministerial post; and many other War Office day to day concerns: is A.G. sufficiently aware of some of these aspects of the morale problem which do not necessarily come directly within the preview of his Department.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">(g) Finally, the morale machinery should be two-way; it should not only obtain reports from Commanders and impress on those Commanders that the careful assessment of morale of the troops under them is one of their most important personal responsibilities; it should also produce in return to the Commander guidance upon the main problems which Commanders' reports have put forward and also a directive on policy to be adopted or action to be taken to avoid foreseeable troubles in the future. At present this "return action" of the morale machine seems only to be fulfilled by the War Office commentary upon the major grouped grievances (see 16A).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">I apologise for the length of this note; its excuse is some attempt to get at the elements of the problems as a precedent course to indicating</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="37">10 May, 1944.</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>