<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Extracts from the Quarterly Report on the Army Morale Feb-May 1942</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-97226517-b2b5-40f9-8924-e8eecd8689c5</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-1e44b046-e85e-4652-816b-b3e188698bc9</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-0d547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="1">Extracts from the Quarterly Report on Army Morale Feb.-May, 1942</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0e547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="2">CONFIDENCE hhh Confidence in the Army’s cause and in its leaders and in the progress of the War.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0f547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="3">There is no trace of defeatism, apathy, or lack of confidence in the outcome of the war in any of the sources used in compiling this Report, in spite of several adverse factors which have to be reckoned with during the period under review, viz.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-10547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="4">(i) reverses in the Far East;</note>
				<note xml:id="q-11547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">(ii) Press attacks on the Army and on the leadership of the country in general; - against this, however, may be set the better weather and pleasanter conditions generally of Spring, and a feeling of optimism, which grew in strength during the last month, and is apparently founded on the belief that "something will happen" in the near future.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-12547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">(i) Reverses in the Far East.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-13547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">These do not seem to have had a seriously depressing effect on the Army. Officers seem to have been upset by them more than Other Ranks, perhaps because they know more geography; to the average soldier Singapore is just "another defeat".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-14547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">(ii) Press Attacks.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-15547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">There is no evidence that the recent press campaign had an appreciable influence on the outlook of the average soldier. On the other hand, a study of the troops' mail suggest that the feelings upon which the Press sought to play, by echoing them in a distorted and exaggerated form, do exist in a large proportion of the rank and file.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-16547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">It appears from the mail that an increasingly large number of soldiers, when confronted by bad news of the war, or by apparent instances of inefficiency or unfairness, are inclined, first, to blame not their national or military leaders but the whole of "the existing system"; second, to express a resolve that the system must be different "after the war"; and, third, to point a contrast with Russia, which is apparently believed to be a paradise of complete freedom and perfect efficiency.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-17547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">Such reflections are often evidently the result of depressing surroundings or bad war news or both; but they are too frequent to be dismissed as the stock complaints of the professional "grouser" or the amateur politician, and Commanders' reports confirm that a very large proportion of the rank and file are preoccupied by the question of what, if any, social and economic changes will take place after the war, and that the certainty of employment in what they consider satisfactory conditions is the nearest thing to "war aim" that most soldiers can be said to have at the moment. Vague assurances from politicians or others, and exhortations to join in a "crusade", do not reassure them on this point. Nor does it seem that they realise how much the worst of the possible consequence of victory is to be preferred to the best of the possible consequences of defeat.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-18547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">On the other hand, only a very small proportion of letters echo the press in its indiscriminate abuse of high authorities; it is the "old school tie" that is the target rather than the "brass hat". Where there is criticism of officers, it is of junior commanders who do not know their jobs properly, and not of senior commanders, about whom it seems that the average soldier knows little, and whom he is inclined to take on trust.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-19547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">Among politicians, Mr. Churchill is still trusted; others are rarely mentioned by name, and there is no enthusiasm for the Government as a team.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1a547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">Confidence is not increased by the manner in which war news is given out by the B.B.C.; there are frequent complaints about this in the letters from the men and in Commanders' reports. The Army evidently prefers facts to "chat" and does not wish that unpalatable facts should be sweetened or disguised.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1b547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">Several Commanders report that [illegible: A.B.C.] performs a useful function by creating a proper sense of proportion in the minds of the men; in particular these talks have helped to destroy the legend of the "invincible" German Panzer Unit.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1c547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="16">CONTENTMENT hhh General</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1d547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">Much light on topics affecting the contentment of the troops is thrown by by [twice, as in the original - Marion] the letters (which number hundreds in each week) from soldiers and their families received (a) by The News of the World and (b) by the B.B.C. as a result of Professor Hilton's weekly broadcast to the troops.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1e547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">Far the most frequent topic in these letters is that of allowances to dependants, most of the letters concerning which came from the men's families. The second most frequent topic is transfer within the Army, or between the Services, or from the Army into civilian life; most of these letters come from the men themselves. Other matters which bulk large in the correspondence are pay, pensions and leave. Miscellaneous complaints, grievances, and requests for information make up a fair proportion of the letters, but these taken all together do not equal the number dealing with allowances or the number dealing with transfer.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1f547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">This confirms the impression gained from other sources that the main pre-occupation of the soldier, outside his military duties and training, are</note>
				<note xml:id="q-20547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">(1) the financial position of his family, and (2)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-21547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">a desire to be engaged in an occupation in which he can make use of his own special skill or aptitude. hhh Leave</note>
				<note xml:id="q-22547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">The Army seems to be satisfied with the amount of leave that is granted to it. There is no doubt that the troops prefer to take their leave in four periods of 7 days rather than in the form of a fortnight and two separate weeks; one of the reasons for this is that many men have not enough money to last them through a leave period of a fortnight.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-23547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">Finance - pay, allowances and expenses.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-24547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">(i) Every source used in compiling this report, including almost every single formation Commander, comments on the disparity between civilian and military rates of pay and allowance. The morale of soldiers' families seems to be affected perhaps more than that of the soldiers themselves, but hard circumstances in the home due to the inadequacy of the family allowance are no doubt in many cases a factor causing absence without leave. Comments arise particularly in units occupying quarters where civilian workmen are at work; and are particularly bitter where soldiers themselves are employed on work such as constructional work side by side with civilians drawing much higher pay and working and living under much easier conditions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-25547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">A similar unfairness is evident felt by troops who have opportunities of comparing their pay and conditions of life with those of the R.A.F.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-26547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">(ii) Reluctance or refusal to take a commission, on financial grounds, is still very frequently expressed by N.C.Os. and others writing to their families - often men who have been singled out as potential officers by their C.O's.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-27547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">(iii) The scheme for post-war audits has not evoked much enthusiasm, according to reports from more than one Divisional Commander. This is borne out by the letters from the troops. hhh Conditions affecting Families</note>
				<note xml:id="q-28547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">(i) Several Divisional Commanders report that there is a general feeling that Family Allowances are inadequate, and letters from the troops and from their families reveal that worries arising on this score are the chief pre-occupation in the minds of soldiers and their people at home.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-29547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">(ii) The conscription of women into the Services is still unpopular, but its necessity seems to be being gradually accepted and attempts to dissuade their correspondents from joining are not so frequently made by soldiers. This may be in many cases because the matter is by now a fait accompli and not because the soldier feels differently about it. hhh Relations with other Services etc.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">(i) Relations with R.A.F.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">In general, soldiers do not feel kindly towards members of the R.A.F. ground staff, who are said to adopt an arrogant and superior attitude and to bask in the rays of glory reflected from the men who fly. Soldiers also feel that the R.A.F. is given an unfair share of publicity and exaggerated glorification at the expense of the Army both by the Press and by the B.B.C. This is not made easier to bear by the knowledge that the R.A.F. are better off than the Army in the matter of pay, allowances, leave, and living conditions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2c547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">(ii) Relations with the A.T.S.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">A.A. Divisional Commanders seem to be satisfied with the relations between their troops and the A.T.S. The work of the latter in "mixed" A.A. Regiments is admired by the men and unfavourable first impressions seem to have been removed on closer acquaintance.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">(iii) Relations with Dominion and U.S.A. Troops.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">(a) Jealousy of Dominion troops owing to their better pay and conditions is reported by several Divisional Commanders. The Canadians are said to diminish their chances of popularity by undue familiarity with the girls of British soldiers and by their lavish use of petrol, with which they are alleged to be in the habit of washing down their vehicles.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-30547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">(b) Relations with U.S.A. Troops do not appear to be altogether friendly, to judge from the men's letters. Commanders' reports show a division of opinion on this matter. The Americans spend their pay, which our men believe to be considerably higher than their own, freely in the N.A.A.F.I. and in local shops, thus creating in some districts in N. Ireland a serious shortage and rise in prices. Nor are they always very modest in their bearing. Feeling was aroused by an American soldier's shooting an Irish bus driver who failed to give way to him on the road, and was not allayed by a verdict of "Accidental Death" at the inquest. Exaggerated stories of the bad behaviour of American troops appear to be current in Northern Ireland, chiefly among the civilian population, who are not friendly to the Americans and try to influence our troops against them.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-31547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">It is reported that "Troops on leave from N. Ireland are drawing unfavourable comparisons between the arrangements made for the comfort of the U.S. troops and themselves. The comradeship between the officers and the men in the American Army is favourably commented on and admired".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-32547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">The two Forces, however, seem to become friendlier as they get to know each other better. hhh Influence of Women</note>
				<note xml:id="q-33547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">Commander, Airborne Division, reports as follows:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-34547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">"I am convinced, from evidence obtained in dealing with the few cases which have occurred of men refusing to jump, that there is a lack of the proper spirit of sacrifice and patriotism among some sections of the women in this country.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-35547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">The Commander of the Parachute Brigade, who has himself raised a Parachute Battalion, feels that the women tend to urge their menfolk in the forces to "play for safety" and only to do what they have to rather than do their utmost for the cause. This may be an exaggeration, but I am convinced the tendency exists."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-36547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">It appears from the troops' mail that reluctance to go overseas is often due to the influence of women, and from facts appearing in cases concerning absence or desertion that their influence is often instrumental in persuading men to overstay their leave. hhh MIDDLE EAST</note>
				<note xml:id="q-37547fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">Indignation persists in M.E.F. at the "invasion" of the U.K. by U.S. and Dominion troops; "Britain out of bounds to the British" is a catchword which has achieved currency in the M.E; it is often accompanied by references to lack of leave on the part of units who have been many months in the M.E;</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>