<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Quarterly Historical Report for the quarter ended 31 March 48</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-ae301128-a1aa-4313-bff9-e4a1a0e78882</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-a6c33665-5b70-43bc-aeaa-8ad8276841e1</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-34557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">War Crimes Group/43/Details</note>
				<note xml:id="q-35557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="2">QUARTERLY HISTORICAL REPORT for the quarter ended 21 Mar. 48</note>
				<note xml:id="q-36557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="3">of the War Crimes Group (H&amp;E) att for</note>
				<note xml:id="q-37557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="4">local adm to Bad Ooynhausen Garrison hhh 1. LOCATION.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-38557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">Bad Ooynhausen, Germany. Map ref. 1:250,000.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-39557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">Sheet L.53 W.7200. hhh 2. STRENGTH.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3a557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">Officers. 49 (within WE).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3b557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">Officers. 3 (att)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3c557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">ORs. 164 (within WE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3d557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">ORs. 2 (att) hhh 3. HO EMPLOYS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3e557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">a) During the first quarter of 1948 War Crimes Group (North West Europe) has continued in its primary role in exactly the same manner as it has done since its formation in January, 47.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3f557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">b) However, during this period the process of transferring extradition responsibilities to the Control Commission which commenced some 10 months ago became complete with the setting up of the C.C.G. Extradition Court in Hamburg in February and no alleged war criminals wanted by allied powers now remain in British Military custody.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-40557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">c) During the quarter 13 trials of war criminals have been concluded and three are in progress at the time of writing this report.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-41557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">d) The four heaviest cases dealt with during this period being the Burghelz Masssacre (one of the many cases arising out of the wholesale killing of East workers by the Gestapo and S.D. in Wehkreis VI during the last months of the War) which lasted twenty two days, the case of Bremen Farge Work Education Camp which lasted from 1 Jan. to 24 Feb., the Wilhelmshaven Yellow-Cress Prison case, which ran from 3 Feb. to 9 Mar. and the second Lahde-Weser Majors case which commenced on 3 Mar and which was concluded just before Easter.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-42557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">e) The number of fresh denunciations and reports of new War Crimes is now very small so that the weight of the Legal Section is now passing from the briefing of investigations to the preparation of investigated cases for trial. A good deal of incidental correspondence is still occasioned by the number of reports, appeals, inquiries, etc., concerning post-trial matters, denasification [?? - illegible] procedure and many other questions outside the scope of this Group's responsibilities received from diverse allied authorities, local Military and C.C.G. Offices, German lawyers and relatives of accused, convicted, extradited or interned persons and their spiritual advisers and also from professional associations, to whom it has to be explained that their letters are being referred to D.J.A.G. or the appropriate C.C.G. or Allied Authority as the case may be.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-43557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">f) These 13 trials meant that 59 persons stood trial for alleged war crimes of whom 47 were convicted, the balance being acquitted. Of the 47 convictions, 12 war criminals were sentenced to death by hanging whilst the remaining 35 were sentenced to varying terms of imprisonment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-44557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">g) During the last three months all Judge Advocates and prosecutors have been civilian barristers sent out from London (see para 3(j) of last report).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-45557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">h) In para 3(b) above ref was made to extradition responsibilities being handed to the Central Commission, but so far as this Group is concerned we still are contacted when British interest is involved and under this heading 51 war criminals have been cleared for extradition to other countries.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-46557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">i) In the early part of the quarter a review was carried out by members of this Group of all internees held in No.2 War Criminals Holding Centre, Fischbeck and of the cases against them, with a result that the number of internees held ………………… [missing from script - Marion]</note>
				<note xml:id="q-47557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">j) During the whole period the release of 469 persons held as alleged war criminals was authorised.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-48557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">k) The field Investigation Section of the Group has completed investigation into 44 cases, of which 21 resulted in sufficient evidence being produced to justify trial of certain accused.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-49557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">l) The Search Section of the Group has continued in its primary roll [LIBBY - should be 'role'? - Marion) of searching for and apprehending war criminals and members of Field Investigation Section and Search Section have journeyed throughout the British, American and French Zones of Germany in their quest for evidence and clues which might lead to the conviction or apprehension of suspected war criminals. hhh 4. ADMINISTRATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4a557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">a) Demobilisation during the current quarter has resulted in a serious drain of our available manpower and the number of releases has far outpaced the number of reinforcements posted.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">b) At the present time a serious shortage of clerks, especially NCOs, and Shorthand-Typists is evident within the Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">c) The fact that many of our best and most experienced clerks were in Age and Service Groups 66 to 68 (R.A.S.C.) was seen many months ago and appeals were made to Judge Advocate General's Dept. at the War Office and to GHQ 2nd. Echelon BAOR and also to "A" Branch, this H.Q. with a view to overcoming the difficulty and posting suitable replacements. However, only an old clerk or so has arrived and in the early part of this year it was decided to request the compulsory deferment of N.C.O. clerks in the Age and Service Groups concerned for a period of 3 months in order to see this Group into early May when a review of establishment and conditions would make a rundown possible. However, although the application for compulsory deferment was submitted, higher authority regretted they could not give this backing owing to the general dearth of clerks within the theatre.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">d) In the last report reference was made in para 4(d) to the possibility of a move of this Group to a new location but HQ BAOR have now agreed that this Unit will remain in BAD OEYNHAUSEN.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">e) The proposed change in establishment referred to in the December report has not yet been put into effect and at the present time a review of the whole establishment is in progress and it is thought there will be a considerable cut in the number of officers employed, especially in the Field Investigation Section of this Group. Consequent upon this, the Other Rank establishment will be reduced accordingly and our proposals for a minimum working establishment are now in course of preparation and submission to our sponsor Branch, J.A.G. at the War Office. It is anticipated that the establishment will be reviewed by the War Office Establishment Committee in April and as from May 1 this Group will be operating on a much revised establishment. The full reasons for permitting this revision will be dealt with in the following section, but the handing over of extradition responsibilities resulted in certain redundancies within the Executive (Trial and Extradition) Section of this Group. hhh 5. MISCELLANEOUS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">The Judge Advocate General's Military Deputy, Brigadier SHAPCOTT, [?? C/O - see ms.] OBE, MC., accompanied by Lt. Col. BARRETT, visited Germany during the third week in March, during which, in addition to a conference of this Group, they visited the Deputy Chief of the Legal Division, inspected Nos. 1 and 2 War Criminals Holding Centres and No. 200 War Crimes Trial Centre and attended trials at the Curie [Curio?? - see ms.] House, HAMBURG. Figures produced at the conference showed that on the day of No. 2 War Criminals Holding Centre's transfer from FISCHBECK to BRUNSWICK (15 March) there were held there 132 prisoners of whom, however, at least 38 were to be handed over for trial by Control Commission Courts. A further 99 alleged war criminals were in arrest elsewhere, in HAMBURG either on trial or awaiting trial, in No. 1 War Criminals Holding Centre, in No. 5 Civilian Internment Camp (women), three undergoing sentences in German prisons or awaiting transfer, others awaiting extradition from Allied authorities, in LONDON District Cage, or in open house-arrest. It was estimated that the gross total of 231 accused represented 80 awaiting advice from London (on cases already submitted), or under investigation, but that …………………. [missing from ms.] cases would probably be handed over to the C.C.G. It was considered that, assuming there were no extension of this Group's existing commitment, the cases in hand could be disposed off [means 'of' ??] by November, 1948, but it should be added that the Search Section is still actively searching for over a hundred War Criminals on the run of whom no account has been taken in these estimates.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-50557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">In connection with his visit to the Deputy Chief of the Legal Division, HERFORD, Brigadier SHAPCOTT intimated that the time had now come for C.C.G. to take over certain War Crimes commitments. All cases at present in our possession have been reviewed and classified and assuming the above is put into effect then responsibility of the Field Investigation Section of this Group will be solely the investigation of cases involving British personnel and all outstanding cases involving Allied Nationals would be handed over to the C.C.G. in accordance with the above policy. It is understood that C.C.G Legal Division were prepared to accept this and a firm decision is now awaited.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-51557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">b) D.C.R.E [??] work has proceeded satisfactorily with a result that about a half of the sleeping accn [??] held on charge has been completely redecorated and rennovated within the last six months and completion of this task is going ahead rapidly.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-52557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">c) In para 5(d) of my last report ref was made to our Liaison Officer with the American 7708 War Crimes Group and this officer is now firmly established for liaison duties from a War Crimes angle with OMGUS in BERLIN.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-53557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">d) An incident well worthy of note in this report occurred on 22 Mar. 48 when Major J. Leniewski was carrying out an interrogation of a German witness by appointment in a house in the Russian Sector of Berlin. The time was around 12 noon when a Russian Major accompanied by a Russian Subaltern and two civilians entered the house, asked Major Leniewski to produce his credentials and then requested him to accompany them to the Kommandantura in BERLIN. Mr. Glass a civilian investigator of this Group later called at the house where Major Leniewski had been carrying out an investigation and found he had been taken away by this Russian Major and he was informed that Major Leniewski was at Kommandantura. He went there and was interrogated for some 2 and three-quarter hours. In the meantime Major Leniewski was first interrogated by a Russian Lt. Col. and subsequently by a Colonel of the Russian Forces, wearing civilian clothes. Our Liaison Officer in Berlin heard of the detention of the officer and immediately made representations through the appropriate channels to the Russian authorities and eventually after a total period of detention of 6 hours Major Leniewski was released. He was treated with respect, except for an incident when a Russian P.S.C. endeavoured to take away the German Secretary who was with Major Leniewski for the questioning. This was strongly objected to by Major Leniewski and the Russian P.S.O. after an argument did not pursue his efforts. It was fortunate that Major Leniewski was a fluent Russian speaker and was able to understand exactly what was going on.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-54557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">There is nothing further to report for the period.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-55557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">Ext: 2246</note>
				<note xml:id="q-56557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">Adm. Section</note>
				<note xml:id="q-57557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="36">War Crimes Group (NWE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-58557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="37">HQ British Army of the Rhine,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-59557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="38">BAOR 1.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">for Group Captain</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">Officer i/c</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="41">War Crimes Group (NWE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5d557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="42">(MAJOR A.W. STONE)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5e557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">AWS/GW</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5f557fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="44">26 Mar. 48.</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>