<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Home Intelligence Weekly Report - No. 64 - 24 December 1941</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-618883c3-a41f-41c2-9eb5-e716d7663729</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-923cf896-d48b-4b2d-978f-e01fe998e0b1</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-865b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-875b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-885b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="3">HOME INTELLIGENCE WEEKLY REPORT NO. 64</note>
				<note xml:id="q-895b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="4">24th DECEMBER 1941</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8a5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">(</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8b5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">Covering period from 15th to 22nd December, 1941)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8c5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">Note: The figures in brackets refer to sources of information, a list of which is given at the end of this report.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8d5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">(No reports have yet been received of the public's reaction to the news that the Prime Minister is in the United States conferring with President Roosevelt.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="9">I. GENERAL COMMENTS hhh 1. General state of confidence and reaction to news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">Although the situation in the Pacific continues to be the dominating factor in the minds of most people, the public appears to have recovered to some extent from the initial shock caused by events in the Far East. There is less consternation and bewilderment, and the recovery of spirits, of which the first signs were recorded in last week's report, has been steadily maintained, largely as a result of Russia's continued successes and the improved position in Libya. With this recovery of balance and increased stabilisation, there appears to be a tendency to sit back and ask questions; together with a growing desire to criticise and to apportion blame. At the same time there is no sign of despondency, nor does there appear to be any lessening of confidence in final victory. Most people, indeed, are said to be resigned to still further setbacks in the Far East, and the general expectation seems to be that the war will be longer than had been expected. This realisation is said to be "accepted with grim resignation by most people".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-905b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">(1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12,13,21 Manchester, Bristol, Carlisle P.C.s.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-915b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">The Allies</note>
				<note xml:id="q-925b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">There are indications that the public is "watching eagerly for any signs of a pooling of strategy", comparable to the pooling of resources which has been going on for some time. There is a good deal of criticism that "there should have been so little co-operation between American and British staffs in the Far East". Many people are said to think that "much closer co-operation between the allies is imperative, and that there is not yet sufficient understanding that this is a world war", There appears, to be a "strong feeling in favour of a unified command of all forces fighting the Axis, with, one man appointed to supreme command".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-935b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">There is also a renewed demand for a reconsideration of the suggested Imperial War Cabinet", this view having, been considerably strengthened by the feeling that "the Dominions are always getting it in the neck". It is felt that they should', there­fore, be given a greater share of the direction of the war, particularly now that Australia is thought to be more seriously threatened, and Dominion forces are bearing such a heavy share of the fighting.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-945b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">(4, 6, 8, 9, 10, 12)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-955b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">U.S.A. See appendix to this report</note>
				<note xml:id="q-965b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">The Far East</note>
				<note xml:id="q-975b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">The turn of events in the Far East, and particularly the position in Malaya and Hong Kon</note>
				<note xml:id="q-985b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">g, has been, the subject of speculation and comment and also of a good deal of criticism, A very strong feeling is reported from Several Regions about the "inefficient preparations on the Dart of the High Command", and there has been particular criticism of Air Chief Marshal Sir Robert Brooke-Popham. Public confidence in our military leaders is said to have had another rude shaking, and the "angry criticisms of Australian newspapers of our Higher Command are widely quoted, while the resignation of those responsible is being loudly called for". (President Roosevelt's dismissal of American Service Chiefs has been commended, and the wish is expressed that "Mr. Churchill Would adopt a similar policy".)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-995b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">The following points in particular are the subject of public criticism: -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">(a) Under-estimation of Japanese strength, the public appears to have adjusted itself to the "new conception of Japanese efficiency" but there is a feeling that there has been a serious under-estimation of Japanese strength. "People are questioning whether we were as prepared for the clash with Japan as the. Premier had suggested we were", Indignation at our failures is only said to have been increased by the "constant official emphasis laid upon our readiness for any eventuality", and by the "publicity given to the powerful reinforcements sent to Singapore and Burma, The Hong Kong developments have also caused indignation, after the way in which the strength of our system of defences on the mainland was advertised".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">(b) Loss of Airfields. Seven R.I.O.s refer to annoyance or amazement at what is considered to be inadequate protection of the aerodromes in Malaya, and there is "angry criticism of what is considered a repetition of' the Crete situation", The public indeed appears to particularly struck with what is considered to be a parallel, between Crete and Malaya, and there is said to be a renewal of the "doubts as to the adequacy of the protection of air-fields at home from sudden aerial attack".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">(c) Lack of aircraft. There has been criticism of our lack of planes, and of want of co-operation between the R.A.F. and the other Services people are asking ''whether there is sufficient air-support, for the land operations now in progress, and whether enough air-support was available for the naval operations in which we lost the 'Prince of Wales' and the 'Repulse' ". Postal Censorship quotes a number of letters commenting on our apparent lack of air-support: one, typical of many, says, "This is not": the first time we have suffered losses, on account of not having-aircraft on the scene; and if, aircraft Were not to be had, then warships of that class had no right to be where they were". Another writer says should have thought Crete would have taught us a lesson on why ships sink which have no adequate air protection". The Navy, which largely escaped criticism during the first shock, has been "increasingly blamed for its failure to appreciate the value of an air shield". There is, incidentally, some scepticism about the "wisdom of relying on cloud-cover for capital ships; and, despite the Prime Minister's statement, many think that our naval losses were due to errors of judgment or to over-confidence". It is asked why the Scharnhorst and Gneisnau are still a float when the Japanese sink the 'Prince of Wales' and the 'Repulse' "in a single sitting".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9d5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">(d) Failure to destroy supplies. There has been some comment on the fact that food and other supplies were apparently not destroyed in Penang and Kowloon, and comparisons are being made with the way in which the Russians have carried out destruction. It is reported' that, with many people, detestation for the Japanese is even stronger than it is for the Germans.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9e5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">Timor</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9f5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">There is reported to be satisfaction that, for once, we have not allowed what some people consider to be our over-sensitive regard for the letter of International Law to prevent our landing in Timor, the occupation of which is favourably commented on as "the first sign of our taking the initiative in the Far East'.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a05b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">China</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a15b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">Some admiration is reported for the part that Chine is playing in trying to relieve Japanese pressure on Hong Kong. There is a feeling that, in doing so, "China has given the lead in mutual co-operation", and there are said to be indications that the Chinese are beginning to be regarded with the same friendliness and affection which the Russians now inspire.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a25b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">Public understanding of the Far East.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a35b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">According' to several reports, "it cannot be too greatly stressed that the mass of people find the war in the Far East completely confusing and cannot form any picture of the vast spaces in which it is being fought". There is understanding of the significance of disasters such as the sinking of battle­ships, or the raid on Pearl Harbour, "but on the other hand, Malaya, Borneo, Sumatra and Timor are remote places in which the public finds it difficult to take a real interest. Even the significance of Singapore is not understood, and the loss of Hong Kong, hourly expected, would only be considered a blow to prestige".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a45b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">(1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12,13,21 Carlisle, Inverness, Bristol, P.C.s.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a55b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">Russia</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a65b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">Public admiration and enthusiasm for the continued Russian successes are, if possible, greater than ever, particularly now that the Leningrad armies have also taken the initiative. There is now some hope that, if the Russian advance continues, "the Germans may be thrown into such confusion that they will be unable to undertake any major offensive elsewhere, at least for some months". Only a minority still expresses disappointment that Russia has not declared war on Japan; and there now appears to be only "desultory discussion of the possibility of her negotiating a separate peace.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a75b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">Fear is expressed in several Regions that the Russian successes may be being over-written up, and that the picture we are getting is too roseate.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a85b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">In some area (Oxford among them) there is said to be "brisk Communist propaganda to the effect that, when it comes to preparedness and effective fighting, the Soviet system can give Western democracy points".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a95b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">(1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12,13.) hhh 3. Libya</note>
				<note xml:id="q-aa5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">Our steady progress in Libya continues to give great satisfaction, and there appears to be complete confidence in the outcome". Although lack of surprise and excitement is reported, there is no suggestion that people are anxious for "another flashy advance". There is great appreciation of General Ritchie's achievements, and there is also said to be "some belief that this campaign has "brought considerable relief to Russia". Criticism of the quality of our tanks and equipment appears to have died down. hhh 4. Germany's next move</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ab5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">The news that Hitler has taken over the Command of the Germany Army has been received with much interest and the first reactions are described as optimistic, and as confirming hopes that relations between the' High Command and the Nazi Party may be strained.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ac5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">There is, however, some speculation as to what Germany's next move will be. Some people feel that the change in command may presage an attack in a new direction, probably through Spain. Suspicion of Spain, though not intense, appears to be fairly widespread.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ad5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">(2, 4, 7, 10, 13) hhh 5. Bombing of Germany</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ae5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">There appears to be some dissatisfaction with our bombing Operations for the following reasons: -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-af5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">(a) Supposed insufficicnt bombing of German industrial centres. People are stated to be asking "what are our bombers doing? Why aren't they blasting Berlin?" The explanation that the weather has been unfavourable for long-distance night bombing appears to be received with some scepticism; there is a feeling that greater improved German anti-aircraft defences may be the true reason.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b05b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">(b) Possible inefficacy of our bombing. In view of the destruction caused by German bombs in this country, the public find it difficult to understand "why we still have to go back to town after town, month after month".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b15b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">(4, 6, 11) hhh 6. Air Raids</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b25b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">The "expectation'' of heavy air raids on this country reported last Week, has given way to "considerable speculation" as to their likelihood. On the one hand, their continued absence is noted. On the other, it is being asked: "Where is the Luftwaffe?" Its apparent impotence in Russia and Libya is adding to the mystery.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b35b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">(2, 4, 7, 10) hhh 7. Mosley</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b45b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">Yet another R. I.O. reports a good deal of discontent, amongst workers, at the privileges accorded to Sir Oswald and Lady Mosley at Holloway-Prison.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b55b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">(9) hhh 8. British Israelites</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b65b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">From the South-Eastern Region, it is reported that at a meeting held-recently under the auspices of these people, ''the gist of the principal speaker's argument was that no good can come "out of our alliance with Russia", and practical instances are given of their sabotaging "knit for Russia" campaigns.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b75b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">(12) hhh 9. Broadcasting and presentation of news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b85b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">The suggestion again comes from industrial areas that the 9 p.m. news is a more appropriate time than the 6 p.m. for announcements and information talks concerning tie Home Front.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b95b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">Mr. Ince's broadcast; Mr. Ince is reported to be up a high reputation by his broadcasts on the problem of man-power. His direct, simple and helpful manner is particularly appreciated". The fact that these talks are being included in the 9p.m. news is also highly approved.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ba5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">Mr. Wilfred Pickles: There seems to be on the whole an even division of like and dislike of his voice and manner; no feeling is expressed against a North Country or provincial accent as such Canadian's postscript: This was much appreciated arid was considered as "very cheering", especially as it came from someone who knew America so well,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bb5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">(2, 4, 5, 7) hhh 10. Rumours</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bc5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">Rumours are fewer this week. It was being said it the London area, in the earlier part of the period under review, that "the Prime Minister has gone to meet President Roosevelt in the middle of the ocean to discuss the new international situation".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bd5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">H.M.S. Barham has again been reported sunk, and there is a rumour that there are three hundred survivors from H.M.A.S. Sydney.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-be5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">Reports of tunnelling under Epsom Downs are said to indicate the construction of "a vast arsenal, underground hospital or underground barracks".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bf5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">Mention is made of a commercial firm "using old confidential Government posters as wrapping".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c05b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">It is rumoured that tinned sardines will be scarce, "as the Germans have bought a large consignment over our heads". vSkinned cats are rumoured to be on sale as rabbits in Shoreditch.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c15b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">(2, 5, 10)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c25b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="61">II. SPECIAL COMMENTS hhh Labour and Industry</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c35b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">Extension of Conscription: Although stories of slackness in war factories and inefficiency of managements continue to circulate, it has been noted that for the moment "interest in such matters has been largely superseded by the new call-up regulations". There is still said to be "considerable uncertainty and worry among individuals as to how they will be affected by the present arrangements", but on the whole there is little criticism of the provisions of this Act, in so far as they are understood. What there is, seems to be focused almost entirely on the exemption of Servicemen's wives, and on the alleged "unfair discrimination in favour of married women generally". There is said to be "some confusion about the nature of conscription, and this confusion has apparently increased the feeling about the exemption of Service men's wives, who are imagined as having to do no work at all! Resentment is still more strongly expressed that "this most mobile and dispensable section of the civil community" Should be allowed to remain at home, while women with more household cares may be forced to work further afield. No R.I.O. this week (as against one last week) records any opinion in favour of exemption for the wives of the Forces, but the men themselves are still vehement on the subject" After all; what does a man fight for besides his wife and home? And for the country to take his wife and leave his home to look after itself -".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c45b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">There is some re-iteration of the opinion, recorded last week, that in the call-up of a woman the criterion' should be whether she has children to look after, and not whether she is married. It has been observed that "women as a whole have just as much right to have their opinions considered as the men in the Services, and that women as a whole feel that these childless women should certainly be conscripted".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c55b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">A.T.S. It is commonly believed that "many marriages are taking place so that girls may avoid the call up" but though strong prejudice against this Service undoubtedly exists, public allegations of immorality in the A.T.S. are now beginning, it is stated, to cause irritation with those who make them. It is believed that the allegations are used as an excuse by those who want to dodge service and also that "these outbursts of righteous indignation deflect attention from the bad housing conditions, lack of proper sanitary arrangements, etc, which are much more important, because they are 1-ore widespread"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c65b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">Industrial fatigue in women: Two R.I.O.s write with concern on this subject. On the one hand it is thought that many women, new to factory-life, are reporting sick with constant back-aches, head-aches etc, which may be due only to the strain of unaccustomed employment. Doctors, it is feared, may be issuing certificates that the women in question are not suited to this kind of employment when actually they "could settle down to it"; and on the other hand there is Concern lest long hours and patriotic response to calls for overtime and increased production should injure the health of the most willing of the new workers. "It is hoped that the Government will give this question serious attention", and that improvement in the welfare services will keep pace with the great new intake of labour in the factories.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c75b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">Wages: People are said to be discussing, "still more freely, the comparative pay of civilians on war work and men in the Services". High wages of unskilled juveniles are adding to the disappointment that the Government has not tackled this problem, "which could have been foreseen by anyone from the experience of the last war", and it is "strongly felt that there must be some way of levelling up the position".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c85b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">Problems of Women Workers: Part-time work, as the best means of tapping a vast reservoir of labour, appears to be more and more a subject of discussion among women with household ties anxious to bear a hand with the war effort; at present they are "somewhat discouraged by the attitude of employers", who are thought to be loath to "embark on the extra organisation, insurance commitments, etc", of providing facilities for half-shift workers. Apart from shopping difficulties and the lack of day-nurseries, which form the standard problems for women war workers, it is thought that the need to provide mid­day meals at home for school children is one of the main deterrents to the older women; and it is urged that school meals, supplied by the educational authorities, have proved of great benefit to local recruiting for industry, and should be extended in all areas where labour is scarce.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c95b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">(1,2,3,4,5,67,8,9,10,11,12,13,21 Glasgow, Bristol P.C.s, 27) hhh 12. Food</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ca5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">Satisfaction with the food situation continues. There is said to be "a general feeling of gratitude at the way the Ministry of Food has tackled the job". Lord Woolton's statement that no reduction in quantities of rations was at present contemplated was received with surprise, as a reduction in supplies from America had been expected and people were "ready for further sacrifices",</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cb5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">Milk: There seems to be less complaint on this subject than in preceding weeks, and people are adapting themselves to the shortage. "Unequal distribution" is, however, still a source of discontent in one Region, while the whole milk question continues to be "a sore point" in Scotland.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cc5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">Points rationing: Satisfaction continues and the reason for the adjustment of points values appears to be well understood. The only complaints come from persons living alone who feel that their coupons do not allow them much choice; and from small traders who consider that combined stores receive preferential treatment in the allocation of supplies of tinned foods.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cd5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">Unrationed foods: There appears to be a growing demand for more foods to be rationed. War workers have expressed annoyance that people with leisure can "cruise around the shops half the day and get served with goods the workers have no time to search for.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ce5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">'Black Markets': Four R.I.O.s report that the increased penalties for 'Black Market' offenders have been welcomed by the general public. There is a definite feeling that profiteering in food and drink should be made a criminal offence in war-time, and there is a demand for sentences of imprisonment to be passed instead of the "customary imposition of a fine",</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cf5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">(1,2,3,4,6,7,9,10,11,12,21). hhh 13. Clothes rationing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d05b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">There has again been little comment on this subject.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d15b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">Heavy workers: Further reports of delay in providing supplementary coupons for workers in heavy industry are reported from the Teeside and from steel workers in Rotherham.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d25b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">Lost Clothing coupons: There have once more been complaints of delays experienced in replacing lost clothing coupons.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d35b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">(1,2,4,7,9) hhh 14. Income Tax</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d45b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">"Confusion among first payers regarding the application of tax assessments, reliefs and payments is again recorded, and it is pointed out that ignorance is still shown despite the publicity already given. Disturbing remarks are often heard to the effect that it pays better to have an occasional holiday from work". Factory welfare officers have reported that "information is needed concerning the accessibility of the Income Tax. Office to the first-payers who want answers to their questions".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d55b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">(3, 4, 5, 9, 10) hhh 15. Service Dependants' Allowances</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d65b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">Sharpened by the prospect of a greatly increased number of Service Dependants in the near future, comment is again heard on the time taken to get War Service Grants through, after the form has been completed, and cases of "real hardship" are cited. "Grants to which dependants are entitled should be speedier, and more automatic - many families involved refuse to ask for charity to tide them over the waiting period". "There is still a feeling that dependants of women in the Services are not receiving fair treatment". 'Some "disgust" is reported-at appeals by Service Charities when such matters are felt to be duty of the whole Community, through the State.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d75b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">(5, 7, 8, 10, 12) hhh 16. Old Age Pensions</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d85b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">Resentment is reported that contributions made by sons and daughters are included in the applicant's resources when the granting of an old age supplementary pension is under consideration. It is felt that this is a particularly unfortunate means test, either deterring families from helping their relatives or penalising the thrifty and kindly who are not deterred.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d95b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">(8, 16, 32)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-da5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">17. Constant Topics and Complaints</note>
				<note xml:id="q-db5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">The problem of shopping continues to be "acute" for office and munition Workers. It is frequently asked why shops cannot open on Sundays "to- give workpeople a better chance"; and comparisons are made between the long factory shifts and the short hours during which the shops are open. The inconvenience to workers of lunch-hour closing of shops is also emphasised. Reports have been received of children being absent from school through having to stand in queues.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">Though-the announcement of no extra trains for Christmas travel is generally approved, there are "serious grumbles" about everyday transport services. There are particular complaints of the restriction of local 'bus services and ­especially - of the early hour at which services terminate. Workers are said to be losing time and pay everyday by being "left on the roads". A firmer Government policy of reserving 'buses or issuing passes for workers is called for, and it has been suggested that "nothing will ever be done in some areas if the initiative is left with the local authorities".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">There is a steady demand for nursery schools, and "some resentment" is reported at the slowness with which the situation is being tackled. It is pointed out that schools must be set up before the demand arises, that transport must be provided, and that the contribution from the mother should not be too high as this discourages those with large families. The lack of day nurseries is said to be particularly hard for Service men's wives who really need to go out to work, for financial reasons. (The child minder system is so well established in some areas that the suggestion has been made that it should be developed as much as possible.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">Comment on waste of paper by commercial firms who are said to be "still pouring forth advertising leaflets" has been angry this week. Lack of wrapping is said to be making shop-lifting easier, and increasing its incidence.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df5b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">Indignation still runs high in Salisbury about the forty-two tons of race-course railings not being scheduled. It is suggested that a wooden palisade would be equally effective. Large quantities of old iron are reported to be lying about on farms in the Ayrshire district.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e05b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">Some protests have been received that various forms of salvage and refuse are either mixed up or riot collected by dustmen. It appears to be difficult to dispose of bottles.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e15b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">The continuing serious shortage of wireless spare part; is said to be the "cause of much irritation and depression". It is pointed out that the radio is no longer, in these circumstances, e universal means of conveying news - or of giving instructions - and, in view of a possible emergency, this is a matter "which should concern the Government".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e25b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">There are renewed complaints of the "insolence" of shopkeepers and assistants. 'This "arrogance" is particularly resented by customers who have stood patiently in queues.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e35b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">The demand for more British Restaurants (particularly in rural areas) and more works canteens continues, as does criticism of waste of petrol by private cars.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e45b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">The milk rationing scheme still draws considerable criticism, -and egg supplies are said to be inadequate for the official ration. (It is also asked what procedure should be followed to replace bad eggs.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e55b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">The chief shortages are of: chocolate and confectionery, tobacco and' cigarettes, wines and spirits, fresh and dried fruit, fish, offals, matches, cigarette lighters and flints, thermos flasks, cheap crockery, kitchen utensils, secondhand bicycles, typewriters, toys, and torch batteries</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e65b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">(No.8 in particular ).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e75b88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">(2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11)</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>