<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Morale Report for period 11 to 18 April 1943</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-cf89b237-5b88-4ed6-ab28-908aaf074256</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-8793feff-a914-43ce-af46-78d3ed7391e4</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-2c4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">CONFIDENTIAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">Equals British SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">ALLIED FORCE HEADQUARTERS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="4">Censorship Branch (INC)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-304d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="5">A.P.O. 512 U. S.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-314d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="6">21 April 1943.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-324d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">C/100/3.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-334d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="8">BASE CENSORSHIP DETACHMENT NO. 3 MILITARY MORALE REPORT. For Period 11 to 18 April 1943.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-344d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="9">G-1, A.F.H.Q., FOR CIRCULATION WITHIN ALLIED FORCE HEADQUARTERS AND FILE IN A.G.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-354d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="10">OFFICE OF THE CHIEF BASE CENSOR</note>
				<note xml:id="q-364d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="11">Base Censorship Detachment No.3</note>
				<note xml:id="q-374d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="12">APO 512</note>
				<note xml:id="q-384d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="13">WHB/c</note>
				<note xml:id="q-394d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="14">19 April, 1943</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3a4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="15">Subject: Morale Report for the Period 11 to 18 April, 1943.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3b4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">To: Commanding General, NATO USA, APO 512, U. S. Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3c4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">1. HEALTH: 98% of references to health in letters examined at this office indicate that health of the forces in this theater is excellent. Comments have been noted as to the excellent treatment that is extended to the injured. The following extracts are typical:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3d4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">"The surgical work being done is marvelous and many cases that died in the last war, seem to recover now because of advanced technique and treatment." (Med. Sec., AFHQ).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3e4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">"I have seen some things which were better forgotten. But the doctors are always doing fine things for the wounded." (48th Surg. Hosp. APO 302).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3f4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">2. MAIL: According to letters read the mail service to this area is still unsatisfactory as 60% of the references are unfavorable.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-404d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">3. TRAINING As this is a subject that is censorable, few letters contain references to it, and those are about 80% favorable. The follow­ing comments indicate that our troops have had excellent training previous to combat, though some references are made as to the speed with which units have gone into the forward areas.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-414d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">"During my period at the front. . . the single most vivid impress­ion that I got was that our troops here are not only good but very very good. That is most particularly and emphatically true of your artill­ery." (Hqs. NATJUSA, APO 512).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-424d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">"I did not expect that they would send me into action so quickly, but sooner or later it had to come. I don't have the slightest fear. When we underwent our first attack practically no one slept that night." (Btry B, 67th C.A. (AA), APO 464).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-434d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">4. EQUIPMENT: No comment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-444d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">5. RATIONS: Approximately 80% of references to food have been favor­able, the most frequent complaint being due to the lack of variety in the menu, as shown by the following extract:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-454d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">"Our food isn't bad but is more or less the same thing. Break­fast-stew-tea. That is the menu but they change it on Wed. and leave out the tea." (95 Sq. 82 Gr. APO 520).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-464d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">6. ENTERTAINMENT: No comment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-474d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">7. SPORTS: No comment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-484d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">8. LEAVE: There has been an increasing number of references to the effect that troops expect to go home when the campaign in North Africa has been completed. There has been some expressions of dissatisfaction by officers that the requirements for relief to go back to the States have changed. The following comments were noted during the past week:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-494d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">"My hopes of returning to the United States are greater, we have been victorious in this sector, and thanks to God, I am safe and sound. It has been difficult and we have had great privations, never­theless, our campaign has been one which will be written in history as a most decisive one. The censor forbids relation of details, although I believe what I have written will pass." (56th P.A., APO 302).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4a4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">"Of course no doubt they have their reasons, but it is pretty discouraging to strive for and reach the present requirement for relief and a trip home, only to have them raise it as the have done three times now. As it stands at the present time, our chances of getting home even at the culmination of this campaign look pretty slim. I've certainly lost a lot of confidence in our leaders in this air force here in Africa because of their repeated ignoring of all orders beneficial to us that have been issued." (541st Bomb Sq. 97th Bomb Gr.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">9. QUARTERS: No comment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">10. POLITICS: No comment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">11. NEWS AND PROPAGANDA: References to Churchill's recent address express disappointment in that the war will last so long. There has been an increasing trend of dissatisfaction in the extensive plans for the post war period, many of the writers preferring that plans for the present are of greater importance. Comments on the Axis radio broadcasts continue to express pleasure at their entertainment features, while ridiculing the propaganda broadcast. There was one comment on the lies published in the Axis press which may be of interest.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">"I sure don't like what Churchill said in a speech a few weeks ago. He made the remark that the War with Germany would be over either next year or the following. Then we would proceed to take care of Jap­an. That would get us home in about 46 I guess. They should shoot him or something because things like that are hard on moral." (Ser. Co., 39 lnf. APO 9).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">"Sometimes we get a paper probably a month or so old and they have big headlines about postwar plans and all that stuff. Boy that makes us very mad. . .We feel the people at home should try and send us all the help they can rather than talk about postwar plans." (2 Bn. Hq. Btry, 56 F.A., APO 302).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-504d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">"The best radio programs of course, come from the States although we get a laugh out of "Sally of the Axis". She tells tall stories about Germany and plays good American recordings for us in the Africa service. One night she said to send over our request with the next batch of prisoners. Ironical, eh?" (66th Bomb Sq., 47th Gr., APO 762).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-514d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">"My favorite radio program is "Berlin Calling"--what a deal-­it's really sad--they broadcast for the benefit of American troops in North Africa. Some of the simplest propaganda with supposedly subtle hits in the usual German manner. So subtle it sounds like a bombing raid. Those damned dumb German clowns gripe the hell out of me. Just a bunch of Fritz the butchers and Hans the baker with heads as thick as eternity." (154th Obs. Sq., AFO 762).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-524d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">Note: Writer is from St. Joseph, Mo. which has a large German population. "I saw a German prisoner the other day and he had a German paper stating that Algiers and Oran had been recaptured by the Germans." (AFHQ, APO 512).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-534d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">12. CHURCH AND RELIGION: No comment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-544d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">13. HOME AFFAIRS: About 95% of comments on home affairs in mail read this week indicated favorable morale reaction.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-554d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">14. RELATIONS WITH CIVILIAN POPULATION: Relations with the civilian population continue to be excellent with 99% of comments favorable in this week's mail. There are many references to meals with French families, of which the following is typical:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-564d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">"Last night I had dinner with a French family and for the first time, I ate a dish called 'goose-goose'." (HQ, NAAF).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-574d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">15. RELATIONS WITH ALLIED TROOPS: Relations with allied troops, principally referring to the British, are also excellent, about 95 of comments favorable. The following quotations are typical:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-584d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">"Having joined with that magnificent fighting machine, the Eight Army, and pushed the Germans back to the Carthaginian bridgehead, a mood of collective optimism has seized all soldiers in North Africa." (PRO, AFHQ, APO 512).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-594d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">"The American boys simply wonderful in the front line. They are able to become the bests of all after small training." (French Liason Officer, Hq. 54th U.S. Div., APO 54). Sent to French friends in Oran.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">"We are working under British direction in our office and take it from that they certainly know their stuff." (INC Censorship Section, APO 512).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">"You have a respect for the British soldier, he is generous with his store of unusually valuable information acquired from experience and gad to help at anytime. I, for one, am proud that we are their Allies, and rumors and misinformation to the contrary are (balder dash), they're a grand lot men, officers and soldiers. The French soldiers and officers are everything you may expect, brave, courageous, and very helpful and it is my contention that the French Army was never licked and never will be. Perhaps the greatest of all fellowships and respect is present here among all of us, the British, The French, and the Yanks, we share and share alike, in ail we have, true we probably give more in material things, but they repay it a hundred times in helpful exper­ience, and we have the benefit. --So when you buy bonds, maybe, who knows--you are buying a new handle for my shovel, and on behalf of my­self and all of the rest of us, our most sincere thanks. P. S. Wingert says, Buy 2 bonds, he may need a shovel, the hell with a HANDLE." (Hq, APO 34).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">16. CENSORSHIP: Numerous references to censorship show increasing consciousness of the new regulations with many of the writers registering general complaints. There is evidence that many unit censors are divulg­ing the contents of the mail they read. There have been many unfavorable comments as the effect that the press may print items that cannot be passed in personal letters, the writers not realizing that the press items may be general in nature, while if written in personal mail they tend to accentuate the activities or location of specific units or individuals. The following extracts are representative:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5d4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">"To write something censorable so that it could be cut out, thus giving you a letter that had been censored, is a demand somewhat on the rough side. I am not without gallantry but providing the subject matter and the corpus delecti for a court-martial seems to me to be above and beyond the exigencies of mere love. . .The truth of the matter is that practically everything which might make up a decent letter is, taboo and the boys spend many a weary hour trying to dream up material. I know; I have to read the letters and it is slowly but surely driving me insane." (301 BS, 316 BG, APO 520).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5e4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">"Tell Tom I can't send him anymore cards. That's a foolish bit of censorship as the same scenes are shown in your magazines." (Sp. Serv. Comd, .A3 312).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5f4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">"I know these letters aren't much out its the best I can write with the censor ready to make confetti out of the paper:" (Btry C 355th C.A.-SLT Bn., APO 70u).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-604d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">"I'd like to make my letters longer but censorship has clamped down on us to the point that we just absolutely can't mention any of our doings up here." (Alst Sq., 97th Gr.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-614d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">"I don't have anything new to tell you, because everything is considered as a military secret, so I can't say anything." (849th Sig. Bn. ) Note: A typical comment by Spanish-American personnel.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-624d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">"I doesn't let the company censor it--the officer's talk about what they read. . .There will probably be no more "blue letters", since the front office frowns on anything it can't censor." (87 Ord. Co., (HA-Tank) A10 668).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-634d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">"Butch, Eisenhower's aide, . . .admitted the censorship had been too tight. It has been loosened up. . . for the press since then. But there is the usual lack of coordination as Bud pointed out. He says my letters to him was heavily censored: yet there was nothing in it I had not already written for publication, and got passed. Everything I write to you I have used in my dispatches, but I suppose your letters are heavily censored too. I raised hell with Scott Bailey about one letter that came back because the Base Censor apparently hadn't found out that a ship was torpedoed, I had been on it and the story had been passed. He apologized and said matters would be better." (gar Correspondent).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-644d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">17. GENERAL COMPLAINTS: No complaints are common, but those most prominent this week are (a) general hardships of life in Africa and separ­ation from loved ones at home, (b) resentment at preferential treatment of soldiers in the U.S., and (c) individual dislike of superior officers. Examples of each of these complaints are given in the following extracts:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-654d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">"It's tough and I mean tough, I certainly miss all the things we have at home. . .I can't get clothes cleaned here in less than two weeks and I'm going to have to do my own laundry this week. My job is tough too." (Ord.. Sec., Force Hq., APO 512).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-664d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">"Will I be glad when I get home--I have done and seen so much misery, pain, suffering and general discomfort that all I want to do is go home and live in peace and buy a home for Janice and the baby." (13th Armd Regt., 1st Armd Div., APO 251).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-674d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">"It makes me burn up when I get letters from home telling about all the friends I have who are still safely back in the States, with nice jobs (army) living at home with their wives and all with promot­ions. The army really takes care of its boys so long as they don't do anything useful." (Gen'l Depot No. 4, APO 536).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-684d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">"Our new boss is due here in a few days I sure hope he's a good one. I've certainly been utterly disgusted with the others." (AFHQ).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-694d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">18. GENERAL: General morale is very high this week as usual with 98% of comments indicative of good morale. The successful offensive in Tunisia is reflected in a wave of optimism and there is a new confidence in the ability of American soldiers to cope with the seasoned Germans. The following extracts are typical:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6a4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">"There isn't much I can tell you right now except that we saw a little action, but the Germans ran so fast we had a hard time keeping up with them. I saw some Italian prisoners and with the aid of an interpreter found out that they had had nothing but some big squares of unseasoned bread for the past two weeks. They were glad to be' taken prisoners. We were with the force that met the British-Eighth Army." (Hq.. 13th Armd Reg. 1st Armd Div. APO 251).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6b4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">"This will all be over soon. Every day German and Italian sold­iers surrender and they say that they don't want to fight but are forced to and as soon as they have a chance they get to our lines and surrend­er at once, and they say that Americans eat well and have plenty of cigarettes. The other day we took an Italian prisoner and he said, 'Leave me here in the kitchen and I can help you with your work'. We did so, and placed a guard with him, and he said 'You don't have to guard me--I have nowhere to go and I like it here with you because Americans are good people.' Also a German lieutenant who surrendered said that he wanted no more war--he had fought for five years and had suffered enough; and that's the way it goes." (Service Co., 13th A.R. APO 251).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6c4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">"I intend to buy some War Bonds here and will send them to you. Papa, I want you to buy Bonds too, so that you will help to win this war." (Co. M, 16th Inf., AR) 1).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6d4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">"The morale of American troops in this sector is excellent, and their equipment is very good and in quantity." (A.C., APO 512).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6e4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">"There is nothing new here, except that the other day we had an encounter with the enemy. I can tell you that they are not as good as they say they are." (Co. C, 19th Engrs., APO 302).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6f4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">"But it is not all tough going at times we have fun and I don't know but what at times I like it." (Cannon Co., 60th C.T., APO 9s)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-704d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">"It looks as if we are doing well--I hope that when you receive this, this campaign will be ended, but there will be other campaigns before this war is over, and we are already tired of it. You in Browns­ville have not had air raid warnings, with planes coming at night, dropping flares and then bombing. If you could only see those flares --they light up miles of terrain just like day." (48th Surgical hosp­ital, APO 302).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-714d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">"You should hear our boys talk--their morale is high and we even see boys go AWOL from the hospital to get back to the front so they can be with their outfits." (Sp. Serv. Coned, APO 512).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-724d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">"I am doing everything I can to accustom myself to this new way of life, and I hope that all this will end as soon as possible. All ray friends here feel the same and I know that they too are doing their bit to make all our dreams and hopes come true." (Hq. Co., 1st Armored (Hq. Co., 1st Armored Div., APO 251).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-734d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">"You are right in saying that 'those who are captive live on hopes and we who are captives of this present job are full of hopes.' Hopes of success!" (37th Bomb Sq. 17th Gr., APO 52u).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-744d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">"We are still in our 'rest camp' and we still don't like it but maybe we will get back in the scrap before long--we hope." (69th</note>
				<note xml:id="q-754d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">MG- Btry., Sup. Airborne, APO 668).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-764d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">WALTER H. BECKER</note>
				<note xml:id="q-774d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">Major, Field Artillery</note>
				<note xml:id="q-784d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">Chief Base Censor</note>
				<note xml:id="q-794d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">13 Inclosures:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7a4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">12 Forms 912, Serial Nos.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7b4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">BCD 3-198 to BCD 3-203, Incl., 2 copies each.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7c4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">1 Statistical Report in triplicate.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7d4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">DISTRIBUTION:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7e4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">3 Theater Censor</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7f4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">1 File</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>