<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Morale Report for period 9 to 15 April 1943</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-06fe1f61-0258-4596-aa12-83ed93a7f87b</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-91c267db-e4fc-4c55-8d23-22d9af137cea</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-c14c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">CONFIDENTIAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c24c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">(EQUALS BRITISH SECRET)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c34c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">OFFICE OF THE CHIEF BASE CENSOR</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c44c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="4">Base Censorship Detachment No.1</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c54c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="5">A.P.C. 700 Hew New York</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c64c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="6">15 April 1943.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c74c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="7">Subject: Morale report for period 9 to 15 April 1943, inclusive.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c84c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">To: Theater censor</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c94c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">1. Health. With the coming of warm weather the climatic condition of North Africa appears to be beneficial to the continued good health of our troops here. About 98% all comments on health have been favorable. It is interesting to note comment from one medical officer, his is one of many we have noted who are interested in the field of epidemiology and control of venereal diseases. The following excerpts were noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ca4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">"Our plans have all been laid out for the Malaria Campaign to Civilian, French Army and our Services. Among other things I am trying to get more and more control over Civilian venereal. We are also increasing the number of vaccinations against the common diseases. We have quite some plans for increased sanitary appliances in the city, suitable material being one of the main problems. We got through the typhus season remarkably well. I am still very much interested in this matter of larvacides. The French do not like the use of arsenic in any form and an effective larvacide here would be one of the best things imaginable."--Medical Section, Base Hq.APO 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cb4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">"I'm feeling fine Dad… everyday I try to take in a ½ hour of the sun, have a nice face tan now, and look healthier than ever."--21st Gen.Hosp.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cc4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">2. Mail. About 70% of all comments on mail service have been unfavorable. Many writers still complain of receiving mail held up unduly for periods of months, one comment by a British soldier indicates the same is true with their mail service from England. Anticipation of better mail service, has been aroused by the announcement that V-mail would be processed here. The following comments were noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cd4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">"Yesterday I received a registered letter dated December 1, 1942. It went from the U.S. to England, England to Africa, Africa to England, and then England to Africa. My what a route to take (how about it)."--156th Inf.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ce4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">"At the present rate of mail delivery, I shall probably get your letter by next Christmas--nobody seems to care about our mail at the American APO's and consequently we are about three months behind with letters from home."-­RAF BNAF (British attached to American Forces).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cf4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">"They are supposed to have V-mail service by the 15th of this month. Our letters should reach each other much quicker. I will be glad to get them quick but I do not like V-mail because you cannot write long letters. You will just have to write more often."--60th Fighter Squadron.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d04c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">"The mail has been coming in much faster lately and I believe I'm getting all your letters. The reason we are getting better service is because most of you people are using V-mail."--Law Enforcement Gp., Base Hq., APO 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d14c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">"I think up to date I have about 60 letters of all types from you and I do get good service and V-mail does not come faster. I found out that the men whose folks write regularly get their mail in good time."--6oth Troop Carrier Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d24c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">"Only today did I receive your last letter. You couldn't imagine how happy I was. There is nothing like mail to raise one's morale."--73rd Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d34c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">3. Training, About 75% of all comments have been critical of the strenuous training. Many comments from the Air Corps indicates overconfidence and advocates additional training. The following comments have been noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d44c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">"Today we ran four miles and we are really getting in real trim shape. The officers training us must think that we are ex-track stars."--Rec. Go., 804th Tank Destroyer En.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d54c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">"We went on a nice little four mile hike yesterday, and today. I am the sorest man in the world today, or at least this side of the ocean. We doubled timed for 1/2 mile and then quick timed for 1/4 mile. We did this for four miles alternating, and I mean that we didn't stop until the four miles was finished. And then we had a half hour of calathesentics and then a little drill. I am so sore today I can hardly move then some brass hats or general or something came along and watched us and then told the colonel and majors how disgusted he was."--Company B, 8th Bn., 1st Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d64c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">"We are still in a staging area, living in tents. Last week our time was taken up with calisthenics, drill, road marches, and various classes."-- 73rd Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d74c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">"They advertize 'Learn to fly in eight hours'. That is silly but not funny. No one can learn to fly in less than 200 hours. No one is safe from himself in less than 500 hours. This may sound exaggerated but I swear it is the truth. More pilots are killed between 299-500 hours than any other time. About this time they began to think they know all about flying and take chances. Pilots with 500 hours in the air begin to realize that they have scratched the surface and they begin to get careful. I have over 1000 hours and I still have lots to learn."--60th Troup Carrier Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d84c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">4. Equipment. About 90% of all comments on equipment are favorable. Equipment in hospital organization is satisfactory, but it has been noted many times, essential parts have not been supplied quickly. It is noted that our flyers continue to praise the ability of their planes. The British Battle Dress has received many favorable comments. The following comments have been noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d94c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">"What equipment we have here is satisfactory. There are two of the Heidbrink Military Model No. 685 gas oxygen machines at the hospital. However, they do not have any rubber parts. One machine was issued in November and it still has not been supplied with the missing parts."--Hq., 301st Ordnance Regiment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-da4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">"This morning I got checked out in, a B-17 (Flying Fortress to you) and without a doubt it is the best ship I have ever flown. I took her up to 34,000 feet and she still wanted to climb on up. I however, lost faith before the ship did as it was 40 degrees below zero and the air is so rarified at that altitude that a man would die in a few seconds if something should happen to his supply of oxygen. So that gives me a 7200 horse power rating and means I have flown nearly every medium and heavy bomber the U.S. Army has with the one exception of the B-24."--Hq. Sq., 11th Air Depot Gp., 12th Air Force Service Command.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-db4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">"My opinion-unofficial-no secret but don't quote me. The leggins are too long. Look at the British leggin-half the canvas and two straps. Also, we missed a bet on British Battle Dress-it's ideal. The men lose too much of our stuff. Field jacket too light for cold weather."--98th QM Company.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">5. Food. About 98% of all comments on food have been favorable. Fresh meat seems to be abundant as well as turkey and ham. The sandwich bar or the Red Cross has received enthusiastic praise. In some instance there appears to be an over-Charge by the Post Exchange of some units, otherwise the supplies are adequate. The following were noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">"We started getting fresh meat here this week and I think it has helped the morale greatly."--60th Troop Carrier Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">"We are all joking over here about sending packages to the folks at home. We have no sugar, butter, or coffee shortage. Fresh meat is not very plentiful as there are no refrigeration facilities, but we don't fare too badly and we surely do get the canned food that you folks are going to do without."--12th Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">"Our food situation has picked up a great deal. We have enjoyed turkey, ham, frankfurters and stew of late. Our French cooks are starting to make cakes and pie."--40th Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e04c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">"Chow has been good in camp and the French food is lousy. I stay in camp."--6th Bn., 1st Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e14c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">"You know, the food we get at camp is none too appetizing and when we get a chance to go to town, the first place we go to is the Red Cross. They have a sandwich bar open all day-free. Sardines, corned beef, ham, orange juice, ice cream, etc. I'm telling you whenever they ask for donations give, because from what I've seen here they do a great job and the boys are all for it."--Co. B, 6th Bn, 1st Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e24c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">"Today we received our ration, for one week. 2 candy bars, 3 boxes of cookies and 2 packages of chewing gum, 1 bar of soap and cigars and cigarettes if you want them. The only thing is that we pay double the price for them." --Hq. Det. 9th Bn., 1st Replacement Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e34c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">6. Entertainment. About95% of all comments on entertainment have been favorable. Some troops are being shown movies and frequently are given the opportunity to see stage shows. The Red Cross has become the center of attraction for personnel during their spare time, thereby keeping them from hanging around local bars. A great deal of enthusiasm is felt for the activities participated in by the Red Cross and Special Service Section. The AEF Radio Station has been openly complemented for their morale uplift. The following comments have been noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e44c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">"The Red Cross has just opened a snack bar in town so while on pass today I visited it. Boy, its wonderful the first time since I left the States that I've had boiled ham sandwiches and ice cream. Real American chocolate ice cream. I had three dishes of it. The have pickles, cheese, ham, mustard, etc. all buffet style and all free. The American Red Cross is doing a wonderful job in this war and deserves every bit of assistance they solicit. It's true that most of the fellows pay if there's a basket to throw it in but the fact remains it's there whether you can pay for it or not. And often times fellows aren't paid for months at a time over here but they're given cigarettes, candy, gum and other things by the Red Cross." --14th Machine Records Unit.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e54c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">"Just got back from another stage show at the officers club. The Red Cross has a special club for officers and nurses. Real nice--they have magazines ping gong tables, a badminton court and other amusements. Think it is a much better place for the fellows and gals to hang out than the bars around. Besides they close the bars early, which wouldn't leave the fellows anywhere to go."--Signal Section, Services of Supply.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e64c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">"The Red Cross try hard to keep the situation. They just opened a food counter, and are doing a swell job."--6th Bn., lot Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e74c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">"We have plenty of food here. The army looks after us well, and we love it. The soldier boys are appreciative of every service we do for them. Most of all they like to talk to us, and so therefore a considerable part of our time is spent in listening, and that is an art, I have discovered. We plan all sorts of entertainment for the boys from movies, songfests, ping-pong tournaments to variety shows."--American Red Cross, APO 700.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e84c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">"We have just set up a radio station here that plays all the latest records. It is the first radio station of this type we have installed, all the rest have been for communications only. Think this new station is great morale scheme. Seems to be the best thing we have the 'high spirits"."-- 71st Signal Company (Special). "An AEF radio station was opened here tonight through the medium of this station we will be able to hear for a few hours each evening a lot of U.S. shows. It will help a lot."--Hq., Fifth Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e94c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">"I am sitting writing this in one of the loveliest American Service men's clubs that I have ever seen. They have got everything here even a theater."--33rd Fld. Baty., 22nd Regt. R.A. B.N.A.F.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ea4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">"Biggest trouble we have here is what to do with spare time. Only thing to do is to go to the American Red Cross or a show. Shows are in English with French words written. Red Cross is really doing a big and good job for the men over here."--5th Base Post Office.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-eb4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">7. Sports. All comments are favorable. Softball, volley ball, ping-pong and horse-shoe teams are very popular sports among the officers and enlisted personnel. Sport activities are increasing where opportunities are available. The following are typical comments:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ec4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">"About all we do is play softball in our spare time. Yesterday I saw a damned good game. There was at least $500.00 bet on it."--Hq., 437th Signal Construction Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ed4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">"I got a soft-ball team here that is the best in North Africa. We have seven straight wins so far. The team makes more money betting on themselves than they earn in the army. So far they have picked up around $700 or 35,000 francs. We also have the best ping-pong players in N. Africa, also the best volley ball team and horse-shoe team."--11th Chemical Maint. Co.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ee4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">8. Leave. No comments.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ef4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">9. Quarters. A few comments of a favorable nature have boon received regarding ac improved living conditions of a few of the units living in 'tent camps'. The following were noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f04c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">"Last couple of weeks have seen movast improvement in our living conditions. Our tents have been fixed up, floors put in, cots obtained, even though mattresses and pillows are not available."--Company B, 49th Quartermaster Truck Regiment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f14c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">"We are changing our camp around tearing down the pup tents, boys now have large tents with built in bunks, this should be much better for their health."--813th Signal Port Service Company;</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f24c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">10. Politics. No comments.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f34c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">11. News and propaganda. No comments on news except the daily signal news bulletins are very gratefully received. The German news and radio programs are still a source of amusement both for their propaganda and new recordings of late the following remarks are typical:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f44c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">"We also get German propaganda broadcast directed at us. The other day they told us that when we went home to our wives we would have a big surprise. We would go home in a box. They also broadcast that we were either killed or taken prisoners. I never knew I could be dead and still ante a letter."-­301st Ordnance Regiment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f54c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">"Well Mil, there is not much new around these parts, I have a couple of funny stories to tell. We are entertained every might by a broadcast from Germany. They give out with some propaganda, and some slamming, and then they have a woman announcer who speaks and addresses us with 'Hello Boys'. She tells us how sorry she is for us to be away from our homes and sweethearts and plays recording in between. She has a very lovely voice and we enjoy the music. The whole thing is the screwiest you've ever heard and they keep it up every night. Then we hear another, Lord Haw and his remarks are very impossible. I really think they are wasting a lot of time with the entire thing but we do enjoy the music."--Hq. Co., 755th Tank Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f64c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">12. Religion. Increasing mention of attendance at church services has been observed, indicating that these services are having a favorable effect on morale. Several references have been observed expressing regret that no church services are available. The following have been extracted from letters examined:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f74c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">"It may interest you to know that religion has a place in the army. And this is, indeed, helpful."--51st Service Sq., 38th Service Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f84c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">"As for the discontinuance of services, here's the story. A few weeks ago I arranged with one of my buddies to conduct services because I thought that he would conduct them better and he might attract more boys to the services. Well, attendance dwindled more each week. Last Friday (day before yesterday) only 3 of us showed up. I consulted the Chaplain and discussed the situation with him. He said he was experiencing the same thing with his congregation--people just aren't interested nowadays, it seems. He told me not to give up so easily, to talk to the Jewish boys in the outfit and to see if they wouldn't commit themselves to attend services each week. I'll do it but I don't like to because I always felt it is useless to go pleading with people to go to services. If it isn't in their hearts, it doesn't help much to use urging or moral coercion. I feel badly about it but I've tried my best and my conscience is clear."--64th Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f94c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">13. Home affairs. Numerous comments have been observed men advising their girlfriends, sisters or wives against joining the WAACS. In practically all cases, they express great indignation and threaten to break their friendly relations if they join that organization. The following are typical comments:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fa4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">"You ask me about enlistment in the WAACS. Every day I hear the same thing. All the boys here get similar letters from their girlfriends, their sisters or wives. The only conclusion I can draw from that is that all of you are put under some kind of a pressure by the Government bar the papers and the radio. You are telling me that the soldiers are very fond of the WAACS. If you want to know our opinion so let me tell you that there are no mowrds strong enough to express our indignation about the attitude of the government in this regard. I think it is bad enough when we men have to be away and we think that we are doing our share in this war. But at least we thought that we could expect that our women will be left in peace and that we don't have to worry about them. You have no idea how such things affect our morale and how badly we feel about it."--531st Engineer Shore Regiment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fb4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">"According to your letter it looks like you don't see many civilians walking around the streets. It's a shame however how some of these young girls join the MACS. Soldiers all think they are a bunch of 'whacks' for joining and any girl in her right mind would stay at home where she belongs."--Hq. Co. 361st Quartermaster Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fc4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">14. Relations with local inhabitants. During the period covered by this report, about 80% of all comments about local inhabitants have been favourable. A few mentioned that they have noticed a more friendly attitude on the part of the local French people. Numerous instances of soldiers being invited to the homes of local inhabitants have been related. From these comments it seems that the friendly relations with the French populations are improving. The following are excerpts from letters:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fd4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">"The French people are beginning to trust us a little now. Some are beginning to hope that we have come to stay. To encounter such feelings makes one feel rather glad to be an American."--12th General Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fe4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">"I just came back from a dinner at the home of a wealthy Jewish man. I met him when I was at the market the other day. He is a seller of dried fruits, and when he heard that I was a member of the tribe, he immediately invited me to his home. The dinner was something to talk about. The French set their table with three dinner plates in front of every guest as well as four different size glasses for champagne, water, wine and coffee. The entrees included all different types of vegetables and such things as sardines. Each one must have a little of all the entrees so it takes almost an hour to eat them as they must be eaten separately. Then we had an egg omelet (kugel to us), then turkey with side dishes of peas and lettuce, and finally cake and champagne. The food tastes a little different from ours as they use a lot of sauces and wines, but it was very good. The inter­preter that works with me was also there, so I was able to carry on a conversation through him. Being that Passover Seder is a week from tomorrow, they invited me to come that evening. The funny thing about the whole thing is that they can't speak Yiddish or English, and I can't understand them yet it's fun to watch their ways and customs. One thing about all the people in Africa, no matter whether they are Catholic, Jewish, or Moslem, is their devotion to their religion. On Saturdays you will never find a Jew working, and the same thing goes for the others."--2604th QM Depot Detachment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ff4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">"As for the Frenchmen-any Frenchman in this vicinity who ever spent a weekend in Paris looks upon his less fortunate Algerians sompatriots as poor white trash. They are really a very snobbish lot. Some of them are so impressed with the wealth of their own culture that they are quite poverty stricken when it comes to the wonderful culture of this locale. Often their attitude toward the Arab is as narrow and as prejudiced as that of a bigoted Southerner toward the lowest negro. I'm afraid that the freedom loving Frenchmen are not here but rather in France-in chains."--32nd Station Hosp.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-004d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">"I am losing my third French teacher; all were leaving for the French army. They have no fear of being drafted. All three boys I am referring to are Jewish and they are all delighted to go particularly now that Jews are finally accepted into the French army on that equal bases with others."-­32nd Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-014d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">15. Relations with Allied troops. Only a few comments were noted this past week by our own troops on this subject, their praise and esteem of other Allied moo s is constant. Many letters written by British personnel try to rectify any feeling they might have had against the Americans. It is to be noted the cordial feeling left with the Brazilian Military Mission. The following are a few comments noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-024d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">"I am more or less a guest of the Yankees at present but expect moving out soon. In a short time I struck up a friendship with quite a number of the Americans, and believe me, in their own language, they're great guys. They went out of their way to make us feel at home."--G Co. 2nd Bn., 1st G.D.D. B.N.A.F.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-034d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">"I've met quite a few Yanks over here and I do think that they are pretty decent easy going chaps. All I hope is that the prejudice feeling most of us chaps have had, dies right away. You can see quite plainly that they want to be sociable with us."--R. Signal, 22nd Fld. Regt. R.A.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-044d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">"At the present time I am in a camp with some Americans, and my word these boys have got everything, honestly their kit, food, tents, Gigs, in fact everything is the very best. I think everyone of us will be sorry to leave them, they are even knocking about with some of our boys, their officers too are grand fellows, we all talk and what we call much in with one another."--D Troops, 33rd Bat. 22nd Fld. Regt. RA.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-054d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">"I got a magnificent reception by the Americans and I had the opportunity to see things of greatest professional interest. I firmly believe that the Americans have the best equipped army of the world."--Brazilian Military Mission.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-064d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">"I am very happy to inform you that I am extremely pleased with the reception and the excellent treatment given to us by the Americans. We are full of admiration for their magnificent army their organization and their equipment. Their effort is outstanding and beyond any description. 7e had the honor to assist a reception at the 'Foyer Franco-Allie' and we were emotionally touched by it."--Brazilian Military Mission.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-074d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">16. Censorship. Illicit posting of mail and disclosing geographic location are the dominant violations of censorship in the past week. A total of 35 Form 912's were sent out of which 18 were for officers and 17 were for enlisted personnel. In the mail the violators were found the following violations: 13 illicit postings, 13 disclosed geographical location other than "Somewhere in Africa", 7 disclosed APO location, 4 had improper return addresses, 4 mentioned casualties, 4 disclosed unit location, 2 disclosed routes of travel, 2 gave details of voyage, 2 disclosed plans of future operations, 2 mentioned names of officers above the rank of Lt. Colonel, 2 gave information which reflected on our armed forces. Other violations included in the above mail were: disparaging remarks about Allies, strength of unit, location of camps in England, movement of unit, and movement of military aircraft. In two cases it clearly showed the neglect of the unit censor of properly censoring the mail. Four violated the use of blue envelopes had other violations as indicated in the above consolidation. Since applying the new censorship regulations it has become apparent many units have not received their copy, their minor violations have been treated with that in mind. There is a continual violation of geographic locations by the use of Postal. Cards marked with names of towns.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-084d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">In examining boat mail of the newly arrived units, it has been found that they have been instructed in censorship regulations but some have been lead to believe they could disclose dates while enroute. In several cases it was found that envelopes contained ship's bulletins, that suggested that they be included in the first mail home. In all bulletins examined, definite violations of censor­ship were found. Among other violations found, ship's menus disclosed names of ships. Members of crews used ships names as a return address together with London G.P.O. instead of addresses authorized. Several serious violations have been intercepted. General comments on censorship have been noted and are as follows:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-094d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">"Different fellows told me at times that our censor makes remarks about things he reads in personal letters fellows in our outfit write, to other members of our outfit that work in the orderly room. I never used to let it bother me too much but today .... was out to the hospital to visit his Lt. and his Lt. remarked to him about how the censor and the captain were mad at me because of the length of my letters and a few misspelled words. Well neither the captain nor the censoring officer made any remark to me so it dawned on me that the censoring officer was making remarks about my personal affairs to the other officers of the outfit. Regulations only allow two blue envelopes a month or it for sure all mine would be blue. Also one of the boys who works for me and sleeps right next to the orderly room told me the time I sent back all my old mail it took two Lts. to censor it. One would say to the other, get a load of this blot, blab, etc, smack, smack, smack. So you see how I feel. I even put it up to the… tonight. He's in the orderly room all day. He said I know how you feel… I make as much as lean blue -mail too. Said he wasn't going to commit himself but I wasn't wrong in my suspicions."--169th QM Co. Service Gp (Avn).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0a4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">"Our mail is under new strict censorship do not be disappointed in how little I write."--433rd C.A.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0b4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">"Censorship regulations have become a bit stricter of late, so maybe this letter will be a bit Co., 15th Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0c4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">"I am a member of the Board of Censors for the Naval Personnel. As a censor I know what can't be said and of course I have to guide myself accordingly. I made a long speech today over the P.A. system of the ship in an attempt to cut down the amount of scissoring that had to be done to the mail of the enlisted aboard. Our cutting has been cut to a minimum and everyone says that I should have had the idea to make the announcement earlier."--4th Beach Battalion, Amphibious Forces.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0d4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">"I can tell you we are still on the ester and that is why I cannot put the date on this letter. However I will be able to date my letters after we land and then I may be able to give you some idea where I am."--Co.142nd Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0e4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">"Naturally most of the things I'd like to write about would constitute violations of the censorship regulations. So I'll just have to skip over that."--Company G, 142nd Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0f4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">17. General complaints. Complaints have been general and constitute about 5% of all comments in mail examined. Subjects that are mentioned frequently relate to: promotions, medical practice, rotation of troops overseas with those in the States, and the loss to the army of technical ability personnel being reclassified for limited service in a non-combatant position. Objection is made to the early curfew hours and spit and polish as required. The following were noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-104d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">"It is impossible to get a promotion overseas in the dental corps."-­433rd C.A.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-114d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">"My biggest headache is patients. I'm just supposed to refer them to a station or general hospital, but they have so much to do they don't have time. So I have been going to the hospital with the patients and doing the work. They really need more dentists here, because there is plenty to do." --11th Air Depot Group, 12th Air Force Command.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-124d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">"As a result I spent six weeks in the hospital and am now on limited service. That means no more troops duty and no more combat. I'm no longer with my old outfit (I'm sorry to say) but an now a grocery peddler. Yep, that is what happens when you have two solid years technical training in a tank outfit and finally go into combat. They make a grocery peddler out of you and you overseas where you can't and don't do a thing. They won't send me home as a instructor. No, that would be doing the right way. I'm so damn disgusted that it's difficult to write."--Civil Affairs Section, Base Headquarters, APO 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-134d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">"I have been overseas so damn long and I hope and pray every day that some form of troop rotation will soon be worked out so we fellows who have been over here the longest will be relieved and sent home and others take their place. It would certainly be a fair way of doing it. You spoke in your letter that you heard of the American soldiers in India whose year overseas would be up this summer, would be allowed to come home. I certainly hope that becomes an established policy of the army."--330th Ordnance Motor Trans. Company.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-144d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">"We are however landed in a rather peculiar situation. Our commander is one who is constitutionally opposed to promotions. Since the regiment was activated there have been only two line officers promoted. Before we left England the Colonel sent for me and told me that my promotion had already been sent forward to higher HQ but I found later that this was not so. After coming here he told me I had been recommended down here but I have also learned that this too is a joke. To give you an idea, the T/O calls for 12 captains and we have 5. Also we are supposed to have 3 Lt. Cols. of which we have none. All the companies are commanded by 1st Lts. except 3."--3/4th Engineer Regiment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-154d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">"Curfew is at 10 p.m. All military personnel has to be off the streets. Civilians can stay outdoors as long as they want to. Few days ago a circular came out warning all of us that acts of sabotage can be expected at any time. I yonder when we should watch out for it if at 10 p.m. we all have to be at home and civilians are able to do anything they just like to do."--755th Tank Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-164d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">"The battle of Tunis must be over, only we haven't been informed yet. Spit and polish are back in vogue again for the season. Was stopped at 1801 hours by the MP's for being on the streets after 1800 hours in a field jacket instead of a blouse. Ever since I've been blitzing brass buckles and shining shabby shoes till they'd blind you. You never know what they'll think of next. Now we all have gone so damned 'garrison' and you never know what they will think of next."--CPC Liaison Office, Eq. Base Hq., APO 600</note>
				<note xml:id="q-174d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">18. General. About 98% of all mail examined commented favorably on the continued high morale. Some speculation is apparent regarding the excess of personnel in this and other theaters of war. It is also indicated, many are looking forward to insure their social position after the war, in that they might not find employment as expected. Admiration is shown for Allied troops and of our own. The following excerpts were noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-184d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">"Irven is being drafted soon from what I have been able to gather. It seems odd that he should be taken after obtaining a disability discharge from the Navy and originally getting a 4-F classification in the Army. I have been in the army long enough to cease wondering why some things are done the way they are."--AACS Radio Station, APO 528.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-194d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">"Once the war is over taxes will be sky high and so will the cost of living. We are bound to have another depression and that's the reason I am saving all that I can now. It will take at least $800 to start out with and then too I may not be able to get a job right away."--Co. M., 30th Inf.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1a4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">"Stay out of the army, Bud, we have plenty anyway. One third is doing the fighting and two thirds having a high old time way back from the front. Sure is disgusting at times to see so many doing nothing and I'm speaking of those over here not counting the ones in the States. There may be a reason but they have to show me first."--439th Bomb. Sq., 319th Bomb. Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1b4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">"Excellent food, quarters and treatment here."--Hq. Co. 1st Repl. Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1c4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">"I stand a chance of going back to the states as a limited service man but what would I tell the folks back home. I want to go back to the glory hunting first and parade down 5th Avenue with them when this war is over."--Co. A, 9th Bn., 1st Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1d4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">"However, all of us must go on until the optimum time, and I am sure all our soldiers think, the sooner the better, in fact, that is probably the main reason they are fighting so hard. Their training and spirit are superb, but do not excel that of the British soldier, who is really most to be admired, as far as I can estimate."--21st General Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1e4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">"Believe me when I tell you that I am well, contented, and somewhat proud, not of myself, but of the fact that I am a part of this great victorious army, where men come to do their jobs without the slightest thought of fear or without the slightest regard for danger--they have a job to do, so they do it, what's the cost, no one knows, no one cares, the main point is to get the job done at any cost, and that's what they are doing, or should I say that's what we are doing."-- Medical Detachment, 28th Quartermaster Regiment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1f4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">ERNST L. PELCHEN, Jr.,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-204d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">Captain, Infantry,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-214d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">Chief Base Censor.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-224d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">71 Inclosures:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-234d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">70 Forms 912, Serial Nos.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-244d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">BCD 1-55 to BCD 1-89, incl., 2 copies each.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-254d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">Statistical Report in triplicate</note>
				<note xml:id="q-264d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">DISTRIBUTION:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-274d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">3 A.C. of S., G-2 War Department (thru channels)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-284d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">1 Commanding General, Fifth Army</note>
				<note xml:id="q-294d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">1 Commanding General, XII Air Force</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">1 Commanding Officer, MBS.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">File</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>