<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Weekly Report by Home Intelligence - No. 56 - 29 October 1941</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-3122d58f-d6a8-4bf0-80dc-b9be35d01f0e</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-a405857c-2774-4c43-b5c1-e10b59b90d5c</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-935a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-945a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">Copy No 36</note>
				<note xml:id="q-955a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="3">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-965a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="4">Weekly report by Home Intelligence - No.56</note>
				<note xml:id="q-975a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="5">29th October, 1941.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-985a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">In reading this report, it is important to bear in mind that it is not meant to be a record of facts, except in so far as public opinion is itself a fact, It is a statement and reflection of the public's views and feelings about the war in general. Therefore, in mattes on which public opinion is ill-informed, prejudiced or inconsistent, the report does not imply any endorsement of the views which are expressed in it.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-995a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">It may be convenient to remind all recipients of this report that it is a confidential document, and therefore should not be disclosed to anyone else except by special authority of the Director of the Home Division of the Ministry of Information.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="10">HOME INTELLIGLNCE WEEKLY REPORT NO. 56</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9d5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="11">29th October 1941</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9e5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">Covering the period from 20th October to 27th October, l941</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9f5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">Note:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a05a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">The figures in brackets refer to sources of information, a list of which is given at the end of this report.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a15a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">No reports have yet been received of public reactions to President Roosevelt's speech or October 27th.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a25a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="16">I GENERAL COMMENTS hhh 1. General state of confidence and reaction to news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a35a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">Public interest continues to be focused almost exclusively on the campaign in Russia; but anxiety, though still considerable, has declined a little. Extremes of both despondency and optimistic complacency are no longer reported, and there is said to be a "general steadying of nerves", with confidence at a higher level than it was last week.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a45a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">At the: same time, the public appears to realise that 'the situation on the Eastern Front is as serious as it can be without being desperate'. 'Although it is felt that resistance in the Moscow sector is being maintained, there is increased anxiety in connection with the Southern sector, where it is feared that the Germans may penetrate to Rostov and so imperil the Russian oil supplies".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a55a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">The factors Making for the slight rise in confidence are:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a65a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">a. The continued defence of Moscow, after its fall had been accepted as inevitable. There are now even some hopes that the city may hold out, indefinitely. If it does fall, it is realised that it will only 'be at tremendous cost and that it will not entail the collapse of Russia. The transfer of Marshal Timoshenko, with its "suggestion that he has gone to prepare a new line of resistance and to organise fresh armies", has been taken as encouraging' rather than otherwise.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a75a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">b. Lord Beaverbrook's account of the "Russian handling of industrial-resources and imports" (and particularly of the 'leap-frog technique).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a85a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">c. A growing belief that we really are sending substantial supplies to our ally, and that Lord Beaverbrook's statements (in particular that "everything promised for October has already been sent") can be trusted.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a95a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">d. The beginning of bad weather in Russia, which, despite M. Maisky's warning, is taken as likely to help the Russians rather than the Germans.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-aa5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">e. The attack on the "Kearney", and the hope of resulting strong American action; and the anticipation of President Roosevelt's speech.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ab5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">f. The fact that the Japanese threat does not seem to have increased. There is some tendency to measure the seriousness of the Russian situation by the degree of Japanese aggressiveness; any decline in Japanese bellicosity is taken to mean that the Russians are not yet in a condition to 'stabbed in the back".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ac5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">g. The renewed, R. A. F. offensive, and particularly the bombing of Naples, without serious reply from the enemy; this has "renewed the feeling that the Luftwaffe is fully occupied in. Russia".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ad5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">h. Our prompt and energetic- action in Afghanistan, which has caused "pleased surprise''.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ae5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">i. The news of the Navy's successes in the Mediterranean against Libyan convoys.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-af5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">(1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12,13) hhh 2. Aid for Russia</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b05a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">The most striking-change in public feeling since last week is that the demand for a Western offensive is beginning to die down. Almost all reports agree that there is "growing realisation that a large-scale offensive by us may as yet be impossible There is "even some resentment at particular persons and bodies advocating Continental landings. It is pointed out that ''those with sons and husbands in the Army do not share the enthusiasm of many journalists for what might well be a costly Continental adventure. Though it is admitted that "there is nothing we can do for the moment", this situation is generally deplored. Lord Moyne's statement in the House of Lords is described by one R.I.O. as having been "widely accepted", but his, references to the folly of an attack in the West are coupled with Lord Halifax's recent remarks, as "encourag­ing the enemy to release further divisions for service on the Eastern Front". A few more subtle thinkers regard these statements as "traps for the Germans".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b15a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">The main causes for the public's change of feeling appear to be: -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b25a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">a. Lord Gort's despatches. The "revelations of the lack of equipment of the first have done much to impress the public with the difficulties inherent in such action". People are "afraid of a repetition", and are reported as saying: - ''For God's sake, don't let's have another Dunkirk, Crete or Greece.".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b35a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">b, The British Communist Party's agitation for a Western Front offensive, ''which appears to be acting in the opposite direction to that intended". Growing annoyance is being caused by the poster "Attack now in the West"; it is suggested that the "majority of people do not associate the Party with Russian propaganda", and that the "best thing Stalin can: do for himself is to disown them".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b45a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">c. The increasing realisation "that our chief role is that of Arsenal for our ally. It is pointed out, however, that the public does not yet seem to grasp the full significance of the industrial front in modern warfare; and it is suggested that MOM should be done to "vitalise this fourth arm of the fighting service in the public mind".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b55a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">(1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,9,10,11,12;13) hhh 3. Feeling about the Government</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b65a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">With the increasing readiness to accept our present position in 'connection with aid to Russia, people are speculating more about why this position has arisen. The Government, the "Civil Service bureaucracy", and the managerial-classes generally, are blamed for lack of both efficiency and initiative.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b75a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">The publication of Lord Gort's despatches, "regarded as damning criticism of the Government of that day", has "intensified the feeling against members of the Chamberlain Government who are still in office", and, in particular, the "appeasers". But the publication itself is welcomed as a frank acknowledgment by the Government of past blunders", and as a sign that the lessons have been taken to heart. It is felt that, by admitting errors, the Government strengthens its positions, and conversely, that by defending mistakes it weakens it.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b85a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">Certain sections of the public; stimulated by accounts of the sufferings of the Russian population, are reported to be, "prepared for greater sacrifices". There is a feeling' that we should be asked to give up still more luxuries and pleasures" (for example, horse-racing; with its expenditure of transport, time and man-power): and that the Government is now in a position to mobilise public opinion for still more intensive effort.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b95a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">(3, 6, 7, 8, 11, 12, 14) hhh 4. Shooting of French hostages</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ba5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">Anger and disgust have been everywhere expressed at the shooting of hostages, but this has "caused no surprise after the countless, worse examples in Poland and elsewhere". Such reprisals are "taken by the ordinary man, as merely another example of German lack of decency, and are considered by the more thoughtful to be fresh evidence of the German inability to govern a conquered people. While there is satisfaction at "symptoms of widespread subterranean revolt among the people in occupied France", it is realised that the assassinations can only bring still more savage vengeance. There is some fear that "the French have started too soon".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bb5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">"Strong anti-French feeling" is said to have minimised the sympathy which would have otherwise been felt for the victims. The publication of Lord Gort's des-patches is aid to have increased dislike for the French in many quarters; and this prejudice has been strengthened by unfavourable comparisons between French and Russian will to resist German attack. Darlan and Pétain are "hated and despised for their complete and crawling subservience to the Nazis". (1, 2, 4, 5, 7, 11, 13) hhh 5. News presentation and Broadcasting</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bc5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">The European News Service continues to gain popularity, on account of its simpler and more vigorous method of presentation"; it is said that a "fair number of people have now ceased to listen to the Home Service News", preferring the 11 p.m. broadcast as a "first-rate cure for depression". People who listen to both say, "It's the' same news but it sounds different"; and they go on to ask, "Why must the Home Service News be so dreary"? A minority view among listeners to the European News is' that the Home News "should not be too dressed up or over-optimistic".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bd5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">The enemy interrupter continues to cause amusement rather than irritation, but interest in him is declining. There are even one or two complaints that the B.B.C. is now so loud that it is impossible to hear the "ghost voice".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-be5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">Frank Laskier's second Sunday night postscript is described as "propaganda put over in the best possible way"; "people would not have accepted it from a politician, but from a man who has gone through it, they would accept anything".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bf5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">There are requests for "more personal stories about the Navy" in the B.B.C. news, "like those about the R.A.F.".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c05a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">(2, 4, 6, 7, 8, 11) hhh 6. Interest in Post-War conditions</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c15a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">There is a fairly steady degree of interest in post­war prospects, ranging from hopes of the "castles in the air" variety to serious constructive concern. The latter "scams to centre round the hope that after the war, certain improve­ments in the economic and social structure of the country, made necessary by the emergency, will be consolidated and extended. War aims now appear to be extending from the overthrow of Hitler to the betterment of our way of life".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c25a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">It is also said that 'Concern about post-war employment exists among those engaged in war industries, and some indication is required from the Government that they will really give everyone a square deal", in order that the mistakes of the last post-war period may not be repeated. It is felt that this would "help to remove apprehension and lead to increased effort among the-workers".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c35a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">On the other hand, among the more irresponsible sections of the public, it is thought that "escapist dreaming" of easy and prosperous days ahead leads to nothing but a slackening of effort; and it is questioned whether it would not be advisable to impress on the lighter-hearted the fact that the reconstruction period will be 'one of hard work and considerable financial stress.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c45a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">(3,7)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c55a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">There have been very few rumours this week. There is a rumour to the effect that at the evacuation of Dunkirk men wore told "to get away at all cost and not bother about equipment; but now men who left equipment behind are being asked to pay for it". Its origin is said to be an "influential source in Suffolk".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c65a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">It is stated that the reason why no publicity is given to our raids on the Continent is that the men go over there to collect letters (brought over at the rate of 3,000 per week). These men are said to be called "Phantom" troops and to have "P" on their shoulders.'</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c75a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">Other rumours are :- that three pilots, known to lack experience of night flying, were killed on a night flight when they 'were landing at a Cornish aerodrome; that there are "heavy and continuous losses of men and material" at a Bath aerodrome, sabotage being feared; and that "light signals are seen at night" in the Reading district.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c85a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">(4. 5, 6, 7)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c95a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="55">II SPECIAL COMMENTS hhh 8. Industry</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ca5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">Proposed Changes in Reservation</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cb5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">Further support has been given this week to Mr. Bevin's suggestion of abandoning block reservation in favour of consideration of individual cases. It is felt that "this would do away with many anomalies now evident".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cc5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">Criticism of Managements: Stories of slacking, muddle and incompetence in war factories and camps continue to circulate, with a marked tendency to stress the view that it is the managements who are to blame, and not the workers, save in isolated instances, (Imported Irish labour is the main exception quoted: Postal Censorship continues to report cases of Irish workmen writing home, "The ganger clocks us in whether we turn up. or not"; Consham Camp still seems to be particularly bad in this respect.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cd5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">Irritation is evinced by the workers at the continued appeals to drive ahead wish production, while it is felt that "it is the executive that needs all the pop talk". There is still a call for more explanation to the workers of the cause of stoppages, hold-ups, etc. It is suggested that where managements can give no reasonable explanation, they may thus be forced to improve their organisation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ce5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">Registration of Women: Strong criticism continues about what is called ''the Government's indecisive policy" over the application at compulsion. Young women are reported very widely as saying, they want us they can take us. I'm not going to volunteer till everyone else has to go". What is the difference, it is asked, between compelling women already engaged in war work to remain at certain vital jobs, which the Government does now, and seeing to it that the slackers share their labours, which the authorities apparently fear to do?</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cf5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">Two R.I.O.s report fooling that many girls who register arc pressed into decisions which later prove unsuitable; it is suggested that skilled impartial advisors (from Trades Unions or Citizens' Advice Bureaux) should be available at registration times, and if the girl or the interviewer wished it, they should be present at the interview.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d05a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">Doctors are alleged to be "snowed under with demands for medical certificates of exemption" as each new ago-group of women becomes eligible for service. The private practitioner, who is dependent on the goodwill of his patients, thus finds himself in a position of considerable difficulty.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d15a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">The unfortunate position of the A.T.S. in public esteem is summed up by .the report of the R.I.O. North Midland Region: "There is still much confusion about the powers of the Ministry of Labour, some people to whom these are now clear have expressed the opinion that girls would flood into industry if they were told that the Services were the alternative; the threat of the A.T.S. would be particularly effective.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d25a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">(1,2,3,4,5,6,7,9,11,12,13) hhh 9. Transport</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d35a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">Five R.I,O,s report discontent about transport for workers, Earlier black-out times, coinciding with -the cutting down of public services and the increase in the number of people who must work away from home, are focusing attention on this problem. Women shoppers, who take up the rush-hour places on the buses, arc regarded as a major cause of trouble. Instances are given of workers who arrive in the mornings "too tired to do their best" after much "scrambling and standing, and the daily strain of wondering whether they will get in at all"; others have to waste two and three hours at night, trying to get home". People attending greyhound races in Manchester are said to be crowding workers off buses and trams,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d45a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">Suggestions are made that :-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d55a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">a. The system of priority passes for workers should be extended.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d65a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">b. Queuing should be compulsory at all bus stops where crowds form.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d75a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">c. Efforts should be made to see that short-distance travellers do not crowd out long distance travellers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d85a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">d. No further 'appeals' should be made to women shoppers, who are evidently impervious to them, but where necessary buses should be reserved entirely for people travelling to and from certain factories, stations, etc.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d95a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">(1,4,6,7,10, 20 Inverness, Bristol P.C's). hhh 10. Evacuation</note>
				<note xml:id="q-da5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">The belief that "the official attitude to the problem is altogether too limp" is expressed in connection with report of children still flocking back to the chief target areas, "Serious misgiving" is voiced in such places as Dover where parents continue to fetch their children home despite all efforts at persuasion. From the reception areas it is reported that foster-parents have now "a feeling of the futility of their efforts and sacrifice in the Past". In this connection it is said that "people who are still doing the 'unshowy' job of looking after evacuees are due for a fillip, and means should be found to show the country's appreciation of their very real contribution to the war effort".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-db5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">The advent of cold weather has again raised the question of winter clothing for children in the country whose parents will not provide it. "Country people complain that the procedure of getting winter kit through official channels is far too lengthy, and some have advocated the establishment of local depots where vouchers, countersigned by billeting officers, could be presented in exchange for Clothing". Bad feeling is recorded in districts "from which parents have taken their children home, after the foster parents have provided warm new winter clothes at great personal sacrifice". (Suggestions have been made from time to time that there is a definite 'ramp'; parents are said to evacuate and re-evacuate. their children under the Government scheme whenever they need new outfits, trusting to the kind feelings of the country people.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">As in all other matters touching equality of sacrifice, there is the desire for the use of compulsory powers; it is thought "unfair" that the coming generation should suffer for the short-sightedness and selfishness of their parents; many people advocate enforced evacuation for children from certain areas. By others it is held that the system of billeting upon householders (both of children and adults) has on the whole been a failure, and that houses given over entirely to evacuees, if possible from the same district, is the only solution. Attention is drawn to the numbers of fair-sized houses advertised for sale in the newspapers: it is asked why, if these places are not wanted by their owners, they cannot be requisitioned by the Government for this purpose.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">(3, 4, 5, 7, 8, 12, 20 Cardiff P.C. 32) hhh 11. Food</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">The food position as whole continues to give general satisfaction.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">Miners: "The demand for an extra meat ration continues, and canteens do not appear to have gained in popularity. It is thought that propaganda on this subject needs to be directed to the women folk rather than to the miners themselves, as it appears that it is the women who are encouraging their men to feed at home".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e05a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">(1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 9, 11, 12) hhh 12. Income Tax</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e15a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">The need for more explanation of where income tax goes is again stressed. Especially is this said to be desirable with "first-payers" in industry, who are saying "Why should I work overtime for the Government?" There is thought to be "surprisingly little connection in the public mind" between, for instance, "new ships and income tax".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e25a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">(5, 7, 18) hhh 13. Service Dependants' Allowances</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e35a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">Discontent continues on the score of:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e45a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">(a) the time-lag before cases of real hardship can be redressed - a lag which is now expected to increase as a result of the new legislation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e55a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">(b) the savour of charity in the whole procedure".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e65a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">There appears to be considerable and unfortunate confusion between the functions of the Public Assistance Committee (now rechristened 'Social Welfare Council') and the Assistance Beard.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e75a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">Recourse to the former, a local-government body, is considered a disgrace, because of its peace-time connection with money Paid out to paupers. It is through the Board that' the increased scale of grants is to be administered, but "people will not go before it until they are desperate".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e85a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">The whole arrangement is considered "a miserable, half-done job". Increase in the basic allowance to children and wholly dependent mothers of Servicemen is once more strongly urged.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e95a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">(5, 6, 20 Special, 17, 32) hhh 14. Boredom among Civil Defence Workers</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ea5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">Complaints of the "mental and moral deterioration" of Civil Defence, Workers as a result of boredom multiply slowly. It is said they have to fill in long shifts on duty with almost nothing to do, with the result that there is reported to be a "considerable increase of gambling and heavy drinking", particularly among the younger men.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-eb5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">(5, 32) hhh 15. Clothes Rationing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ec5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">Clothes rationing continues to be an important topic of conversation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ed5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">There are more complaints this week from "war workers in heavy industries, especially those using oil", that clothes, in particular boots, wear out quickly and cannot be replaced owing to lack of coupons.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ee5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">"Much bad feeling" is reported from mining districts that the new coupon allowance for miners is exclusively for underground workers. "It is pointed out that many surface workers are doing jobs which are almost as destructive to clothing", 'and that it is "just asking for trouble" to allow 60 extra coupons to underground workers only.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ef5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">Extra coupons for growing children are still "eagerly enquired after", and the lack of detailed information is adversely commented on".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f05a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">There is said to be "a tremendous demand" for forms for obtaining new ration books, "and little check up as to whether the application is genuine".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f15a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">(3, 4, 5, 6, 11, 12) hhh 16. Constant Topics and Complaints</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f25a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">Delay in letters to and from men serving in the Middle East, and in the Iceland mail, is "causing widespread comment".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f35a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">The continued shortage of wireless batteries and spare parts has given rise to such criticisms as: "It is downright swindling on the part of the Government to take the money for the licence, and then not allow batteries to be made".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f45a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">"Considerable apprehension" is felt about a probable shortage of coal during the coldest part of the winter. Rural areas continue to report difficulty in obtaining paraffin.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f55a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">The price of flour for home baking continues to agitate North Country housewives. There have been more protests against the requisitioning of railings for scrap metal. At Newbury, there has been a demand that the Council remove its own railings before taking those of private residents.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f65a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">At Portland it is said that there are 500 tons of old railings which have been lying derelict for years. Further complaint is made of waste of steel on bombed sites in London, and of non-collection of salvage by local authorities.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f75a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">The match shortage is "still acute". Cleveland miners claim that they should have prior supplies, "as matches are necessary for their work".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f85a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">A shortage of children's Wellingtons, "and even of children's shoes, is said to be "serious in view of the approach of winter".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f95a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">Other shortages are: flints for cigarette lighters and lighters themselves, cigarettes and tobacco, beer, vinegar (now improving a little), and sanitary towels, combs, electric light bulbs.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fa5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">Eggs are variously reported as scarce and bad.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fb5a88b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">(1, 2, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 15, 20)</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>