<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Report on the State of Home Morale</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-43d22637-c9e0-42c9-b901-a40c16a6cab2</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-aee3013f-4aa7-4bde-b8b3-262f626b1c82</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-3c5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">DRAFT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3d5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3e5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="3">REPORT ON THE STATE OF HOME MORALE</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3f5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="4">This paper is circulated in accordance with the War Cabinet's decision of 15th April, 1942. Lack of time has prevented the views of other Home Front Departments being taken as will be done in future.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-405888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="5">1. GENERAL -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-415888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">For the past three months the prevailing mood had been one of frustration and loss of interest in the war and war news. Throughout April, however, there has been a steady improvement in spirits. Widespread satisfaction has been shown at the increasing weight of raids on Germany and the occupied territories, the growing number of combined operations, the bombing of Tokyo, and "the new austerity". The heavier penalties for black merketeers, the promise of restrictions on luxury meals, the extensions of points rationing, the abolition of basic petrol, and above all, the Budget, have been welcomed as real evidence that the Government is in earnest. Criticism of the Government has sharply decreased. The fall in interest in party politics, which has been in evidence for nearly two years, steadily continues.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-425888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">The most striking feature of the country's present mood is a sense of almost pleasurable expectancy, principally induced by the growing belief that we are about to open a second front. News items are beginning to be scrutinised from this point of view. The absence of a named objective in the Boulogne raid, for instance, is taken to mean that "we are spying out the land"; and the cut in the meat ration leads to suggestions that "the troops need the tinned beef for invasion". The enemy's renewed raids on this country seem to be being accepted with fortitude by the victims; while the country at large regards them insignificant in comparison with our own raids over Germany. There is no evidence of any desire for us to reduce the scale of our attacks. Demand for the bombing of Rome as a reprisal for Malta is growing.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-435888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">There is little belief that this country will be invaded, but the formation of local Invasion Committees and the Lord President's statement have stimulated a demand for details both about the duties of these committees and the conduct of the civilian in invasion.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-445888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="9">2. OFFICIAL NEWS &amp; INSTRUCTIONS -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-455888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">Criticism of official news has declined, but the public remains ready to pounce on anything suggesting that the Government is "holding bad news back" or "not being frank". Euphemisms for retreat like "Straightening of lines" always produce widespread sarcastic comment. There are signs that the multiplicity of Government instructions to ordinary citizens, particu­larly housewives, is causing bewilderment. Salvage drives have also made the public increasingly critical of anything which they regard as official or commercial waste of paper, such as Press advertisements of goods which are in short supply or which are no longer on the market, and official forms of excessive size or unnecessary complexity.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-465888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="11">3. INDUSTRY -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-475888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">Official statements of our positive achievements in realm of production seem to have produced the desired result, for criticism of our industrial effort has strikingly declined. The transport difficulties of workers remain the biggest single cause of complaint but hold-ups and idle time, the reasons for which have not been explained to the workers, are still reported.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-485888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">Women seeking part-time war-work in factories complain that their services are rejected. Shopping difficulties of whole-time women war-workers are still prominent. Disparities in pay between the services and civilian war-workers continue to be a grievance, particularly among service dependents. The need to supply the Russian front continues to be a powerful stimulus in industry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-495888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="14">4. CIVILIAN CONSUMPTION AND RATIONING -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4a5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">In contrast to other "austerity" measures, the fuel rationing proposals are being received with concern. People are prepared to go short of any commodity which has to be brought from overseas, but they attribute the coal shortage entirely to a mistake in calling up too many miners, and they are not convinced that the rationing scheme will be practical or fair to all.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">Warmth in the home is looked on as a necessity if food is to be short. And the housewife, already harassed by shopping problems, food, soap and clothes coupons, household salvage, the domestic black-out, and frequently her own war work, is dismayed at the prospect of being penalised for misreading her meter.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">The only outstanding food complaint is the very high price of green vegetables.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">Recommendations -</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">1. In view of the public agitation for a second front guidance on the following points would be welcome.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">A. Is it desirable from the military standpoint that the enemy should be kept guessing as to our intentions?</note>
				<note xml:id="q-505888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">or B. Is it desirable that he should engage his forces in the East believing that an attack in the West is impossible thus reducing his ability to meet an invasion if and when made?</note>
				<note xml:id="q-515888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">or C. Is it desirable that he should be made to believe that an attack is likely and thus be persuaded to withdraw troops from the East?</note>
				<note xml:id="q-525888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">Attempts to guide public opinion at home on the second front issue should be conditioned by which of these three points is considered most important militarily.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-535888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">If (A) is the desired course, it may be necessary in order to avoid a public feeling of frustration and irrita­tion to remind the public that in war surprise is of paramount importance and that for this reason there can be no official comment in the "Second Front" controversy, so taking them into a partnership for the mystification of the enemy. It might also be worthwhile deliberately inspiring unofficial but influential controversy in which the case for and against was argued.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-545888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">If (B) is the desired course, the public clamour for a second front should be met (1) by an explanation of the shipping and other difficulties in the way of landing an army on the continent, and (2) by more explanation of the world-wide strategy of the war, of the number of fronts that are already in being and of the fact that the name "second front" is a misnomer for something much better described as a Continental land front. The name second front with its implication that there is at present only one front of importance in the war - the Russian front - needs deflating.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-555888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">If (C) is the desired course, it will be necessary to consider very carefully the effect at home of allowing expectations to develop which may not be realised. Should it be adopted, it may become necessary to make it clear that while the idea of a second front this year is accepted, the choice of the right moment is a technical military matter and may have to wait until the first impact of the German spring offensive on Russia has lost its momentum, so that our attack can coincide with a Russian counter-offensive. In this way the urgency of the call for a second front now might be reduced to some extent while keeping alive the second front idea.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-565888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">2.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-575888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">While the public has been reassured as to the fighting capacity of British troops by the courage they have shown in Burma, an impression of strategical incom­petence, created by the fall of Singapore still exists. If Burma is not to be regarded as simply another depressing defeat, it is therefore necessary that as much information as possible should be now released to show the positive value of the campaign against the whole background of the war. The public was quick to appreciate the strategical importance of the defence of Crete and its effect on the course of the German/Russian Campaign when this was pointed out to them, although Crete had at first been regarded as an almost unrelieved disaster. It is necessary to do the same so far as is possible about Burma and to show generally the positive value of delaying actions at this stage of the war. The more the public can be brought to think in terms of a broad picture of the whole war and less in terms of isolated campaigns in which troops may seem to be sacrificed for no immediate gain, the better. But information and education is necessary for this.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-585888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">3.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-595888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">If the fuel rationing proposals are to meet with popular acceptance, further explanations, of the need them, must be given.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">4.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b5888b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">The policy of telling the public more about the positive achievements of the Nation's War effort (as has been done, for example, in the recent speeches of Lord Halifax and Lord Beaverbrook) has proved its value should be continued.</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>