<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Home Intelligence Weekly Report - No. 211 - 19 October 1944</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-222204e7-4d67-4de8-af26-bb58dd85f812</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-80a7817d-28a8-4191-97ad-595ed339d5aa</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-5d497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">Wt 16746. 10M 5/44. W.R.R. &amp; S. Ltd. GP 38. (14).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5e497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5f497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="3">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-60497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="4">HOME INTELLIGENGE WEEKLY REPORT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-61497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">No. 211.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-62497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="6">19th October 1944</note>
				<note xml:id="q-63497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">(Covering Period from 10th to 17th October, 1944)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-64497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="8">I. GENERAL COMMENTS hhh 1. General</note>
				<note xml:id="q-65497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">A further drop in spirits. The great majority are resigning themselves to the war lasting well into next year, and there is considerable disappointment, and some depression at the thought of another winter of war.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-66497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">There is still little comment on war news; the most generally discussed. Topics are the Social Insurance White Paper, the miners and the coal situation, and housing and employment - immediate and post-war. In Scotland, especially among the working-classes, the "coffin case" has aroused most comment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-67497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13) hhh 2. The battle for Germany</note>
				<note xml:id="q-68497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">Disappointment continues at our slow progress. While many expect the present tough fighting to continue "all the way", others think we are amassing supplies and men for an early all-out offensive.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-69497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">Aachen is the focus of interest, and its refusal to surrender is taken as a sign that all German cities will be as strongly defended. At the same time people disapprove of the option given to the Commander: "Each town should be completely destroyed as we reach it, not asked to surrender"..."The Germans, who treated Rotterdam and Warsaw ruthlessly, must learn what war is."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6a497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">Arnhem: Much sad comment again, on familiar lines. Opinion is still divided as of whether the tragic outcome was due to a blunder or to pure bad luck. Notification of casualties and returning survivors have increased the feeling that "it must have been hell on earth for the lads".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6b497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">Holland: There is considerable sympathy for the Dutch in their horrible plight, and anxiety lest the Germans implement their threat of flooding the country. At the same time people wonder if the Dutch, said to be dour and aloof to our men, are helping us..."Is there, for instance, a Dutch underground movement?"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6c497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">The bombing of Germany: Awe and great satisfaction are reported at its increasing intensity; also hope that such onslaughts will hasten the end.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6d497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">The Dunkirk truce: Exasperation continues: "Fancy giving the Germans time to replace mines!"</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6e497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13) hhh 2a. Attitude to Germany and the Germans</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6f497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">Fear continues that we are going to be too soft with the Germans after the war - "they will be pampered as the Italians are". People are unanimous that war criminals must be punished and Germany strictly controlled for a long period.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-70497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">(2.3.5.6.7.8.9.10.11) hhh 2b. Condition in liberated countries</note>
				<note xml:id="q-71497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">Resentment continues at the contrast between "the destitution we were led to expect", and the "well-fed and well-dressed reality" as portrayed in the Press. (Most of the comment again refers specifically to the French.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-72497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">In Scotland, news reels and press photos are being watched, to see if the Greeks really look as though they are starving.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-73497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">(1.3.4.5.6.8.10.11.12) hhh 3. The Moscow talks</note>
				<note xml:id="q-74497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">The visit to Moscow of the Prime Minister and Mr. Eden has been generally welcomed, and Mr. Churchill's determination, energy and agility are greatly admired. Nevertheless a good many people seem to think it is time Stalin did some of the travelling, both to prove his readiness to co-operate and to save Mr. Churchill some of the risks and fatigue.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-75497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">There are many guesses as to the subjects under discussion, which are variously thought to be:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-76497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">(a) The Russo-Polish question (All Regions). This is generally assumed to be the main theme of discussion. There is a widespread hope that the talks may result in the settlement of this problem, and the invitation to the Polish Prime Minister was considered a hopeful sign.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-77497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">Most people seem very bewildered as to the rights and wrongs of the Russo-Polish question, but "everyone agrees it is in a hell of a mess", and many fear the complications are so great as to endanger Allied plans, both for war and peace. Opinion is divided as to whether the Russian or the Polish point of view is more widely supported but a good many people believe that the Russians could have saved Warsaw if they had wanted to.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-78497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">(b) The final all-out offensive against Germany (Seven Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-79497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">(c) The war against Japan (Four Regions). A few people wonder if Russia will join in against Japan.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7a497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">(d) The post-war treatment of Germany (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7b497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13) hhh3a. Russia</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7c497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">Very little comment on the fighting, though people are glad that the Red Army is "on the move again". Some satisfaction is reported that Riga has boon taken and that the Russians arc now driving towards East Prussia. The apparent break-up of Hungary is noted with pleasure. Russo-Polish situation (See Section 3.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7d497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12.13) hhh 4. White Paper on Social Insurance</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7e497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">Widespread approval continues (Twelve Regions). The plan is again described as a great step forward and a hopeful sign for the future. The appointment of a Minister for Social Insurance has particularly pleased people as showing that the Government "means business".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7f497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">More detailed explanation of the plan, to help people understand the proposals, is asked for (Five Regions). It is suggested that the Brief Guide hoe not had enough publicity.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-80497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">Comment is on familiar lines:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-81497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">Implementation of the plan (Nine Regions). Scepticism as to its ever becoming law in its present form continues (Five Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-82497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">An increased number this week think it "only election bluff" (Five Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-83497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">Paying for the scheme (Eight Regions) People continue to wonder if we can afford the cost of so great a scheme, particularly in view of the other plans on hand. Some think it "can't -possibly be done"; a few continue to say "if we can pay for the war, no can pay for peace" (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-84497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">Fear of the possible effects on people's characters (Six Regions). Some people fear it will encourage shiftlessness and that the conscientious will be incomes for "the work-shy"; others think "spoon-feeding:" people will undermine our sense of responsibility "until we become notion of machines exactly like the Germans".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-85497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">Contributions (Four Regions). The high cost for employers (Three Regions) - particularly those in a small way of business, and for employees (Throe Regions) continues to be commented on.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-86497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">Comment about specific provisions</note>
				<note xml:id="q-87497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">Family allowances (Seven Regions). people continue to think that the cash allowance should be greater (Five Regions) and that the first child should have on allowance (Two Regions). Some criticise the allowance being payable to the father (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-88497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">A few dislike the .allowance (Two Regions; on the grounds that "they will be posing for other people's families".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-89497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">Retirement pensions (Six Regions) continue to be bought inadequate. Some think they should be adjustable to the cost of living.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8a497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">Some also think retirement for men should be at 60. Others think people should not be encouraged to work on after reaching retirement age, "so that young people will be given a chance". Benefits generally (Five Regions) arc thought insufficient particularly for unemployment (Four Regions)..."they do not provide freedom from want".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8b497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">Superannuation schemes and private insurance policies (Four Regions each). Anxiety continues as to what will happen about them.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8c497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">Approved societies and insurance companies (Three regions). Their future continues to be discussed. hhh 4a. White Paper on Industrial Injury Insurance</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8d497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">There is again little detailed comment - but some satisfaction. It is suggested people do not understand the proposals.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">(1.5.9) hhh 5. Italian prisoners-of-war</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">Resentment and dissatisfaction continue at the freedom and amenities allowed the Italian prisoners... Ordinary working people can't forget, even if the authorities can, that the Italians helped to bomb England. When we have beaten Germany, vie hope there will not be co-belligerent Germans." Specified complaints are: (a) luxur­ious travel facilities, (b) freedom to visit cinemas and dance halls unattended, (c) billeting in houses which could be used for bombed-out families.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-90497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">While criticism is mainly directed at "official coddling", strong feeling is also reported about the Italians associating with British women and girls... "not diminished by the foolish behaviour of some women".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-91497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">Many people again feel that these men should be sent back to Italy to help in the liberation of their own country..."Our boys are fighting and dying daily in appealing conditions, while the Italians time of here are having the time of their lives". Some also think that greater use could be made of them in agricultural communities, or that they should be "sent down the mines like our prisoners in Germany".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-92497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">(1.2.5.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12) hhh 6. Italy</note>
				<note xml:id="q-93497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">Military: Comment is again limited and on familiar lines. Bad weather is for the most part blamed for slow progress, which is cousin: anxiety and disappointment Confidence in General Alexander continues also sympathy and praise for the troops, particularly for the 8th Army who are thought to have borne "more than their share of war".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-94497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">Political: Dissatisfaction continues at our political handling of Italy. It is not understood why she is receiving such favorable treatment from the Allies, instead of being considered a defeated enemy. Some wonder also whether we are the help and guidance required; the food situation is thought to show defects in our administration.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-95497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">There is criticism, too, of the suggestion that Badoglio may become ambassador to Britain; also of the "absurd demand" of Italy for the return of her colonies - which may give a lead to the Germans after Allied victory (One Region each).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-96497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.12) hhh 7. Greece</note>
				<note xml:id="q-97497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">Great pleasure and relief at the landings in Greece and the liberation of Athens. There is much sympathy for the sufferings of the Greeks; it is hoped the whole country will soon be liberated and that food will follow as soon as possible. The political situation is looked on with misgivings by some.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-98497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">(1.3.4.5.7.3.9.10.11) hhh 8. Dumbarton Oaks proposals</note>
				<note xml:id="q-99497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">The proposals have, on the whole, been favourably received as a real sign of a determination to maintain peace. Otherwise, the chief points made are as follows:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">(a) Will it just Ne another League of Nations with the some weaknesses? (Seven Regions), few cynics say "the old plan with knobs on".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">(b) Even though the day of separated nations is over and collective security-essential, will the great nations really agree? (Four Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">(c) The principle of an armed force to support decisions is a good one (Four Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9d497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">(d) Whet would happen if one of the Biz Five became the aggressor? (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9e497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">(e) Some would like to see provision made against the withdrawal of major states from the proposed organisation, as happened in the Case of the U.S.... after the last war (One Region).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9f497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">(1.3.4.6.7.3.9.10.11) hhh 9. Flying bombs</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a0497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">Concern continues at the attacks, though interest has declined. There is some relief at their produced scale - and some hope they may soon cease.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a1497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">People outside target areas wonder whether airborne flying bombs can be used against other parts of the country as well as against London and the South.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a2497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">Reactions in target areas</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a3497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">London: There is depression and disappointment at the recurrence of raids, though only a fool alarmed or worried. People are anxious at the possibility of the raids going on throughout the winter; they live in hope that they will soon be checked. The sounding of alerts when they are not followed by bombs is criticized in one quarter as merely "keeping people on thorns to no purpose". Some bitterness is felt that those in the North and West "think flying bombs are a thing of the past - while for us the war is far from over".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a4497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">Eastern Region: Uneasiness at the continuance of flying bombs. People in country districts are said to be particularly nervous because they come over before the siren goes. Many are said to yet up at every siren during the night, and are getting tired. They are also upset at the prospect of this going on all winter.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a5497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">South Eastern Region: People in Kent and Sussex are thankful to be no longer in the flying bomb target area. hhh 9a. Explosions</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a6497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">London: Comment has considerably increased this week; discussion and rumours are said to be general. There is a certain amount of nervousness about what is generally believed to be rocket bombs -and some apprehension lest the numbers sent over increase, or lest "the weapon be perfected", Some want a Government statement.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a7497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">Eastern Region: Rumours of rocket bombs having fallen are said to be persistent, although sonic do not believe them. Where explosions have been heard, people are thought to have "accepted things calmly" and to regard the destruction as being less than with flying bombs.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a8497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">South Eastern district: Where explosions ore said to have been heard, it is wondered if B.B.C. news reports ore correct as they have not reported any activity on some of these occasions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a9497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">The rest of the country: Rumours of rocket bombs continue, though on a reduced scale. Some resent the absence of a Governemnt announcement that a new weapon is used.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-aa497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">(1.2.3.4.5.7.8.10.12) hhh 9b. Evacuation</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ab497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">Evacuees continue to return, or to think about returning. Criticism of Mr. Duncan Sandys' speech also continues. hhh 9c. Shelling</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ac497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">The inhabitants of Dover and Folkestone are "quietly thankful", particularly for unbroken nights. There is no "over-jubilation" and indeed some resentment at the "influx of nosey sightseers who drink all the Deer, and eat everything in the restaurants and shops".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ad497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">(3.7.12) hhh 10. Far East</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ae497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">Little comment this week; this general loch of interest distresses relatives of servicemen there.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-af497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">Satisfaction with progress in Burma continues, and there is pleasure that the "Forgotten Army" is having more publicity. Anxiety about the men's health is mentioned.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b0497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">The U.S. successes in the Pacific are giving encouragement and pleasure.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b1497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">China: The lack of news about the military situation is causing some disquiet and speculation. It is feared that unless help reaches. China very soon it will be too late.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b2497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">Prisoners-of-war: Pleasure that they are to be allowed to send one cable home at Christmas.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b3497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.10.11.12.13) hhh 11. The Town and Country Planning Bill</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b4497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">The Prime minister's intervention was approved by the many people who felt that, in view of the desperate housing situation, development must not he held up. Others, however, felt the "shelving" of the compensation clause meant that vested interests had won again.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b5497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">Most workers are now cynical at the Government's "surrender to landed interests"; and a large minority of people generally favour some form of requisitioning or control of land by the local authorities.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b6497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">(1.2.3.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12) hhh 12. Civil aviation</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b7497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">During the past two weeks, a little desultory comment has been reported on the appointment of a Minister of Civil Aviation. The choice is said not to be entirely popular.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b8497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">(1.2.5.6.8.10.13) hhh 13. News presentation and broadcasting</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b9497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">Praise continues for (a) Major Lewis Hastings' War Comentary; (b) War Reports - particularly as they now cover several fronts, Reports not only the Western; (c) Controversial discussions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ba497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bb497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="95">II. SPECIAL COMMENTS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bc497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">BRIEF WEEKLY REVIEW hhh 14. Coal output</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bd497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">People are increasingly- concerned and anxious about coal output and domestic fuel supplies- particularly in view of the Durham and Scotland strikes and the threatened Yorkshire one. The high price of coal is also much resented.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-be497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">Impatience with the miners is growing. Absenteeism is still largely blamed for low output; the drafting of younger absentees to the Forces continues to he urged.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bf497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">The Ministry of Fuel Power and the Government (Eight Regions) are also criticised for their "weak handling" and mismanagement of the industry. Nationalisation, however, continues to be urged (Five Regions)..."if it's the only solution, then yet on with it".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c0497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">The American report on British mines (Two Regions): It is asked why this report has not been published. Miners are said to believe it answers many of the criticisms levelled at them and allege that it is being intentionally withheld.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c1497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">(1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.12) hhh 15. Demobilization</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c2497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">The Government's plan continues to receive general approval, with particular satisfaction that compulsory recruitment is to continue, so as to relieve those who have already .served for long periods.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c3497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">A number of reservations continue, nevertheless, to be made, chiefly on the grounds that:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c4497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">(a) Points should be added or overseas service (Six Regions) ­"Those who have seen abroad longest should come home first" ­and for combat at service (Four Regions)...The soldier who has had five year service without leaving this country is thought to come off cry well.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c5497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">(b) Priority should be given to various classes, such as teachers, married men with one-man-businesses; and students who joined up in the midst of their studies. Opinions differ as to the claims of older men "who have a shorter time left to live in peace ' and younger men "who are sweethearts and husbands, and the father of the future generation".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c6497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">(c) Jobs are just as important as demobilization. Some go so far as to advocate that no demobilization should take place till plans for re-absorption into industry are made. People fear "all the decent jobs will be snapped up by the first out".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c7497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">(1.3.4.5.6.7.9.10.12) hhh 16. The announcement that the Home Guard and Civil Defense Serviced may retain their uniforms</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c8497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="108">Home Guard (Ten Regions): Great pleasure is reported... "The War Office has far exceeded expected generosity".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c9497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="109">Civil Defense (Five Regions): Great pleasure, hut some uncertainty as to who is eligible and for what. hhh 17. Points rationing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ca497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="110">Press stories (since denied by the Ministry of Food) that points rationing was shortly to be discontinued, or greatly curtailed, caused more dismay than rejoicing It is felt that if points rationing: were to be discontinued, "people with money would comb the shops and get everything". "Housewives would prefer more points allocated", rather than do away with points altogether. Those who welcomed the news only did so "as long as it doesn't mean canned food becoming unobtainable".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cb497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="111">The press is criticised for publishing the story without seeking the Ministry of Food's confirmation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cc497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="112">(1.2.5.7.8.9.10)</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>