<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Apprecation Report No. 8, for the week ending April 10, 1943</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-206f8109-928b-4a60-a996-28fd52460713</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-1abfeae8-9578-4898-bc36-3bcd6dc49ed4</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-f316e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="contact" n="1">OFFICE OF THE CHIEF BASE CENSOR BASE CENSORSHIP DETACHMENT No. 3 APO 512, U.S. ARMY</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f416e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="theme" n="2">Appreciation Report No. 8</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f516e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="3">For the Week Ending April 10 1943</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f616e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="4">1. The following report is based primarily on officers' mail. Be­cause of existing conditions, information on enlisted men’s' mail obtained this week does not present a well-rounded and representative picture. Un­less otherwise noted, quotations are from officers and the discussion applies mainly or solely to them. Brief reports are also presented on two special groups, Red Cross employees (par. 2) and other civilians (par. 3). Such data on particular small groups are not presented each week but certain groups are singled out for comment from time to time as observations warrant. As usual, the bulk of the report refers to military personnel of our area as a whole. Mail from 12 A.P.O.'s is included in this week's tab­ulation. About two-fifths are from A.P.O. 512. Some morale quotations from soldiers' foreign language mail are given (par. 5). These have been gathered over a period of two weeks and are typical of this particular sort of mail.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f716e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="5">Officers Red Cross Employees Other Civilian % % % Mention 56 49 71 GENERAL MORALE Good 99 65 91 Bad 1 35 9 Mention 20 22 7 HEALTH Good 96 23 100 Bad 4 77 0 Mention 8 12 4 MAIL SERVICE Good 23 17 17 Bad 77 83 83 Mention 6 10 6 RATIONS Good 91 70 38 Bad 9 30 62 Mention 3 11 4 QUARTERS Good 98 54 67 Bad 2 46 33 Mention 1 8 + OFFICERS Good 83 25 -- Bad 17 75 -- Mention 8 7 1 RELATIONS WITH FRENCH Good 97 43 100 Bad 3 57 0 Mention 5 3 RELATIONS WITH BRITISH Good 96 100 -- Bad 4 0 -- Mention 15 11 57 DOMESTIC AFFAIRS Good 96 36 100 Bad 4 64 0 + = Less than 1%</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f816e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subject" n="6">COMPLILATION OF MORALE INDICATIONS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f916e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subject" n="7">AS MENTIONED IN PERSONAL CORRESPONDENCE</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fa16e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="8">2. RED CROSS PERSONNEL:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fb16e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="9">A special morale and security check was made this week on personal letters written by American Red Cross personnel throughout their operations in the region served by this office. The mor­ale check is given in the preceding table. This is much the worst morale record of any unit so far checked. In almost every case the percentage of "Bad" comments is very much higher than for any strictly military personnel. Although general morale is bad only in a minority of Red Cross letters, 35%, this is incomparably higher than the percentage for members of the armed forces, average 2% Complaints of bad health, 77% of references to health, are remarkably numerous. Complaints about rations, 30%, quarters, 46%, and superiors- (tabulated as "officers"), 75% also indicate unusually bad morale conditions. Red Cross workers are the only group so far examined in which unfavorable references to the local French, 57% outnumber favor­able. Even their reaction to news from home is usually unfavorable.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fc16e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="10">Only as regards condemnation of mail service, 83% unfavorable, and approval of the British, 100%, do they agree with the reactions of military personnel.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fd16e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="11">The security record of Red Cross personnel is also outstandingly bad. They show definite improvement (especially in the personnel that has been in Algiers for some time) as a result of returns and instructions from this office, but this week 29% of their letters still required some censorship action, mostly excision to prevent revealing localities of A.P.O.'s. This percentage is extraordinarily high and indicates a serious security problem. Although Red Cross personnel is small relative to the military, they write very frequent and often voluminous letters.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fe16e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="12">On the other hand, references by military personnel to the work done for them by the Red Cross are favorable with few exceptions.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ff16e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="13">3. CIVILIAN PERSONNEL:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0017e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="14">A special check was also made on personal letters of American civilians, other than Red Cross employees, working for the Army or otherwise accredited at this headquarters. Some of the data are presented in the preceding table. Although general morale within this group is somewhat lower than for military personnel, it is satisfact­ory, 91% good in comments in letters. More specific morale reactions resemble those of army officers in most respects. The principal exceptions are that the civilians complain much more about food, 62% of comments bad against an average of only 6 for officers, and about their quarters, 33% bad against average of 8% for officers. The morale record of other civil­ians is uniformly better than for Red Cross employees except as regards complaints about food. This exception doubtless reflects the known excell­ence of the Red Cross mess in Algiers. It is noteworthy that officers, who certainly are fed no better than civilians to whom the army messes are open and who perhaps are not fed as well as Red Cross personnel, complain much less about food than do either of these two civilian groups.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0117e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="15">The following comments are believed to be of interest as regards con­ditions among civilians at headquarters and the reaction of some officers working with civilians. (Continents are from letters by civilians unless otherwise noted). Although gathered from the mail of a few days, these are typical of remarks common in mail from and about civilians throughout the period of our operation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0217e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="16">"You used the right word when you said you imagined me ensconced in a villa as I am just that. . .The Army gave me a guard with the house. He is very obliging serves me coffee in bed and does all the things for me personally such as clothes pressing shoe shining etc." (N.A.E.B.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0317e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="17">"The British ration is free, the American costs almost nothing. I don't get enough smokes of the kind I like, but I take everything and I've already got a small hoard locked up in my wardrobe." (AFHQ).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0417e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="18">"As I've said before don't let money be a big hurdle. . .The financial situation is bound to improve. . .I go to the 5600 a year bracket without delay. . .Two checks for overtime pay sent to the bank. .</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0517e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="19">"As you know besides our salary we have been receiving 7.00 dollars per diem. However, new government regulations are going to cut down that sum to something like 2.00 dollars per diem. . .But here's another angle. If by chance I should be moved from my present locality. . .I would again be entitled to the 7 dollars per diem."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0617e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="20">"That, of course, is the nice thing about the apartment that we can entertain, thus creating a social atmosphere that helps in the work. I really think that you should make some investment in government bonds. Everyone is expected to do that, and I don't recall that we were doing it." (Civ. Affairs Div.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0717e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="21">Officers' comments on civilians are almost uniformly unfavorable. Ex­amples:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0817e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="22">"I curse the day I was ever snared into Public relations. This job is just an empty vacuum filled with fat-headed prima donnas who call them­selves war correspondents, claim all the rights of soldiers and refuse to accept any of the responsibilities. They all suffer from diarrhea of the tongue and constipation of the ego." (Officer, P.R.O.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0917e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="23">"There are twelve jeeps and around 30 correspondents. Each correspond­ent wants a jeep. The agency men won't ride with any other agency man and the specials won't ride with other specials, and the still photographers. Won’t ride with other still photographers. " (Officer, P.R.O.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0a17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="24">4. GENERAL MORALE:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0b17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="25">There is no particular change in general morale. Mentions are about average (56%) and a very large percentage of these (99%) continue to be favorable. The more specific morale situation also continues without noteworthy change. As before, the only particularly bad morale factors are mail service and (among officers) dislike of superiors and disappointment in promotions. In both cases some improvement over last week is indicated. Confidence in an early victory continues to be reflected in letters and references to an early expected return to the U. S. are rather numerous. Quotations:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0c17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="26">"Ours is really a great outfit and I am proud to be with it." (1st Bn., 18th Inf.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0d17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="27">"We had a very successful day on the 5th and have been complimented highly all down the line. I'm very proud and for once could tell them I was completely satisfied. I don't think your ancestors will like us one bit." (99 B.G. (H.)), to a girl with Italian name).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0e17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="28">"The machine gunners of the bomber crews we've worked with have done a marvelous job and we have a lot of respect for their ability." (81 Ftr.. Gr., 93 Ftr. Sq.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0f17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="29">"I suppose you think that we are fighting a helluva war talking about shows and (lances, but this kind of work gets monotous once in a while and it's not all pie and honey either. Although we can't complain a bit." (205 M.P. Co.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1017e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="30">"I still don't know what this war is about but I do know she is a rough game if it’s for fun." (95 Sq., 82 Gr.). "Honey, after I get back, I'm going to try my damn best to forget everything that ever happened over here and just concentrate on our happin­ess. I wouldn't relive this for a hundred million dollars." (48 Surg. Mosp.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1117e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="31">"I swear that if and when any more (Censor: promotions) are handed out and I am not the first to get the next one, they will never get any work out of me again--I have had enough of this damn outfit and everyone connected with it." (97 B.G., 340 B. Sq.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1217e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="32">"Brother I'm tired, homesick, scared and disgusted. I withdrew my application for a regular commission." (414 B.S., 97 B.G.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1317e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="33">5. FOREIGN LANGUAGE:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1417e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="34">The following quotations are by enlisted men, all privates or P.F.C.'s, who are first- or second-generation Americans writing to families or friends in America in Spanish, Italian, or Portuguese (extracts translated by examiner). The extracts are fairly typical of all the mail of this sort passing through this office. Morale in this group is invariably excellent and these letters are also good from a security point of view. Religious expressions are unusually prevalent in these letters.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1517e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="35">"I always wanted to be a Ranger. . .They are the ones who have the first name in the world and one must prove himself a man to become a Ranger. So far, thanks to God, I have so proven myself." (Spanish, 1st Ranger Bn.). "May God grant that I live to see the finish of the detestable German race which has caused so much suffering to peoples everywhere." (Portuguese, 178 P.A.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1617e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="36">"I feel downhearted at being separated from you but as the saying is ’When a Mexican has worries he hides them with song.' After all we are men and it is our duty to fight until God gives us victory." (Spanish, 432 C. A. (A.A.)).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1717e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="37">"Mother I don't need the recommendation of a political sponsor in order to get promoted. I am very happy being a first-class private. Here among the Americans we are all equal." (Spanish, 62 Sig. Bn.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1817e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="38">"It doesn't bother me that we are face to face with the enemy, because my faith is very great and I have full confidence and trust in the Virgin of Guadalupe." (Spanish, 36 F. A.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1917e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="39">"I am writing this while squatting in my foxhole - ha: ha! and it isn't like your office either. Anyway this is war and what do I want -- Eggs in my beer?" (Spanish, 36 F.A.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1a17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="40">"I have little to tell you only that I pray God that this war will end once and for all and that everyone may live in peace." (Italian, 213 A. R. ).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1b17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="41">"A few days ago they passed a law providing for the return of us older men and I think I may apply for a discharge. . .I'll have to think it over. I think my record so far is good and I have tried always to make myself useful. . .I like my officers and comrades--that is the main thing." (Ital­ian, 213 C.A. (A.A.)).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1c17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="42">"The newspapers back home say that we are in a paradise--well, if paradise is like that, what must hell be like?" (Spanish, 175 F.A. Bn.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1d17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="43">6. HEALTH:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1e17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="44">The data on health are almost exactly the same as last week. The only new note encountered was a reference to cases of malaria appearing in the army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1f17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="45">7. MAIL:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2017e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="46">Opinion of the mail service is a little less servere than last week, 77% of comments unfavorable as against 85% but the generally low opinion is not much improved. These comments on mail are typical of the frequent emphasis of its importance for morales.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2117e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="47">"We know that we don't get it all but are mighty thankful for all we do get." (77 Evac. Hosp.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2217e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="48">"I received your first mail in North Africa and boy was I glad to hear from you and boy a:a I reading that letter over and over again. I read it every time I have time off. I guess I will read the ink right off of it." (Enlisted man, NATAF).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2317e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="49">8. RATIONS:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2417e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="50">Officers' approval of rations, 91% of comments favorable has increased somewhat over last week (86%) but is still a little below the previous average, about 94%. These fluctuations probably are not sign­ificant. Approval is usually in general terms. Disapproval tends to be more specific:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2517e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="51">"I don't think I'll want any more stew for a while after I get back from this business. We are so much better off, though than many people in the world, who have nothing to eat. Hope we can start feeding them one of these days. I'll divide my share with them." (HQ, 1st F.G.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2617e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="52">"Told my Dad there were 4. things we boys want over here:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2717e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="53">1. Steak dinner, ketchup, apple pie and ice-cream.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2817e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="54">2. Women - been months since we saw one and then she wasn't a specimen of feminine pulchritude.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2917e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="55">3. Seconds on the dinner.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="56">4. One way ticket home." (805 T.D. Bn.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="57">"The food is terrible. All the meat you are doing without must be going to the ground officers in back of the lines for all we eat is dried beef, hot dogs, cabbage, or stew. No kidding it's no good." (91 Ftr. 93 Ftr. sq.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2c17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="58">"The only thing I complain about here is the food we get. We live mostly on 'C' rations. The boys back on the west coast of Africa who aren't doing a damn thing get good food." (81 Gr., 93 Sq.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="59">9. QUARTERS:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="60">Approval of quarters continues high, 98% of comments favorable, which is somewhat the hi host yet observed. Previous average was 92.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="61">10. OFFICERS:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3017e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="62">Adverse criticism of superior officers is 17% of comments on this topic, still more than the earlier average, 14A but a marked improvement over last week, 32% Despite this frequency of condemn­ation by fellow officers, the most severe criticism seen this week happens to be from an enlisted man:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3117e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="63">"As far as I am concerned I am so disgusted with my outfit I don't care to try for anything. . .The officers are so lousy it's a shame to call them 'Sir.'" (Co. A, 2619 Prov. Tr. Bn., 551 Shore Regt.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3217e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="64">11. RELATIONS WITH LOCAL POPULATION:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3317e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="65">Comments on the French are unusually numerous in this week's mail (in 8% of officers' letters) but indicate about the same level of approval (98%). Amorous episodes with local girls seem to be increasing and as the troops move on they give rise to odd attempts to write French, G.I. style, such as "Jespere vous alley pardon me," Moi chez est overt a vous," or "J'ai sui bien et jai voulez you etrie bien osee." Evidence of less amorous good relations is also abund­ant.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3417e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="66">12. RELATIONS WITH BRITISH:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3517e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="67">References to the British are also unusually numerous, 5% (previous average 2%) and continue at the same high level, 96% favorable.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3617e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="68">13. DOMESTIC AFFAIRS:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3717e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="69">No noteworthy change.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3817e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="subheader" n="70">14. CENSORSHIP AND SECURITY:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3917e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="reporttext" n="71">References to censorship have become very numerous since the issue of NATOUSA Circular 39. A special memo­randum on these has been sent to the Chief Censor and no comments are included in the present general report. Reference to special factors of security is also omitted here.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3a17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="contact" n="72">CHAS. T. HEREFORD</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3b17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="contact" n="73">Captain, Infantry</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3c17e013-1390-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="contact" n="74">Assistant Chief Base Censor</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>