<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Weekly Report by Home Intelligence - No. 17 - 29 January 1941</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-ff32f4e7-304c-4e18-80e3-0fbc179a14b3</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-a5c46e88-94d0-49f7-a52f-77011ae2711e</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-1f5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-205988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">Copy No 1</note>
				<note xml:id="q-215988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="3">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-225988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="4">Weekly Report by Home Intelligence - No.17.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-235988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">(From Wednesday 22nd. January, to Wednesday 29th January, 1941)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-245988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">Note: The figures in brackets refer to sources of information, a list of which is given at the end of this report.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-255988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="7">I. GENERAL COMMENTS hhh 1. General state of confidence and reaction to news.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-265988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">Though the realization is growing that "we are in for a critical period in the near future", (2,5x, 11, 22 Manchester, Glasgow, Inverness P.C.) a feeling of confidence still prevails. Anticipa­tions that "the end of the war is drawing near" are fairly frequent (5x, 22 Cambridge P.C., 27). "The tide of battle is fast changing, and this year will see old England on top of the lot" is a remark quoted by Postal Censorship which characterizes the trend of many letters (22 Birmingham, Bristol, Leeds, Glasgow, Inverness P.C.). Delighted with "the crumbling of Italian forces", many people are inclined to believe that "Italy is on the verge of capitulation" (22 Birmingham, Manchester, Cambridge, Reading, Inverness P.C.), The absence of air raids has caused a certain amount of speculation about Hitler having "something up his sleeve (1,4,5x,739), but the possibility of this seems to arouse no serious anxiety. The suspicion is gaining ground that what his sleeve conceals are plans for invasion, probably through Eire (2,4,5x,6,11,12,22 Bristol, Glasgow, Cardiff P.C.,39). There is, however, complete confidence in our ability to deal successfully with such an adventure. At the same time, many people appear to have forgotten the instructions-' issued about "staying put", etc. (4,11,39), and it is suggested that some of the earlier publicity about what to do should be revived (6,18,39).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-275988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">Interest in America's attitude shows some signs of stimulation. This is attributed partly to Roosevelt's extremely cordial welcome to Halifax, and partly to Willkie's visit to this country, which are described as "alleviating the unimaginative and critical apathy" of the public's attitude towards American assistance (7,12,13,18,39). hhh 2. Reprisals.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-285988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">There is still a chorus of opinion favouring reprisals. (5x, 7, 11, 18, 19 S.Western,22 Birmingham, Glasgow, Inverness, Belfast P.C.). hhh 3. Extremist activities.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-295988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">Except for a leader in the Daily Mirror, Press reaction to the suppression of the Daily Worker was favourable. Subsequent articles by Cummings in the News Chronicle, by Frank Owen in the Evening Standard and an article by Cameronian in Reynolds expressed doubt about the means invoked to impose the ban. The Tribune says that the ban "will enormously strengthen the Communists' propaganda."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">German propaganda stations make use of the news, as might have been expected. Haw Haw gives the news with little comment; Workers' Challenge and N.B.B.S., while dissociating themselves from Communism, make much of the fear and tyranny which caused this "suppression of workers' liberties".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">Indirect methods of studying public reactions showed that as many people opposed the ban as supported it (26). Many, however, were disinterested. Those who were against suppression gave as their main reason the importance of having a safety valve for airing grievances. There was little evidence that people thought that the Daily Worker and/or the Communist Party were engaged in sabotage or subversive activities.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2c5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">The main Communist periodicals now circulating in this country are:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">Challenge weekly</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">World News and Views weekly</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">Labour Monthly monthly</note>
				<note xml:id="q-305988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">Russia Today monthly</note>
				<note xml:id="q-315988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">Inside the Empire monthly</note>
				<note xml:id="q-325988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">Labour research monthly</note>
				<note xml:id="q-335988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">New Propellor monthly</note>
				<note xml:id="q-345988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">There are in addition a number of specialist publications addressed to workers in various industries. hhh 4. Political matters.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-355988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">The debate on production and manpower aroused only a confused reaction: many people welcomed the sign of Government activity, but Bevin's statement was given a critical press, and the Prime Minister's assurance that "the Government was getting into its stride" was received with some scepticism. The omission to set up a national wages policy was also criticised in several papers (5x, 18, 19 North Eastern, 37). hhh 5. Broadcasting.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-365988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">Interest in enemy broadcasts is the-subject of a B.B.C. listener research report, 20th January (29). From this it appears "there has been no increase in listening over the last few months, and though there may be a tendency to under-estimate the amount of listening, there is every reason to accept the evidence as broadly indicative." Listening to Italian and other foreign stations is said to be negligible. The report indicates a decline in "the audience, as well as the influence, of Haw Haw and probably of Workers Challenge too." This is corroborated by evidence from other sources (22 Bristol, Manchester P.C.,24), which confirm also that the chief inducements to listen to foreign stations are bad reception of B.B.C. programmes, and the hope of hearing news which might be delayed or suppressed by British censorship (8, 29, 39)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-375988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">Listener research has also made recently a special summary of the public's radio habits (29) which shows that "about 15 million of the total adult population of 35 million listen nightly." On week days the audience rarely exceeds an average of 3 million in the morning, "or reaches as much as 3 million in the afternoon."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-385988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">Week-Days</note>
				<note xml:id="q-395988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">6:30pm - 3.5 million</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3a5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">8:30pm - 6 million (Sat. 11 million)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3b5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">9:30pm - 5 million (Sat 6 million)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3c5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">11:00pm - 1.5 million</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3d5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">Sundays</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3e5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">(Morning and Afternoon) 4.5 million</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3f5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">Nearly 8 million</note>
				<note xml:id="q-405988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">Over 6.5 million</note>
				<note xml:id="q-415988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">The audience average is highest at 1 o'clock on Sundays, when there are about 17.5 million listeners.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-425988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">Priestley's return to the microphone has not aroused much comment, but what has been said has been, on the whole, favourable (1, 11, 39). hhh 6. Rumours.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-435988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">A decline in Haw-Haw rumours is indicated by the direct evidence of Police Duty Room reports (24), and indirectly by the very small number quoted by other sources.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-445988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">Among tales of mystery and imagination reported this week are accounts of 50,000 parachutists descending on Newcastle - a story afterwards attributed to the escape of a barrage balloon; the machine-gunning of the King and Queen (after they had watched a mock raid at a Suffolk aerodrome); and a "gas scare" at Southampton, resulting apparently from the destruction of a cold storage plant (4, 22 Birmingham P.C., 33). hhh 7. Air Training Corps.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-455988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">"Great enthusiasm" is reported for the Air Training Corps (1,4, 9,13,18, 19 Midland,39). The only criticism is that the scheme was Said to have been prematurely announced on the wireless, so that the authorities Were overwhelmed with enquiries to which they could give no reply</note>
				<note xml:id="q-465988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">(1,2,39). hhh 8. Juvenile Crime.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-475988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">Growing alarm is recorded at the growth of juvenile crime (2, 10, 39).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-485988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="42">II. SPECIAL COMMENTS. hhh 9.Air Raids.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-495988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">Slackening of nightly air raids has led to a reduction of the tube shelter population from its peak - 177,500 on 27th September to 65,000 on 28th January 1941 (19).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4a5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">The compulsory nature of the fire fighters order still receives favourable comments (5x, 14). Progress in organisation for protection of residential property is reported from Manchester, with accompanying ''slowness of organising business and commercial schemes" (23 Manchester T.C.) Good response to appeal is reported from several Regions (1,9) and movement to provide both voluntary and paid fire fighters has been "much accelerated" in Scotland (11). Some perplexity is voiced by volunteers with regard to "payment for hours put in at night", and/ or whether they will be given a food allowance, and of details of compensation for injuries incurred while on duty (6). Misgivings are stated to exist among women who anticipate "that their menfolk will be taken away at night leaving them to look after children and cope with incendiary bombs single-handed" (7).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">This week there has been considerable press criticism of the Government's Raid Compensations scheme, chiefly on the grounds that "owners have to pay a fixed contribution, though no clause is made for the compensation to be paid at any fixed time." (18, 19 Midland and S.Western).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">Although there is still occasional expression of apprehension of a possible sudden use of gas, (5X), the proportion of people carrying gas-masks has dropped to "less than half" in ten out, of 16 towns studied (37), and to "less than in Yorkshire, apart, from school-children and some factory workers" (2). A recent survey taken in Barnsley, Halifax and Cleckheaton reveals "a general belief that the chances of a gas attack are extremely remote".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">It is said in Manchester that "as a result of the blitz 50,000 people are without masks" (10) hhh 10. Shelters.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">Improvement in many communal London shelters is reported to be "moving at a good round pace" (5x), but many complaints are voiced at persistent flooding and dampness in large numbers of Anderson shelters, in spite of recent concreting (19.39). Bad effects on the health of pregnant and nursing mothers who travel long distances to spend nights in communal shelters with little food are deplored (14 Bristol). Requests for facilities for drying clothes and for lock-ups of valuables are requested in the East End of London where pilfering is reported, and workmen cannot dry their clothes (5x, 39). hhh 11. Evacuation.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">The publication of the Government White Paper on Evacuation ha€ roused considerable press comment, but raises no new issue of importance (19).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-505988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">Little change in the actual situation is reported, but apprecia­tion of the value of communal feeding centres is reported to be growing in some reception areas" (4).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-515988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">The "trickle back to the South Coast" is shown by Postal Censorship to have grown into a "steady flow" (22 Manchester P.C.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-525988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">The nocturnal and week-end evacuation from Bristol is stated to be causing much local controversy and irritation (7) and also a serious crowding. of all roads leading out to the country. "Disorgan­ised voluntary evacuation is helping to strengthen class bitterness and to prepare the ground for defeatism and subversive propaganda". (14 Bristol). (Note: Bristol has now been declared an official evacuation area, so this situation should gradually be eased.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-535988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">Main reason for mothers and young children returning to London is still stated to be the impossibility of "managing on present rate of allowances for working man and wife who maintain two homes" (5x, 39). hhh 12. Food.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-545988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">The food situation still occupies the forefront of the public mind and complaints are increasing in number and variety (4,5x,6,7, 8,11,18,19 London, 22 Inverness, Glasgow, Leeds, Cambridge, Birming­ham P.C.,33,39).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-555988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">Shortage of meat and difficulties of obtaining substitutes are main reasons for grumbling, especially among the working-classes who cannot easily think of new dishes to take the place of those made from unobtainable commodities (7,8,11,22 Inverness, Leeds, Birmingham P.C.,27,39).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-565988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">Lack of meat and other proteins is reported to be a serious grievance in factory canteens and Government Training Centres (5x, 32, 39). The supply of meat to restaurants and people able to eat there without coupons arouses protest (5x, 22 Inverness P.C., 39).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-575988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">The difference between Service and civilian rations is shown when soldiers are on leave, and cause difficulties to retailers and much adverse comment - e.g. that they are allowed 7/6d for meat per week as compared with 1/2d (18). Complaints of waste in army camp: are received from many sources (6,18,22 Bristol P.C.,33,39), and that N.A.A.F.I, canteens are "heavily stocked" in districts where there are serious shortages (7,18).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-585988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">Criticism of distribution is growing (5x, 8, 22 Birmingham P.C.), and Postal Censorship begins to show criticism of Lord Woolton, largely for tardy price control which "tends to make foods disappear from the markets" and restrictions on unrationed food (5x,6,8,11,18, 22 Cambridge P.C.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-595988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">Queues for and inequalities in supplies of eggs to local retailers come in for many unfavourable comments (18). Local authorities and retailers are often blamed for shortages by the general public (27) and there is much resentment when "full rations are not obtainable" (27,39).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">A recent B.I.P.O survey reveals that 42% of housewives have "difficulty in getting unrationed foods"; 29% stated "no difficulty; 165 said, "price too high"; 13%,"don't know" (19). hhh 13.Trade and Industry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">"Tremendous need for more day nurseries and more day centres for children of women workers. Lack of these facilities is said to be one of the greatest drawbacks to women entering essential industries" (5x, 32, 39).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">Women workers, especially married ones, are seriously concerned about the shopping situation. "For working women the dinner hour, their only shopping time, does not enable them to buy the food they need, as much of it is sold out early in the morning and many shops close during the middle of the day." Some factories stagger hours for women workers to meet this need (5x,32), but this practice is not universal and some women workers are reported to have left industry because of these difficulties (39).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5d5988b6-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">HOME INTELLIGENCE.</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>