<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Home Intelligence Weekly Report - No. 167 - 16 December 1943</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-37692600-ca49-44fe-87c6-96e8eba27ba8</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-485094b7-be95-4f5c-9ed0-655b7e951e53</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-be487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">Wt 39944. 10M 11/43. W.R.R. &amp; S. Ltd. GP 38. (14).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bf487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c0487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="3">MINISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c1487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="4">HOME INTELLIGENCE WEEKLY REPORT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c2487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">No. 167</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c3487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="6">16th December, 1943</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c4487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">(Covering period from 7th to 14th December, 1943)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c5487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="8">I. GENERAL COMMENTS hhh 1. General</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c6487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">Spirits are at about the same level as last week. Pleasure is again reported at the successful outcome of the Teheran Conference; Mosley's release still causes some bitterness; but there is comparatively little comment on any war event, and personal affairs come first:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c7487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">(a) The flu epidemic and illness generally are causing a good deal of depression, discomfort and inconvenience. Tiredness and war weariness arc also widely reported.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c8487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">(b) Christmas. Though many look forward to Christmas as a rest and a break in the routine, there is much anxiety about Christmas fare and grumbling over the price and shortage of toys.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c9487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">Other home front topics: Scepticism over post-war prospects continues; so do complaints of insufficient coupons, particularly for renewing household goods; and problems of footwear, children's specially.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ca487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11.13. 17) hhh 2. The Allied Conferences</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cb487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">Widespread satisfaction, particularly with the Teheran Conference, and strengthened hopes of an offensive in the West or the Balkans. Interest, however, does not appear to be intense, nor comment varied; .this is attributed to lack of information as to the decisions reached, and -to a certain impatience with "momentous conferences" - a desire for deeds not words.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cc487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">First Cairo Conference: Much approval for the promises to China and the decisions about Japan. Many, however, feel that to announce the drastic curtailment of the' Japanese Empire is rather premature and over-confident. There is a slight increase of interest in the Far Eastern War.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cd487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">Teheran Conference: Again great pleasure that "the Big Three" have met at last, that their meeting has been so cordial end that it appears to have resulted in complete agreement. The fact that Stalin has actually been out of Russia is in itself considered "a wonderful stroke of business".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ce487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">Accounts of the presentation of the Stalingrad Sword caused pleasure.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cf487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">Turkey and the second Cairo Conference: There is widespread speculation as to what Turkey will do. When the Churchill-Roosevelt Ineunu talks were first announced, there were high hopes that she would come into the war at once or in the near future. Now people seem loss hopeful and there is some irritation with optimistic press headlines which suggested Turkey was about to enter the war. It is variously thought that she will do nothing till Rome has fallen or till we land on her shores to back her up, that the loss of the Dodecanese has discouraged hers that she will remain on the fence till the ends and that she may even betray some of our secrets to the Germans.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d0487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">The news presentation of the Conferences: Again criticism of our getting the news last. It is suggested that delays which allow the German radio to make announcements before our owns tend to make the public listen to and believe other items in enemy broad­casts. There is some criticism that the festive side of the Conferences was too much stressed; the reference to 37,500 eggs having been consumed being particularly resented. A few ask why Mr. Churchill is "always on the left of the pictures as if he came third"..."and why his name is last in the signatures".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d1487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11.13. 17 ten provincial P.Cs.) hhh 3. The Mosley release</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d2487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">Discussion, though still widespread (Eleven Regions), is slowly dying down. It continues on the lines reported last week with feeling against the release strongest in industrial areas, and most support for Mr. Morrison's action among the middle-classes. Those who still feel strongly now allege that the voting after the debate clearly showed that Parliament is out of touch with public opinion (Four Regions). The growing minority who feel the Home Secretary is right are now inclined to blame the press for having exaggerated the whole affair.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d3487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.9.10.11. 17 one Special, twelve provincial P.Cs.) hhh 4. Allied air offensive</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d4487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">Great satisfaction-continues (Eight Regions), particularly with the raids on Berlin. Still more intense bombing is wanted. Losses in men and planes cause some anxiety.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d5487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">The raid on Emden by the U.S.A.A.F. (December 11) is praised (Three Regions), though there is some scepticism about the claim of German fighters destroyed (Two Regions); from a third Region it is reported that U.S. claims are thought to drop when our fighters accompany their bombers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d6487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">People variously feel the air offensive is shortening the war (Three Regions), making the second front unnecessary and saving many soldiers' lives (Two Regions each).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d7487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">However, regret among a minority at the killing of German civilians and the general destruction is reported from six Regions. It is said there can be no rejoicing at the smashing of homes. On the other hand a "storm of anger" is said to have been aroused in the diocese by the Bishop of Gloucester's Diocesan Letter in which he roundly condemned the bombing of Germany. It is felt he should retire if he can't stop "upsetting folk"; and that such sentiments should not be publicised in wartime.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d8487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8. 17 eleven provincial P.Cs.) hhh 5. Reprisals and Secret Weapons</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d9487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">A few people in London, the South East and the North feel apprehensive about reprisals; people in other parts are "undisturbed".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-da487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">Discussion of the secret weapon threat has declined (Three Regions) and little concern is now reported.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-db487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">(1.2.3.5.5SE. 17 two provincial P.Cs.) hhh 6. Russia</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">Admiration for the Russian progress continues widespread. People are pleased that recent German counter-offensives achieved so little, but a minority fear that Kiev may be recaptured by the Germans. There is some speculation about a Russian winter offen­sive.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">Speculation is also reported about the extent of Russian influence after the war (Five Regions). Whilst most are hoping for post-war co-operation with Russia, there are still a number who view post-war Russia with doubt.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9. 10.13. 17 two provincial P.Cs.) hhh 7. Italy</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">There are still many references to disappointingly slow pro­gress, which leaves the enemy far too much time to dig himself in. Nevertheless some arc satisfied that the advance, if slow, is sure. People are said to realise the toughness of the going.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e0487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">There is again praise for the 5th and 8th Armies which are fighting under such difficult conditions. Some people are beginning to feel that this front is only a side-show..."we are not falling into the trap of concentrating large forces there and playing into German hands".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e1487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">Despite the announcement about an Italian unit fighting alongside our men, the Italians are still looked on as not being of much use. It is thought that a much firmer attitude should be adopted to protect our troops from Italian profiteering, hhh 8. War at Sea</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e2487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">General satisfaction with the recently announced defeat of the two U-boat attacks on an Atlantic convoy. In three Regions the news is said to have been accepted as further proof that the battle of the Ltlantic has been won. The results are thought to speak well for the co-ordination of the Services engaged.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e3487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">(1.2.3.5.5SE.6.7.8.10.13) hhh 9. Lord Woolton's speech in the House of Lords (December 8) and post-war planning</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e4487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">There has not been much comment, but the speech appears to have been well received. Opinion is, however, divided between those who think it was wise not to promise too much, and those who feel that promises are necessary in reconstruction: "We want to know what we've got ahead of us".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e5487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">Post-war planning: Fears continue to outweigh hopes. Some regard Lord Woolton's appointment and speech as clear signs that the Government is really beginning to plan. But many - particularly workers- remain skeptical.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e6487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">Homes, jobs and social security continue the main pre-occupations.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e7487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.10.11.13. 17 one Special, six provincial P.Cs.) hhh 10. General Smuts' address (November 25)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e8487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">Praise continues for what is generally regarded as a personal expression of opinion by a realistic and far-sighted statesman.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e9487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">Most comment is about his references to France; opinion is divided between those who approve his outspokenness and those who regard it as ill-timed and likely to damage Anglo-French relations.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ea487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">A few people think he was "put up" by the Government to make the remarks. His references to Britain being poor after the war also arouse mixed feelings. Some say it is time we faced this fact; others that it is nonsense.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-eb487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">Reports from four Regions refer to some speculation about the delay in publishing the speech.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ec487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">(1.2.3.4.6.7.8.9.10.13.17 Seven provincial P.Cs.) hhh 11. Yugoslavia</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ed487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">There is confusion about the guerilla forces, and about the merits of the rival generals.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ee487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">(1.2.3.5.5SE.6.11) hhh 12. The French</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ef487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">Criticism of the French, in part stimulated by the Lebanese affair continues on a reduced scale.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f0487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">(1.3.5.5SE.8) hhh 13. Broadcasting and presentation of news</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f1487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">Little comment on news presentation. Complaints continue of the inaccuracy of news (Four Regions), the press being especially criticised for over emphasizing minor points and for sensational headlines. There is also criticism of delay in releasing news, thus allowing German stations to announce it before us (Four Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f2487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">Programmes: B.B.C. entertainment programmes are again criticised: too much modern music and jazz, and too little good music (Four Regions). Broadcast plays are liked and more would be appreciated (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f3487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">The Mayor of Narvik's postscript, December 5, is highly praised (Five Regions)... one of the most memorable postscripts given".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f4487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f5487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="56">II. SPECIAL COMMENTS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f6487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">SHORT WEEKLY REVIEW hhh 14. Health</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f7487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">The prevalence of influenza is widely reported this week (Eleven Regions), although in two Regions the epidemic is thought to be past its peak. People are said to be very tired arid to lack resistance.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f8487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">The prevalence of illness generally is variously attributed to food deficiencies, long hours of work and extra duties, the black-out, poor quality shoes and lack of warm under-clothing, long waits for transport in bad weather, and overcrowded buses. Official statements concerning the good health of the-nation are looked on as contrary to experience and cause irritation..."it is clear that resistance to infection is generally much lower".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f9487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">Doctors: The shortage of civilian doctors and the proposed further call-up for the army, when the civilian medical profession is so over-worked, is causing some concern. The temporary releases of some army doctors for civilian work is welcomed. Long and weary waits in surgeries which sometimes remain open until 10.30 p.m. are reported, and it is thought that many people "just drag. on as best they can".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fa487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11. 17 one Special, six provincial P.Cs.) hhh 15. The ballot for the mines</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fb487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">There has again been considerable comment on the scheme. The general reaction has been a mixture of approval and criticism; it is felt to be a "necessary evil". Approval: The scheme is generally accepted as fair and democratic (Eight Regions). Some, particularly miners, have doubts, however, as to whether it will be equally fair in practice (Three Regions). Exemption, it is feared, will be too easily obtained by those with education and influence.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fc487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">Criticisms: Chief criticisms of the scheme have been as follows</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fd487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">(a) It is impractical (Six Regions), because:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-fe487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">(i) Such "haphazard" selection will mean many misfits (Five Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ff487fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">(ii) "Green labour" will not provide the required production (Four Regions). Miners think the war will be over before the boys become adequately proficient.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-00497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">(b) It is unfair to force boys into the mines, while strikes are tolerated (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-01497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">(c) It has been made necessary by "muddling" in the past (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-02497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">The boys themselves are said not to relish the idea of mining instead of the Forces. Some are saying that they will refuse to enter the industry..."prison before the pits". Mothers are in many cases equally anxious.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-03497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">Alternatives suggested are: The release of miners from the Force and industry (Eight Regions), nationalisation of the mines (Six Regions) and "settling the miners' grievances" (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-04497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">Other points raised have been:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-05497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">Cadets: The waste of training is deplored (Five Regions). It is felt that membership of the various corps will suffer accordingly.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-06497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">Billeting: It is feared that mining families and billetees will not mix very successfully (Four Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-07497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11. 17 five provincial P.Cs.) hhh 16. Toys and other Christmas presents</note>
				<note xml:id="q-08497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">There are many complaints of the shortage, high price and poor quality of toys (Seven Regions), and the difficulty of providing Presents for children. There is also comment on the difficulty of finding "seasonal goods" and on the exorbitant price of fancy articles.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-09497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">The following are each mentioned in one Regional report:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0a497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">(a) Appreciation for the release of more toys.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0b497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">(b) The announcement that retailers may now sell second-hand metal toys acquired from private individuals has been received with the comment; "It'll just be a racket". Some think that the sale of home-made and second-hand toys generally is "a regular ramp which should be looked into without delay".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0c497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">(c) Christmas cards, on sale at high prices in spite of paper shortage and restrictions, are the object of criticism.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0d497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">(1.2.3.5.5SE.6.7.10) hhh 17. Food</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0e497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">General satisfaction remains, although comment continues about the shortage of fish (Five Regions), and the smallness of the present milk ration (Four Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-0f497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">Other topics now in the public mind are:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-10497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">Christmas fare (Eleven Regions):</note>
				<note xml:id="q-11497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">(a) Turkeys (Eight Regions). Hopes and fears - mostly the latter - regarding the prospects of getting a turkey are widespread. A few complain that hotels and large towns are to have all the turkeys and other poultry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-12497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">(b) "Extras" (Five Regions). There is some disappointment and crumbling at the "limited" Christmas food this year.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-13497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">(c) Profiteering and black market (Four Regions), especially in -turkeys and whisky are criticised. One Region mentions America "encouragement" in this respect; Americans are said to be offering up to 26 for a small turkey.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-14497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">(d) Shortage of dried fruit (Three Regions) is anticipated with disappointment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-15497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">(e) Christmas and Now Year drinks: People in Scotland and the South East are anxious about supplies.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-16497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">(f) An increased sweets ration over Christmas is hoped for by a few (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-17497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">Food for invalids and old people (Five Regions): These people's "plight" is regretted. It is felt that the shortage of milk, fish and oranges enhance' problem.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-18497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10.11.13. 17 one Special, twelve provincial P.Cs.) hhh 18. Housing and billeting</note>
				<note xml:id="q-19497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">Complaints and anxiety continue to be reported on familiar lines.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1a497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">(2.3.4.5.6.7.9.10.) hhh 19. Clothing</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1b497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">Comment on the usual lines, with special reference to:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1c497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">(a) Footwear difficulties (Eleven Regions), particularly shortage and poor- especially for children; also the difficulty of getting shoes repaired and the delay entailed.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1d497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">(b) The shortage of coupons generally, particularly for replacing household goods (Nine Regions), and for children.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1e497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">Extra coupons for larger children: A few complaints of or inequality are reported (Three Regions) Some inefficiency on the part of the schools is alleged. One report refers to a school whore children were refused coupons if they were absent on the day of examination. Another mentions a child who just missed the extra coupons by ½ on the day he was measured, yet whose feet were of the requisite size by October 31, the final date for measuring. In these tests, much is said to depend on the teacher. It is asked when there will be further tests.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1f497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">Some complain of the conditions, not understanding by "growing boys just under the height limit, but with small feet, get no coupons, yet a small child with large foot gets extra".</note>
				<note xml:id="q-20497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10. 17 one special, five provincial P.Cs.) hhh 20. The Services</note>
				<note xml:id="q-21497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">50th and 51-st Divisions: The return of members of the 50th and 51stDivisions is causing comment and many believe they are to be the spear-head in the invasion of Western Europe (Four Regions). Some consider they have had enough fighting and should not be sent abroad again.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-22497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">Forces' mail. Two reports refer to parcels from men in the Forces abroad being tempered with. One refers to "organised thieving" from parcels from the Middle East, many of which fail to arrive intact - "food parcels often do not arrive at all". It is suggested that the contents list should be erased after censorship, as this particularly when it mentions silk stockings is a temptation, Some concern is also expressed by the public on learning of the "non-arrival of parcels sent to the men out East''. One case is alleged where seventeen parcels were sent, not one of which was received.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-23497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">R.A.F.: Some concern is expressed (Three Regions) at the alleged loss of pay and rank" incurred when men are grounded through circumstances beyond their control. This is thought unfair.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-24497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">(1.2.3.5.6.7.10.11) hhh 21. Agriculture</note>
				<note xml:id="q-25497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">Comment is again reported on the revised farm prices announced by the Ministry of Agriculture (Five Regions), outside farm circles, some people think there is no reason for complaint; but farmers themselves are disappointed and fearful for the future. They resent the public being given the impression that subsidies give profits to the farmer, whereas in fact they only reduce the price of bread and milk to the public.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-26497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">Feeding-stuffs for farm stock (One Region): The increase announce by the Minister of Agriculture (December 8) has given pleasure.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-27497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">The control of sales of poultry from December 1 (One Region) is thought to have had a "very devastating effect on sales". Many complain that the prices are uneconomic.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-28497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">(3.4.6.7.8)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-29497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="108">III. PERIODICAL REVIEW hhh 22. Youth</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="109">During the past four weeks concern at the behaviour of young people has continued widespread. Complaints have been chiefly of:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="110">(a) Excessive drinking (Nine Regions) , which is held largely responsible for the increase in V.D; and</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2c497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="111">The immorality of young people, particularly girls (Seven Region The following factors are considered responsible:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="112">(i) Access to public houses is too easy for people under eighteen (Four Regions). Publicans are thought often to be indifferent as to whether people under eighteen are being served.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="113">(ii) The lack of social centres for young people (Three Regions)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="114">(iii) men and women in the Forces particularly are thought to need more clubs to</note>
				<note xml:id="q-30497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="115">keep them off the streets at night.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-31497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="116">(iv) Insufficient women police (Three Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-32497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="117">(v) Lack of soft drinks (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-33497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="118">(vi) Absence of a "No Treating Order" (Two Regions).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-34497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="119">(b) Juvenile delinquency and hooliganism (Nine Regions). Wanton damage to property and unruly "gangs" in the streets are deplored. Lack of parental control (Four Regions), high wages, and the films are blamed. It is suggested that the Hereford Court Case gave undesirable publicity to the only form of correction which might act as a deterrent.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-35497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="120">Youth Organisations are praised (Six Regions) and it is hoped they will be extended. A new interest in them is thought to exist; some who were formerly against compulsory membership of youth organisations are now veering round to the view that this is the only way to check juvenile delinquency.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-36497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="121">It is felt that youth organisations are best run by people not much older than the members.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-37497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="122">(1.2.3.4.5.5SE.6.7.8.9.10. 17)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-38497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="123">SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-39497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="124">Copy No. 283</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3a497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="125">MININISTRY OF INFORMATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3b497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="126">HOME INTELLIGENCE WEEKLY REPORT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3c497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="127">The aim of this Report is to present an impartial assessment of public feeling about the war and the war effort. It is not a record of fact, except in so far as public opinion is itself a fact. The public is sometimes ill-informed, prejudiced, or inconsistent. The recording of such feelings without comment implies no endorsement of them.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3d497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="128">The public is more prone to criticise than to praise. Good work or efficiency is usually taken for granted. An accurate record of expressed feeling will therefore, Lend to be critical rather than laudatory. Though this Report must inevitably represent mainly articulate opinion, it has been found in practice that the views of the less articulate do not substantially differ, though their range is smaller.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3e497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="129">The method of compiling the Report is such that the amount of space devoted to each subject, and the order in which subjects are placed, are roughly indicative of the amount of public interest each is arousing. The omission of a subject from the Report means that it is not a matter of widespread comment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3f497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="130">In assessing the state of public feeling there are no absolutes. Findings can only be comparative. Each Issue of this Report must therefore be read as part of a con­tinuous series. Unless the series is soon as a whole, the significance of fluctuations in feeling cannot be appreciated.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-40497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="131">The figures in brackets at the end of each section refer to sources of information, a list of which is given on the next page. The weekly reports from Regional Information Officers (R.I.Os.) are compiled by their Regional Intelligence Officers from a large number of sources. Details of the methods of compilation and cross-checking are contained in a paper on "How the Rome Intelligence Weekly Report is made". This will be supplied on request to the Homo Intelligence Division of the Ministry of Information. P.T.O. hhh REFERENCES</note>
				<note xml:id="q-41497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="132">1. Northern Region (Newcastle)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-42497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="133">2. North Eastern Region (Leeds)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-43497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="134">3. North Midland Region (Nottingham)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-44497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="135">4. Eastern Region (Cambridge)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-45497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="136">5. London Region (London)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-46497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="137">5SE. South Eastern District Office, London Region (TunbridgeWells)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-47497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="138">6. Southern Region (Reading)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-48497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="139">7. South Western Region (Bristol)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-49497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="140">8. Wales (Cardiff)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4a497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="141">9. Midland (Birmingham)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="142">10. North Western Region (Manchester)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="143">11. Scotland (Edinburgh)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="144">12. See 5SE.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="145">13. Northern Ireland (Belfast)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="146">14. Special Reports from R.I.Os.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-50497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="147">15. Regions Adviser's Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-51497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="148">16. M.O.I. Speakers' Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-52497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="149">17. Postal Censorship</note>
				<note xml:id="q-53497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="150">18. Police Duty Room Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-54497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="151">19. Wartime Social Survey Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-55497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="152">20. B.B.C. Listener Research Papers</note>
				<note xml:id="q-56497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="153">21. B.B.C. Special Papers</note>
				<note xml:id="q-57497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="154">22. Scottish Unionist Whips' Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-58497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="155">23. Liberal Party's Reports</note>
				<note xml:id="q-59497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="156">24. Primary Sources</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="157">1-13 are Weekly Reports from R.I.Os.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="158">391</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c497fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="159">D 37138-1 10,000 6/43 R P W</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>