<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Morale Report for the Period 2 April to 8 April 1943</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-1e496192-4120-4c56-99d9-f389b2ab0f77</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-4b08481b-77f4-4e70-a689-3fd0c6d12065</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-1a4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">CONFIDENTIAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1b4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">EQUALS BRITISH SECRET</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1c4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="3">OFFICE OF THE CHIEF BASE CENSOR</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1d4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="4">Base Censorship Detachment No.1</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1e4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="5">APO 700 Postmaster, New York, New York</note>
				<note xml:id="q-1f4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="6">8 April 1943.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-204c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="7">Subject: Morale report for period 2 April to 8 April 1943, inclusive.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-214c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">To: Theater Censor (thru channels)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-224c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">1. Health. The good health of our troops is evidenced by favorable comments received through references in letters. There is continual praise for the manner of performance of the medical personnel. Evidence continues to indicate that venerals are prevalent. About 95% of all comments on health have been favorable. The following are excerpts from letters examined:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-234c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">"Medical inspection is frequent and sanitation of equipment and personnel excellent. Appearances not as nice as the 'Biltmore' or some other fine hotel, but sanitation probably better than in many commercial restaurants. If our Medics are a fair sample, then the health of the army should be better at the close of the war than at present, as we have very good Medics, bother officers and men."--431st Sep. C.A. Bn. (AA).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-244c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">"Our sick calls are usually small--the general health of the command is very good. V.D. is quite a problem, of course, but is most anywhere."-­344th Engineers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-254c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">"We got 550 patients here with clap and other V.D. Most of them got clap from the hore houses in Oran. Keep away from the hore houses the pros don't help. They say here the clap is worse than in the States. And besides the hare houses belong to the French. We got more nigger patients here than white."--2nd Convalescent Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-264c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">2. Mail. About 70% of all comments on mail service have been unfavorable. There continues to be numerous complaints of not receiving mail for long periods in some units though it is evident that those in the postal system are attempting to do all in their power to push the mail out quickly. It is indicated that confusion still exists over the original shipping A.P.O., thereby causing undue delay in receipt of mail. Continued adverse comments are frequently noted concerning articles published in the States on mail service to troops overseas. The following comments were received:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-274c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">"You should see the boys when they get mail in. Everybody breaks their neck to get it out, they are all looking for a letter for themselves. We get in 59 pouches of mail about supper time and they will work it up before bedtime, hoping to find a letter or two for themselves, that is the reason we have the best APO in the world. Vie don't let mail lay around we get it out as soon as it comes in. If the rest would do the same the mail service in Africa would be as good as in the States, but you can't give the boys mail service if you don't open the place until a certain time if the mail comes in late you close up and leave it lay." Postal Section, Hq., Fifth Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-284c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">"It surely is funny about a soldier--you can starve him, shoot him up, no sleep, no nothing and he takes it as the unpleasant part of army life-but take his mail away from him and he really howls. I've had men tell me that they could not sleep, knowing that a letter was in the orderly tent. So now I never fool around with the mail-as soon as it comes in it goes out, regardless of the hour or the weather."--66th Armored Regt. "The first letter I got here made me really happy. The secret of soldiers morale is a good mail organization."--lst Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-294c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">"Any mail from home is really the main thing we boys thrive on. I speak from actual experience. My bunch of boys can be down lower than as....well, you know what. Then when our mail man comes through with happiness (mail from home) I have a new outfit full of pep and raring to go. So you know we must have received lots of it last week. How do you like the news from our side now? Mail did it; so keep 'em writing."-- 1661 Ord (MW) Co.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2a4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">"Mail service is vastly improved. V-mail goes into action on the 15th of April, this will without doubt help the service even more and it shouldn't be too long before mail reaches either side in less than two weeks. I am living for that day."--Hq. Co., Fifth Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2b4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">"I received my 1st APO 700 letter from you yesterday--2 of them in fact. It sure is like a shot in the arm to hear from home."--6th General Disp.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2c4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">"Mail day is our biggest day over here. Gee, we all look forward to it. For almost two weeks no one has received any mail except local mail."-­32nd Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2d4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">"We have had no mail from home in weeks. I wonder why, we certainly miss it."--40th Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2e4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">"Mail to us is terrible, we never seem to get it properly. You can't blame us for being whoppy about it, it's so silly."--19th Replacement Bn. APO 700.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-2f4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">"We are still trying to get some news on our APO 3404 so we can get some mail. No one seems to know anything about it though we will probably get the mail after the war."--444th Bomb. Sq., 320th Bomb. Gp.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-304c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">"The C.O. just received a phone message saying that a month's mail has lying at another station 80 miles away, so once again the van is going for it. There should be a lot for me."--RAF A 9181.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-314c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">"In the March Readers' Digest, I was reading an article called "Soldiers Mail", or something like that. It was saying what great pride the post office took in getting soldiers mail all over the world in such a short time. Then it 'set forth' a set of rules for the people in the states to follow in writing to a soldier. It said to write V-mail, because it was faster, safer, and saved space. That is all nothing but a damn lie. It may save space but who cares about their damn space. We didn't come over here for our health and at least the damned post office idiots could get regular letters over here to us without printing lies like that. It also said write cheerful letters. That is more 'poppycock'. I want to know just how you are and how you feel. I don't want you write and make things sound better than they are. The whole article made me so damn mad I could kill and enjoy it. In the first place, the people who write those articles are sitting behind a desk making a big profit writing war 'ballyho', and they don't know one thing about how conditions really are. They write as they were authorities on the subject."--111th Observation Sq.,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-324c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">3. Training. Comments have been noted regarding the state of training of newly arrived troops from the States and their apparent lack of basic experience. Lack of comments on this subject is usually referred to by writers as being cen­sorable. About 85% of all comments on this subject are of a critical nature. The following comments have been noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-334c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">"We have been getting new pilots in and I am going to lose...as my co-pilot. He had been doing a hellava swell job and if he checks out it means a promotion for him, so more power to him. You can bet your old man is going to be busy pulling up his own wheels, setting throttles and RPM and pulling up his own plabs until I am damn sure my new co-pilot knows what he is doing. They are all fresh out of school and will have plenty to learn when they get going."--441st Bomb. Sq., 320th Bomb. Gp.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-344c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">"We get quite a kick out of these guys who come over here direct from the States; boy they really find plenty to gripe about. The men who have been in England certainly get much more army experience than the men coming from camps in the States. Some of them even don't know how to pitch a pup tent, never were on maneuvers, never slept on the ground."--Med. Detach. Base Hq., APO 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-354c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">"Flew an hour and thirty minutes this morning, practice formation and bombing. Sure wish we would start to do something useful. Course this stuff will come in handy when we get into combat, but it gets awfully tiresome right now."--441st Sq. 320th Bomb. Gp.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-364c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">"I must tell you about my unique experience last night. I had the opportunity to go up in a plane with some 'paratroops' that were making a night practice jump. Boy, what a thrill--rather they then I. They certainly are a tough bunch of boys--they have to be." - -52nd Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-374c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">4. Equipment. About 90% of all references to equipment have been favorable. The effectiveness of the Bofor gun is praised in comparison with the 37 MM gun. Comments on messing equipment are favorable for the new over the older type of ranges. The following comments have been noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-384c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">"Our weapon is the Bofors gun which is worth its weight in ten 37 MM guns. It's good for anything it's called upon to do, and I don't mean antiaircraft solely"--431st C.A.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-394c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">"I am still flying B -26's. It's a darn good airplane. I don't believe I would want to fly anything else in combat outside of a fighter plane."-­441st Sq., 320th Bomb. Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3a4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">"We were held up there because of engine trouble. I'm glad we got across the pond before that happened. Besides that, a B-26 stalls out at higher speed than any airplane I've ever heard of. They're not exactly amphibious."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3b4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">"Got checked out in a British Spitfire last week--of all the funny little airplanes. It's like driving a ford after being used to a Packard. They're supposed to be good, though--I don't know."--319th Ftr. Sq., 325th Ftr. Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3c4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">"Our cooking and eating facilities are quite an improvement over the older army methods. Gas field ranges replace the cumbersome coal and wood type, and even the mess kit has an improved design."--431st Sep. C.A. Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3d4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">5. Food. About 98% of the comments on food have been favorable. It is evident that the rations are varied and plentiful and have been enthusiastically received. There is still a slight feeling of discontent in some units that are using 'C' rations. Comments have been noted on the lack of PX supplies and their availability of purchase from the 'black market' by civilians. The following comments have been noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3e4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">"As to the American troops food it always was good, and always more than enough, but we are getting now fresh American beef three times a week. Last week in the hospital we had chicken all of which makes the men very happy."--70th Tank Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-3f4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">"The food over here is much better. When we first came over we had to eat out of cans, now we have fresh meat, chicken, steak and ice cream."-­38th A.D.G.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-404c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">"Needless to say that this kind of life seems to be agreeing with me, because I'm getting so very fat on the food. Whoever begins to complain about the rations that the army has put out needs their head examined, sure they aren't all the fresh vegetables but they are plenty to get along on."-­180th Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-414c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">"The food is still excellent. Even had steak on Sat. and roast beef the next day. It was our first steak over here and it went over big. Here's our menu for today--Breakfast-dried apricots, oat meal, powdered eggs and coffee. Lunch-canned salmon, tomato sauce, string beans, fruit salad (canned) and tea. Supper-chili concarne, new peas from No. Africa, bread, butter and jam, coffee and canned peaches for dessert, also oranges. Not bad I'll say- probably better than you are doing right now. The rationing must be tough."-­62nd C.A. (AA).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-424c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">"Just had a steak for dinner-my morale is reaching a new high-it's the first time I've seen any reason why a soldier needs teeth while doing overseas duty."--Co. C, 6th Repl. Bn, 1st Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-434c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">"There's no kick about the food. It's excellent. Last night we had ice cream."--591st Engineer Regiment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-444c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">"Food still continues to be good. Believe it or not but we did have ice cream one day and it was a treat. Then too we had fried chicken. When food like that is placed on the table, in silent reverence I thank God for the favors he bestows upon us."--3486th Ordnance Company.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-454c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">"Our food has picked up wonderfully too. We are getting fresh meat and eggs about twice a week. We have a new mess officer who seems to be able to produce better variety. The P.X. rations are adequate."--Hq. VI Corps.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-464c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">"I only wish that some of the civilian population could see us eat. Everything from Long Island roast duck to plenty of good hot coffee graces our festive board."--2nd Bn., 509th Parachute Inf.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-474c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">"I must admit that I'm eating very well and about all American rations. From soups to nuts--almost. But it is awfully good chow and we really appre­ciate it."--Service Co., 509th Parachute Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-484c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">"Food is good particularly when a ship load of fresh meat comes in. The C rations which we get quite often are good if you are starving but as a steady diet, they really become a little monotonous. Of course, there is little complaining, for we all know that there are many people in this world who would give a lot to have a dry crust of bread."--21st Station Hosp.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-494c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">"Our food is terrible. Still on C rations. Preserved butter once a day-no milk at all....can buy eggs however from the Arabs...."--21st Gen. Hosp.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4a4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">"For the last four weeks, we have been getting PX rations galore. For a while were getting all of our things free, but now we have to pay for them. We got our start with abundance of things when a few weeks ago, we started with getting 3 Baby Ruth bars, 1 Neco Wafer roll, 1 pack of gum, 1 box of fig newtons, tobaccos and many of the necessities. All of the things were not taken so we had seconds, and I was able to duplicate the candies and sweets, call me pig if you want to, for there was enough for thirds for many of us, so I ended the week with 9 Baby Ruth, 3 gum, 3 Neco, 3 Fig. The next week it was practically the same thing, except that there were seconds and no thirds and the following week about the same thing again."--Sig. Sec., Base Headquarters, APO 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">"The PX furnished us every week 7 packages of cigarettes. You pay 3 francs per package. Unfortunately you only get 4 packages of the brand which you are used to smoking, the rest is issued in Chelseas, Kools, or Raleighs. This stuff nobody wants to smoke and you even can't give them to your French friends because they know already that these are the cigar­ettes which you don't like. It always makes me mad when I come to a French family and see that they have plenty of Luckies and Chesterfields which they buy on the black market paying 20 francs per package."--Press liaison, Base Headquarters, APO 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">6. Entertainment. All comments on this subject have been favorable. The increasing facilities and equipment provided by the Red Cross and the Special Service Sections are being used constantly and have been received with much enthusiasm. The following comments have been noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">"Once in a while we get a movie. Sound and everything. It's really a thrill sometimes to sit on the ground and watch the Ritz brothers toss cracks. Even though the movies are very old, it makes a person really appreciate Hollywood and it's picture industry. Another source of amusement are the radio receivers provided by Special service. We also receive news this way--although never enough."--39th F.A. Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">"I've been into town once or twice, where we visit the American Red Cross. It sure is a wonderful organization. It provides everything for the troops. I would spend a whole day at the place alone. It has a smashing theatre, reading room, games room and restaurant. That more could you ask for on active service? And the food they dish us up in the restaurant is really first-class. It's American food, naturally."--RAF.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">"The red Cross has two very nice service clubs and a restaurant where you can ,et your fill for 20 cents and a snack bar where you get sandwiches and drink for one franc--if you have it. They have two shows daily. We decided to see the afternoon show but made the mistake of going a bit late. The place was jammed to capacity; not even standing room."--Hq. Co. 3rd Infantry Division.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-504c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">"The Special Service people and the Red Cross have joined hands to make non-work hours quite pleasant around here. Several clubs have opened. Movies are regular. Lots of athletics. Time passes swiftly."--Hq. Fifth Army. "It is the Yanks who have organized it. You can't beat them for organizing entertainment for the troops; they fairly look after the troops."-- RAF.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-514c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">"Tonight, we are again having a movie given by the Special Service. I believe it's going to be 'George Washington slept here.' If it wasn't for these Special Service units supplying us with entertainment, I don't know what the boys would do."--67th Q.M. Ref. Co. (m).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-524c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">"We have an excellent USO club in this vicinity. It has a motion picture theater, game rooms, large library, and a swank bar where one can get all the sandwiches and drinks that one can eat for one franc. Of course we don't get the latest Hollywood pictures, but we do get to see some excellent stage shows."--Hq. &amp; Plotting Co., 560th Signal Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-534c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">7. Sports. Team spirit is being built up around sport activities. The sports that seem to predominate at the present time are softball and volleyball. Team competition receives a favorable reaction in units that have made an effort to have athletic activities. About 100% of all comment on sports is favorable. The following are typical comments:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-544c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">"I just got finished playing ball. You know dear, we do our work and if we have time, we play ball, volley ball, football, etc. We didn't do so well, it must have been our day off. After beating this opposing team in succession, they decided to play a three game series, which we took an awful beating for the first game. It was a good and exciting ball game. Well tomorrow, we'll decide the series."--Battery B, 505th C.A. (AA).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-554c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">"Baseball and volleyball are popular at present, and almost all take part in some form of sport at one time or another."--431st Sep. C.A. Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-564c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">"Played softball today. We really enjoy that so much. It's really fun kinda makes you relax and forget your troubles temporarily."--62nd T.C. Gp.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-574c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">8. Leave. About 75% of all comments on leave are unfavorable. One typical comment indicates the method used by most units to allow personnel to have time off. One comment which has cause much comment, due to rumors, but seems to sum up the feelings of the troops as a whole. The following comments are typical and are as follows:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-584c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">"If the army would set some date that after a person spent so many months overseas, they would let him go home they would have a better army, and harder workers. But the way it is now we work day in and day out, with­out knowing when this darn thing is going to end."--3486th Ordnance MM Co.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-594c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">"I was offered a pass the other day, Friday to be exact. I took it just to get away from camp. They allow ten men to go from the company to to every day. They took us on trucks to a town which is about 30 miles away." --Company K, 15th Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">9. Quarters. There has been very little references to quarters this past week. It has been noted however that there seems to be a little discontent when there is an opportunity for comparing quarters of adjacent units. The following was noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">"The British Isles are represented at this base--we can thank them for being in tents--they got the barracks we did live in. But this is their dish so all we can do is think and fume."--318th Ftr. Sq., 325 Ftr. Gp.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">10. Politics. About 90% of all comments on politics are unfavorable, this includes local as well as that in the United States. Critisim of Gen. Giraud's policy in regard to local administration and fascist sympathy has become apparent. The following were extracted from mail examined:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5d4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">"The headlines from the different front lines certainly sound good and things must break soon. I know that history tells us that there always will be wars and military showdowns but I think when this war will be over that there will be a lot of soldiers who are going to have more to say than some congressmen will like. And I am sure they will help to make a peace for the common people. And they will give a darn whether the stock market racketeers and Wall Street will like it or not."--Hq. &amp; Hq. Sq. 322nd Service Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5e4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">"There is still a lot of sabotage going on among the French officials. The recent speech of General Giraud regarding the cancelling of all Vichy laws and decrees was followed by a big scandal. Although the official version was published the following day it took more than one week before the gigantic pictures of the Marechal. The slogan 'Famille, Patrie, Travail' which also was ordered to be removed are still visible even in localities which are requisitioned by the American authorities."--Base Hq., APO 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5f4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">"Giraud and Nogues are the twin brothers of law and order here. Much power still remains with the local administration and there is still consid­erable fascist sympathy around here, and that though the police are aware of it they do not bother its workings. That can only mean that Giraud knows about that and is playing the unsettled condition for all it is worth. If things were politically settled here then with some semblance of a progress­ive, libertarian regime, General De Gaulle would easily be a much respected and worshipped leader. At present, power politics call for the influential managing hand of one who has contacts with the extreme right. But as the successor to Darlan, Giraud I feel will ultimately follow his footsteps. I feel too, that it is not unwise to allow Giraud to handle the present transition stage. Open opposition to De Gaulle would be the result of his leadership here and would present many difficulties which can be avoided with Giraud. After the transition stage De Gaulle can unite all sentiments towards rebuilding France on a democratic equalitarian basis."--8th T.C. Sq., 62nd T.C. Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-604c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">11. News and propaganda. About 50% of all comments and news are unfavorable. Daily news bulletins which are put out by some units meet with very favorable resp­onse. In other units there are repeated references to the lack of news available and express desire of being able to obtain up to date news. There have been some references to the fact that though the Allied Nations are putting forth propaganda, it still is not equal to that put out by the Nazi regime. German radio stations are being listened to by a large part of the troops, all of whom state that the news put out by them is absurd, though their entertainment features are good. The following remarks are typical:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-614c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">"I've an idea that you get all of the news in a good deal more complete form than we do, since our only news sources consist of one mimeographed bulletin (1 page) which comes out daily, plus an occasional report from the BBC in the evening. Someday a real good up-to-date American newspaper is going to look mighty good."--Signal Section, Base Hq., AFC 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-624c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">"Understand that the newspaper headlines have been screaming lately. The signs are good but do not get overoptimistic....this will be a long war. We are over the hump and all fronts are in our favor but that does not end a war. Complete destruction of the enemy army ends a war. We are too prone to underestimate the lasting ability of our enemies."--Hq. Co. 1st Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-634c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">"Little or no news--it seems that the closer one is to the news the less we hear of it. We read the news in U.S. papers 2 to 3 months old and that is a long time dead even old news. But from what I hear the boys are doing a good job of making news."--Signal Section, APO 750.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-644c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">"The BBC and the Berlin radio seem to try to outdo on musical programs. We listen more to Berlin because the German broadcasts are the best over here. The Germans are certainly very efficient with their broadcast propa­ganda. We have a lot to learn from them in that regard. Although we brag so much about our propaganda systems I must admit that here we don't see too much of it. And it certainly would be a very important thing to make some radio propaganda here."--286th Signal Company.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-654c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">"For a long time all we could see in Africa was pictures of Marshal Petain and Vichy-inspired slogans painted on walls. Now they're all gone and replaced by 'Vive les Americans' and 'Vive De Gaulle'. Doesn't look the same as when we first cane in back in November."--Hq. Fifth Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-664c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">"A couple days ago I thought everyone was going to go crazy. We heard a rumor that the Germans in Africa had surrendered. For a while vie were like a 4th of July mob, but after a bit everyone settled down to wait official confirmation of the rumor. It never came."--Company A, 15th Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-674c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">"At this writing I'm listening to a propaganda program from Berlin. Berlin calling the A.E.F. in North Africa. It is supposed to breed dis­content and perhaps it does. Our bunch gets quite a bang out of it and wouldn't miss it. They play sentimental pieces to remind the boys of home. Also they have short commercial like talks to breed discontent. Many of the talks are very absurd and comical because they tell of conditions(miserable that we know aren't true. They also tell jokes, many of which are very good. To make the jokes better the fellow that tells them speaks with a Yanky accent."--438th Sq., 319th Bomb. Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-684c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">12. Church, and Religion. References indicate that military personnel avail themselves of every opportunity of attending religious services, and appreciate that they are available. 95% of the comments are favorable. One comment is as follows:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-694c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">"I'm beginning to get rather pure, go to church and all. War also makes you extremely conscious of God and all. There are no atheists in this area."--3rd Aux. Surg. Gp.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6a4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">13. Home affairs. References to home affairs still dwell upon the effects of rationing and strikes. Many refer to the fact that they are saving money and expect to have substantial savings when the war is over, as shown by the following comment:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6b4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">"I read something about Congress passing a bill that would give soldiers 6 months or a year's pay upon discharge from the service. That sounds too good to be true, but it would be very east to take. Most of the boys that are overseas are sending a good part of their money home, so I don't suppose too many will be flat broke when they are discharged."--Hq. SOS, Sig.Sec.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6c4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">14. Relations with the civilian population. The relations between our forces and the French continue to be very friendly as indicated by 90% of the mail examined. There are still a few complaints of the high prices charged to Americans. The following comments are typical:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6d4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">"Most of the native and practically all of the French are very co-operative, and are glad to have U.S. troops here. Of course there are a few minor exceptions, but on the whole they consider the change from German to Allied control a great improvement."--431st Sep. C.A. Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6e4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">"The people over here have been very kind to us Americans. They even look upon the drunk soldiers with a sort of amused benevolence and say 'Oh well, they are far from their homes and families'. One fellow told me that the Americans are all overgrown children."--Base Headquarters, APO 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6f4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">"The greater part of the people here are quiet friendly and the remaining few are rapidly overcoming any suspicion which they might have entertained towards us when we first got here."--21st Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-704c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">"I can see a definite change in the attitude of the people here over the time when we first came. The, they were inclined to suspicious-just if the Americans were not going to be able to hold their new found gains and they might again be plunged under the Nazi yoke. Now, they are becoming more and more trustful and friendly. I think that when we let them harvest this year's crop (which is quite bountiful indeed) their faith in us will be complete."--21st Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-714c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">"Americans are charged more than the natives and as usual are entirely responsible because they can only think in terms of dollars. A large part of the population resent this because it makes life more difficult for them. The American forces are paying a common laborer 1500 francs a month which is at least 4 times what he was ever paid before."--Hq.SOS.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-724c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">"Of late I've had an increasing number of patients among the local population. The word has gotten around that there is one type of specialist and another at the 'American Hospital' and there seems to be a demand for the services of the 'specialist'. I don't mind seeing the patients. I feel that as long as it does not interfere with my hospital routine it can't possibly do any harm. The colonel knows about most of these calls and he doesn't seem to mind. The result is that these people are made very happy. Usually, all they need is a little word of encouragement (usually that is all that I can give them).--32nd Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-734c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">15. Relations with Allied Troops. All comments were favorable. The letters written by British personnel that passed through this office praised the Americans very highly especially as to the treatment they received:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-744c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">"Censorship is quite rigid, however I can state one fact and that is that I have gained a very healthy respect for the British army based on what I have seen and heard since my arrival here."--lst Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-754c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">"We have stayed several times with Americans who received us with open arms. If at any time you can do any of them a good turn, please do so for me. All we have met have been the same, one camp or another it made no difference. We haven't left one of their camps without sweets, cigarettes or gum. During the evenings if they could entertain us, they would and the first thing they have always done was to see that we had food and somewhere to sleep."--Hq. RAF B.N.A.F.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-764c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">"We have no NAFFI, being rather isolated from British supplies, but we are privileged, being near to Americans to use their NAFFI supplies--PX they are called. I can get 200 American cigarettes and 'bags' of matches for 40 francs, every week plus spearmint, chocolate candy, note paper, soap, toothpaste, etc. If you spend 80 francs per week (8 shillings) you get a load of stuff--quite ample to meet all requirements."--Hq. RAF.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-774c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">"You have heard them say this and that about the yank but I am finding some good chaps amongst, and if you are stuck they are always willing to give you a hand. I won't have anyone saying a thing against, always give honours where honours are due."--RAF.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-784c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">"The Americans we meet are the most sociable chaps you could imagine. A medical corporal and I exchange addresses and he wants me to keep in touch with him. He lives in Maryland, USA. All the Yanks think British are tops and the compliment applies both ways."--RAF.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-794c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">16. Censorship. Illicit posting of mail continues to dominate the different violations of censorship. A total of 25 form 912's were sent out in the past week of which 9 were for officers, fourteen for enlisted personnel and two for merchant marines. The following is a numerical listing of the various types of violation: 16 illicit posting, 11 disclosed geographical location of unit, 7 disclosed geo­graphical location of A.P.O., 4 disclosed movement of troops, 3 disclosed inform­ation of military value, 1 use of code, enclosures in envelopes contrary to regu­lation and found with the above violation (1) naming officers in grade of colonel and higher, (1) private diary, (1) organizational publication. In one case an enlisted man complied with regulations, but the unit censor failed to stop the information from being released. In the past week as before there is a tendency of unit censors and officers in disregarding the rule of censorship as applying to post cards. Many units have to have all their cards returned. As much as 40% of all post cards have unauthorized names of cities or towns in this theater. The new censorship regulation seems and have been distributed to all units and the comments noted seems to indicate that most individuals have the impression that the new rules are too stringent. The comments noted are as follows:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7a4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">"Today one of our officers explained the new censorship regulations to us. We aren't allowed to mention the weather or any certain date however we are allowed to mention that it was muddy weather sometime back. He also told us we could not mention cities close by, we are not to describe the looks of the camp, but can say that we are living in pup tents. I guess it will be hard writing from now on."--561st Signal, Company C. We are getting new rules and regulations regarding mail and censor­ship, so I don't know what I'll write about in my ensuing letters but may be able to manage a V-mail now and then."--21st Signal Co.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7b4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">"Censorship restrictions have been made ridiculously strict, to my mind, as we cannot say very much. The foolish part is that we can say 'Did you read such and such a picture or article in Life or Time, etc. and then go on to say that that was our unit etc.' Oh well, I guess they have to keep those millions in Washington busy with something."--Hq. V Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7c4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">"Censorship regulations are becoming stricter. All outgoing mail is censored. Now I understand that incoming mail is to be spot checked. This process will inevitably delay the passage of mail even more than it is at present. No wonder that we get more and more disgusted with the mail situation."--Hq. VI Corps.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7d4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">"There is a new rule on censorship, so don't expect too much in detail from over here. I censor my own mail but it is to our welfare to be most careful. The circular on new censorship has not come to us however."-­1st Replacement Depot, 19th Repl. Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7e4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">"Today I sent three photographs to the Base Censor to see if I could mail them. The censorship regulations have recently been extended and many things that we used to write about and the picture post cards are out."--Hq. VI Corps.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7f4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">"All I can say is that I usually write once a week, more often if there is anything to write about but you must remember that there is a nice long ocean to cross and mail censors have a great deal to do in addition to censoring mail. It may take him days before he gets around to censoring mail. I know of cases where it has. That is.at least one reason why you don't receive mail as often as you would like to."--Battery C, 505th C.A. (AA).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-804c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">"Darling, have the censors done any snipping of any of my letters? The reason I ask is that one of the officers in our outfit learned from his wife that they were chopping all sort of stuff that regulations permit us to say. For instance, if we happen to visit some big city like Oran, Casablanca, or Algiers we can say so. We can't reveal the location of our base or even the general area in which we are operating, of course. They have no right deleting the name of one of the cities I mentioned if we happened to visit it and mention it. Even over here we get some time off, of course, and get an opportunity to do a little looking around. The guys that do the censoring have a tough job and on the whole do a good job of it, I think, but once in a while I suppose you will encounter some officious squirt who doesn't even know his own regulations."--Hq. 325th Fighter Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-814c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">"Ray, I don't know how you get by with the things you say in your letters. Ours are censored about three times and if there is the least thing wrong, they bounce right back."--509th Parachute Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-824c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">17. General complaints. About 5 of all mail examined have in them some complaints. The majority are complaints concerning the delay or non-receipt of allotments by their families at home. Inactivity is another complaint that is seen often, especially in mail from officers in the replacement depot. The following are a few of the comments noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-834c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">"There is something on my mind that is worrying me. It seems to me that you are not doing so well. It worries me that you are not getting my allot­ment checks. You tell me that you have not received any of them since Dec.12. I really can't realize the reason why they are taking so long to send them out."--Company M, 28th QM Regt. (colored).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-844c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">"I'm mad clear through. Not at you but at the government office that is holding up your checks. There is no excuse for them not sending your checks for 5 months like this. I've made complaints everywhere I know to make them ever since November last year, and nothing I do seems to help." --12th General Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-854c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="108">"I don't mind working long hours but it worries me and upsets me to see the patients-my patients as well as everyone else's- being neglected, not getting the attention they should have. This darned army system of writing up cases and writing discharge notes may protect the U.S. from being sued but it sure as shooting deprives the patients of medical care. What we need is an army of clerks along with us."--64th Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-864c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="109">"I said that theoretically, I'm a line officer. I intend to see that, shortly, I'm a line officer in practice. I'm fed up with hanging around a replacement depot. That's a job for super annulated fogies. My application for re-assignment is going in Monday and I'm going to holler and scream until I get it. This place is driving me nuts. I'm getting fat and out of shape sitting at a desk and bawling out bolos no filling though, it gripes the hell out of me to be sitting on my derriere when there's a full sized war going on that I'm all primed to get into."--9th Bn., 1st Replace. Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-874c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="110">18. General. About 98% of all mail examined commented favorably on the high morale. There is every indication that our troops are in good condition and well trained, and all anxious to invade Europe now. Many are looking into the future and investing their money in bonds, furthering their belief in the outcome of this war. The following comments have been noted:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-884c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="111">"The boys all seem to be getting itchy feet to get moving again. If they let them I believe the American soldiers would be ready and willing to start the march to Berlin right now."--329th Service Squadron. "There are four things that the boys look forward to and consider the most important now. The first one is going home, 2nd seeing if they get a letter when the mail comes in, 3rd seeing how much money they can save. Last going to the shows we have now and then nothing else seems of much importance to them. Of course, their work is important to them and winning the war. Which we will surely do, I hope soon."--10th T.C. Sq., 60th T.C. Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-894c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="112">"A good many of the troops over here saving money and some of them are saving plenty. Being in the Finance we know just about what is going on in that respect. The boys in the service are not only fighting this war but are financing it to a large extent by buying bonds."--Finance Dept., 329th Service Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8a4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="113">"You should have seen the German prisoners being loaded on transports-a sorry looking lot of German boys, age about 19 years, bedraggled and beaten-looking, with a bunch of tough looking M.P.'s standing over them with tommy guns. The Heinies didn't look much like the so called super race then. Yet these are the same who caused all this affair and brought all these good American kids thousands of miles from home to a strange continent. Our boys really hate now all those German nazi bastards because they start to realize that they are the cause for all our sufferings."--Base Headquarters, APO 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8b4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="114">"The soldiers don't have any difficulty whatsoever with the changeover in currency American to French. There is just one bad feature to the whole situation. The American is very careless in spending money and pays any price asked. A 100 franc note is unconsciously taken to be worth only a dollar when it really is worth two dollars. But a soldier here in Africa gets more money than he even wants. While censoring mail I was surprised to see the amount of money being sent home."--lst Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8c4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="115">WALTER H. BECKER,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8d4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="116">Major, F.A.,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="117">Chief Base Censor.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f4c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="118">49 Inclosures:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-904c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="119">48 Forms 912, Serial Nos.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-914c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="120">BCD 1-30 to BCD 1-54, incl., 2 copies each.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-924c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="121">Statistical Report in triplicate.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-934c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="122">DISTRIBUTION:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-944c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="123">3 A.C. of S., G-2, War Department (thru channels)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-954c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="124">1 Commanding General, Fifth Army.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-964c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="125">1 Commanding General, XII Air Force.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-974c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="126">1 Commanding Officer, MBS.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-984c7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="127">File</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>