<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Morale Report for the period 19 to 25 March 1943</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-02e60790-ec49-42b0-846b-c35e69478a12</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-499e64b9-9d37-4f52-89d8-c6174270d0d5</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-3f4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">CONFIDENTIAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-404e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">(EQUALS BRITISH SECRET)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-414e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">Base Censor Detachment No. 1</note>
				<note xml:id="q-424e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="4">A.P.O. 700, New York, New York</note>
				<note xml:id="q-434e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="date" n="5">25 March 1943.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-444e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="6">Subject: Morale report for the period 19 to 25 March 1943, inclusive.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-454e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">To: C. G. NATOUSA (through channels)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-464e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">1. Health. The health of the troops continues to be excellent. Numerous letters express surprise at the continued good health of the writers in spite of lack of bathing, and other sanitary facilities, but express concern about the effects of coming warm weather will have on their health. A complaint has been noted in reference to the large number of men being sent overseas needing dental treatment. The presence of fleas in front line units has been mentioned. About 95% of all comments about health are favorable. The following are excerpts front letters:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-474e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">"I have survived the winter months O.K., and am still feeling like my old self."--Battery C, 36th Field Artillery.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-484e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">"Most of our cases are now fairly recent wounded, arriving by the most rapid means of transportation which is extremely efficient. I am getting a fair amount of experience as a foreign body remover and secondary wound closer with skin grafting. 99% of the cases are extremely well handled at advance hospitals."--21 Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-494e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">"My health is exceptionally good. I can't understand it all. I've never felt better in civilian life. Maybe I should sleep outdoors and on the ground at all times. Or maybe my beard of four weeks has something to do with my health. Perhaps it's the bath I take very seldom."--66th Ordnance Company (Am).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4a4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">"Still have more work to do than I can possibly take care of. I had no idea that they would send men overseas needing teeth fixed so badly. I thought that a few other hospitals began functioning around here that my work might decrease a little, but I have noticed no difference."-­7th Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4b4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">"I am still lousy from the damn fleas. They make me miserable front their damn bites. Well, I have not been sick while I am here."--18th Inf.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4c4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">"So I stayed in bed all day, feeling simply miserable, and the Doe gave me a physic to clean me out. I ate nothing till supper and then only some bread and potatoes and now I feel moderately O.K. but not too chipper. This kind of thing results from living in the field, where the mess isn't too sanitary, dishes not well washed, rubbish and garbage and latrines exposed to disease--carrying insects. I'm afraid our biggest problem is going to be disease, insects particularly when the hot weather sets in." --318th Fighter Squadron, 325th Fighter Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4d4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">2. Mail. About 60% of all comments on mail service continue to be unfavorable, though some units seem to be receiving mail regularly. Frequent reference to the receipt of long delayed mail has been noted. Others remark about the receipt of a large number of letters at one time. The following are comments received:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4e4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">"I have been receiving your letters quite regularly just keep on writing and they will keep coming in."--Cannon Company, lath' Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-4f4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">"Last night some of our mail got through. It was the first for quite a while and I was so glad. I got 17 letters from you--4 air and 13 V-mail, All of them did me so much good."--Company B, 751st Tank Battalion (M).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-504e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">"We have very little faith in our great Postal System....not having received any mail at all in two months now we have decided that it traveling around someplace waiting for the A.P.O. to make up their minds where they will send it...." --15th Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-514e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">"My mail seems to have got tangled up some place, as I haven't received any letters from you in a long time and I know you must be writing. One of these days I'll probably get your letters all at once."--Cannon Company, 18th Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-524e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">"Well the mail has been rolling in pretty well for the last few days. The Army Post Office must have gotten a shipment of cots and decided to put into circulation those bags they were using to sleep on, because a few old letters turned up dated about November 15--four months on the way, and another batch dated between Christmas and New Year. Most of the first clam mail mailed in January and up to about February 20-25 came across in good time." - -Hq. 322nd Service Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-534e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">"I have written you at least three times a week for months. I don't know what is the matter. I write the folks at least twice a week. The kid in charge of our group mail told me this morning that he knew less than 25% of our mail was coming through to us. I suppose it is in storage in New York, or England."--11th Repair Squadron, 11th Air Depot, XII AFSC.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-544e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">"I hope you are receiving my letters better than I am receiving mail. Since we landed in December I have only one letter from you and that was about a week ago and dated December 30 and have only received five from Georgia."--Company C, 727th Ry Opn Battalion.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-554e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">"Mail seems to be very uncertain now. It is apparent, that no one cares about the delivery of mail to us on foreign duty, well, can't keep it, I suppose."--A.P.O. 520.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-564e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">"There should be mail soon. Somehow our mil service has been very slow and poor. However, we've come to the point where we don't look fox it anymore."--21st General Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-574e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">"Today (3/16/43) I received your letter dated (Dec. 12/42. Isn't that something 3 months."--26th Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-584e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">"The mail is so slow it must be coming by rowboat."--Battery B, 436th 436th C.A. Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-594e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">"I haven't received a letter from you in four weeks. I can't under­stand why the mail service is lousy here."--62nd Engineer Company (Top).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5a4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">3. Training. Only a few references to this subject have been observed and they express confidence that the training received has been adequate and with battle experience, they will be able to defeat the enemy. Note the following:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5b4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">"Whatever takes place, I can honestly say I am not afraid, and that we are trained for it."--Medical Detachment, 755th Tank Battalion.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5c4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">"Our men are getting valuable experience here-experience which no amount of training in the States can furnish, for they are learning the real tricks of fighting. It was the same way on Guadalcanal-the American soldier was not cognizant of the enemy and was taken in many times by their trickiness. But once they got wise to them they were not only able to defeat them, but they proved to be better soldiers. Now the myth of the Japanese soldier is exploded and that is what is happening to the Germans. For every trick there is a solution and each new weapon is neutralized by a counter weapon." --12th General Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5d4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">4. Equipment. The only comment on equipment received during the past week remarks, unfavorably, about the pup tent in comparison with the British tents. Note the following:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5e4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">"I understand that they have new pup tents back in the States. Are they any good? We have the old type and they aren't worth a damn. They are open at one end and they leak like hell when it rains and it rains often. Some of the fellows are lucky. They got hold of some British pup tents and they are nice. Heavier canvas than ours and closed at both ends with a mosquito bar at the entrance."--53rd Ordnance Company (Avn).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-5f4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">5. Food. References to food indicate general satisfaction of the ration. Unfavorable comments have been noted from units about the British ration. Receipt of fresh meat has been welcomed by some units. About 90% of all comments on food are favorable. The following have been noted during the past week:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-604e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">"We are getting well fed, and we are getting plenty of cigarettes. As for food and cigarettes concerned we are better off here than we were in England."--822nd S.M. Co. P.C. /C.W.S./ APO 600 /British soldier.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-614e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">"The American troops certainly get a great variety of food these days. Gives us a chance to fatten up after the slim rations we had in England. You can't blame the English, as practically all their food is imported and has to be rationed."--Battery F, 62nd C.A. (AA).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-624e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">"Believe it or not we had ice cream for supper tonight and roast pork for dinner and the other day we had pork chops. Boy were they good."- - Company C, 95th Quartermaster Bakery.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-634e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">"I suppose the army does have most of the food because we are eating food over here. We even have butter now and lots of coffee and sugar. Some fresh meat now and then. We had chicken 2 days in a row."--1038th Ordnance Company (Avn) AB.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-644e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">"You say there is a shortage of different foods, how would you like to be in our place. All us get, due to some funny arrangements, is has, stew and bean, it is getting so we don't know what good food is like, but anyway we are eating regularly and that is better than nothing."--Co. D, 1st Ranger Battalion.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-654e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">"We are still on British food after having American rations for 1 day. Please don't get the idea I'm starving or anything like that. It's merely this British food isn't up to what we are used to by any means."--Battery C, 151st Field Artillery.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-664e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">"We have been living on British rations ever since we came into action and they are not so good. There is not anyone of us that likes them. Hope we get something better before long."--151st Field Artillery Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-674e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">6. Entertainment. Movies, stage shows and other entertainment provided by the Red Cross and Special Service units have been the subject of many favorable comments. Units and personnel also receive much pleasure and benefit from radio broadcasts. Propaganda releases from the enemy seem to have resulted in elevating morale by providing amusement for the troops. The following are typical comments:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-684e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">"Listened to a very good army band last night composed of boys from several big name bands in the States, my were they good. Then saw a movie. All of this didn't coast either of us a cent, strictly Red Cross and they are doing a pretty good job over here-quite different from what you told me about their work in '17'."--7th Battalion, 1st Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-694e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">"Last night we had a Special Service show for the patients. It was awfully good and the patients loved it. Their morale was 100% better today and we hope that we will have more entertainment. The boys who have been in my ward so many weeks really need a morale builder."--7th Station Hosp.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6a4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">"The dispensary tent turns into a casino after 6 p.m. Never a night during which it is not well attended. But it is a good place for the boys takes their minds off of flying for a short time, and keeps them out of town where they might be exposed to all manner of diseases."--317th Fgtr. Squadron, 325th Fighter Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6b4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">"Many boys have arrived at the conclusion that wine is to be taken moderately and the results is a greater majority staying in camp taking advantage of different means of diversion afforded them. For instance a game of ball is underway right after supper and when darkness makes it necessary to call the game, each one of us grab a blanket and goes to the show which has become a nightly affair."--Company B, 344th Engineers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6c4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">"Tonight I am going to the show. The name of the picture is 'Secret Enemies'. The other night I saw Abbott and Costello in 'Pardon My Sarong'. We see all the latest pictures here sometimes ever before they are shown in the States."--Battery B, 103rd C.A. (AA).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6d4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">"Last night we tuned in America on the radio and listened to the program for the boys in North Africa and you can tell them for me it was terrible. We have better entertainment here in the company than they had on the radio, Mickey Rooney pulled some rather rotten jokes and Cecil A. De Mill said that as long as we kept fighting they would keep buying bonds."--39th Engineer Regiment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6e4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">"I heard a radio program from the States the other day. Cecil A. De Mille put it on and it sure was grand but it made us all home sick believe it or not I had a lump in my throat, tears in my eyes. I wasn't the only one either for there was several others. I guess we all get homesick at times."--Company C, 95th Quartermaster (bakery).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-6f4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">7. Sports. Frequent mention of men participating in sports during their off duty hours seems to indicate that there is no lack of recreational equipment. The organization of leagues within some regiments and air corps groups has been favorably commented on, and has resulted in keen rivalry between teams of different units. The following is a typical comment;</note>
				<note xml:id="q-704e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">"After we finish our duty we play football, basketball, baseball, or softball. We really have a fine time."--1963rd Ordnance Company.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-714e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">8. Leave. Very few references to leaves have been observed. The restrictions on leaves in this theatre evidently is the reason for the absence of comments on this subject. Note the following:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-724e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">"I just got back from a 48 hour pass Chats the largest time I have had off since a year ago last December. I had a good time considering this is Africa. I was in Algiers and stayed at the Red Cross Club. They have a swell place there."--35th Troop Carrier Squadron. 9. Quarters. In general, quarters provided for the troops seems to be satisfactory. Newly arrived units usually complain about the quarters, but after they have become settled and added a few improvements, their remarks are usually favorable. The following remarks by a British Officer about a hotel requisitioned by the American billeting officer:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-734e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">"Had an unfortunate experience in one hotel in which I stayed, which is requisitioned by the American billeting officer, I got eaten alive by bed bugs. It isn't all serious, but I have been scratching for six days, and the bites are just beginning to go down. These French middle class hotels are certainly a dirty mess."--Royal Signals, 31 Cipher Section.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-744e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">10. Politics. No comment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-754e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">11. News and propaganda. Several unfavorable comments were observed about a news item in a Signal Corps News Bulletin quoting Vice President Wallace's remarks about Russia. The news of the slowing up of the Russian offensive and the speech of Mr. Churchill has had a depressing effect and caused a change of opinion in regard to the length of the war. The enemy propaganda broadcasts continue to provide amusement for our troops. Frequent mention is made in letters about a rumor that units will return to the States after a year's service overseas or at the end of the African campaign. The following are typical comments:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-764e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">"Read a very disgusting article in the paper, and enclose same. It is about our country's attitude and lack of confidence in Russia by our Vice President. It is a blow to our men in service, as it leaves us in sheer doubt as to our standing with our allies who are doing such wonderful work. All the men in my unit feel as I do--that it was disgusting coming from a man in a high place, as Wallace is."--Hq., 434th C.A. (AA).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-774e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">"Joe Stalin is screaming for the third front... and he is darn right to do so. Too bad that he does not send one of his generals to us. I bet they would not fool around as long as we do."--27th Bomber Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-784e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">"The war is by no means over. I really think the worst part has still to come. One thing is certain, the Nazis will lose this war and they know But in the meantime they ruin every country and that is what their leaders intended to do, when they started this war."--344th Engineers.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-794e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">"I listened to Mr. Churchill's speech. His opinion that the war will not be over before 1945 seems to be right. A terrible long time but I'm afraid we have to face it with the usual 'chin up' and maybe when we work harder then we could finish our job sooner."--16th Medical Regiment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7a4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">"Last time I wrote you I was quite sanguine, too, about an early finish, but now I am back in my old pessimistic state. The marvelous advance of the Russians seem to be halted, the Americans seem to have their hands full with a small group in North Africa and bombing of civilians by any nation has not yet won a war, as witness Spain, England and now Germany. An offensive against the continent seems to be an adventure that is not embarked upon lightly and knowing how long it took us to get set for this second rate encounter in North Africa, I can't see an invasion before summer. By that time Russia will be again on the retreat and the whole foul play will be repeated. No sir, this war looks like a long drawn out war of attrition to me but I hope I'm wrong."--Medical Section, Base Hq., A.P.O. 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7b4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">"Some of the patients were awfully disgusted when an article came out in an army paper here that one of our war executives at home had made a statement that unless certain conditions were fulfilled, that we would be having war with Russia. They were much put out about that and talked about it for days- -think it was a mistake myself to send that sort of news over here. It's not good for the morale."--21st General Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7c4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">"Over our short wave receiver we get all kinds of programs but the funniest come from Berlin and Tunis. They have American speaking men and women on the programs and do they lay it on. The one from Berlin plays all the latest records and in a roundabout way tells us we are on the wrong side. We all call her the Berlin Bitch. The one that broadcasts from Tunis calls herself Your Gal Sal, but we call her Stiff Sally. She always says that if we want to have a request played on her program all we have to do is to write the request on a piece of paper and put the paper in our out­stretched hands AND WALK across the lines and let the Germans take good care of us in a nice concentration camp. Boy the way they lay it on is really funny and we get a big kick out of it."--111th Observation Squadron, 68th Observation Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7d4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">"We get quite a bang out of listening to Nazi propaganda, some of the fellows hiss the commentators and carry on as though we were at the ring side of a good boxing match. The commentator is strictly a German rat but tries his best to get across the English pronunciation and never has a good word to say of the Allies."--Hq., 591st Engineer Boat Regiment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7e4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">"All our Allies seem to be very good soldiers. I also have to say that the German soldier is a darn good fighter and he is not ignorant and a dumb foreigner like some people think. He is shrewd, clever and very brutal, which of course made this conflict possible. Still as we operate we learn and as we learn we win. So it will be a question of time before it will be over."--Special Detachment, G-3, NATOUSA.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7f4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">"Several days ago word was sent up to us that after a year of foreign service we can go home to the U.S. for 30 full days. August 5th I'll have a full year of oversaw service and boy oh boy will I head home."--591st Engineer Boat Regiment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-804e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">"There is a rumor flying around in our outfit that sounds pretty good to me, of course I can hardly believe it to be true. The rumor is--When this African Campaign is over our battalion will return to the States;"-Battery B, 105th C.A. (AA).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-814e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">12. Church and religion. The efforts put forth by the chaplains to conduct church services have been the subject of many favorable comments. It is evident from comments that the large majority of the troops are very anxious to attend church services. Soldiers of front line units especially, praise their chaplains for conducting services under adverse conditions. The following are comments received:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-824e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">"As for church services over here, our Chaplain is doing a wonderful job, and I attend most of the services unless I am on duty. There have been times when we could not leave our positions in the daytime but the Chaplain held services at night by the light of the moon or flashlight."-­Company F, 16th Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-834e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">"Yesterday I went to communion and I hope our prayers are answered. It was about 2 months since the last time, that is the longest since I came into the army."--A.T. Company, 16th Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-844e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">"We had services on board ship, incidentally, which I helped conduct inasmuch as there was no Jewish Chaplain on board ship. We have two here. Tonight is Purim and they are having services at the Casino which I expect to attend."--Company A, 7th Battalion, 1st Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-854e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">"As yet we have no chaplain so today I went into the church in our little town to mass, and away out here in an African outpost they had an organ and an adult choir that would do credit to any of our churches at home. I closed my eyes and travelled across all those watery miles to you, darling and we were once again side by side at St. Josephs at nine o'clock mass."-­2nd Prov. Prisoner of War Admin. Section.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-864e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">"Today being Sunday I went to mass and it was swell. It was outdoors and we had about six priests present. We sang hymns and it just was like a mission at home. God love and protect the Army priests, they are the only blight light the man has left over here in a foreign country."-­Company B, 7th Battalion, 1st Replacement Depot.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-874e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">"Mother wants me to write some pastor of some church to accept my membership. Well, for her I guess I will do it, but it isn't my idea. If I live through this war I am not worried about hell because this is living hell."--1634th Ordnance Company.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-884e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">13. Home Affairs. Comments on home affairs criticise the strike of the coal miners and black market activities. Others express dissatisfaction with the attitude of the people toward the war. The following are comments received in mail examined:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-894e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">"Will drop you a few lines this afternoon to let you know that I'm still alive and kicking but mad as hell. What kind of Americans have we there at home, who will pull a labor strike at times like these are. The whole damn bunch of them should be shipped over here and shoved right up to the front as shock troops. Believe me, they would soon realize that there is a war in progress. From what I can gather from magazines and newspapers that we get I don't think the largest part of the people have awakened to the fact that this war is serious."--517th Engineers WS Co.(S).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8a4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">"If these coal miners don't quit striking we'll quit fighting, fine mess they have there at home."--26th Infantry, Company D.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8b4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">"I have been reading quite a bit in some of these publications from the States concerning 'black market'. All these stories make us awfully mad about conditions at home. It is a darn shame and there is no punish­ment strict enough for those criminals. It is the worst sabotage not only by the meatleggers but also by the population which buys from those gangsters. The articles of war should be applied for those crimes."--Hq. 101st Military Police Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8c4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">"Well, I see now that they are going to defer the farm boys. I should think they should by the way the farmers write. They say that they can't get no help at all. That sure makes it bad."--Hq. Atry., 434th C.A. Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8d4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">"How do the people like it around there with practically everything rationed, I bet there is some that bitch like hell. But they'll get used to it."--26th General Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">"I believe that you know, Tommy, that our country is fighting for its life--for yours and mine, and all of our friends, and you are doing your part. You've got to keep on doing your part. Don't loaf and kill time like some of the others there are doing. Not for the 80 cents per hour, but because it is wrong. You've got to produce all that you can just as soon as you can, so that my friends over here, at the front, will have it to work with, so that they will have another plane in the air, the one plane that makes the difference between victory and defeat, when they meet those Junkers and Messerschmidts. Our fellows are better than they are, but they've still got to have the equipment in order to let Jerry know that they are better than they are. Savoy? Tell those people who are loafing on the job there, that. They will understand if they have a brother or a husband out there meeting Jerry, and if they haven't they still should understand."-­Claims Commission, A.P.O. 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">. Relations with civilian population. It is evident that, in general, the French people are doing everything in their power to make the troops feel welcome. Numerous instances of troops being invited to the homes of local people have been mentioned in letters. One of the chief obstacles to more friendly relations seems to be the inability to converse in the French language. Lack of pamphlets and booklets as an aid in studying the language has been commented on in many letters. About 80% of comments observed during the past week have been favorable. Note the following:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-904e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">"We attended a dinner party last night in Oran given by a Jewish family in honor of the Col's birthday. The party was of double significance because the Jewish community celebrated Purim, the feast remembering liberation from bondage in biblical time. This year it was a real Purim celebration for the people here. And they are so appreciative for what the Americans stand for and for the fact that we liberated them from humiliation and terror. At the end of the party they were singing the Marsailaise and the children broke down and wept. The Col. had tears in his eyes and I had them rolling down my cheeks. There wasn't a dry handerchief in the house. All these people are swell to us, they just can't do enough for the Americans because they are so appreciative. I don't think that I ever will forget this evening and it makes me feel proud that we are here to prevent just those things from happening in America."--2nd Conv. Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-914e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">"I have come to the conclusion that I like the French altogether. All those I have met have been extremely hospitable. I was glad to be able to take them some cans of food I had to spare, things which are unobtainable for them, and they were very much appreciated, but they don't expect any­thing in return for their kindness. Quite different from the idea I had of the French before coming oversea."--Royal Signals, 31 Cipher Section, 365 Indep. Coy. (British).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-924e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">"It is very hard to find a nice girl here. People are awfully afraid of the American soldiers because they behave like wolfs. I am sure the situation will get worse because our reputation in regard of women is far from being good."--Battery C, 432nd C.A.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-934e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">"There are many of our officers and men who have found no adequate aid for getting around among the French speaking people. No one seems to feel that the pamphlets and booklets which are available to date are adequate. So, the sooner this aid can become available, the better for those who want to learn and the better for the good relations with the French people. --Eq., Northwest African Air Force.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-944e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">15. Relations with Allied troops. It is evident that relations with allied troops are excellent. Numerous expressions of admiration for the British and French soldiers have been observed in letters. Comments concerning the French soldiers have been observed in letters. Comments concerning the French soldiers usually deplore the poor equipment that they are forced to use and express the hope that they will soon be provided with American equipment. Comments were 100% favorable. Note the following:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-954e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">"The British Tommys are perfect soldiers as usual and we certainly cooperate 100%."--Hq. Co. 805th Tank Destroyer Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-964e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">"I for my part am very happy that the French and the Americans are uniting their efforts in the same military operations. Once more the Yanks are marching side by side with the French soldiers like their fathers did and they know the same difficulties of the language, the same preferences for the French wine and they have the same experiences to get used to foreign customs. And the American and French soldiers are certainly getting along with each other as well as they did during the last war."--Ordnance Section, Base Headquarters, A.P.O. 600.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-974e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">"We have a lot of fun here at times, near us is a camp of French soldiers and they come over a lot and play volley ball with us. We can't understand them, nor they us but we get along and have a good time."-­Company A, 755th Tank Battalion.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-984e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">"Our French soldiers and sailor friends are a proud gang-and with good reason-they are darn good soldiers."--28th Quartermaster Regiment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-994e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">"The Algerian French troops have the reputation to be excellent soldiers and that is certainly justified. But they have nothing to fight with. The equipment which they have is absolutely useless in modern warfare and with such arms it is a suicide mission to fight against the Germans."-­Company Bp 81st Armored Regiment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">"Many of the boys are very alarmed about the recent defeat of the American forces in the African Campaign. They fail to realize that most of the Germans are still engaged on the Eastern front and that they are receiving a terrific beating from the Soviet forces. After comparing the scenes of battle and the number of troops that are engaged in both, about 3 million on the big front and a much smarter one on this front. I person­ally feel that all is well and that Hitler is definitely on the road to doom. It is a hard way to learn but this set back to our forces will eliminate a lot of criticism concerning the ability of some of our Allies, and will teach some of the very stubborn fools how deeply indebted we are to the contribution that other countries have made to the destruction of a mutual problem."--64th Station Hospital.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">"Very many French officers are unlucky chaps, they have their families back in France and they worry of course very much for them. And they all put a pretty good face on it, and seem to enjoy life as far as possible. Occasionally, one will become confidential and tell you that they 'laugh on the face, but not from the heart'. Those here are more than 50% escaped from German hands. At present, they are pitifully equipped, but they are training hard. And they all seem dying to have another go at the Germans. I hope they soon get some American equipment. I am sure they will give the Germans a terrific fight."--Royal Signals, 31 Cipher Section. (British).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">"The 40,000 Frenchmen are really in a very poor way--they have got very little equipment and very poor clothes. I think it is marvelous that they have done any fighting at all. I don't think we would have done much if we have been in their situation."--Hq., 18th Army Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9d4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">"At the moment I am living with the Americans. The same chaps that took a bit of a knock on the Kasserine pass. They are all delightful fellows. I get on with them very well and they are most awfully kind to me. I am living at a Divisional Headquarters--the General is really a charming man. The General and his staff are 'all boys together' if you know what I mean and he is not nearly so 'shut off' from everyone as he is in our army. As a matter of fact I think they overdo it a bit because the poor man never seems to have an opportunity to think quietly by himself. They are all keen to learn and as far as I can gather I am welcomed in hopes that I may be of some assistance. As a matter of fact I find absolutely nothing wrong in this Division." Hq., 18th Army Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9e4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">16. Censorship. It has been noted that there is an increasing number of instances of illicit posting by troops in this area. Of a total of 31 violations requiring Forms 912 to be sent out, 15 were for that violation. It is evident that troops are not familiar with the requirement that all personal communications must be posted in Army Post Offices only. Other violations included: information as to the presence of units in the combat zone; details of air journey; details of training being conducted for future operations; location of unit; details of ocean voyage; linking an A.P.O. with an exact geographical location; morale of troops; armament and equipment; abuse of blue envelope privilege; enclosing a secret document in private letter; and use of code. Mail of recently arrived convoy was found to be 'clean' indicating that they had received some instruction before embarkation or enroute. Minor violations by troops aboard ship were the use of dates on letters and then referring to that day being the, example: "11th day at sea". The writing of day by day accounts of the voyage required numerous deletions in order to prevent disclosure of date of embarkation, length of voyage and date of debarkation. The following complaint of delay in the unit censoring of mail by unit censors has been observed:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9f4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">"Honey, I suppose you wonder why I send your letters in these blue envelopes once in a while. Well they don't have to be censored by the Company Officers, and they always let the letters lay around for 3 or 4 days before they censor them."--Hq. Co., 3rd Bn., 6th Armored Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a04e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">17. General Complaints. Lack of opportunity for promotion has been consistently complained of by officers. Also numerous complaints of delay in payment of allotments to families of soldiers have been observed. The following are typical comments:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a14e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">"It isn't a bad outfit except that there never has been any openings for promotions. As soon as there is an opening, Brigade transfers another officer in who has the rank. (We're under the old type Brigade). We have quite a few 2nd Lts. who are 30 years of age and over. I've been recommended for a promotion three times but it never did go through."--531st Engineer Shore Regiment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a24e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">"I am about the ranking Lt. of the division and all I get here and since I left the States is promises."--67th Armored Regiment.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a34e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">"Approximately a month ago I wrote regarding my allotment. I have just received word from home that my son's allotment has never arrived and yet his allotment has been deducted from my pay each month. My son is in dire need of this money and I would greatly appreciate it, if you would give this your immediate attention. None of my relatives back home can speak English, and this makes it difficult for them to make any inquiry from that end."--Cadre Company, 2642 Training Battalion.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a44e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">18. General. In general the morale of the troops is excellent. Comments reveal that troops have learned to respect the fighting ability of the German soldiers, but they are also convinced that they can and will beat them. A few evidences of low morale have been observed but it seems that they pertain to individuals rather than units. The following comments on morale have been observed during the past week:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a54e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">"But after being in the army for a while trying all the guns etc. you get to the point where you want to get in there see what you can do. I actually believe morale jumped up about 75% when we learned we were moving up to the front."--Unit unknown.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a64e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">"Those huns had better 'give their heart to God' because we are here to rub their nose in the mud. I'm saving mine until we reach Berlin where we intend to make the boche realize that they have been 'barking up the wrong tree'. When they start crying for peace this time Uncle Sam isn't gonna hear them for a long time. There will never be another Germany when we finish the job this time."--Hq. 13th F.A. Brigade.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a74e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">"Honey, I've run from bullets so have others, I've ducked in fox holes from bombs, I've seen ships torpedoed, and destroyed, men killed, men suffering from shell shock, fright, wounds etc, we all have.... But listen honey, this war is not easy, it is hell, het the amazing fact is that in spite of all this the boys never weaken, they are always anxious to get another crack at the enemy. Yes, believe me, we have a great army. The American spirit is never weaken by all this and the American people can be proud of these boys, it's wonderful. It is one for all and all for one over here. We have no amusements as you know them. For all those things we are fighting. I love my country and am happy to die for it if necessary. I am writing this just before I go into the worse and I pray to God that he helps us all."--1st Quartermaster Company.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a84e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">"My working days are long and there are seven of them in every week. However, if my humble efforts will in anyway hasten this mess to a success­ful conclusion I don't mind the long hours."--282nd Quartermaster Co. (Ref) (Fixed).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a94e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">"I was awarded the 'purple heart' while I was on the operating table on the front. It was a swell stimulant and I have passed the danger mark. I am fine and I expect to go back into action shortly."--Special Detach. G-3, A.P.O. 512.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-aa4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="108">"The situation is very satisfactory. Our food is very good considering the conditions. Our clothing is warm and comfortable. So really we have only to prove ourselves as good soldiers and win. We will. All my buddies are first raters. Good men and good soldiers. No distaste or grumbling. Everything is working out per schedule."--Spec. Det. G-3, A.P.O. 512.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ab4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="109">"Naturally I shall always do my utmost for my mother and country. Although, for the time being it is mostly my country, in this outfit."-­Company B, 1st Ranger Bn.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ac4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="110">"I believe they passed some kind of a law sending all men over 38 years old back home. It only affects one fellow in my company No I'm not sorry I'm not 38, I think I can stick this out to the end."--53rd Ordnance Company (Am).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ad4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="111">"I got to drinking pretty heavy- you understand when a guy over here is lonely- and we all are home-and lovesick-has no place to go, no fun and no recreation that the only thing he can do and that is drink. I must do something to get rid of this terrible habit because my girlfriend never would talk to me if she ever would know that."--432nd Battery C.A.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ae4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="112">"Things have taken a very bad turn for the worse for me now my dear I am a private again. It was rather a hard blow to take but I guess I can, and don't worry my dear I am not going down without putting up a fight which I have started today and the dear Captain, does not know if he is coming or going and he knows I am right so he gave me my notice tonight that I must select a company and so I am in for a transfer and to be frank about the whole thing I can't say as yet what company to pick since I can take my choice. Perhaps I will be better off out of this place for you never get any thanks for working at night and Sundays and believe me dear I am not the only one who is disgusted and I have all the boys on my side when the time comes for a show down I'm sure there will be one surprised Captain and I'm sure I will win the case for I have so many on my side."-­Service Company, 18th Infantry.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-af4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="113">"Believe me those fellows on the other side are plenty good and have the stuff to do it with too. And they are fighting a combat war not like we do only a war of supplies. I sometimes wonder where our combat troops are."--27th Bomb. Group.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b04e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="114">WALTER H. BECKER,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b14e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="115">Captain, F.A.,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b24e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="116">Chief Base Censor.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b34e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="117">32 Inclosures:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b44e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="118">31 Forms 912, Serial Nos.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b54e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="119">350 to 380, inclusive.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b64e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="120">Statistical Report in triplicate</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b74e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="121">DISTRIBUTION:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b84e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="122">3 A.C. of S., G-2, War Department (thru channels)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b94e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="123">1 Commanding General, Fifth Army</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ba4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="124">1 Commanding General, XII Air Force</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bb4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="125">1 Commanding Officer, MBS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bc4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="126">File</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>