<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Morale Report for the week of March 21 - March 27 1943</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-b806d9b3-65de-4d9a-b18a-890b57c2952c</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-2d87d6d2-4634-400f-aa97-46a85a3fb0e8</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-bd4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">C ONFIDENTIAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-be4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="2">MORALE REPORT FOR THE WEEK OF Mar. 21 - March 27, 1943</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bf4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">Office of Field Base Censor No. 2 hhh 1. HEALTH</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c04e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="4">Favorable comments 40%; unfavorable 60%. Favorable comments reflect a gain in weight, while the unfavorable comments concern specific ailments and cases of many common colds. The latter is attributed by one writer to the fact that there is no time to enjoy the sunshine. A Major, (File No. 285) says:- "Personally, I think we would have fewer colds is we spent one afternoon a week in the sunlight." (6th Gen. Hosp.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c14e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">Another Major writes that he is amazed at the amount of rheumatic fever he has seen as well as a few cases of coronary thrombosis. There is mention made of the death of a Lieutenant from typhoid fever.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c24e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">Under the general category of health, there is specific mention of the necessity for dental care, (File No. 335) "Almost 50% of the men need fittings, about ¼ need dentures or adjustments or repairs." (3Bn. Eng. Arm.) hhh 2. MAIL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c34e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">Favorable comments 66% unfavorable 34%. While these averages may not be exact with respect to mail, it is difficult to fix an average, as some of the men complain about not receiving mail in months, then getting it all in a bunch, and among the letters were some that took only 12 days in arriving. The average time for the receipt of mail is about 15 days. Those who received delayed mail, stated that they were receiving Christmas mail, forwarded from their last station.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c44e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">A Major complaining about delays in the mail, attributes it to censorship, (File No. 331) "Self-imposed censorship is a joke--now that the censor opens and reads all officers mail anyway. Your mail deliveries will be long delayed." (2nd Aux. Burg. Group) hhh 3. TRAINING Unfavorable comments 100%. It is to be seen that this does not apply to training here, but to lack of training in the States. The only comments in point are dealt with in full.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c54e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">"(File No. 322) As you know, I was surprised to be sent overseas so soon after being commissioned. Well, there are several others (most all of us, in fact) in the same boat. I frankly don't know enough about being an officer or about the Armored Force to go into battle with a platoon of men and 5 tanks, but it looks as though that is just what I am going to do." (10th Repl. Bn. Co. A).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c64e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">(File No. 320) "I am sorry to state that in many respects our training in the states is far from what it should be, but unfortunately we didn't realize until we arrived over­seas what it was all about. We need Medical Observers to pass their observations back to the people in the States ----to the people who really need it like the Division Surgeons---I will go into detail on a number of these matters and forward them thru official channels one of these days for your information there." Note: this let­ter is addressed to a Colonel in the Office of the Surgeon General. (HQ. 2nd Armored Div.) hhh 4. EQUIPMENT For convenience sake, this category is subdivided as follows:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c74e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">A. Guns and Ammunition: Unfavorable 100%. There seems to be a lack of ammunition in some outfits:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c84e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">(File No. 314) "The men do not even have any ammunition for their rifles." (Co. I, 3rd Bn., 21st Eng. Avn. Refit.) (File No. 397) "Need more planes, guns, ammunition" (59th Evac. Hosp)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c94e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">B. Medical Equipment: Favorable 50%, unfavorable 50%. While one comment states that equipment troubles continue, another states that the very best medical equipment was brought along and (File No.241)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ca4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">"you could get at a moment's notice everything from a set of false teeth made, to X-Ray pictures." (Gq. ABS)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cb4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">C. Athletic equipment: There seems to be an oversupply of same, though there are no complaints Against receiving same. There was one comment sheet referring to stealing of equipment (File No. 373)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cc4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">"I've stolen everything from 5/8" bolts to 16 ton Bull Dozers from other outfits." (Co. D. 540th Eng. Regt.) hhh 5. FOOD</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cd4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">Favorable comments; 75% unfavorable, 25%. Again there are the usual commendations concerning the food, and credit is given to the cooks and mess officers. From the slips submitted, the following articles were mentioned: Fresh meat, ham, chicken, pork, beefsteak, hamburgers, coffee, cheese, butter, mashed potatoes, cabbage, canned fruits of all kinds, chicken, baked beans, apple sauce, jam, graham crackers, cocoa, and cake. The usual comments are that the men feel sorry for the people back home with their rationing of food.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ce4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">The unfavorable comments concerned canned rations and food for the enlisted men on board ship, though one nurse, (File No. 281) states:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cf4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">"The food here is abominable and know now that we will certainly lose a great deal of weight--therefore we don't talk too much about food as we are always hungry. I pray hard each night that we might get a little bit of milk for our coffee, but no, it is as black as mud. We are so hungry at night that we actually cry ourselves to sleep. ... Mother, dear, pray for us here so we won't get sick, as it is Hell." (69 Station Hospital)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d04e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">(File No. 361)says: "Those--- guys way back there behind the action stop all the food they want and more, passing meager rations on up to the ground and air combat outfits." (379th Sqdn. 310th Bomb. Gr.) hhh 6. ENTERTAINMENT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d14e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">Favorable 100%. Under this category, special mention is made of the radio station for the service men, and Bob Hope is the favorite program, most of the men gathering around to listen to the program. The special broad­casts are well appreciated by the men. hhh 7. SPORTS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d24e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">Favorable 100%. From the information slips, the boys are anxious that the folk back home know that they are well equipped with athletic supplies, and that they appreciate what the government has done for them. A list of supplies, all being used, is as follows:- baseball sets, volley balls, footballs, soft balls, handballs, ping pong sets, checkers, dominoes etc. Mention is again made of the fact that it is enjoyable relaxation to indulge in the sports after a day's work. hhh 8. LEAVE 9. QUARTERS 10. POLITICS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d34e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">There are no comments covering these subects. hhh 11. NEWS AND PROPAGANDA</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d44e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">Favorable 100%. With regard to news itself, the only mention is of articles in Life Magazine, concerning North Africa, which one writer states in the bunk. The main comments concerning broadcast of propaganda are the German broadcasts to the A. E. F. in North Africa and the following are made.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d54e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">(File No. 362) "Our 'favorite' radio program is the German propaganda broadcast which comes on from 8 P.M. to 8:30 P. E. nightly. This program originates in Berlin. .. Am afraid it doesn't have the effect the Germans apparently hope for." (Hq. 3rd Inf. Div. Arty.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d64e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">The opinions of the listeners do not vary from that of taking it as a joke, though they do enjoy the music broadcast.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d74e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">Another wonders why he cannot disclose location in his writing back home, since it is evident that the Germans know where the troops are stating their location, now and then. hhh 12. CHURCH AND RELIGION Favorable 100%. Sincere compliments are paid to the church services offered, and the men are testifying to the help they receive from the services. One writer, having led the services, writes: (File No. 339)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d84e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">"It was encouraging for all those men to crowd in, sing heartily and listen so intently." (437 CA Bn.) hhh 13. HOME AFFAIRS Favorable 50% unfavorable 50%. A nurse (File No. 291) states:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d94e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">"Blood plasma is wonderful and I know that if the folks at home knew how much good it did they would be only too willing to give all they could." (6th Gen. Hosp.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-da4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">One writer a private first class worries whether his mother is ill or not and asks, (File No. 292) "Did mother write a letter to the War Department saying she was ill." (Co. D. 61st t. M. Bn)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-db4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">From the scarce information in the communication, it is believed that this soldier does not know about the facilities offered to help the families of service men. hhh 14. RELATIONS WITH CIVILIAN POPULATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">Favorable 10%; unfavorable 90%. Even the favorable report, which consisted of an invitation to dinner with a few French families, mentions the following:- (File No. 357) "Of course, those in business treat us like all business people treat tourists-like suckers--raise their prices up sky-high, 300 to 800% and I ain't kidding." (Med Det. 205 of Bn. "G.S.")</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">Another in describing an invitation to a dinner with some Arabs, states that they (the Arabs) hate the French because of the high charges for necessities. There is a distinct unfriendly feeling and a definite restraint evidenced between the service men and the French, and a decided lack of camaraderie, as one writer mentions:- (File No. 375) " There is none of the camaraderie that should evidence itself between two peoples fighting for the same thing." (191st Tank Bn.) hhh 15. RELATIONS WITH ALLIED TROOPS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">Favorable 50%; unfavorable 50%. Commendation of the British is set forth in the following from a Captain,(File No. 332) "The British are fine fighters and we are proud to fight beside such men. They are doing most of the fighting over here." (Med. Det. 17th Eng. Bn)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">Regarding the French soldiers a Captain comments, (File No. 375)" We see all types of Trench soldiers around....we all live and train side by side, but with no friendly gestures at all. It looks to me as if there is pro-German sentiment to a certain extent among some of French and most of the crabs." (191st Tank. Bn) hhh 16. CENSORSHIP</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e04e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">Unfavorable 100%. There is a dire need for proper instruction in censorship which evidently cannot be portrayed in directives. The constant question raised is why the men should not be permitted to state things that are mentioned in daily newspapers back home, and that as a result of the re­straint being put upon them their letters amount to inanities and drivel.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e14e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">A cross section of the situation is shown by the following:- (File No. 401) "Quite a number of the officers in the outfit are pretty much burned up tonight about the news we got today regarding censorship rulings. It seems if the cart can't be in front of the horse, it isn't the American way.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e24e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">Ever since our arrival in North Africa the censors have told us it is permissible to mail small monetary notes (native) home in envelopes. We could also send post cards home providing they didn't depict cities or town, (unless otherwise indicated by authorities) or instal­lations of military value several days ago about 25-30 postcards were returned to me by the base censor with no explanation. None of them contained military information and the pictures were strictly of native markets and the like. Today an officer friend of mine got a letter back that contained a five franc note. ...Mind you the censors never gave one word of explanation. It was then and only then that he found out the latest rulings, which incidentally souhd childless as hell to me. The censors said that a directive would be out in a few days in regards to new rulings. In the meantime thousands of officers and men are buying cards, stamps and stationery only to have it thrown back in their faces with the stamps cancelled. Just one more example of the American way of doing things. Doubtless, our base censor is not at fault. Chances are the new rule was slapped in his face and he has to abide by it. Somewhere along the lines things are being fouled Yet, we get New York papers every day that contain fancy dia­grams as well as military info of untold importance to the enemy. Just last night, I was looking through a New York Daily News and saw a diagram depicting all the different routes that our planes have flown. But if I wrote you a letter giving you the route of a trip I might have taken, I'd get someone's well known shoes shoved down my throat… Thousands of us got here to fight for our country. Naturally, we want to write the folks back home and in some of our letters (damn few) we might slip up and give something away. Bingo, it goes in our 201 file so we're held upon promotions, maybe court martialed." (Hq. 14th Fighter Group)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e34e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">(File No. 317) "A lot of the things we censor rigidly here are broadcast on the radio and newspapers in the states." (hq. &amp; hq. Co. 2nd Ar. Div.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e44e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">(File No. 358) "It is highly amusing though, to read things in Life and Time which we wouldn't dare breathe a word about (writer refers to some snapshots returned to him.) (67th A. R. 2 A.D.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e54e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">(File No. 279) "I have been having a few tiffs with the censorship people I am afraid and have decided to write nothing but inanities and drivel." (Eq. ABS.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e64e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">In criticising censorship, one writer in a letter to his wife says they all are in a beautiful mood, what with missing the folks, no mail and the new bunch of censors, who return mail to them. One writer maintains that there are restrictions on letter writing and says (File No. 245)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e74e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">"Just got off a tour of O.D. which consisted of censoring about umpty ump letters. Whew. .... We have an unwritten law in our organisation that two letters per week is the maximum output, for that alone gives each O.D. about 100 letters to correct, but nobody adheres to it, nor does any O. D. ever enforce it. Letters mean too much to our men and those in the states with whom they correspond." (239th big. Opns. Co. Sep) hhh 17. General Complaints</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e84e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">A. Promotions:- Opinions are that it is only back in the states where the people get promotions fast and many gripes are found in letters about this. As one man put it,(File No. 390)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e94e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">"I'm sure that if I were back in the states I would be a captain by now, while over here I don't even hope for a captaincy for another year." (Co. E. 21st Eng. Avn. Regt.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ea4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">B. Safe Arrival cards:- There is no variation in the opinions of the writers regarding this subject as most of them cannot get over the fact that the Government did not send out our safe arrival cards.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-eb4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">C. Money order facilities:- Many are carrying as much as $200 in their pockets as there are no forms available to send money orders back home.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ec4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">D. V-Mail and stamps:- Requests are made for these things in many letters as the post offices have run out of both. hhh 18. General</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ed4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">There seems to be a general let down in morale, brought out by the various complaints mentioned in this report. Of all the slips examined, there was only one mention in so many words of the excellent morale of the men. Many find that they are not in their proper job and chances for transfer are slim because of the set up of the organization they desire to enter.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ee4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">Among the general items mentioned the following were found-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ef4e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">1. Trouble with the natives digging up soldiers graves.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f04e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">2. Stealing in the army. A Captain writes (File No. 302) "He, (a Qm. Lieut) keeps us well stocked with canned fruits, juices, coffee, etc. (File No. 321) "One soldier sold one Arab a mattress cover for $20." (Co. ii.- 10th Repl. Bn)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f14e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">3. Pranks in the army which are dangerous:- (File No. 377) "One of the current pranks of some of the flyers is to fly low over our hotel to wake up a room-mate."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-f24e7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">Though previously mentioned, almost all who write on the subject praise the work of the Red Cross and their clubs in no uncertain terms, and are very well pleased with the facilities the Red Cross offers.</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>