<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Appreciation Report No. 6, for the week ending March 27, 1943</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-f7525286-753e-463e-b11b-41dc9f4cea0a</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-f945c6df-0d5a-4936-822b-6bc9b4f0b894</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-764b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">ALLIED FORCE HEADQUARTERS (INC)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-774b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="2">FIELD BASE CENSOR No. 3</note>
				<note xml:id="q-784b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="3">A.P.O. 512, U. S. ARMY</note>
				<note xml:id="q-794b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="4">Appreciation Report No. 6</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7a4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">For the Week Ending March 27, 1943</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7b4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">1. The accompanying tabulation of morale indications is not subdivid­ed this week according to source as has been done in previous reports. The great increase, in mail routed through this office and the sharp reduction in examining staff made it impossible to spot check much unit censored mail, aside from postcards which provide no good indications of morale. It was also necessary to spot check officers' mail from many scattered units and localities, so that a subdivided tabulation would not provide enough letters in any single category to give reliable percentages. The combined tabulat­ion that is presented is based mainly on officers' mail but is otherwise a fair sampling of all the units represented in mail flowing through this office.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7c4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">GENERAL MORALE</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7d4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">%</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7e4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">Mention 57</note>
				<note xml:id="q-7f4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">Good 98</note>
				<note xml:id="q-804b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">Bad 2</note>
				<note xml:id="q-814b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">HEALTH</note>
				<note xml:id="q-824b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">Mention 19</note>
				<note xml:id="q-834b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">Good 96</note>
				<note xml:id="q-844b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">Bad 4</note>
				<note xml:id="q-854b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">MAIL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-864b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">Mention 12</note>
				<note xml:id="q-874b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">Good 15</note>
				<note xml:id="q-884b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">Bad 85</note>
				<note xml:id="q-894b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">RATIONS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8a4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">Mention 5</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8b4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">Good 86</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8c4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">Bad 14</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8d4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">QUARTERS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">Mention 4</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">Good 93</note>
				<note xml:id="q-904b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">Bad 7</note>
				<note xml:id="q-914b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">OFFICERS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-924b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">Mention 1</note>
				<note xml:id="q-934b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">Good 68</note>
				<note xml:id="q-944b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">Bad 32</note>
				<note xml:id="q-954b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">RELATIONS WITH FRENCH</note>
				<note xml:id="q-964b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">Mention 4</note>
				<note xml:id="q-974b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">Good 99</note>
				<note xml:id="q-984b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">Bad 1</note>
				<note xml:id="q-994b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">RELATIONS WITH BRITISH</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">Mention 3</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">Good 96</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">Bad 4</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9d4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">DOMESTIC AFFAIRS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9e4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">Mention 13</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9f4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">Good 92</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a04b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">Bad 8</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a14b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="44">COMPILATION OF MORALE INDICATIONS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a24b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="subject" n="45">AS MENTIONED IN PERSONAL CORRESPONDENCE hhh 2. GENERAL MORALE:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a34b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">The percentage of letters indicating general morale is higher than last week, but over a longer period it is about average for a group composed mainly of officers, whose letters normally give more frequent indications of morale than do those of enlisted men. The average condition of morale indicated is excellent, as usual, 98% good. This has varied very little in the six weeks during which a check has been kept by this office. Resumption of the offensive in Tunisia is reflected in the mail and gives rise to many optimistic predictions, but this makes surprisingly little difference in the level of morale, which continued good during the Axis advance.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a44b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">In this connection, it should be noted that many letters, both from officers and enlisted men, repeat a rumor or state a belief that the writers will be sent home either on leave or permanently as soon as the Tunisian campaign is over. This causes cheerful optimism at present, but it is sure to cause complaint and a slump in morale if this prediction proves to be ill-founded. If an announcement on this subject were made before the rumor becomes still more widespread, it might prevent future disappointment and difficulty. Some typical expressions on general morale:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a54b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">"My morale has gone up 100% since I've been here where it counts all the time." (Officer, 12th A.F.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a64b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">"I thought how lucky we are to be serving in the best fed, best equipped army in the world." (Officer, AFHQ).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a74b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">"I also am satisfied about everything, doing my part, although small, for Democracy. As Cervantes said--'Liberty is a cause which merits even the giving of one's life." (A Spanish-American soldier writing in Spanish, 213th C.A. (A.A.)).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a84b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">"Honey first place we don't want come back till here is over. When we come back we want stay back. We want stay with piece like we want." (Sold­ier whose wife asked him to come home, 1O53 M.P. Co.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a94b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">"Would like to be in Augusta today. . . But instead I am a hero or some­thing way over here in Africa. I'm awful sore at those Germans. I'm going to tromp le 'em and end the war quickly. S'help me, I'll mow 'em down." (Officer, 751st Tank Bn.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-aa4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="53">Aside from such expressions of high morale at the moment, letters rather frequently allude to permanent benefits derived by the writers from army life. Examples:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ab4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="54">"You remember that inferiority complex that I always had? Well I have­n't got it any more, as I joined the army and lost it." (51st Sig. Co. Serv. Grp..</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ac4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="55">"I'm going to be able to get along with people a whole lot better when I get out of this war. We have to share. everything to such an extent that it has cured an antisocial condition that had grown on me back in the states. . .I find it not hard to knuckle under any more, and very few people who I can't get along with. . .Getting along with people is the magic key to most things we want." (Officer, HQ, EBS).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ad4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="56">"This is broadening my outlook and showing me many things I could never learn by sitting at home. It is also increasing my appreciation of all the things I accepted as a necessary part of life." (Officer, 185th P.A. Bn.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ae4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="57">A few special comments from the Air Corps:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-af4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="58">"I'd much rather be here than at home." (Officer, 94th Fighter Sq.). Apropos of commendation of his unit: "Gosh, I could hardly believe he was talking about us. We haven't done so much; I think we are just trying to make up for the fact that we don't go into combat. . .by pushing our missions through. . ." (Officer, 17th Troop Carrier Squadron).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b04b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="59">"I know you and all my friends are praying for me for otherwise would not be as safe now as I am. . .I'll tell you just before we get near our target and encounter fighters and anti-aircraft fire--I look up at God and ask him to please help me through the danger ahead--then after I am on my way back home I thank him for protecting me. . ." (Officer, 3O1 Bomb Grp.). "The air corps didn't turn out so glamorous after all. Not here in Africa, anyway. Where the sun seldom shines, where it's cold and damp, where there's not a white girl for fifty miles, without a damn place to go or anywhere to spend your money, to live in a mud-hole in the ground, never taking a bath, never eating a half decent meal, to wear dirty clothes, to work from dawn to dusk to keep the airplanes flying only to have Jerry come over and bomb or strafe the hell out of you and your planes. Old General Sherman wasn't far from wrong when he said, 'War is Hell'." (Officer, 47th Bomb Grp.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b14b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="60">"If I told the truth I'd probably be court-martialed." (Officer, 47thBomb. Wing). Some divergent opinions:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b24b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="61">"I am in the country where Jesus Christ was born, Jesus Christ, I wish I was where I was born." (133 Inf.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b34b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="62">"Sure wish I could go home as I'm tired of shooting people, but then I guess someone has to do it, at least they damn sure shoot back." (Off­icer, 68th Obs. Grp.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b44b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="63">"The same old thing that exists in every HQ--petty jealousies, throat-cutting galore, polishing the old apple with the Colonels. . .You can put it on the record that this is the LAST war I'll ever engage in--come what may::: Glamour? --Phooey!! Excitement? --Phooey!! Saving the world?--honey!! . .Ah-h-h-h-h-h-h--NUTS!!!! I loves yah!" (Officer, Hq XII AFSC).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b54b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="64">"I'm so sick of this damned war that when I get home I don't want anybody to ever associate me with it. " (915 Sig. Co.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b64b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="65">"No matter where I am I'm always half awake at night expecting, on alert, or air raid, The way I figure, the odds are 6-2 even for my getting back anyway, but I would like to know when I'm going to get it. Im not trying to wave a flag. I'm scared plenty so scared that I change underwear three times a week. So take it from me buddy you try and stay over there as long as you can." (751st Tank Bn (M)). hhh 3. HEALTH:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b74b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="66">96% of the references to health in letters say that the writer is well. This does not indicate any change from previous reports. Typical: "My health and spirit is as ever and I'm confident the war cannot change that." (Officer, 68 CA (AA)).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b84b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="67">A new complaint: "Over here, I get a few 'desert sores.' They are ordinary cuts on the hand, but are hard to heal up." (Officer, 82nd Bomb. Sqdn. ). hhh 4. MAIL:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b94b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="68">85% of the comments on mail service declare that it is bad and the complaints are even more widespread and bitter than usual. Typical comments:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ba4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="69">"WHERE IS MY MAIL? I have never gone thru such terribly maddening mental torture in my whole life. . .I will positively go nuts if this mail situation is not cleared up damn soon. I think it should be investigated by the army officials as my case is merely one of many similar cases. How can good morale be maintained when our mail is not coming through to us. .?" (Officer, APO 65O, unit not given).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bb4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="70">"All we can hear in the U. S. news is the large number of merchant ships being launched but none seem to carry any mail. After this war we should have a period of accounting from the lousy bastards who are respon­sible for such inefficient blundering. However I suppose we should be glad they do not hold more responsible positions where their gross stupidity could do still greater damage to our war effort." (Officer, 61f T. C. Group).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bc4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="71">"I am still awaiting the regular mail that I have coming. . .was read­ing a little article in the Digest about the way Uncle Sam takes care of our mail and we all had a laugh out of it." (Officer, 64. T. C. Grp.). hhh 5. RATIONS:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bd4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="72">The mail indicates general satisfaction with rations, as usual, but the percentage of unfavorable comments, 14%, is greater than it has been for a group composed mostly of officers, which seems to mark a trend of increasing complaints. The enlisted mens' mail, however, suggests normal or even increased approval of rations. The officers' complaints (aside from the apparently universal dislike of British rations) refer mainly to monotony of food and to what are considered insufficient PX issues. Quot­ations:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-be4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="73">"It's almost chow time. We're having lamb stew as usual. I never did like sheep, but didn't think I'd have to eat them all to get rid of them. Little Tom Horner, sat in a corner, Eating his lamb-stew pie, He stuck in his fork, and pulled out a cork, and yelled 'WHERE IN HELL'S THE BOTTLE?'" (Officer, 751st Tank Bn.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-bf4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="74">"Another thing that burns us is that the English seem to get lots of American made chocolate and we usually settle for one English ration bar. They also get a quart of Scotch a month through their mess, and we can't get a damn thing but wine." (Officer, AFHQ, Ry. Ser.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c04b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="75">"We can't get soap, shoelaces, writing paper, etc., but they can truck millions of these goddamned yellow income tax forms up here to us." (HQ XII AFSC). hhh 6. QUARTERS:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c14b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="76">93% of the mentions of quarters are favorable, about an average figure. It is interesting that personnel living in dugouts at the front do not complain any more than those living in apartments at force headquarters. hhh 7. OFFICERS:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c24b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="77">32% of the statements of opinion on superior officers are unfavorable, a radical change from the previous average (14% for officers and only 3% for enlisted men). Most of the complaints are vague, however, and many clearly represent personal grudges or are written by officers to whom their superiors seem to be barriers to promotion. The following is unusually enthusiastic but otherwise more typical than are the complaints:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c34b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="78">"The man I am under is swell--really swell--he knows just what he is doing--can do anything you can do. . .I respect and like him tremendously." (W/O, AG Sect., AFHQ). hhh 8. RELATIONS WITH LOCAL POPULATION:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c44b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="79">The soldiers continue to love the local girls and the officers continue to eat three-hour meals with the girls' parents, making the comments on the French even more favorable than usual (99%). Typical of the widespread enthusiasm, for French beauty:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c54b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="80">"She's a nicely reared girl isn't she? Yes, and she looks good from the front, too." (133rd Inf.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c64b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="81">There is some slight improvement in attitude toward the Arabs, outside of the cities. Unusual comment:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c74b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="82">"In some sections of the country the Arabs are fine--clean, wear good clothes, fair complexed--and the Arab women have large black expressive eyes. The women even the young girls wear veils but in some sections they are extremely clean." (Officer, AFHQ, Transp. Corps). hhh 9. RELATIONS WITH THE BRITISH:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c84b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="83">Derogatory remarks about the British continue to come only from isolated individuals who do not, as a rule, seem to have had opportunity to form a balanced judgment. 96% of letters referring to the British are favorable. Typical comments: "We have our differences and different ideas for approaching problems, naturally. But the English officers I have met and known well are for the most part swell fellows - -and the same goes for the French. For every stinker you find in their ranks you won't have to look far for his counterpart in our own." (Officer, G-4, AFHQ).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-c94b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="84">"The English are really a most charming lot and we have much fun along with our work."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ca4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="85">(Officer, AFHQ).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cb4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="86">Effect of enemy propaganda on opinion of the British:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cc4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="87">"We do get a good program from Italy and one from Germany. They are just as funny as listening to a good comedian back home. . .Their prime objective is to create a feeling of distrust and antagonism between the Americans and the British. I have met a number of officers and men of the British Army and they seem like very good chaps." (68 C.A.-A.A.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cd4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="88">Comment by a French Officer attached to the U. S. Army:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ce4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="89">"I have brought back from my stay in England and from what I saw there unlimited admiration for the intelligent preparation that the English bring to the wan" (Officer, in French, AFHQ).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-cf4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="90">An English enlisted man attached to the U. S. Army says: "We are liv­ing with the Yanks and are feeding on their rations and if you could only see what we get, it would certainly make your mouth water. . .When we get to know the Yanks they are pretty good guys and they are doing some good work at the moment and they look like keeping it up." (AFHQ).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d04b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="91">An exceptional comment: "Beer. . .I'm afraid will have to wait until new years for wine is the only beverage available unless one becomes chummy with a British officer and then it's the lesser of two evils. I'll take the water." (68th C.A.). hhh 10. HOME AFFAIRS:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d14b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="92">This week for the first time a check was made on the morale reaction to news from home. As previously established (Reports 3 and 4) at least a third of letters read here, in all categories, contain same reference to home affairs, but only 13 of those examined this week give a clear indication of the effect of these affairs on morale. This is, nevertheless, one of the major specific morale indications in letters, exceeded this week only by health. 92% of the morale reactions to news from home are favorable. In most cases the favorable reaction results from letters received with family news of good health, fortune and love. Reaction to less personal news from the U.S. is less common and less favorable. Indeed the reaction to news of the home front is almost wholly unfavorable as exemplified by the following extracts:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d24b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="93">"That income tax is really going to be something. Looks like nearly everything that I am saving I'll have to turn over to the government by the time I get home." (Officer, 64 T. C. Grp.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d34b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="94">"Someone had a letter from home saying that all girls between the ages of 21 and something were to register on July 1st and then I suppose they'll be drafted. If that isn't a hell of a note. Seems about the cheapest thing I ever heard of. Another idea they borrowed from the dam British I suppose." (64. T.C. Gp.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d44b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="95">"My wife writes me that you are doing a marvelous job and that the CIO is picking on you, but the American people are behind you 100%. To hell with the slackers in industry--should be drafted into the army." (Officer, to Rickenbacker; HQ XII AFSC).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d54b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="96">"We'll win--never doubt that-IF: Those of you back there are fully cognizant of the fact that there is a WAR on and put every last drop of energy you can into WINNING it with us." (AFHQ).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d64b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="97">"You say people are pretty sporty about doing without gas, shoes, tea, etc.-well they better be--I think a lot of boys over here are pretty sporty about doing without arms legs and eyes and sight! Tell them that." (3O1 Bomber Gr.). hhh 11. CENSORSHIP:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d74b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="98">There are increased references to the tightening of censorship, which, according to letters read recently, was very lax before this office opened. Most of the comments accept the fact of censorship with­out complaint. Typical comments:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d84b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="99">"There is little I can write about as the censors are strict." (Officer, IP "Now my censor and I both send you our love, and after the war one of us will have a lot easier time writing you letters." (149 WAAC).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-d94b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="100">"If you find this boring--remember, it's not my chatter--it's censorship." (849 Sig. Int. Serv.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-da4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="101">"Pardon me--Mr. Censor--But I just have to tell Andy that I think he is tops!" (Nurse, 38th Evac. Hosp.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-db4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="102">"And now, Lorna, comes the time in all my letters or me to pay respect to those lovable 'Yankee Clippers'--the censors. (Aside to the censor: All this blank space belongs to you--Get going, cut up). " (Stars and Stripes).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dc4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="103">"Understand that all mail will be censored before it goes to the States . . .Some jerk probably blew his top and said too much--so we all must suffer--hope the censors soon get tired of reading all this stuff." (Officer, 19th Serv. Gp.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-dd4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="104">Reactions of unit censors:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-de4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="105">"This evening I have been censoring mail. That is an unpleasant task . . .Well I suppose that I've got to earn my money somehow." (Officer, 68C.A. (AA)).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-df4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="106">"Honey I have to read so many letters when I censor mail it makes me feel like I would never want to write another letter because of the crap and lies that the soldiers write home about." (Officer, 915 Sig. Co. Dep. Avn.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e04b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="107">Reactions to base censorship:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e14b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="108">"I am going to use the Base Censor because I want my mail censored as it should be and I know those boys know what they're doing." (Blue envelope, 829 Sig. Ser. Bn.). "Guess it's all right to say that but had better be careful or FBC -3 will get on my neck again. He hasn't bothered me much in the past 3 or 4. days. Maybe he was feeling the way I do sometimes and used me to work off his steam on. Granted that I gave him a chance." (Officer, 849th S. I. S. ). hhh 12. PROMOTION:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e24b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="109">Comments on promotion occur in 5% of officers' letters (see Report No. 3). This is an important morale factor in many cases. Some comments:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e34b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="110">"The major gripes, in fact the only ones you hear are MAIL and promotion policies." (Officer, AFHQ).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e44b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="111">"I sit and wait for word on my recommendation. It has bogged down temporarily, I guess. It's the same old story. I won't be much good till I know for sure. (Officer, 951 Eng. Topo. Co.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e54b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="112">"Promotion as such doesn't mean anything to us here other than recognition of the fact that we are doing our work well. . .In fact we would all be happy to do without promotions if things were on an impartial basis. . . There are so darn many full colonels here that were sgts. and warrant officers before the war! They are the ones that are promotion conscious." (Officer, AFHQ).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e64b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="113">"Our squadron commander thinks only of his own promotions and no one elses." (Officer, 301 Bomb Grp.). hhh 13. MISCELLANEOUS:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e74b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="114">"It always takes the army ten times as long to do a job as it should." (Officer, 951 Eng. Topo. Co.).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e84b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="115">"Sometime during the day I had gotten the bright idea for another story and so sat down to start it. It's good but I'm afraid I won't use it.---Reason I'm afraid of it is that it's another story laughing at the Correspondents. This, in itself is all right but makes things sort of one sided. I'd like to show their good side but it seems a bit difficult to find suitable material for stories in their good side." (Officer, PRO).</note>
				<note xml:id="q-e94b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="116">"This talk back their about peace gives me a pain in the fanny. . . There can only be one kind of peace anyway and that's annihilation of one side or the other from the two-year olds up." (Officer, 68 C.A.(AA)). hhh 14. SECURITY:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ea4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="117">A very large percentage of postcards mailed in this theater reveal location directly or indirectly. Although these are now stopped, as far as possible, it is probable that in this and various other ways the locations of many units in this theater have already been made known.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-eb4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="118">Air Corps mail, increasingly routed through this office, is found to have an unusually high percentage of minor violations. Most of these violations have to do with locality, some also with details of equipment and operations. It appears that many Air Corps officers have not received adequate instructions in security regulations.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ec4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="119">CHAS. T. HEREFORD</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ed4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="120">Captain, Infantry</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ee4b7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="contact" n="121">Chief Field Base Censor</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>