<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">Morale and Home Intelligence Reports</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Report: Morale Report for the week of March 14 - March 20 1943</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-q-d1414a1f-1105-4844-8a63-f22fbd4e97d7</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-q-eb6b03b9-38f9-4936-bbc8-c4bedadeec91</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-3a2313f7-095e-4014-875d-f4b321231f34</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Morale and Home Intelligence Reports, 1941-1949</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<note xml:id="q-804d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="1">CONFIDENTIAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-814d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="theme" n="2">MORALE REPORT FOR THE WEEK OF Mar. 14 - Mar. 21, 1943.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-824d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="3">Office of Field Base Censor No. 2 hhh 1. HEALTH</note>
				<note xml:id="q-834d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="4">Favorable comments, 50%; unfavorable 50%. One writer (File No. 230) complains that he is one of the few who has not gained weight and adds: "some have gained as much as 25 pounds." (11th Eva. Hosp.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-844d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="5">A lieutenant (File No. 176) gives the following statement: "… the men of the command and we serve are in as excellent health as a large group of men could be - - illness is at an absolute minimum - - malaria has practically disappeared."</note>
				<note xml:id="q-854d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="6">Unfavorable comments showed loss of weight in one writer, while another sets forth his fears in the following comment, (File No.258)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-864d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="7">"We are going to have trouble with summer Gastrointestinal disease in the officers' messes if water is not hotter and in E. L. eating in cafes." (5th Gen. Disp. ABS) hhh 2. MAIL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-874d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="8">Favorable comments 5%; unfavorable 95%. A favorable comment was that mail was received within 12 days, while the unfavorable comments state that letters were received after three months. The following excerpts from letters bear upon the complaints against the mail service. (File No. 240)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-884d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="9">"Finally in desperation I started to scour all the APO's in sight and… I brought back a sack of mail...I found it laying on the floor of one of the Post Offices and some of the letters had been here and sent back and then came back across. " (426th Eng. (DT) (File 158)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-894d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="10">"Our mail must be all balled up because none of the boys have had any mail." (1st Air Defense Wing, F. S. &amp; R.C.) hhh 3. TRAINING hhh 4. EQUIPMENT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8a4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="11">No comments on these subjects. hhh 5. FOOD</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8b4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="12">Favorable comments 65%; unfavorable 35%. Among the favorable re­ports many menus are listed and for brevity, the following list of foods is shown in the mails:-fried chicken, steak, fresh fruit, eggs, white bread, poultry, white bread, fresh vegetables and ice cream. Others compare the food presently served with that on the boat or in England and in no uncertain terms condemn the food served on the latter two. Unfavorable comments concerned the lack of meats.- (File No. 189)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8c4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="13">"We don't get it (meat) very often, maybe once or twice a week." (2d. Repl. Depot, 21st. Bn)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8d4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="14">In connection with meats, too much Spam was being served, and as one stated, fried, boiled, baked and (File No. 234) "...last night we had spaghetti and moat. balls with span for the meat balls." ( 499th Ca. Co.) hhh 6. ENTERTAINMENT</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8e4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="15">Favorable comments 75%; unfavorable comments 25%. Eentertainment as set forth in the few comments on the subject, consisted of musical shows put on by the colored enlisted men, movies in the open air at camp and Red Cross entertainment. There seems to be some difference of opinion as the quality of the pictures being shown, some complaining that the pictures are old ones.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-8f4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="16">One specific complaint was found as to reading matter (File No. 227) in which a corporal stated;</note>
				<note xml:id="q-904d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="17">"I'd give alot for a good book to read or a paper when I'm off duty." (Hs. Co. 3rd Bn. 21st E.A.) hhh 7. SPORTS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-914d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="18">Favorable comments, 100. There never seem to be any un­favorable comments when it concerns sports and once again, the mail contains lists of the sports indulged in, football, softball, volleyball, badminton, and others. Again competition is keen among the men and a P. S. in one letter (File No. 205) is as follows:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-924d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="19">" The men are in good spirits tonight as a hilarious volley ball game is in progress. Can you imagine that?--after a hard day's work too." (64th Ord.Co. AL)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-934d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="20">Regarding the equipment furnished for athletic facilities: (File No. 247) "Uncle Sam furnishes us with beautiful athletic equipment, it makes this place seem like a California summer camp. (Hqs. 3rd Inf. Div.) hhh 8. LEAVE</note>
				<note xml:id="q-944d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="21">One unfavorable comment was made in the mails, from a Lieutenant, (File No. 168) as follows:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-954d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="22">"Since being in Africa, I've had one 12 hour pass and the pass I had the other night for 5 hours. I could hardly enjoy these two occasions thinking of the cross examination and red tape we have to go through." (Hq. Co. 3rd Bn. 66th A. R. 2nd Arm. Div) hhh 9. QUARTERS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-964d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="23">Favorable 50%; unfavorable 50%. Although billeted at an hotel, which ho claims is a good one, a Major (File No. 226) states that</note>
				<note xml:id="q-974d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="24">"Marsh bitten up by bed bugs." ( 6th Gen. Hosp.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-984d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="25">A Lieutenant, (File No. 266) claims there are no bathing facilities and,</note>
				<note xml:id="q-994d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="26">"I haven't had a decent bath since I left the states, I smell almost as bad as the natives." (Btry. D 533 C. A.) hhh 10. POLITICS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9a4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="27">No comments. hhh 11. NEWS AND PROPOGANDA</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9b4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="28">Favorable comments 66; unfavorable 34%. Discussing this subject, with particular reference to German Broadcasting Stations sending out news and propaganda in English, the following comments were made:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9c4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="29">(File No. 181) "I get a kick from the German propaganda. They invite us over. Just put a note of surrender in your left hand pocket and walk up to their front lines and they will take very good care of us. Ha Ha. ....They try to make us lonely and discussed and it works just opposite." (345th Ser. Sq. 332na Ser. Gr.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9d4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="30">Comments regarding German broadcasts were that the boys take it as a comedy half hour. However, they do listen to Berlin, because they have good American music. hhh 12. CHURCH AND RELIGION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9e4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="31">Favorable comments 50%; unfavorable 50%. The unfavorable comment was to the effect that( File No. 157) "Downstairs the Catholics are praying, we don't have a priest but we are saying prayers anyway." (2nd Aux. Sug. Unit) One writer describes the spirit of the men in the church services held out in the open, as wonderful. hhh 13. HOME AFFAIRS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-9f4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="32">Repeated unfavorable comments concerning safe arrival cards are made to the folk at home. Every comment relates to a "breach of faith" and has done more to make the men lose confidence than any other thing. The comments long these lines, can be expressed in the words of one writer, (File No. 275) as follows:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a04d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="33">" I fear that our safe arrival cards have never been sent as promised. To me that was a terrible breach of faith." (433rd C. A.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a14d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="34">A corporal in writing to his family, (File No. 216) states-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a24d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="35">" The whole sqdn. is plenty burnt up because the folks never received safe arrival cards." (Hq. let A. D. Wing) hhh 14. RELATIONS WITH CIVILIAN POPULATION</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a34d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="36">Favorable comments 40%; unfavorable 60%. The soldiers complain of stealing of things by the crabs, and it is often stated, "they will steal anything that they can get their hands on". In this connection the following was found in a letter, (File No. 222)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a44d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="37">"One of the guys in Co. B shot a 10 yr. old Arab kid in the thigh today for stealing a suit of fatigue clothes off the line." (Co. C, 562nd S.A.W. Bn. Sep. Spec.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a54d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="38">The favorable comments concerned the fact that the stores in the cities have more to sell and that the people are friendlier. hhh 15. RELATIONS WITH ALLIED TROOPS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a64d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="39">No comments under this heading. hhh 16. CENSORSHIP</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a74d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="40">Favorable 80%, unfavorable 20%. There seems to be a definite trend toward abiding by censorship rules and regulations and many can understand the reason behind it, even going so far as to caution their correspondents to be careful. Some, however, believe that censorship is the cause for the delay in receipt in the United States of the mails. (File No. 161) is explicit upon this point:-</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a84d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="41">"I didn't write for the past three days because they don't censor the mail as they should. They hold it around for about 5 days, then they sensor it and mail it out." ( Hq. Co. 756 Tank Bn.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-a94d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="42">Some complain that the censors abuse the right of censorship, while others guess that there must be a reason for it. Many state that it is dif­ficult to write interesting letters without running afoul of censorship, but then go on to understand that they realize the necessity of censorship. hhh 17. GENERAL COMPLAINTS</note>
				<note xml:id="q-aa4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="43">Beside the general complaint of safe arrival cards mentioned under items 13, Home affairs, the general complaints can be put into the following categories:- Shortage of stamps at Post Offices Difficulty in obtaining money orders. 80% complaints. (Pile No. 180)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ab4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="44">"I am getting tired of carrying so much money around. Hope I can get some (money orders) soon." (1st Bn. 15th Inf.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ac4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="45">In connection with the latter complaint, many are buying bonds solely for the purpose of having same cashed after the required period, at home, since it is difficult to obtain money orders.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ad4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="46">Complaints have been made about the way things are run by superior officers, and many desire to be transferred to other outfits, in view of this. By reference, the writers maintain that politics is being played so far as promotions are concerned, A Lieutenant (File No. 246) writes:</note>
				<note xml:id="q-ae4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="47">" There hasn't been a promotion yet, but all the other units around here are getting them. I think we are getting a Royal American screwing." ( 6th Port Hq.)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-af4d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="48">Facilities for washing clothes and laundry facilities are still unavailable to many and those who are compelled to do their own laundry complain that it must be done in cold water. One interesting complaint is about the lack of African campaign ribbons, which have been given to other outfits.(File No. 197)</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b04d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="49">"Do we get our African campaign ribbons with the one star on it for the battle (first wave that attacked) or the overseas ribbon? Yet, every outfit, spanking brand new catches up with us decorated like Beau Geste." ( 92 Fighter Sq.) One complaint concerned the lack of Chaplains and was written by a Lieutenant (File No. 207) whose address is 21st Bn. 2nd Repl. Depot) hhh 18. GENERAL</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b14d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="50">The correspondence as a whole shows that the men are in fine spirits a definite contributing factor toward this being the recreational activities.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b24d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="51">Complaints are again made about the increased cost of living, one writer stating that he paid 20 cents to have a towel washed that cost him 29 cents. The men here have learned plenty of the "black market", and the information adduced in the letters shows, because of the prices quoted, that the black market is being furnished in part from G. I. equipment. American cigarettes sell on the black market for $2.00 to $3.00, thus giving an excellent margin of profit to anyone who might care to sell cigarettes. Many are approached with offers to sell shoe polish, G.I. trousers, etc. Whether or not the people approached have attempted to sell is not revealed in the communications.</note>
				<note xml:id="q-b34d7fbc-9e9d-e411-b1ae-00155df55c12" type="reporttext" n="52">Compliments are heaped upon the Red Cross for the splendid work they are doing.</note>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>