<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 132</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-d0278357-01dd-4f83-8215-a338a5e14593</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-fd548a10-b041-4bd2-81f9-2132db7d4e37</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-bc805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflecting</note>
      <u xml:id="q-bd805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">I left school at
				eighteen and joined the W.R.N.S I visited Gibraltar, Germany, Hongkong and Cyprus
				and served at least in each port. It was a great life. By the time I was 27 I was a
				captain. After serving 10 <sic>years</sic><corr>years'</corr> service left to concentrate on my family and
				personal side of life. With twins it was a lot coping but I managed. I missed the
				service it was so friendly and so many different jobs to do you couldn’t get
				bored.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-be805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I managed to get
				a part-time job when the children started school but when they got older I worked
				full time and got a good job as an <sic>acocuntant</sic><corr>accountant</corr> for a shop. The training in the
				W.R.N.S had come in handy.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-bf805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">The children left
				school with a handful of O and A levels and a journalist.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c0805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">We had a family
				reunion on my 25th wedding <sic>aniversary</sic><corr>anniversary</corr>. I was 47 my husband 49. We both carried on
				with our jobs. I helped to run a youth club and my husband Mark ran an athletic
				club. One of the girls got married to a doctor at the same hospital as she worked.
				It was just a family affair. When the kids left home we looked around for a smaller
				more modern house. We ended up having one built.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c1805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">My husband
				started a firm off which did very well. Then one of the girls got the sack the the
				journalist. Her and her common law husband had an accident in their car nothing
				serious. The nurse had a boy then a girl. The other <sic>finaly</sic><corr>finally</corr> got married.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c2805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">I retired and
				became involved with the <sic>nursry</sic><corr>nursery</corr> school I did child minding. We had an extension
				built on at the back of our house.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c3805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">My husband
				retired through ill health and died shortly afterwards. I then got involved with the
				church.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>