<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 46</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-042871c2-14cc-4bae-99db-cc28ff7702a0</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-3b3a07dc-e59a-4a48-81a4-ade6e449cab5</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-387e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Long Ago</note>
      <u xml:id="q-397e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">
        <sic>Im</sic>
        <corr>I'm</corr> now knocking
				60, <sic>Im</sic><corr>I'm</corr> quite wealthy I haven’t had too many ups and downs and <sic>Ive</sic><corr>I've</corr> got quite a
				healthy sum of money. I left school when I was 16 and went straight into a job quite
				a good job in fact it was an apprentice motor mechanic, a recognised trade in that
				day. My first wages was £25.00 in which I gave my mother £7.00 for board, with the
				£18 I had left I put a deposit down for an electric Bass guitar, the guitar cost
				£335.25 and it was an excellent bass for the money. My wages were coming in every
				week and I had to make sacrifices such as going out and such like just to buy this
				bass. After about a year I had paid up the money and had a 100 watt amplifier given
				to me for Christmas. Time was going fast and I practised every single hour of my
				spare time.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-3a7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I was just coming
				up to 20 when I finished my apprenticeship as a motor mechanic. I became quite good
				on the bass and then was the first real breakthrough. I had decided to form a group
				calling it Wreackage. I went around <sic>Nite</sic><corr>night</corr> clubs and working men’s clubs looking for
				different talents on different instruments. I found a boy by the name of Kev
				Harrison and asked him if he would join my group and he said yes. Me on the bass and
				Kev on lead, a friend of Kevs tony played drums and had a good drum kit a Ludwig I
				think. We auditioned a boy called Roger who played Rhythm Guitar and Tony on drums.
				We instantly started to record songs and rehearse for rehearsals we used the old
				dockyard church where I was inspired for my first song I wrote called Broken
				down.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-3b7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">We also had
				<sic>learn’t</sic><corr>learnt</corr> some Queen, Quo, numbers and started off looking for booking. I got us two
				bookings over the Queen Phillipa and Kev got is one over the V.C. The very first
				nite over the Phillipa we had developed technical troubles with the P.A. system so
				we had to sing through the amps. The place was packed and everybody wanted more they
				cheered and cheered that night we got £50 to be shared out and with what we had left
				we spent on new <sic>gadgits</sic><corr>gadgets</corr> to make us more <sic>amasing</sic><corr>amazing</corr>. We were popular all over Sheppey
				and word got around {illegible} Kent and we were playing to huge crowds. One day
				Wreakage had an argument and we just split just out of the blue split the end of
				Wreakage the end of a cult. After the groups had split I had just forgot about
				playing bass and just went on with my normal occupation as a motor mechanic quite a
				nice job really.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>