<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 99</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-c01faa62-185b-4d3d-ba54-4a0316a90507</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-f46121bc-83b8-407b-8091-e9788781aa73</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-ac7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">“Reflections of the Years”</note>
      <u xml:id="q-ad7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">The only past
				time that I find pleasure in doing, is looking back at the past years of my life.
				Sometimes I find joy in my thoughts but of course there is always a tear to
				<sic>shread</sic><corr>share</corr>.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ae7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">Yes I left school
				about 1978 when I was 16. Yes I had my whole life in front of me, knowing that it
				was only then that I was really going to live. All I wanted to do then was to be
				considered as a “woman”, and I soon was.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-af7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">I got the job of
				working in the local supermarket, it only paid £26 a week, but I enjoyed that I was
				doing, and it was better <sic>then</sic><corr>than</corr> being at school or on the <sic>dolle</sic><corr>dole</corr>. I made lots of <sic>knew</sic><corr>new</corr>
				friends (girls and boys) and that was where I met my late husband Steve, we courted
				for two years and soon become married. We could only afford a flat at the time, and
				we was lucky to get that on the little island we decided to stay on the Island being
				as we both had our families here, and anyway there wasn’t anywhere we could afford
				to go, and Steve had a steady job as a labourer. I kept my job for about three years
				after we were married, that is until I fell for our first child, Paul. He was a fine
				little baby and we loved him dearly, but when there was three mouths to feed life
				became a little harder, the money didn’t go far and we missed the money that I used
				to bring in, but we got over the little crisis, Steve soon got another job and the
				baby grew up to be a healthy boy. I found it hard being with a wife and a mother and
				it seemed if the harsh realities of life was play a great part in our life. When
				Paul started school, more problems {illegible?} being as he hated school and was
				rebelling by <sic>causeing</sic><corr>causing</corr> trouble, and I can understand him <sic>hateing</sic><corr>hating</corr> school because when
				I was young school was my <sic>worse</sic><corr>worst</corr> enemy too. It <sic>begain</sic><corr>began</corr> to feel that our <sic>lifes</sic><corr>lives</corr> were
				drifting apart, Steve would go out nearly every night and left me in, this went on
				for nearly two years, and so I decided that it was best for us to separate but when
				Steve found out my intensions, he tried to {rejoin?} himself to being the perfect
				<sic>husbound</sic><corr>husband</corr>, so we stayed together until the day he died. As the years passed on we
				become the perfect family, and we soon passed our own home after fifteen years of
				married life. When Paul became nineteen he decided it was time for him to leave
				home, it was a bit shock to Steve and I, but we respected his wish and so he left
				and went up London. And we was alone once more, but we was happy enough. As the
				years passed on we <sic>begain</sic><corr>began</corr> to feel our ages, Steve especially and he couldn’t take
				becoming old and he turned to drink once more, and it was this that finally killed,
				well not drink itself, he was in a car accident and was killed instantly. The police
				report said “Death while under the influence of drink”</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b07f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">After <sic>Steves</sic><corr>Steve's</corr>
				death my life just seemed to come to a <sic>hault</sic><corr>halt</corr>, and I seriously considered killing
				myself, but I just didn’t have the gut to end my life in a few minutes, so I decided
				to wait until the good lord calls me himself to join my lost ones.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b17f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">My son visits me
				once every year with the girl who lives with, or you could say there married accept
				for a ring and an official certificate, but even that is just a duty visit on the
				poor old lady, he feels he owes me something, well I just smile and his good will,
				but nobody gives you that anymore without something in return. Yes that just my
				hobby looking back over the years while I’m waiting for the call of the Lord, and to
				be reunited with with the lost one’s which I earnt want to see. I’m not afraid of
				death just afraid of living on in the world today, just to be another statistic as
				far as the world is concerned.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>