<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 133</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-6758873d-8639-4131-ab2b-fdf2f3ffce07</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-8b9b6b0d-062a-493e-ad45-44f9516c2c57</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-c4805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-c5805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">My career began
				while I was still at school. I had thought for a long time, what I would <sic>liked</sic><corr>like</corr> to
				have done with my life. My appointment was made and I had to visit my careers
				officer, she was then going to try and decide on my career. I had already made up my
				mind. So she was no help at all. She asked me a few questions about the career which
				I wanted to lead. I told her the answer and that was that. She had been no much help
				at all. It lasted for about ten minutes which wasn’t hardly long enough to get a few
				questions and answers out. She told me the wage which I should earn, but this wasn’t
				exact. I more or less knew all this before I even entered her room. So that career
				interview <sic>didnt</sic><corr>didn't</corr> do me much good.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c6805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I think that the
				choices of subjects are chosen much too late. They should have been chosen at about
				12 years old. So the choice of career should come sooner. Another thing which I
				thought should have been done, was that the girls of the 5th form, also the boys,
				should have been taken round different jobs and try each job out to see which person
				is suited to which job.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c7805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">Special subjects
				should be brought into the time table, so each person can get qualifications for the
				jobs which they would like to do. My career had been successful, but I am now glad
				to retire into the relaxing life.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>