<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 49</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-b3d0b5d0-524f-45c6-8b99-7467eeccbf8c</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-024439a7-e9e1-4711-924c-e42ba0db0a2b</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u xml:id="q-547e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="1">An old man walked
				from his modern detached house, he didn’t bother to take his two year old family
				saloon, as the sun was brilliant on this certain August day. He was on his way to
				the corner shop, but as he stepped onto a zebra crossing a young learner
				motorcyclist of about 16 years old unwittingly knocked him over. The doctor said he
				was in a coma, but he was only dreaming of his life.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-557e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">He’d passed all
				six of his exams and was soon settled into a nice college at <sic>Chatam</sic><corr>Chatham</corr>, where he me a
				nice girl from a neighbouring college.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-567e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">At 18 he left
				college with an O.N.D. in building and soon got a job in an Estate Agency at
				Sheerness. He stayed at home for two years until he got a high position in the
				Surveying profession when he took out a <sic>morgage</sic><corr>mortgage</corr> on a small, but modern semi-detached
				house.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-577e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">He then went to
				live in this house with his girlfriend, future marriage partner.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-587e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">With two wages
				coming in this bank balance rose dramatically and the <sic>morgage</sic><corr>mortgage</corr> shrunk slowly but
				steadily. At 23 they married and in that same year he left the Estate <sic>agence</sic><corr>agency</corr> and
				joined an independent Chartered Surveyors firm which gave him an extra £30.00 a week
				extra. Soon they settled into a typical married life with a couple of kids, a small
				family car and a healthy bank balance. At 40 years old they moved to a detached
				house and brought a bigger car and then another. Soon the kids left home and at 53
				he realised his life long ambition, that is, to own a boat and take people out
				fishing, for a price of course. In other words a charter boat. At 65 years old he
				died after a collision with a young motorcyclist. His wife said he always wanted to
				die suddenly without any pain or any prolonged suffering beforehand.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>