<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 111</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-df844db8-74e3-4bc5-a906-02ad177b601a</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-ff4b45f5-aff4-49fc-9f57-bc09333a97b3</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-11805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">My Past</note>
      <u xml:id="q-12805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">As I got out the
				family photo album to show my daughters children, a few school photo’s caught my
				eye. They were of Zoe when she was 15. She looked just like me. Later when she had
				gone these photos were still on my mind, I sat down and thought about my past all
				the memories came flooding back. The good times, and the bad times, the tears and
				the laughter.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-13805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I remember the
				terrible time I had going through my exams, I used to throw a fit when my dad said I
				had to stay in and revise, and all my friends were going to the local disco. I tried
				all sorts of tricks to get out of it. But after my exams were over I had all the
				time in the world, and I was glad my dad made me stay in, because I know I <sic>tryed</sic><corr>tried</corr> my
				best in all my exams.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-14805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">Then there was my
				first interview, I made all sorts of excuses so I wouldn’t have to go. When I was at
				school I loved the idea of leaving but now I was literally shaking all over. But I
				got over it when I got there, and I quite enjoyed the interview, the man was very
				friendly. I got the job. I worked in a children’s home just as I had always wanted.
				I worked there for 3 years and then I changed to office work. Six months after I had
				been working there I left to get married, what a lovely white wedding I had and a
				lot of my school friends came; I was nearly 20years old when I got married. I worked
				at the office for another year and a half then I left to have my very first child.
				It was a girl called Jackie. In the next five year I had, had two more children.
				After Jackie I had a boy named Alan, he was named after my grandfather and then
				another girl named Zoe, Zoe was the youngest.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-15805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">After having Zoe
				we moved off of the Island and down to Dorset where we had a nice house. I had some
				relations down there.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-16805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">The children
				hated moving at first and so did I, I’ve never really liked moving, but I’d always
				liked the idea of moving down there, and now that my husband Mark had been offered
				the job, I thought we should take it.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-17805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">I <sic>cryed</sic><corr>cried</corr> my eyes
				out when we left as I was leaving all my old friends and old secret hiding places
				behind, but when I got to Dorset I made new friends and I loved it.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-18805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">When Jackie was
				19 she got married to Paul who was also 19. They bought a house not far from us.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-19805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">Then a year later
				Alan got married to Susan, he had known her since we first moved. They lived next
				door to each other.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-1a805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="10">The last one to
				get married was Zoe, I never thought she would get married, she’d never seemed the
				type.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-1b805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="11">Jackie had two
				children John and Donna.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-1c805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="12">Alan’s wife had
				three children two boys (twins) Terry and Tony and one girl called Heidi.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-1d805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="13">Jackie had just
				one little girl called Janey. She was 3 years old and was really beautiful.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-1e805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="14">As time went by
				I just seemed to get older and greyer everyday. I just wished I was young again,
				back at school having fun but instead, I just done the usual thing, collected
				pension got the shopping and the <sic>usuall</sic><corr>usual</corr> every day things. I didn’t really go out
				much.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-1f805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="15">The only thing I
				get enjoyment out of is having my children’s children round to play, to see them
				grow up the way mine children did, and the way my mother saw me grow up. If only I
				could start at the age of sixteen, be young again live my life having fun and
				enjoyment like I used to. But as people day you only live your life once make the
				most of it!</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>