<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 101</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-2312a4c0-7646-4645-83be-d36b158d3beb</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-719eb4c0-50ef-4454-8471-fffa3ae983b4</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-bf7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">My Past</note>
      <u xml:id="q-c07f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">Looking out of
				the window at the children walking down the street makes me remember my past years
				especially from leaving school. After spending two years on a <sic>cermercial</sic><corr>commercial</corr> course at
				school I finally left 1980 it must have been yes. I was thrilled to bits one morning
				to find they had accepted me in a firm a few yards down the road I was to be a
				junior secretary/clerk I’ve never ran down the passage so fast. The first day was
				the best getting to <sic>no</sic><corr>know</corr> all the different people and places to go. I’d always wanted
				to work there and finally to my amazement after being there for two years I finally
				got promotion to personal secretary/clerk to the general manager. That Christmas the
				lads from the tool makers yard came to our party that’s where I met Keith my husband
				he was so nice and kind. We went out together for about two years and then got
				engaged. We were the happiest couple any one could imagine we started to put some
				money away for when we got married then finally the big day came May 13th 1985 we
				got married I was in a lovely white long dress with a headdress Minster Abbey at
				3.00 we had professional photographs the bridesmaids (6 of them) they were a
				beautiful shade of orange. 1986 I left my works to work at an estate agency personal
				manager’s secretary it was a big estate agencies.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c17f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">About a year
				after this my sister finally got engaged and within a year she was married. I’ll
				always remember it because it was the middle of Autumn the colours were so <sic>preaty</sic><corr>pretty</corr>.
				1990 we packed our jobs in and with the children Cheryl 1 year old Trisham 3 years
				old we finally got the house of our dreams a big house with a big garden. Keith and
				I went into our own <sic>bussness</sic><corr>business</corr> and it had prospered ever since we are both near to
				retirement the children have left and got children but I’m happy for them. I’ve been
				married thirty seven years and we are still the happiest people around. The children
				grew up very quickly and know have children. Keith’s and mine grandchildren Paul and
				Claire we are proud of them.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c27f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">There they go
				down the street they look like Paul and Claire. “Oh well Keith make a cup of tea
				love”</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>