<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 36</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-d43277f3-79ba-4622-92c7-2cc65faa297a</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-57dbc607-74d7-42c4-a0b8-362eeb6f7647</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u xml:id="q-117e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="1">I wanted to get
				an apprenticeship with a firm but I failed the interviews. I fortunately managed to
				get a job as a landscaper with a firm whose manager was the brother of a woman down
				the street I used to <sic>babby</sic><corr>baby</corr> sit for. It was quite skilled worked and I enjoyed it. It
				didn’t offer security but I was paid quite well. Landscaping was an expensive job of
				which more and more people done themselves. I got quite good at it and was promoted
				to a higher <sic>possision</sic><corr>position</corr>. It was got fun working as a landscaper, you met people and
				you travelled. In 1981 I managed to by an old car and a house. My car brought me a
				<sic>lots</sic><corr>lot</corr> of advantages. I could get about much <sic>easilier</sic><corr>easier</corr> which was a big help. I worked
				my way up to <sic>assiting</sic><corr>assisting</corr> manager which was a bit of a break. This offered a bit more
				security and more money. I married in 1987 and settled down. It was a bit of a
				struggle but we didn’t live badly. I fathered my first child in 1989 and second in
				1991. I did not have any more children than this because every family was only
				allowed two children because of the population problems. Because many people were
				getting paid more they wanted landscaped gardens, and so we were getting more
				business than ever which was very good.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-127e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">My son and
				daughter grow up very quickly and my son the eldest managed to get an <sic>apprentiship</sic><corr>apprenticeship</corr>
				with a firm. The school leaving age was now eighteen and the year was 2007. when he
				began his apprenticeship. I retired at 58 and lived on the savings and pension. I
				went fishing most days and they were the most enjoyable days of my life.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-137e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I am <sic>to</sic><corr>too</corr>old now
				to go fishing and I just sit indoors waiting.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>