<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 103</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-ba2a0f0c-c9f3-4c3f-b880-7261aebcfd75</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-401b4691-501f-4cc2-81fe-42ae8deb676a</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-c97f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-ca7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">I sat looking out
				of my living room window and I could see young girls of about sixteen going past my
				window, the fashion has really changed from when I was that age. I am now sixty.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-cb7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">As I thought of
				this I began to think back to the days when I was that age. I had just finished my
				exams and I was looking around for a well paid secure job. I can remember keep going
				into the job centre to see if any new jobs had been put out. One day I saw one that
				I thought was the ideal job for me, it was well paid and it sounded quite
				interesting, so I rung up the personal officer and <sic>a</sic><corr>the</corr> interview was arranged. I went
				for the interview and I got the job.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-cc7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">Once I had
				started the job I thought I’d be there for life. The next important thing that
				happened in my life was that I passed my driving test and so that <sic>meat</sic><corr>meant</corr> I could start
				looking for a new job in London or somewhere like that so that’s what I started to
				do. I looked at all the advertisements for jobs and flats in London.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-cd7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">In the end I
				managed to get a good well paid job and a nice cosy little flat. I used to go out
				about 3 or 4 nights a <sic>weeks</sic><corr>week</corr> with friends to a disco.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ce7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">When I was 24 I
				got married and moved into a fairly big bungalow just outside London, but I still
				carried on in my old job in London.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-cf7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">After about 2
				years left work to have a baby. I stayed at home to look after my child until she
				was 8 years old then I went out and got a job.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-d07f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">carried on
				working all the time my daughter was growing up, then it was her turn to get
				married. After that nothing much seemed to happen until about 2 years ago when my
				daughter had a little daughter of her own. Now I have her running around the house a
				lot and it reminds me of when my daughter was a baby.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>