<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 142</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-02ec6b91-6cff-4330-91dd-f85c4d9bbb97</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-eb667233-d3a9-4a21-af62-19c8ba6b7cc1</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-07815d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflection</note>
      <u xml:id="q-08815d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">Reflecting back
				on my life to me the best time was that when I was at school. I now wish I had
				studied harder than I did. I stayed on for a year <sic>ay</sic><corr>at</corr> my last school and left at the
				age of 17. Sometimes I wonder why I took that extra year, look at the job I ended up
				with, a shop assistant in Woolworths. I worked there for about twenty years going
				through the near on same routine day in and day out except for the odd exceptional
				days when there was the Christmas rush. At first I was poorly <sic>payed</sic><corr>paid</corr>, I earned £18 a
				week. But slowly the wage in my pay packet went up and the most I ever earned there
				was £38. I left the job once because of having the children but kindly a place was
				kept for me.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-09815d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I married at 23
				and have two children, <sic>we</sic><corr>who</corr> are now grown up and have children of their own. When I
				was younger I used to hate the idea of becoming old and becoming a grandmother but
				to look at my grandchildren now it seems all <sic>worth while</sic><corr>worthwile</corr>.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-0a815d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">At 38 I left
				Woolworths for good to be a housewife and to look after my second child. There are
				ten years between my first and second child. At the age of 50 I got a part time job
				of working in a small shop which I worked in full time 2 years later. The job <sic>payed</sic><corr>paid</corr>
				fair. I found this job more boring than the first, there were less customers, but
				those who did come to shop there I got to know fairly well, unlike the job at
				Woolworths where you hardly got to know anyone, but you hardly had the time to
				usually.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-0b815d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">At 60 I retired.
				Old age seemed to be quiet and things that needed to be done were done with time to
				spare. I always wonder why I moaned about school because I had longer holiday time
				then and more time to enjoy myself.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>