<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 67</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-abc773d8-7c71-48c7-9c83-90976e5033d7</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-ae8189e4-89f9-4316-a9b9-c38cdf6ff642</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u xml:id="q-c07e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="1">I remember it like it was yesterday. I was sixteen at the time and just leaving school. I sent away for an apprenticeship with the Royal Navy, and got in. When I left school in June. I went straight into the Navy doing an apprenticeship as an electrician. At the age of 19 I had finished my apprenticeship and went aboard a ship. Here I served what was left of my time and when I left at 25, I’d travelled all round the world. At the Age of 26, I had got me self a place in London. At the age of 27 I would get myself a motorbike and {toured?} the country. At the age of about 30 I’d settle down and have got married. I’d got myself a job as electrician by now and had a steady job. Then then moved to another country. We lived in United States for quite a time before we moved back to England. I was thirty three when we had our first child, and it was a boy. At the age of forty we all moved back to England and I was forty. My wife died when I was fifty and I went into an old people’s home. I remarried at the age of fifty five and we both lived in a flat in London. We moved out when I was fifty nine and moved into my old people’s home because of my wife’s bad health, where we are still living at the age of 60.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>