<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 137</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-ad77d032-518d-4f0a-82a0-7ad80074b21a</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-0487c967-e35c-4292-aad1-323c2efc9201</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-de805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflecting</note>
      <u xml:id="q-df805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">When I left
				school at 16 I felt as though I was now grown up and I could leave the secruity of
				school and venture into the world outside.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e0805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">What I wanted was
				to look after children either in a home or at home. But this was slightly harder
				than I had thought it would be. I had the choice of either going to college and
				doing a course or going to work until I was eighteen and then trying for a job.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e1805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">Of course I took
				what I thought was the easy way out and took a job in a coop supermarket until I was
				eighteen and this was where the fun and games started.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e2805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">The career’s
				officer was the first person I saw. She gave me form to fill in and said I would
				hear from her. Finally a letter came asking if I would like an interview at a
				National Children’s Home as a <sic>Nursey</sic><corr>Nursery</corr> Nurse. But when the day came they asked me what
				training I had had which of course was none so I was turned down. This went on I had
				about 4 interviews but in all of them they asked the same thing “have you had any
				training”. In the end I gave up. No job to go to on the dole!! Because I had worked
				for over six months I was picking up twenty-five a week unemployment benefit but
				this wasn’t what I wanted.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e3805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">I had thought,
				while I was at school that it was easy, getting a job. I soon found out it wasn’t. I
				still remember sitting in my lessons not doing anything ‘thinking why bother’ but I
				wished I had.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e4805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">The teachers
				weren’t really all that helpful not strict enough.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e5805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">After two or
				three jobs in shops I saw the job advertised “child help needed. No Qualifications
				Necessary. Good with children” I applied and got the I have not looked back since.
				Altogether I have looked after kids of 3 different family’s watched them grow up. It
				was what I wanted I had fulfilled my ambition. I got married at 33 and had 2
				children of my own one boy and one girl.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e6805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">I thought that
				would have been the end of my career but No, I still looked after family’s until I
				was 58 and it was then I decided to retire to enjoy my grandchildren.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e7805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="10">Now thinking
				back, I was lucky really to succeed in the job I wanted. If I had taken the
				opportunity of going college I would have done much better. You don’t know how hard
				it is until you go out into the world. I think children should be taught more about
				jobs and working so they what to expect so they don’t end up like a lot of people
				unemployed!!</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>