<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 19</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-164d019a-63ee-4416-b83b-6adf7089f24f</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-a798c601-54df-47ee-8b9b-d4fdf80ea14d</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u xml:id="q-bb7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="1">After leaving
				school at 16 years old my first employment was in a factory. This employment was
				only found through four months hard slog looking for a job, even then I was not
				happy in the job I did. The factory was small situated on the island making clothes
				and other garments. To a <sic>surtain</sic><corr>certain</corr> extent, with school behind me I was happy to have
				“freedom”. I would work from eight thirty in the morning to five thirty at night,
				travelling back home to my <sic>parents</sic><corr>parents'</corr> house on the no.9 bus which ran from {?} the
				factory to Minister. Every Friday I would receive my wage package containing £23.50
				net; £25.50 gross. The work was not physically demanding or hard but I know if I did
				not turn up on time or not even at all I would pay financially or even pay with the
				sack, at that at the time I could not afford. The car my parents were going to buy
				me needed insurance, tax and some minor extras which all cost money. At the age of
				18 I decided that the money I was earning could not support me fully. By Now I had a
				car, out nearly every night drinking and my wage was only £35. I found employment
				through the job centre, It was again factory work but it offered me better working
				conditions and hours. The factory was again on the Island, just outside Leysdown
				producing Japanese car <sic>componants</sic><corr>components</corr>, for the cars which were being imported as now
				British Leyland had been liquidised six months ago. I still lived at home but
				thought about moving in to a flat with a girl friend but financially I found that
				unsuitable as the landlord was asking £30 per week rent, too much for me. By now my
				parents had begun to question me about moving out of their house (father mainly) and
				thinking of settling down finding some property and getting married of course. If I
				had had it my way I would <sic>of</sic><corr>have</corr> never got married but this I did at the age of 27.
				After several unsettled jobs and several bad decisions, the one which landed me in
				court after driving with two illegal tyres of the front of my car for example. My
				wife was of a middle class family, her parents being mildly well off. She found
				employment quite all along easily with her seven ‘o’ levels. The marriage did not
				last too long though, we had no children and an agreeable divorce, on both sides,
				came as a relief.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-bc7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">After looking
				back at the past I had realised that now at 30 years old I had {done} bloody sod all
				with my life and had no goal. This is when I decided to return to night school and
				get some qualifications. Yes! Little pieces of paper which portrayed my
				intelligence, flexibility and responsibility to an employer. I got my qualification
				and even at the age of 31 decided to make a career out of engineering, electrical
				that is. I worked not in a factory but in one of the new large hydro-electric
				powerstations in Scotland, all this new employment was created by the uses of sea
				power. My job was comfortable. I was also happy in what I was doing. I then slowly
				began to climb up the ladder eventually becoming head of the department and then
				director. All this stayed the same until I retired, a happily married man, married
				to the <sic>secon</sic><corr>second</corr> wife at 35. I had money in my pocket and my own property not to say one
				of the more luxurious car <sic>moddles</sic><corr>models</corr> produced in Russia. I thought about those years
				between the age of 16 and 30 and shamed my self because how I had wasted them. All
				that I did <sic>achive</sic><corr>achieve</corr> was done after school hours when nearly it could have been
				done.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-bd7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">Please tell me
				why I did not do it? Is it me, society or is it just the way life goes?</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>