<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 107</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-d7686056-a6d2-4f98-9c65-1acaa176c46c</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-4c53f265-6944-4acf-b92a-eafb7ae58ee5</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-ef7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-f07f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">As I sit here
				<sic>memorys</sic><corr>memories</corr> of my younger days flash through my head I look back at my life from when I
				was sixteen. I left school all set to go to <sic>colledge</sic><corr>college</corr> for a two year course in
				hairdressing and beauty work. Though two years past very quickly and were the start
				of my adult life. In though two years I found out just what it was like to live on
				your own. After I had come out of <sic>colledge</sic><corr>college</corr> I had found a job in a quite busy salon
				on the out-skirts of London. I lived away from home but I visited my parents most
				weekends. I worked in the same salon for about four years I entered lots of
				hairdressing competition and found those help me along in my profession. By this
				time I was twenty-two and thinking about settling down. I had made quite a lot of
				friends, but had still kept in touch with my friends on the island. I had found it
				hard at eighteen to have no money but in the long run hairdressing paid off.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f17f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">One day my life
				was completely changed the man I knew I was going to marry walk in to it. He came
				into the shop to have his hair cut. We naturally got talking and from then on it was
				all go. We got on very well and soon got engaged. We were engaged for two years and
				then decided to get married. By this time I was twenty-five. We had saved enough to
				put a deposit on a house. My husband worked as an engineer. We lived quite near to
				where I worked, so it was only a little way into London. We did have some wonderful
				nights out together. I gave up my work when I was expecting our first child. It was
				a boy and we named it after Chris, my husband.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f27f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">My life had
				changed again now we didn’t go out very much only once a week together. My time was
				consumed with our baby boy. As soon as Chris started school I started my profession
				again, but instead of in the shop I did it at home. I used to make a bomb doing it
				at home. We had soon saved up enough money to move to a larger home. I was also now
				expecting our second child at the age of thirty-two. Our second child was a girl and
				we called it Marie. We decided this was our last child, one of each was enough.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f37f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">The house we
				moved to was a three bedroomed semi-detached house. It was first large enough for
				our family. Chris grew up very fast so did Marie. The years flew by. Soon Chris was
				fifteen and Marie was ten. By now I was forty-seven. It was strange to see Chris
				take an interest in girls and start bringing them home. I knew that soon both Chris
				and Marie would just start their life while mine was nearly over. But I had lead a
				full life and did not regret getting old.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>