<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 100</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-2abaf66d-0f13-43bc-8904-0f897ae824b2</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-13a87b27-1968-4db3-8730-9af3a48b4e3a</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-b27f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">My Past</note>
      <u xml:id="q-b37f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">My grandchildren
				were playing in the garden I looked out the windows, they were playing games I once
				had played. I sat in the chair and thought my last day at school. I left May 26th
				1978 at 16. I joined Toyota GB LtD as a junior office clerk on Tuesday 30th May I
				can remember sitting at home scared stiff up at half past 6 so not to overlay (did
				not start till nine, with a five minute walk). In 1980 had been promoted to an
				clerk, doing wages etc. That year I also met Jim at the works party (Christmas).</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b47f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">Enjoyed the work
				more and more, now girls had joined us, I had to take them under my wing I knew how
				they felt.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b57f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">1981 Brother
				married I was chief bridesmaid I also got engaged. I applied for office secretary
				but turned down.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b67f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">1982 my 21st had
				a large party and cried when my mum gave me a silver watch from her and dad, I cried
				again (with happiness when Jim proposed I accepted.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b77f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">The first few
				months of married life were hard, our social life was virtually nil, as we saved as
				much as we <sic>good</sic><corr>could</corr>. The day of the wedding was 14 May 1982. We stayed on the Island at
				Rushenden but Jim changed his job. 1984 I was a mother I can remember my mums face
				when I told her she was going to be a nanny. It was spoilt by her and dad a lot.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b87f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">1986 I was a
				mother again I had left work for the first child but never gone back, told I could
				go if I wanted to.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b97f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">I waited till the
				children started school. Jamie the first child cried he didn’t want to leave, so
				when it was Claire’s turn I was prepared, only she didn’t and went off happily.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ba7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">1984 Also was mum
				and dads 25th wedding anniversary, sister-in-law and I had prepared a huge tea for
				them and a <sic>presant</sic><corr>present</corr>.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-bb7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="10">1986 started back
				to work to fit in times with the children.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-bc7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="11">The children
				grew up quickly and I can remember their first words still.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-bd7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="12">1990 it was our
				<sic>eigth</sic><corr>eighth</corr> anniversary and the children brought us breakfast in bed cold coffee and bread
				and marmalade (I smile as I sit I my chair) that first Christmas was hectic.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-be7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="13">The year 2000
				dad died of a heart attack it broke my heart and mums, she came to live with us but
				a few years later she died as she was to lonely on her own and couldn’t live without
				him (As I remember this tears come into my eyes but the children come in and put my
				mind at rest).</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>