<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 57</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-7d75dccd-41ac-4cd9-87c8-d32168c30d6c</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-16a816e2-eb01-4396-95e9-c910a71a50e3</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-727e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflecting</note>
      <u xml:id="q-737e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">It was in the
				year 1978 that I left school. I was 16 years of age and had my job already lined up.
				I was going in to the <sic>navey</sic><corr>navy</corr> as a junior <sic>seamon</sic><corr>seaman</corr> operator 2nd class. The training went
				on in barrack until I was 16 ½ we had had six months training on land and now was
				our chance to go to sea on the training ships for a further 1 ½ years.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-747e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">It was after this
				2 years that I was made a <sic>seamon</sic><corr>seaman</corr> operator 1st class. I had signed up for 12 years
				and had ten left to serve. It was a good life and four years later I got my first
				real promotion. I had in my four years <sic>traveled</sic><corr>travelled</corr> to a great number of places and was
				about due to set off for a six month stay in America. When I <sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr> a distressing
				letter from my mum.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-757e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">She had written
				to tell me that my younger brother mark had been knocked down by a bus and, was
				lying in hospital in a coma. I went to my captain and asked his <sic>permition</sic><corr>permission</corr> for a time
				off on leave. This was granted and the next day I was on the train home. My brother
				took six days to come out of his <sic>come</sic><corr>coma</corr> and I had to fly out to America and pick up my
				ship from there. The next few years went past quite <sic>uninterupted</sic><corr>uninterrupted</corr> and, I got another
				promotion I had one year left to serve and decided there and then that I would sign
				up for the next twelve and get my <sic>pention</sic><corr>pension</corr>.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-767e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">Between finishing
				my first period at work and signing for my next I had two month <sic>of</sic><corr>off</corr>. In this time I
				went around and visited all my old friends. One of <sic>whome</sic><corr>whom</corr> was called Stephen. During
				this time we went fishing a great deal and, met some of our old girl friends. It was
				while we were in a pub that we decided when I finished my next stint in the <sic>Navey</sic><corr>Navy</corr> we
				would get together and buy ourselves a charter boat. There was to be no stopping
				this plan, and while I was a way Stephen got every thing settled.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-777e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">Two years into my
				stint I got married to a lass called Jill. We decided the best thing we could do was
				get ourselves a house with a mortgage no that at least we would have a place of our
				own. We did not find this too hard as over the years I had saved quite a today
				sum.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-787e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">This arrangement
				went on very well for a good few years we had now got two children both boys with
				only two years to go until I came out of the <sic>navey</sic><corr>navy</corr>. I heard from Stephen that he had
				found the right <sic>boar</sic><corr>buyer</corr> and paid the down payment.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-797e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">After this news
				came to me my last two years seemed to fly past. Within no time atall I was out. I
				had been given a <sic>pention</sic><corr>pension</corr> of thirty pounds a week and a lump sum of eight thousand to
				get my self started on. It was hard work for the first could of years and this money
				was needed.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-7a7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">We had to make a
				good name for ourselves as there was a lot of competition in this field. As we had
				both been keen fishermen all of our lives we did not find this two hard and in our
				firth year we had no difficulties at all in filling our <sic>timtables</sic><corr>timetables</corr>. This life was to
				suit me for the next thirty years of my life and now at the age of sixty eight I
				have retired still a fit man.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>