<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 95</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-652b2ca4-4e32-4e96-854b-5d912cbcaa17</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-1cd61208-048f-4eb6-bc2a-0b7f8b8719a1</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-897f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">My Past</note>
      <u xml:id="q-8a7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">Over the past
				fifty years:- when I was sixteen years of age. I had just left school on the 16th
				May 1978. I signed on the dole and the 17th May because I was not going to start
				work until the 31st May. My first job was in a fuse factory I never thought that I
				would see the day when I would work in a factory. I had to catch the 8 minutes past
				seven train to be at work for 8 o clock. Then I had to work my hardest until Quarter
				past five. That was Mondays to Thursdays. I used to look forward to Fridays in those
				days, because I got a good wage, and we left work at 1.00pm.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-8b7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">On the 5th August
				1978 I left home and I went to live with my nan in Northamptonshire. It was a big
				step to take at the time, but <sic>its</sic><corr>it's</corr> what I wanted to do. I had a job there waiting for
				me in a shoe factory, there I became a sprayer I worked with an old friend whose
				name was Karen. We used to have a good laugh in the spraying room, and we got on
				ever so well together. I worked there for four years until I was almost 21. Then I
				did a good days work. I got married without any doubts. I married an old boyfriend
				who I had liked from my sweet old age 16. His name is Mick and he is still very good
				to me. He has never said a word out of place, I moved to his hometown which is in
				Corby. And we were very happy and we still are now. We used to go on holidays a lot
				when we were first married, we went to Spain and Italy and travelled most of the
				world. That went on for two years. Then I found out I was having a baby when I was
				23, Mick and I were both very pleased about this, but we knew we would not be able
				to go on holidays and go out at night as much as we used too.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-8c7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">Well I had my
				baby boy and I called it after his father Michael. He was a very nice baby and I had
				no trouble with him at all. Mick and I took him to Paris with us when he was only 9
				months old. We didn’t think it would be a relaxing holiday not with the baby along
				with us, but we had a lovely time and we enjoyed <sic>ourselfs</sic><corr>ourselves</corr> very much.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-8d7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">When Michael was
				two years old I found out I was having another baby. So I had to stop in and rest a
				lot. While Mick used to go out and enjoy himself with his mates. But it didn’t
				bother me as much as it did when I was having Michael. Anyway 9 months later I had a
				baby girl. I named it Sylvana after my mum. She was a lovely baby also. She only
				weighed 5lb when I had her I was a bit worried at first but she was alright.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-8e7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">Eight years later
				my two children were both at school and enjoying it <sic>two</sic><corr>too</corr>. So I thought I should go
				out and work again. So I went out looking for a job and I managed to get one in
				Marks and Spencers as a shop Assistant. It was a big change from working in a
				factory. And I was not as young now I was almost 34 years old. But I’m glad to say I
				didn’t feel it at all.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-8f7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">My husband Mick
				had an accident in his car. I was at work and the phone rang to tell me to go home
				quickly. So I went and Mick was already taken into hospital. He had crashed into the
				back of a lorry coming back from London where he had just been to his Aunty’s
				funeral. I phoned him in Northampton Hospital. I had my car then so I went all the
				way over to Northampton. Very upset of what I might see when I got there. But things
				were not so bad. He had a broken leg and head injuries. So he stayed in hospital for
				two months. He came out of hospital on my 35th birthday. We got a babysitter in and
				we went out celebrating. It was good to have him home again.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-907f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">Ten years had
				gone by and my children had grown up so fast. Michael was now 22 years old and
				engaged to a lovely girl who is now his wife and I am a Grandmother at the age of 45
				years of age. My daughter Sylvana has just got engaged and she will be married in
				two years time. She is now 20 years of age. My husband Mick bought a new car. It’s
				what he always wanted a Ford Mustang. It was a lovely car. We used to go on holiday
				a lot with my son and his wife and my daughter and her boyfriend Tommy. As the years
				went by I had lost my mum and dad, my nans and granddads. It was very rare I saw my
				two brother because they lived abroad in Italy with <sic>there</sic><corr>their</corr> Italian wives and
				children.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-917f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">Mick and I had
				both turned 60 years of age. And we look back now thinking of the happy years we had
				had together, not knowing how much longer we are going to live. Our daughter and son
				were both married and we were grandparents to eight children. We used to spoil all
				of them. And they used to stay at our big bungalow at the weekends they never
				missed. While there mums and dads went out enjoying <sic>thereselfs</sic><corr>thereselves</corr> like Mick and I used
				to do. Yes we’ve had some good memories to look back on and both of our children
				have been very good right from the time they were <sic>baby’s</sic><corr>babies</corr>. We’ve led a good life
				together and I hope my children and their children lead good life also as Mick and I
				have done.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-927f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="10">Mrs Kay
				Bullimoore writing from the past of her good memorial life.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>