<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 108</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-34fb6bbc-39fc-4eba-8f63-65106b8a20c7</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-7a59176b-def2-4113-bdba-c1500364a053</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-f47f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Looking at my Past Years</note>
      <u xml:id="q-f57f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">The years seem to
				have gone by so quickly it only seems like yesterday that I got my first job.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f67f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I’m sixty now and
				it’s the year 2028. I got my first job after I’d taken a trainee course as a cook in
				1980. I had decided to do this after I had received the results of my exams. That
				was August 1978. I was so excited the day my results popped through the letterbox.
				All my hopes had come true I had obtained the grades I had wished. It was September
				1978 that I started the trainee course. I was looking forward to being a cook. But
				there was one problem I had to have lodgings off the island because there was no
				sort of work that I wanted to do.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f77f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">After some
				thought I decided to train at hospital in Maidstone. I enjoyed the training period
				very much so much in fact that I wanted to make a career of being an assistant cook
				and hopefully moving up to head cook. After two years as a trainee there as
				assistant I eventually had my dream come true in 1984 I became head cook.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f87f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">It was while I
				was working that I met my future husband David. We met in 1985 at a Christmas dance
				that was being held at his works. David was a marine engineer, he had obtained very
				good qualifications at school so he was to try for the job he wanted straight after
				he’d left school.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f97f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">Soon after the
				party we got engaged, I think it was Boxing Day. Then in 1987 we were married. It
				was 5th August, a day before my birthday, I’ll never forget it. I had a beautiful
				white dress and veil. I’ve still got it. There were 200 guests at the reception,
				most were David’s relations as I haven’t got many.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-fa7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">In 1992 we had
				the first of our two children, it was a very wet night in January, it had been
				training all day non-stop. Peter was born 10 o’clock in the evening. It wasn’t a
				difficult birth though I was sad because I wanted twins, everyone thought I
				would.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-fb7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">In 1994 I had are
				second child Rachel, she was born in May</u>
      <u xml:id="q-fc7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">We celebrated the
				turn of the century by having a party. We invited our relations and friends, there
				was dancing, eating and merriment. The party went well into the morning. We thought
				the year was going to be a good year for us but it wasn’t. We had financial trouble.
				We had to sell <sic>our</sic><corr>out</corr> and buy a smaller one. We also sold our car, we missed having
				that. We were glad when the year was over and we had managed to pull through. Every
				thing went well for the next five years until 2007. That year my mother died. Two
				years later my father followed her.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>