<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 72</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-3075138e-9a6b-48f3-99e0-48ecf01fabda</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-65126112-d574-4dd4-ac23-a4eb12c78cc8</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u xml:id="q-dc7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="1">I left school,
				and had to look for a job, I <sic>throught</sic><corr>thought</corr> I found a job that I liked but it would mean
				working nights which I did not fancy and the money we not very good. It was a <sic>chife</sic><corr>chef</corr>
				at a hotel in London. As I could not find a job I wrote <sic>of</sic><corr>to</corr><sic>Thant</sic><corr>that</corr><sic>Collage</sic><corr>College</corr> for a <sic>Chife</sic><corr>Chef</corr>
				course I was expect when I was 17 and stayed <sic>their</sic><corr>there</corr> for three years. When I come out
				of <sic>Thant</sic><corr>that</corr><sic>Collage</sic><corr>College</corr> I had to wait for a few weeks to find a job, then I looked in a
				newspaper, it said <sic>chife</sic><corr>chef</corr> wanted at London Hotel so I wrote to see if I could a
				interview, they asked me if I would come up, so I did, they seemed friend the wages
				were good, and you got hour of for lunch I did not to start until 9 am then when
				went to lunch at 2 pm then back until 5 pm, so I took the job. I did not have to
				work on Sundays that was good <sic>becaues</sic><corr>because</corr> I had a <sic>hobey</sic><corr>hobbey</corr> football. I played for the <sic>twon</sic><corr>town</corr>
				local team, top of the league in two cup finals. I planned to get married when I was
				26 years old.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-dd7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">When I was 26 I
				got married my job as a <sic>chiefe</sic><corr>chef</corr> was in rocks, as the hotel had been bunt, blady , but
				I would not be out of a job, <sic>becaues</sic><corr>because</corr> I was offered a <sic>concert</sic><corr>contract</corr> with a <sic>formous</sic><corr>famous</corr><sic>footmall</sic><corr>football</corr>
				team which I took, At 27 I played my debut against Liverpool which was a hard game
				we just about won 5-4 that was <sic>they</sic><corr>the</corr> only game I played all season, so I would see
				what would happen just year not much so I asked for a transfore. I got it when I was
				31.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-de7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I played in <sic>divison</sic><corr>division</corr> 4 with Reading I won a cup couple of <sic>medles</sic><corr>medals</corr> with the {Illegible} for the next 9 years
				I was happy at Reading, my wife got her first baby a boy we called him Paul, he grow
				up and followed his dad’s footsteps. When had another kid a few years later, my wife
				was <sic>take</sic><corr>taken</corr>ill, she had to stay in <sic>hospite</sic><corr>hospital</corr> for a few weeks.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-df7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">So the death of
				my wife, so I had to look after the children, a boy and a girl, the boy just in the
				most import time of his life, when he had to take his exam, if you passed any ‘o’
				level he would ten pound, and for CSE five pound. I <sic>eneded</sic><corr>ended</corr> up paying 45 pounds for
				the exam, five six CSE and two ‘o’ level my <sic>sone</sic><corr>son</corr> left us and went into the army.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e07e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">I had to retire
				from football but was offered a {illegible} has a <sic>manger</sic><corr>manager</corr>, which I took up we did not
				do well in the first year coming six from bottom, but the next two years were good
				fishing 5 and 7 and the year after that we won <sic>promiption</sic><corr>promotion</corr> to <sic>divison</sic><corr>division</corr> 3, I was on the
				{illegible} of 60 I was only my now as my daughter left to go with her boyfriend, at
				63 {could be 65?} I retired from football all together I still watched a bit I had
				to <sic>retiler</sic><corr>retire</corr><sic>becaues</sic><corr>because</corr> I was in a road <sic>crush</sic><corr>crash</corr> and could not see out of one eye. A 70
				years old I had to go to an old peoples home as the house become <sic>to</sic><corr>too</corr> big for me so i
				sold it by I only last a few years there.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>