<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 42</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-e2f2726f-15c8-4eb2-8d80-b7723d797216</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-3cfb37e7-fee5-4dac-aa7c-c7c9be9393a2</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-207e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-217e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">I left school at
				the age of 16 <sic>hopeing</sic><corr>hoping</corr> to find a job after giving up the hope of becoming an art
				student at Medway college of Design. I was on the dole for six months after leaving
				school, until I got a job in a garage, just helping clear up and help serve the
				customers who come to get petrol. Then after a couple of months the manager asked if
				I would like to try something like an apprenticeship <sic>emidiatly</sic><corr>immediately</corr> I took the offer. I
				spent three years as an <sic>aprentice</sic><corr>apprentice</corr> motor mechanic, after that I took on a job as a
				motor mechanic at Sheppey Autos and worked for a mister Turner. I stayed <sic>their</sic><corr>there</corr> for a
				couple of years, as I liked it very much <sic>their</sic><corr>there</corr>.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-227e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">Around this time
				my mum started nag me to try to find some other place to live well I was twenty two.
				I had had some girl friends but never really took to any particular one. Then I
				started to go with a girl named Emma, she was quite nice.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-237e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">I was twenty
				three when I got an offer from my <sic>uncal</sic><corr>uncle</corr> in Derby to go and work with him in his
				garage, dealing with Rolls Royce. I took his offer and I earned £51 a week. Emma and
				I finally got engaged, we saved and managed to get a house and then the big day we
				got <sic>maried</sic><corr>married</corr>.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-247e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">At the age of
				thirty one I still had the same job and me and Emma had a house just inside Derby in
				Tutbury. It was a big year because we were <sic>exspecting</sic><corr>expecting</corr> patter of tiny feet. Not much
				happened after that, it was just day in day out routine, Paul grew fast and it was
				not long before he was at school. He had just settled down when me and my wife
				decided to move to the Isle of Sheppey back to my home. Eventually we did move. And
				when I saw the Island I was shocked. It was much cleaner and better than when I was
				a kid.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-257e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">We stayed on the
				Island we got a house in Minster quite nice near the beach. The years <sic>past</sic><corr>passed</corr> on we had
				another little one when paul was a comprehensive school. Funny enough the one I went
				to, I was surprised it was still standing.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-267e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">Then it had to
				come I reached the age of <sic>fortie</sic><corr>fourty</corr>, by this time I was managing my own garage and
				<sic>imploying</sic><corr>employing</corr> youngsters.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>