<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 7</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-b22a1163-e9eb-4f01-9a5f-a6ec8cd432a8</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-f1482730-9482-446a-bdc1-d350b70c889b</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u xml:id="q-767d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="1">I left school at
				the age of seventeen with 3 ‘O’ levels and several C.S.Es and joined a small company
				as an office boy at the age of eighteen in Sittingbourne. When the company expanded
				I was transferred to a London branch, which meant leaving home and getting a flat in
				London with a friend. After six years with the company slowly progressing I became
				assistant manager. Soon after I bought a house just outside London, then eventually
				a car. At the age of twenty-six I left the company and became a production manager
				with a different one. By that time I was thinking about marriage having a car and
				house and soon hoping to getting a small yacht. I began visiting other countries
				every year for a holiday, with a group of friends and a girlfriend. At twenty-eight
				I was offered a job in America with another branch of the same company. I took it. I
				rented out the house and took a flat in America. After four years then, I came back
				with thoughts of marriage renewed, still with the same company. At thirty-four I
				marry a blonde, who is thirty. We live in the house with two cars and after a year
				she has a baby boy. Eventually when I am thirty-eight we are divorced on grounds of
				being sick of each other. She takes care of the boy and a car and alimony. After
				this I put in for my job in America again and spend another six years then during
				that time I met a Canadian girl and marry her. By this time I would assess myself as
				a middle-classed manager, divorced, <sic>remarryed</sic><corr>remarried</corr>, three children, (one with my ex-wife
				and twins by my second). and go to Canada where my mother lives, every year and to
				England to see my parents every two years. At the age of forty-nine we go back to
				England and soon after wife has another baby, this is to be the last (we hope).
				After three years in England my parents die, leaving me with two houses and quite a
				bit of money. I hear of my first son has gone on to university and his mother has
				died. I am now fifty-nine and I don’t want to live any longer, so I will leave all
				my money and property to my wife and children (including the one at university).
				Retire with them and on my sixtieth birthday, I will kill myself (I hope).</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>