<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 41</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-42547812-8079-42af-bf5c-24f1912b6339</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-1e97ec15-6925-4c37-8bef-73fc35710808</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u xml:id="q-1c7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="1">I left school at
				sixteen and a half with two O’levels and a few C.S.E.s. The job situation was a bit
				bleak, but not as bad as a few years earlier but I managed to get an apprenticeship
				as an electrician at a factory which made windscreens, this was alright for about
				three or four years. Then I left for a job a world wide firm which paid very good
				money.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-1d7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">Once I was
				settled at this new job, I got married to a girl I knew from my school days, she was
				also working at a well paid job a we was living well for a short time until we both
				decided to come down a peg or two and we ended up in a semi-detached house in
				Sheerness.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-1e7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">As the years went
				by a couple of kids appeared. My job came along well and I was offered a post out in
				Canada but with the kids around it was impossible so I had to refuse it, but now I
				wish I had not. I suppose the kids got have had just a good education out there.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-1f7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">I had been with
				this firm about seven years so I decided it was time to move on. I never really
				could stay at one job for very long. By now my wife had left her job to look after
				the kids. So my new job had to pay well. It was the same kind of job but it gave me
				less time off and I wasn’t very happy about this, but the pay gave us plenty to save
				up, but I worked out a swap with a workmate and this gave me plenty of time off to
				stay with the family. This was the job that I decided to stay with now until
				retirement.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>