<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 106</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-3b0e61e9-f342-4c32-a899-6110ec3a0bf0</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-4c406afd-e0ac-4cea-8db8-17ebbb2bd020</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-e37f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-e47f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">I am sitting in
				front of the television, feeling rather fed up with life, when I hear voices and
				laughter outside. I cross over to the window and look out. There are a group of
				teenagers on their way home from school, about five girls and five boys. I wonder if
				they are in their last year at school, just about to take their exams.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e57f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">They laugh and
				joke, crossing the road without looking properly and they join their friends in the
				crowded coffee bar.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e67f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">I remember back
				to when my life followed the same daily routine as theirs. My last year at school
				having great times, then taking my exams, and gradually saying goodbye to most of my
				friends as they left school.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e77f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">Like them I left
				and went to college for two years, to do social welfare. There another crowd of new
				friends. Saying goodbye to them, as gradually we drifted apart and got jobs.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e87f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">I still lived at
				home and life carried on much the same. But there was one difference I was working
				as a social worker. I suddenly felt a lot older and although I had left school just
				two years ago it seemed a lifetime ago.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e97f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">I got another job
				and moved off of the island and moved into a flat with a few other girls.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ea7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">I loved my job
				and the city life, I had a busy social life and at one party my whole life seemed to
				change. I met Dave and we got on really well straight away. After a year or so, we
				were engaged. I didn’t want to get married early, so we waited three years and then
				married. We had bought a small house near London, and were very happy I still had my
				career but after a year gave it up to start a family. We had three children two
				boys, then a girl. As they grew older and went to school, I went back to my
				career.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-eb7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">Eventually the
				children left home, and led their own <sic>lifes</sic><corr>lives</corr>.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ec7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="10">Dave and I were
				about forty-five by this time. We saved and with the children gone, had a lovely
				time travelling together.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ed7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="11">Of course we
				were getting older and we both retired. We have a lazy life now which can get very
				boring at times.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ee7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="12">The teenagers
				are leaving the coffee bar now, probably going home, doing homework, then they will
				be off out somewhere to have some fun. As I watch them disappear round the corner, I
				cannot help but envy them. What I would give to be in my ‘teens’ again.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>