<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 74</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-a2b5f28a-a0db-4ec1-b476-0af12245843e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-bbf87c0c-11dd-440e-9120-4f1af974134a</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-f17e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Sixty</note>
      <u xml:id="q-f27e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">Here I am at the
				age of sixteen finished my exams which are bad. So <sic>its</sic><corr>it's</corr> out into the open air,
				looking for work. All vacancies taken so <sic>its</sic><corr>it's</corr> the dole queue for me.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f37e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">Seventeen, nearly
				eighteen still no work. Come up eighteen and I found a job not what I expected but
				it will have to do. Twenty six quid and forty-three pence, and most of that goes on
				tax and my keep.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f47e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">Twenty now and
				life’s hard but I will be getting married soon and I be bringing up my family. Worse
				thing about getting married is the settling down. Wedding was ok, the honeymoon was
				ok but now were home and its finding a house. The one thing I didn’t want to happen
				was to stay with my family. Now <sic>its</sic><corr>it's</corr> arguments all the way. The only way I thought of
				getting out of it was to get a proper job.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f57e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">Twenty seven and
				I got two boys three and one years of age. And I out in the cold hoping and looking
				for a job with good pay.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f67e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">Thirty and now I
				get seventy five quid a week. We have a house now semi-detached also a little girl,
				so now I pay to look after my wife three kids, a house and a saloon car.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f77e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">Forty three and
				the kids are finding troublesome now there out in the world and its seeing there
				alright the eldest nineteen is married, so again I low on the money and it keeps
				going down, the other boy sixteen is wanting to go to <sic>collage</sic><corr>college</corr> and the girl is
				starting to get bad at school and is hardly there.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f87e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">Fifty and the
				parents are slowly finding away and its starting to hit the family our-selves for
				instance we are working up and are starting to live our best now the kids <sic>of</sic><corr>have</corr> gone
				away and we haven’t heard a word for a few years and we are now alone in a terrace
				two-bedroomed house and soon it will be time for me to retire and then it will be
				just the rest of our lives to live out as we are now sixty and it is not long now.
				Looking back on my live over forty-six years I always wondered if it was worth
				it.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>