<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 105</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-d056865b-9d6b-4490-8188-e3d3640284c0</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-09504641-2960-4e55-b17d-df5750f52461</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-dc7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-dd7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">As I sat looking
				out of the window of the old people’s home, I watched the young teenagers coming
				home from school. How smart they looked in their navy blue uniforms. It made me
				remember my schooldays, I was just sixteen years old when I left. At that time my
				main ambition was to get a job and earn some money, so that I could buy and do all
				things that I had wished for.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-de7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">Luckily, due to a
				lot of help from my father I became a clerical assistant in the civil service at
				Chatham dockyard. My father and brother were both working <sic>their</sic><corr>there</corr> at the time. I
				started on thirty pounds, I thought this was pretty good money, well it seemed to be
				then. I had great fun as a teenager. As I my money rose, the better the time I had.
				At seventeen my family and I moved off the island nearer to Chatham. I went out most
				nights of the week. Occasionally during the summer I would spend weekends at Sheppey
				staying with friends and they would come back to stay with me. The best bit came
				when I was eighteen. I got a really smart car, well I thought it was, really it was
				an old banger but I did it up and hit the road. From then I really got round, went
				to London with my mates, <sic>shoping</sic><corr>shopping</corr> and going to concerts etc.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-df7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">The next biggest
				step was when I met Steve, I fell for him a few months after being introduced. We
				started going out together and eventually got engaged. The engagement lasted for six
				months and we got married when I was twenty two. It was a fabulous white wedding and
				we honeymooned in the South of France. We had a small but nice house which we saved
				the deposit for before marrying. I had my first child at twenty five, a little boy
				called Danny. He was a proper lad, always in the mud or fighting and playing
				football. At twenty eight I had a girl which we called Kelly. With the children we
				just didn’t have the money to go out like we used to especially since I had given up
				work. Steve was earning about eighty pound a week and we didn’t do too bad.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e07f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">Life didn’t
				change a great deal again until my own children left home, except that gradually we
				got better off. I was nearly fifty when both had left home. Kelly got married and
				Danny lived single for about a year, then married. After that Steve and I were
				lonely but soon began to enjoy life in the way we did before having children.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e17f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">“Hello dear,
				daydreaming again”</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e27f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">“Steve, your home
				early, I’ll get the dinner ready”.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>