<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 52</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-426529f7-ecd8-45d7-b51f-d90277ee22c6</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-a1c57e2b-c68b-4712-b1d1-a3317c71e185</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-607e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflecting</note>
      <u xml:id="q-617e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">Looking back over
				my past, I suppose I can be fairly satisfied. After leaving school I got the
				<sic>apprentiship</sic><corr>apprenticeship</corr> I wanted, and in the five years it took for me to learn my trade, I did
				have some fun while I was still in my youthful stages. I had good mates and we knew
				how to enjoy ourselves. After all, it’s no good working and slaving your heart out
				it you can’t have leisure and freedom to do what you want.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-627e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">Later on in my
				life, I can’t say getting married was a bad thing. I know I perhaps wouldn’t have
				the freedom i once had but we got on allright, and it was worthwhile. As for work,
				well as soon as I finished my trade, I left, and got a job as a {mate?} in Sheerness
				Docks. I found it was no easy work and the money a lot better than doing my trade
				work. I also took the occasion day off, and then I would do my favourite pastime,
				fishing. I also went out in my dinghy I had ever since I was sixteen , and
				especially if it was a calm day, I’d chug out <sic>their</sic><corr>there</corr> in midwater, and just sit <sic>their</sic><corr>there</corr>,
				and take it all in. This was the perfect thing, and now I still admit I love having
				a {dab?} in the sea. As time went by, I packed in my job, and I got a job as a mate
				on a fishing boat. This was I think a great move as I was now doing the thing I
				loved. We had some great times in that boat, and later on, I was forced to leave had
				the boat got smashed in a storm. Up to then I was fairly lucky job wise but now I
				had to go back for my profession, and there I remarried until I retired. I had
				become very slow, and the whole face of the world had seemed to have changed since I
				was a youngster.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>