<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 43</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-136a5313-610a-4ead-bce1-665eb476e892</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-43238666-8c65-4f80-838e-a88cc37b0c06</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-277e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">The Past</note>
      <u xml:id="q-287e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">In the summer of
				1978 I left school with only half the ‘O’levels I had hoped to get. But didn’t stop
				my chances of getting into the army as an officer. I was nervous at first when I
				joined but I soon got over it as I seemed to fit in so well. Those years in the army
				were some of the best in my life, I met some real good mates and always seemed to
				{illegible} a laugh, but the army had <sic>it’s</sic><corr>its</corr> disadvantages with Northern Ireland and
				such places. The fives years in the army seemed more like a five weeks holiday, it
				was in the last year that I met my wife at a party on leave. She was two years
				younger than me and we got along fine. She made my days off something really to look
				forward to. It was her that prompted me to leave the army since we had become
				engaged.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-297e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">When I left I
				went into the timber trade early learning the pros and cons of running a business.
				By the time I had learnt enough to move on to another firm as a representative, to
				learn how to sell your product, I was married with a house in Sittingbourne and a
				baby on the way. We had a lot of good times in that house and many memories of the
				children growing for badies to children.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-2a7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">After eight years
				as a representative I felt confident enough to go into business on my own. I brought
				a small piece of land in Queenborough and moved back to the Island where I myself
				had been brought up.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-2b7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">Money was short
				in my first few years of business but it soon picked up and began to make instead of
				lose. The children, 2 boys 1 girl, were now tall (the eldest bigger than me), and
				Susan, my daughter was beginning to show signs of being a woman and demanding her
				own way.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-2c7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">The business
				grew, and life went on. The children began one by one to leave home. Lynn, my wife,
				and I were beginning to slow down and with <sic>bussiness</sic><corr>business</corr> booming and the children <sic>goon</sic><corr>gone</corr>
				we decided to move to a new home. This was more luxurious but was never quite the
				same as our last home.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-2d7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">I began to leave
				work more and more <sic>untill</sic><corr>until</corr> it was merely a once a week visit, but I received the same
				income. My wife and I saw less and less of other people but we had our children and
				our grandchildren to keep us company.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-2e7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">I was deeply
				shocked when the communist party gained power and all <sic>bussiness</sic><corr>business</corr> taken away from
				people who had work had to gain them. I lost my firm and was dismissed as a
				director. I was forced sell my house and buy something smaller but I don’t really
				mind I still have Lynn and our children. I now don’t care what happens as long as me
				and Lynn can finish our days together.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>