<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 140</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-25852ced-93a8-4eee-b18c-6c8e3c91f6a2</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-f30ddb20-c69b-427c-acd5-6e88dcd0f43e</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-f9805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflecting</note>
      <u xml:id="q-fa805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">As I look back
				over the years of my life, I think back when I was at school at the age of fourteen
				when we had to make a <sic>disition</sic><corr>decision</corr> what we were going to do when we leave school. I can
				remember what kind of <sic>disition</sic><corr>decision</corr> I made, it was at first I was going to stay on then I
				decided that I would leave I wouldn’t often do this sort of thing, but in the end I
				did make up my mind and it was, that I was going to leave.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-fb805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">When the day same
				when I was going to leave I was, quite worried because I hadn’t got a job in hand.
				Well when I did leave I stayed at home and I can remember my mother telling me to go
				out and get a job but I knew it wasn’t so easy to go out and just get on my mother
				would go on all day and night she kept on because my father had not long died and I
				had three brothers and two sisters and they were all younger than me, that’s why my
				mother kept on because she was working only part time who wasn’t much money to keep
				six children.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-fc805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">Soon I had got
				myself a job working in a factory I didn’t like it much but it was something, I was
				earning just a little but more than my mother and every penny that I had went to my
				mother for keeping us all.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-fd805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">Later I became
				married and it was a very happy marriage my husband earned a quite a bit and I still
				{illegible?} the job I started with when I left school. Quite a bit later we had
				children which was one girl and one boy.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-fe805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">My life as a
				child wasn’t all that good that’s why I had children, so that they could lead a
				better life than I did.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ff805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">Well over the
				years my life was getting a little bit better until my husband died that wasn’t long
				till I had to retire and looking over the years my life I don’t know why I ever
				moaned in the first place.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>