<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 134</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-2e1d1d7b-dfac-415d-a525-7b173f5f8d0e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-81f347e6-d62f-46d5-a48c-beae60d78a4d</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-c8805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflecting</note>
      <u xml:id="q-c9805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">For the last
				seventy years my life had been pretty normal. I left school at sixteen and a half
				and waited for one month before I finally got the job I wanted as a Beauty
				consultant in London. I had to leave home because the traveling became <sic>to</sic><corr>too</corr> much. I
				moved to London, thinking that everything would be ok and I would have not a thing
				to worry about. But when I finally moved up there I found out it was not so good
				after all being on your own not knowing many people around me who to trust etc. So
				one of the girls I worked with wanted to leave home and she lived with me. We used
				to have a great time.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ca805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">When I was twenty
				I was asked by my firm to go and work abroad. For a while, after a long thought I
				decide to go. I stayed in France for eighteen months. Then came back here for a
				month then back in France.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-cb805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">When I was
				twenty-seven I fell in love with a Frenchman and got married we had only known each
				other for two months, and the marriage only lasted a year. “That was a year to
				long”.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-cc805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">So later on I got
				involved with another Frenchman but I <sic>didnt</sic><corr>didn't</corr> get married again even though I was
				pregnant. I was not going to fall for that old game again. We got on very well
				neither of us had to ask <sic>premission</sic><corr>permission</corr> to go out with the opposite sex. Until I had the
				child I could no longer go out because I had to look after it, things between <sic>is</sic><corr>us began</corr> to
				fall apart until I left and came back to England. Where my mother looked after the
				baby while I went to work. I work in a factory the money was very good.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-cd805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">For eighteen
				years I had saved up to go back to France to live even though I had some bad luck
				the country was really nice and the people were friendly.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ce805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">I was forty five
				and my child was no longer a child he was an adult. He was architect so I was very
				proud of him.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-cf805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">In France I got
				my job back as a beauty consultant and retired at sixty. I have enjoyed my
				retirement so far and have also been on one cruise around the world, and intend to
				go on another one on two <sic>years</sic><corr>years'</corr> time.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>