<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 90</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-160371cb-d937-460d-815c-77b4e521feb1</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-d4072c93-fac3-4f1c-a9bc-a469c15a6ec8</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-5d7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-5e7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">I left school at
				17 years of age and started work in Abbotts Laboratories as laboratory assistant. I
				liked my work I enjoyed going out in the evenings with Paul. By then I’d already
				been going steady with him for a year. When I was 20 I got married to Paul. It was a
				<sic>lovley</sic><corr>lovely</corr> wedding then sun was <sic>shinning</sic><corr>shining</corr> and everyone enjoyed themselves.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-5f7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I stayed at work
				until my first baby was born I was 22 then. She was <sic>lovley</sic><corr>lovely</corr>; she had Auburn hair and
				lots of it. We called her Hiedi. Three years later I had another baby a boy this
				time he was really cute. We called him Danny. He turned out to be a right little
				monkey. Hiedi started school when she was 5 and Danny started 2 years later. I went
				back to work. The children grew up and the four of us had a marvellous time,
				especially on our Annual Holidays. We were doing alright financially, Paul had a
				good job so at 38 I left work and became an ordinary housewife. The next year mum
				died, it took a long time to get over that as we were very close. Dad moved into our
				road so that we could keep an eye on him. That year seemed full of deaths. <sic>Pauls</sic><corr>Paul's</corr> Dad
				died three months afterwards I think it was the shock of his dad dying that caused
				it. Although the doctors said it was heart trouble I was glad to see that year out.
				Heidi got married when she was 18 she looked lovely all in white. Danny got married
				at 20, in the same year Hiedi had her one and only child, Samantha. She had a
				difficult birth and decided not to have any more. Danny had 3 children the first
				came two years after his marriage it was a girl called Jayne. The other two came
				both together, twins, a boy called Simon and a girl called Veronica. I spent nearly
				all of my spare time with my grandchildren right up until now. I love them dearly
				and so does Paul, he gets on especially well with Simon, I think it’s because he’s
				the only boy. He’s a comedian, just like his dad used to be. Every weekend all 10 of
				us get together at our house. We’re one big happy family who get on just fine. When
				Paul had a spell in Hospital two months ago all four <sic>grandchild</sic><corr>grandchildren</corr> came to stay with
				me, they were good company and cheered me up no end. Anyway Paul’s alright now and
				we’re all back together again, I hope we will stay like that for a long time, for as
				long as I live anyway.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>