<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 1</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-cb1688f8-3984-4a1c-8a07-9173891630e8</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-c2299f89-eee4-4202-8bae-f141e6d13bc5</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-427d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-437d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">When I left
				school at the age of 18 I had just taken my ‘A’ levels. I past them all with grade
				C’s and I was quite pleased with myself. I got accepted at Bradford University on an
				electronics engineering course. I enjoyed the time I spent at university although I
				didn’t like being away from home for so long at first. I used to go home every so
				often though. After getting the necessary qualifications I left to find a job. That
				was much easier than it is now even though the unemployment was higher then. I think
				finding a job was one of the most pleasing moments of my life. I hadn’t enjoyed
				learning much at all but putting it into practice was much better. I was twenty two
				by this time and I felt great having a job when unemployment was up to an all time
				high. It was about this time that I met Anne my wife. She was two years younger than
				me and worked for the same company as I did. I had met girls at university but my
				relationships with them weren’t anything serious. I’d never none anyone I’d really
				liked before and it seemed a natural step to get married. It was only a quite affair
				in a registry office as I didn’t particularly want a church wedding and Anne’s
				family weren’t very religious. We just invited a few of her friends and a few of
				mine. It was long before we had found a house thanks to a friend of Anne’s father.
				It was a pretty large mortgage but I liked the thought of having a house of our own,
				instead of living at Anne’s parent’s house. We were quite happy together aside from
				the usual rows which go with <sic>marrige</sic><corr>marriage</corr>.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-447d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">It wasn’t long
				before our eldest son Mark was born and we had two others John and Karen, they were
				all three years apart. After we had had children I think we grew closer together.
				Mark is now married and he works in Administration. John is very happily married and
				he has done well in the plastics industry. Karen was also married but divorced and
				remarried- she is now a housewife and they have two children.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-457d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">It was a great
				experience for me to see my children growing up. I had often wondered what it would
				be like when I was young. When they had all left and gone their separate ways it
				felt very empty and it was so quite I think Anne missed them more than me even
				though she had had a hard time bringing them up, she seemed at a loose end.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-467d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">I retired not
				long ago after forty years with the same company. Life is very tedious now and I
				spend most of my time just sitting around thinking of the past.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>