<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 25</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-accfb878-f2aa-4d2a-99c2-35b7285b6114</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-e80a2807-0207-45a6-bb00-c565d1d0c8fd</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-da7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">The Past</note>
      <u xml:id="q-db7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">I left school at
				seventeen after staying one year in the sixth form. I waited three months before I
				got the job I wanted, which was in insurance. I stayed on the Isle of Sheppey living
				with my parents until I was twenty one. At this particular time of my life I moved
				to Maidstone nearer my company. I had to move because travelling became a problem,
				and I had moved up the promotion ladder. So I had more responsibility.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-dc7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">From about the
				age of twenty one to about twenty six my life seemed quiet with nothing much
				happening. When I was twenty eight I had planned to live abroad and work for a
				company in Europe. I was turned down because I had not much experience of foreign
				languages. I remember very well, being upset by this. I thought that past could well
				of changed my whole life.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-dd7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">At the age of
				thirty I got married. At the age of thirty two we had our first child a boy. About
				three months later I was promoted to sub manager.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-de7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">With my job I was
				meeting different people and going to special functions. This was different to when
				I was at school because I was shy and quiet. When I was thirty four we had our
				second child this was a girl. Two years later I decided to stand for the local
				council, and to my surprise I got on by a majority of six hundred. I only stayed on
				the council until I was forty two. I came off because it was interfering with my
				family and work life. When I was in my middle fortys my wife and I were thinking of
				emigrating but decided against it because it could interfere with the childrens
				schooling.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-df7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">When I was forty
				eight I left the insurance company to work for a big industrial firm and join the
				board of directors. They needed someone who had a experience in Insurance because a
				lot of my work was to deal with the keeping of the companys head above water, keep
				safe. At the age of fifty three my wife and I emigrated to Austria, because the
				company wanted to expand in central Europe.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e07d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">When I retired
				two years ago my wife and I decided to come back to England for the rest of our
				lifes. We are at present living in Norfolk.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>