<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 113</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-20eb0ca9-d8bc-4557-b8a4-85f2cfa2a769</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-b15d3428-af4f-417d-a3a8-6e56eab66c07</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-28805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">My Past</note>
      <u xml:id="q-29805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">I left school in
				the summer of 1979 to work in an office as a secretary it was a big place is London
				and I didn’t know many people, after I didn’t know many people, after about a year
				and a half I left to work for a bigger and better company where I could earn more
				money as I was planning to marry within the next year or two and we had planned to
				save to buy our own house near his parents. After about 6 months the engagement
				broke up and I didn’t get over it for ages. I thought I would change my job, I would
				go in for nursing, I would learn a profession and find other interests. In the next
				five years I had gained A husband, a family and a house of our own is a nice part of
				London. When my two children started school I started nursing again at a hospital
				again at a hospital nearby. But it got too tiring with the children as well. So I
				decided to pack it in. When I was in my late twenties my husband was offered a job
				is Saudi Arabia. He went on his own, and sent money back for me and the kids. The
				kids grew rapidly and hardly saw their daddy. When my husband eventually come home
				the children were leaving school and going out to work. They were twin girl and boy.
				The girl worked in a Bank and the boy joined the navy. My mother was really good to
				me while my husband was away so we bought a holiday of a lifetime on a cruise around
				the <sic>meditteranean</sic><corr>Mediterranean</corr>. But on her return we sadly lost her it took me two years to get
				over that. But when I went back to nursing. We moved house down to a little cottage
				in Kent nearer home. It was a lovely place and we never left it for long because
				everything in it belonged to us and we had worked hard for it. When I was 55 a
				grandmother to 5 my husband passed away through a serious operation.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-2a805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I still had our
				family though and my grandchildren were lovely 2 girls and three boys. I family
				emigrated to Australia and the others lived nearby. They asked me if I wanted to go
				but I said that I was nearly at the age of retirement and the travelling would be
				too much for me. Many other things happened in my life but these were the most
				important to me. I suffer from <sic>Arthuritus</sic><corr>arthritis</corr> now very badly but <sic>its</sic><corr>it's</corr><sic>too</sic><corr>to</corr> be expected
				when you get old.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>