<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 91</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-cabda39f-cf97-4acc-afcb-0db5e6372531</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-2609c471-9f20-4e0f-9c51-bb5ef253a919</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-607f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-617f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">After leaving
				school at 17 I got a secretarial job in a Sheerness firm, twinlocks I think unless
				that was later, anyway. I stayed <sic>their</sic><corr>there</corr><sic>till</sic><corr>until</corr> I was 19 then got a job in London in a
				much bigger firm and better wages. I led quite a good life, had my own car and flat.
				I</u>
      <u xml:id="q-627f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">t was about 18
				months later that I met my husband. And another year later I married him. For the
				first 10 months of our marriage we lived in a one bedroomed flat I stayed on at
				work. Then he changed jobs and we moved to a house nearer my parents.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-637f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">I left work to
				sort the house out and get straight.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-647f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">It was soon after
				that I fell for our first baby. A girl Lisa, then three years later a boy Stephen.
				As soon as they got older and Stephen started school I got another part time job
				locally as a receptionist. But I only stayed 2 years then pack up work altogether.
				But I didn’t laze around all day, bringing up two young children prevented me
				anyway. I started at a an art school in the afternoons which I enjoyed.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-657f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">The rest of my
				years I enjoyed very much, having two lovely children (not always lovely!)
				around.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-667f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">We had a holiday
				each year, always abroad then when the children left and married, we moved to
				another, smaller house, locally. We were a very close family and our children
				regularly visited us.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-677f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">There was only
				one bad, really unhappy time which was when my parent died, they both died of old
				age, no illnesses, my father the first, and my mother broken hearted the following
				year.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-687f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">Overall I think
				my memories are all happy ones and I hope I live long enough to have many more,
				especially watching my grandchildren grow up.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>