<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 81</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-b0a0df75-a223-4f72-8a7d-3fd0053c6c6e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-fff1179e-580b-4b25-b5a5-f60608e2e6d8</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-197f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflecting</note>
      <u xml:id="q-1a7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">At 69 I have
				often looked back over my career. I left school at 18 and went on to university. I
				started my career at 21 with a degree. My career was geology. One of the reasons why
				I chose geology was that I found it very interesting and it also included lots of
				travel. The pay wasn’t bad too!</u>
      <u xml:id="q-1b7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">At school,
				especially the term before my ‘O’ levels it was very bored, but during this time I
				went to see the careers <sic>officed</sic><corr>office</corr>. Our school, Sheppey Comprehensive, was very large
				and I didn’t like going to school, because it was so big. When I went into the sixth
				<sic>for</sic><corr>form</corr> to study ‘A’ levels things seemed to change. I enjoyed going to school. The
				sixth form was a pleasant area, carpeted etc. I was a little sorry to leave it to go
				to university.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-1c7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">A university
				student was a great life, with many opportunities to do what I liked. Holidays were
				also great, and the friends were always good for a laugh.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-1d7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">When I was 21 I
				left university with my geology degree and I got a job with the civil service. I was
				soon travelling all round the world studying these land formation and those land
				formations. Some of the surveying was also in the seas as well. And I found my
				career thoroughly enjoyable. I was very sorry to retire four years ago.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-1e7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">At the age of
				forty I settled down to study the rocks of my own local environment until I
				retired.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-1f7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">After first
				reading about geology at school, when I was about 15, I became hooked on the
				subject. It seemed to fascinate me but a year later I had gone off it, but I still
				wanted to be a geologist.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-207f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">It was nearly
				hopeless when I tried the careers centre. They could give me some information of the
				exams I would need and on further education (i.e. university) but they could not
				really give me and leaflets on the actual subject of geology. The only real
				information I obtained was from book from the library or from a few science lessons
				from school. To become a geologist, I had to put in a lot of work for myself. Once I
				had made it though I was laughing. The job with the civil service was great. Most of
				it was a holiday not a job. I was often being sent away to the far reaches of the
				earth, in, sometimes, the remotest places. I had to work in the <sic>extrimes</sic><corr>extreme</corr> of
				<sic>tempreture</sic><corr>temperatures</corr> and in almost every country throughout the world.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-217f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">It wasn’t all
				plain sailing though sometimes I had to work under the great depths of the ocean, or
				the high mountains. I even had to work near volcanoes, even the active ones. Where
				there was an earthquake disaster I was sent there, especially those where a
				seismograph station wasn’t very near.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-227f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="10">Other times I had
				paper work to at seismograph station. I had to take sesmic readings of earth
				tremours plot them on graphs and other various paper work, but this was only
				fractional.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-237f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="11">On the bright
				side of my career though, I often visited exotic places, which people only dream
				about. I also had long holidays and the pay was good, with an increase in yearly
				salaries. With this money I was able to sometimes, really “live it up”. The great
				attraction though was the travel, and my interest in the land.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-247f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="12">During my spare
				time, I was often on holidays, either camping/hiking, or on a cycle tour. These kind
				of holidays were always the best for me. I always seemed to enjoy the most. I found
				that these holidays always added to the good things in life.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-257f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="13">At 28 I got
				married to a French girl and she has also travelled with me, when I was at work, and
				also on holidays.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-267f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="14">Looking back to
				the struggle of becoming a geologist, I think that if I had not made it I would have
				tried to become a warden of a national park or perhaps something like that e.g. a
				game keeper, <sic>forrestry</sic><corr>forestry</corr> warden, so long as it was something I could enjoy a great
				deal.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-277f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="15">Even now, in my
				large farmhouse (but there isn’t a farm no more) on one of the <sic>hymalayan</sic><corr>Himalayan</corr> mountains.
				I look back and thing to myself, what a fantastic life I’ve <sic>lead</sic><corr>had</corr>, and that I wish I
				hadn’t retired from geology. I still study the various rock formations of the
				<sic>Hymalayan</sic><corr>Himalayan</corr> range, here near Tibet.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>