<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 68</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-0578ccef-49c7-4a8e-bbf5-7e900ef7d1a3</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-d5701625-942f-4584-9e70-722e487d30c3</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-c17e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Back in Age The Good Old Days</note>
      <u xml:id="q-c37e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">Back into sweet
				sixteen, the age of legalness, whereby you come of age for sex, motorbikes, smoking,
				pubs. A good age but the worst for trouble, I <sic>new</sic><corr>knew</corr> I was old enough for sex, driving,
				and smoking so I started doing all of these which got me into trouble most of my
				life. I got engaged at 16 and tied myself down for life. Between 17-18 I took
				driving lessons and went for my test I failed 10 time but eventually I managed. I
				got married and settled down at 20, <sic>payed</sic><corr>paid</corr> deposit on a house mortgage it wasn’t a
				good house but we cleaned it up and done well, oh by the way you haven’t met my wife
				this is Dawn. At the age of 22 I bought a bigger house, a better car and worked
				hard, started off in <sic>factorys</sic><corr>factories</corr>, but got an apprenticeship, and passed at 22, I went
				on into business on my own, it worked out pretty well I never became no fantastic
				millionaire, but I was happy living on £90 a week. At the Age of 25 I took my HGV
				license and started driving <sic>lorrys</sic><corr>lorries</corr>, I remember I first drove for bennetts at
				queenborough on Sheppey transportings pascalls I work there for 5 years earning good
				money. At the age of 30 half my life gone left behind but another half ahead of me.
				I left driving and went back into business. As an electrician on my own. 32 it had
				come, my mother died of cancer of the liver. She was 72, I let me dad come and live
				with me, and because of this I saw my sister for the first time in ten years, anyway
				I was pleased to see them and they still come now. 35 came up quick I went to Spain
				for the first time in my life, just for a holiday but I came back with a brand new
				car. At 40 I bought another new house, this time I fully furnished it and carpeted
				it out. It cost a bomb, but then I always said you only live once. 43 my dad died
				suddenly with heart failure at 82, ten years after me mother and my sister came and
				lived with me and dawn for a year. 46 life was getting rough the standard of living
				just kept on going up and up until I nearly went down to the ground bankrupt but my
				sister bought me back up and its lasted well. So we moved house, as the kids had
				moved and left home, dawn had kids when I was 25, now there the age I was and have
				left home. We bought a small bungalow. 53 Dawn in hospital for check ups as we both
				had suspected TB but it didn’t work out, we were both OK. At 60 we both retired
				collecting <sic>pention</sic><corr>pension</corr> now with a good home and family, 4 nephews and 12 <sic>neises</sic><corr>nieces</corr>, by the
				way I forgot to tell you we had two boys and a girl.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>