<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 112</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-8c91a26e-f6ed-4d1a-9eb9-55f5505afbd9</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-f8c8c2f0-2399-4cc0-99a1-e80cc95f420b</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-20805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections (My Past)</note>
      <u xml:id="q-21805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">The day after I
				left school I had a job to go to. It was only a short while after I gave my
				resignation in because I thought it was time to move on. To live somewhere <sic>were</sic><corr>where</corr>
				there was more opportunities and more <sic>exitement</sic><corr>excitement</corr>.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-22805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">Four years later
				I found myself engaged to be married. The whole prospect of a home and later on a
				family looked good. But there was one problem my husband to be didn’t like the idea
				of me working when we were married. Eventually we together solved the problem. We
				compromised I was to work part-time.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-23805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">After being
				married a year our first child was born, it was a girl. Two years later our second
				was born. Then we waited another six years when our third child was born, this time
				a boy, another two years later our <sic>forth</sic><corr>fourth</corr> and last child was born, another girl.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-24805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">When the last
				child started school I decided to go back to work, by this time I was 36. As the
				years went by. I found my children gradually growing up and leaving me.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-25805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">By the time I was
				52 I had my first grandchildren, a girl. I was still working and all the family
				visited my husband and I every so often. We had our own little house with a nice
				back garden and garage for our car.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-26805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">When I was 60, I
				decided to retire all together we had a lot of money saved so there was no reason
				why I had to go to work. Now I had four grandchildren three girls and one boy in the
				order I had mine.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-27805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">5 years later I
				am 65 my time is just about up, my husband died two years ago. He was sixteen years
				older than by myself so in all consideration he lived to quite an old age. I have
				ten grandchildren, seven girls and three boys. The eldest is thirteen. All my
				<sic>posesions</sic><corr>possessions</corr> will all go to my children and perhaps one day their children</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>