<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 8</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-b4b0490d-0c4e-4653-b990-24e95a4da9a4</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-4b7918dc-c760-486b-8924-dffd38fda65e</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-777d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">My past life</note>
      <u xml:id="q-787d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">At sixteen I took
				seven O’levels and passed six of them. In the sixth form I took three A’levels in
				geography, maths, and physics, of which maths and physics I passed. When I left
				school at eighteen I joined an engineering firm as an <sic>apprentise</sic><corr>apprentice</corr>, and went on a
				college course to take H.N.D. in engineering, while being paid by the firm. With my
				H.N.D. I joined a union, and a body of professional engineers, and was earning seven
				thousand pounds a year. At 23 I bought my first car and moved away from home to take
				up residence in a flat nearer to the firm. I began thinking seriously about getting
				married and started to take girls out but I was twenty five before I meet the right
				girl. She was also intelligent and with both of us working we were earning one
				hundred and fifty pounds a week between us. We courted for fourteen months and got
				married in a large church. All the family was there and it was a bit “do”. We
				settled down in our own house on a housing estate in West London. After being
				married for two years we had our first child, a boy and we called him William. My
				wife stopped working and became a full time housewife. Both my wife and I enjoyed an
				active life and marriage was not going to stop that. We often went camping on the
				moors and fishing on {illegible} beaches at night. We also went in rally driving
				races, and we both had a private flying <sic>lisance</sic><corr>licence</corr>.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-797d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">Life at work is
				not to bad and promotion is not to far away, so I am happy at work and not thinking
				of changing any thing. At thirty two we have another child, this time a girl, and we
				name her Sue. We are feeling more energetic than ever now and we sell the house and
				move to a very large cottage in Devon and I get a new job as production engineer in
				a large engineering works. This job is more interesting because you get out a lot
				and your job covers larger ground. When I am forty seven my oldest son gets married
				and we all travel up to London for the weekend. It was a nice week and we get to see
				all the sights when we were first married. He marries a {illegible} young lady from
				up North who has just left the W.R.A.F. They settle down in rather the same
				conditions as we did, only William was a banker and was already in a high
				position.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-7a7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">After a happy
				working life I retire, reluctantly, to my cottage in Devon with my, still loving
				wife. I settle down to a life of fishing in the local streams and digging the
				garden. My wife continues to do the housework and we still enjoy each <sic>others</sic><corr>other's</corr>
				company, even though we are fairly old. At sixty seven we go to a party, as one of
				my school friends has died when his parachute did not open. He lived for much longer
				than he expected and as promised left some money for a party on the sad day. Now all
				my wife and I do is enjoy life until the end.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>