<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 120</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-fe5c96fb-7799-44ff-bcd7-0aa58f1e59de</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-108984f2-d51f-4a1e-9a48-8dd035d15e12</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-62805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Looking Back</note>
      <u xml:id="q-63805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">I decided to stay
				on at school at the age of 16, I took a Business studies course, I wanted to leave
				at 16 but the course was not available to me until I’d finished in the 5th year. The
				reason I wanted to leave at 16 was, I wanted to get a job and save up.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-64805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I was engaged at
				16 and my boyfriend Ian was saving and had been for nearly three years. I wanted to
				help him so that we could get a good place to live. We wouldn’t get married until we
				had a decent place.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-65805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">When I did
				eventually leave at 18 I started work, as a secretary, Ian wanted me to get a job in
				one of the <sic>london</sic><corr>London</corr> Transport offices, that was where he worked.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-66805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">When we <sic>finaly</sic><corr>finally</corr>
				had enough to get a decent flat in Wimbledon we got married and I moved jobs, I did
				work at London Transport just as he wanted.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-67805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">We carried on
				saving for two and a half years, and I fell pregnant with our first baby, Natalie.
				Our second child came along three years later, we called him Chris.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-68805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">It was a struggle
				for four or five years, as I couldn’t go to work but we managed. It was a nice break
				from working anyway.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-69805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">My parents died
				when I was about thirty my father died first. I used to think I couldn’t face life
				if Ian died first, but you have to, you’ve still got a few responsibilities when
				<sic>your</sic><corr>you're</corr> old.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-6a805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">I was very upset
				when my mother died we were always so close, but she was getting on so I was quite
				prepared for it.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-6b805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="10">Not much happened
				after that for about five years, then I had an unexpected visitor, a baby which we
				called Maria. I was pleased because the other two were now almost grown up and all
				the pleasures of them being toddlers were still in mind.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-6c805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="11">My first child
				got married at the age of 19 I was about 39 to 40 old then.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-6d805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="12">I was <sic>begining</sic><corr>beginning</corr>
				to feel old, 39 ½ sounded a lot younger than 40.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-6e805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="13">The years passed
				quicker after that and by the age of 52 all my children had left home and Ian
				eventually died and left me on my own.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-6f805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="14">I did OK though,
				Ian was insured and I still had my job not for long though, then I had to make do
				with my pension and the Insurance money.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-70805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="15">I was scared at
				nights after all the years of having somebody with me, also I got wary of young
				people, some were ok but others, well you heard so many stories of muggins and
				things, the last five years have been lonely, but my children and grandchildren, of
				which I have 10, still visit me. I suppose I’ll eventually go into a home for the
				rest of my days. But until then I’ll manage.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>