<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 18</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-fe7697b7-56bb-4de9-b9b4-debf282e22b3</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-59b03f6c-e070-4bb0-b544-01def8bef4f4</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-b77d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-b87d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">I stayed on at
				school until I was seventeen, the idea was to take more ‘o’ level examinations
				because the year before I only took one ‘o’ level. I wanted to be a racing driver
				and I realised if I failed I would need ‘o’ levels to try and find another job with.
				After leaving school at Seventeen I went for an apprenticeship as a mechanic. I was
				told by the motor racing school that I would need to know a lot about the mechanics
				of the car. While I was working I was trying to save some money but I just kept
				spending it with nights out with friends. About half way through my apprenticeship I
				began to realise that I would not be able to save all of the money required for my
				motor racing lessons. The only way I could get enough was to borrow money from
				someone, but who? I tried my father first and he said that if I could raise half the
				money I need I will pay the rest. I did eventually raise my half and began my
				lessons. At this time I was still living at home on the Isle of Sheppey, and my
				motor racing lessons were at Brands Hatch. I could not catch a bus or train to the
				circuit so my parents were driving me over, but they did not want to make a habit of
				this. I’d have to get a flat near to the circuit but I could not afford to run it
				myself I had to share with another driver but after about six <sic>monthes</sic><corr>months</corr> we fell out
				with each other. I had nearly finished my lessons but I decided to come back to the
				island and get a job as a full time mechanic.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b97d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">The money I had
				saved up was now almost gone, I went back to live at home. Until I came back I had
				hardly any social life in the evenings and it wasn’t long till I had a steady
				girlfriend and job. My girlfriend and I saved enough money to marry and move into a
				small house. We had two small children when we moved into a bigger house. Our
				original house was kept in very good condition by my wife and I, so it sold quickly.
				The new house we went into was a bit of a challenge, it needed a lot of time spent
				on it decorating, which we did on our own at weekends and any spare time we had. It
				took two years hard work to get the house how we wanted it. We decided we would know
				save up to go on a holiday abroad. We hadn’t had a good holiday since our honeymoon.
				We went with our two children for nine days in the South of France.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ba7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">Looking back it
				seems funny that I never bought a car before we moved house. I had passed my test,
				wanted to be a racing driver, and worked on cars all day long. I soon started up my
				own business as a mechanic but went in for selling d.i.v. goods mainly, this is what
				everyone wanted to save themselves money.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>