<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 138</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-03d5e288-2d7c-476d-b326-b964e04860ce</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-a043b06f-4416-4f77-aaf3-feefc1db176b</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-e8805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflecting</note>
      <u xml:id="q-e9805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">Today was my
				eighteenth birthday. Looking back on my life I reflected over all those years and
				what I had done with them.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ea805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">After leaving
				school at 17, I went for my first proper job. It was working for the ministry of
				Defence in London while at school I had visited the careers office several times, it
				was from there I obtained the information about the ministry of Defence, and by the
				time I had left school was pretty clear on what sort of work I would be doing.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-eb805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">After working
				there as a clerical officer for a few years I decided that it wasn’t really my sort
				of work. So I started to think about becoming a nurse, something I would have liked
				to have done from a child.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ec805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">A few months
				after leaving I started training to be a nurse, my five ‘o’ levels which I had
				acquired were <sic>helpfull</sic><corr>helpful</corr>. This work I found more to my <sic>likeing</sic><corr>liking</corr> because it involved
				people, and not just sitting around in an office all day.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ed805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">Five months after
				starting my training I was married at 20. I found it difficult at first carrying on
				my training and having a husband. Finally three years training I became a fully
				qualified nurse, and also a mother. I was a bit depressed at first, I remember after
				all I had been <sic>sloging</sic><corr>slogging</corr> away for three years to become a nurse, then I became one and
				had to give it up. But when I saw <sic>there</sic><corr>their</corr> faces I didn’t mind so much.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ee805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">After three years
				I went back to work, by this time I found it a <sic>releaf</sic><corr>relief</corr> to get out. I found the work
				more interesting then when I had left it, because I had no worries. The children
				were at nursery school, and my husband at work as a builder we had a lovely home,
				and I felt very happy. Life carried on like this until I retired, after sending my
				children out into the world.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ef805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">Life had
				basically been good to me, apart from a few ups and downs.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>