<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 28</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-28247a4b-a833-454c-8926-12bb3c1a9e51</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-28c528c9-5de7-413d-8c6d-0956036b3f96</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-ed7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Memories</note>
      <u xml:id="q-ee7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">Here I am now at
				the end of my career, I collect the much coveted present for forty two whole <sic>years</sic><corr>years'</corr>
				service to the Fire Brigade the day after tomorrow. Following much in the path of my
				older brother who also was a Fireman now retired. I can still remember vividly the
				day it all started…</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ef7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I <sic>teared</sic><corr>tore</corr> open the
				envelope anxiously, impatiently waiting to study the actual results of my exams. A
				big grin shot across my face as I saw English Language ‘B pass’ and then Maths ‘C
				pass’, my chin then hit the floor when I read ‘Physics D fail’. I knew then it would
				be another year at school to try to obtain the physics ‘o’ level I needed to become
				an apprentice as an electrical engineer. After much studying I scrapped a ‘C pass’
				and then began the electrical engineers course in the September of ’79. I will never
				forget the day I walked out of school never to return, it was one of the <sic>sadest</sic><corr>saddest</corr> days
				of my life. I knew I had to change all of my present friends and make new ones.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f07d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">With not much
				success at electrical engineering I left the <sic>apprenticship</sic><corr>apprenticeship</corr> very disappointed, as the
				unemployment situation was grave I was left with little hope of employment. Then on
				a visit to my brothers he persuaded me that I should have a ‘crack’ at the Fire
				Service. So with little else to do I applied with success, and realised perhaps this
				was what I was looking for, a job with exciting prospects.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f17d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">I was twenty two
				years of age when I became a fully qualified Fireman, I now had a flat of my own, a
				small motor-cycle to get me about, plenty of girlfriends and I was really enjoying
				life. I was now living in the heart of London away from the increasingly boring Isle
				of Sheppey.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f27d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">A few years later
				I decided that perhaps it was time I settled down, got married and live in a house.
				A girl I had been seeing for a long time seemed to be the right choice for me, so I
				married her and I sold the flat for a nice profit and moved in to a beautiful house
				on the out-skirts of London.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f37d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">Soon after I
				became a proud father of twins, and so more money was needed so I studied extremely
				hard for promotion and with a lot of success. Everything was going perfectly when my
				mother and father died in the short space of two years. Life had to go on and I
				celebrated the beginning of a new century in real style. Life seemed to slow down by
				now and I was gradually watching my children grow up and eventually leave home to
				start off their own lives.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f47d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">I was now a
				governor of a Fire station with nothing else to look forward to but a few more <sic>years</sic><corr>years'</corr>
				service, and a nice pension at the end of it all. I now have my own car, own house
				and a loving wife.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-f57d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">Well the day has
				come, I now get up for the last time to go to work, a very sad day but the rest will
				be very much appreciated.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>