<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 55</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-ff7cc6b4-ab5e-445d-81dc-16f83a66e4dc</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-1b0ea441-0c9d-4d99-973c-9387083a28e2</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-677e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflecting my past</note>
      <u xml:id="q-687e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">At the age of
				fifteen I was worrying about my exams. But when they did finally come they went all
				right in between time while they exams were coming up I would visit the <sic>carreers</sic><corr>careers</corr>
				office to find out if there was any more application for apprentice engineers or
				motor mechanic. The next thing was my interviews all of these went well and I think
				I pleased every firm. Then my sixteen birthday came which was {fun?} a couple of
				mates came round and we had a drink and played snooker a couple of days later I
				<sic>recieved</sic><corr>received</corr> my results of my cse exams. They were maths 3, English 3, physical science
				3, local studies, 2, Art 2, metal work 2, tech drawing 3, so overall I was pleased
				then on the 30th of August I received a letter. I opened it and read through it. I
				began to smile the letter said I had <sic>suceeded</sic><corr>succeeded</corr> in the interview at Bowaters and had
				got the job as apprentice vehicle mechanic at the lorry yard and could I start my
				course on the 2nd September 1978.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-697e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">On the 2nd I went
				to Sittingbourne at the Bowater lorry depot and me my boss and workmates then after
				we had dinner we had a talk about weather I had any transport as the first year will
				be off the job training. I told him I had more. So I took the train journey to
				Maidstone so he could show me where to go when we got there he introduced me to some
				lecturers and told me I would either travel each day or get lodging and I suggested
				I might be able to stay at my sister and brother-in laws place. I got things sorted
				out and the first year went <sic>realy</sic><corr>really</corr> quick and in the test at college I done <sic>realy</sic><corr>really</corr>
				well. Then I started training at the yard itself. When my seventeenth birthday came
				my mum and dad had brought me a second hand mini so this was my year to be but I
				failed my first test but got through on the second go. The next three years went
				quick and only 1 bad thing happened and that was when I was working on an engine and
				I fell and twisted my ankle really badly which put me out for a couple of
				months.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-6a7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">Then the day came
				when I had served my full four years as an apprentice and I received my sitting
				guilds and the certificate to say I had served my apprenticeship. Then I went onto
				the workshop floor for the next day as a mechanic along with the other mechanics
				that were already there. When I was twenty two I got married to Jenny and we moved
				to Sittingbourne. The at 35 I was made assistant mechanic then I served Ten years as
				that then at forty five I was made chief mechanic then I stayed as chief mechanic
				until 65.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>