<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 17</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-8c880be2-5ec1-4ea5-8329-832ccb67857b</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-60f75ca7-64d0-482d-a02f-9ee9b51305ac</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-a37d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-a47d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">I like to watch
				the kids play across the road in the park. It gives me a sense of satisfaction, not
				that they realise it mind. There too locked up in their own fantasies to a dam
				anyway, shut away in their private worlds of solitude, free from the arms of
				reality. They <sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr> know how lucky they are. But <sic>lets</sic><corr>let's</corr> face it, they <sic>dont</sic><corr>don't</corr> care anyway,
				well why the hell should they? It’s not their turn to suffer; not yet.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-a57d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">They will
				realise, as I did all those years ago, that time is not the illusion that they have
				created within themselves, when it can free its self, it will burn them first, then
				run away.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-a67d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">Maybe I was like
				them once; not so free though, I think they have love, neighbours, perhaps a little
				honesty. Me? Well I was alone, unafraid yes but alone, and it hated me and I it,
				because like time it burned me. It still does.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-a77d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">I remember, now,
				how I stood at a similar window, oh forty five years ago at least, on my last day at
				school in fact. I watched the cars leak, on that particular day and I hid myself
				away from the tears that those so much entangled with the place, shed as their last
				friend {sieved?!} through the gate.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-a87d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">Mine had gone, <sic>to</sic><corr>too</corr>
				soon I thought, but my inclination meant nothing, they were only whispers after all,
				to quiet to burst into reality; and no-one heard them.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-a97d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">The cold floor
				made me shudder on that day. Funny how it hadn’t before. I was sixteen and faced
				with nothing, only a hearse of a life that would eventually lead me to the cemetery
				gates. I didn’t want to go, and I fought time in vain and I was shoved into the big
				bad world that called me.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-aa7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">I had
				contemplated suicide. It was away, as I had explained to a friend, she begged me to
				reconsider, I did. I loved her.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ab7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">I still remember
				her name. Simple, but <sic>meaningfull</sic><corr>meaningful</corr> if you know what I mean. God knows I didn’t think
				I’d survive without her. But well, I managed didn’t I. She saved my life, I hadn’t
				expected it at first, but her actions cheered me, I fought, I won. I thanked
				her.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ac7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="10">Then I was faced
				with real life and it’s lust for my innocence. How I hated it, but I could not
				conquer it. It urged me on. My first job was meaningless and obscure, but I
				tolerated it’s meagreness for my own sake because it offered a hint of salvation
				from the obscurity of my inner self.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ad7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="11">Packing crates,
				that was it. Hundreds of them, day after day. Straw, cups, straw saucers and my
				hands wept with the sweat of my labours and the offensiveness that surrounded them.
				There was, again, no satisfaction, no streak of content, biting me, no memories able
				to save me, and I sacrificed my last ounce of sanity for a measly 20 pounds a week.
				Hell, I <sic>earnt</sic><corr>earned</corr> it. Those crates were so heavy, a burden, took two of us and a lot of
				stress and strain to shift them, but we managed.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ae7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="12">Complication was
				my shroud, my continual oppressor. Christ I tried to escape it, and, thus learn from
				my mistakes, but it was hopeless. I was a fly caught in a wed of incrimination that
				starved me of my right to be free, until I no longer expected it.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-af7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="13">I tried again,
				and my second job was better. A news reporter for a small local paper that paid me
				only on delivery. It was hard, but strangely, rewarding. I ate myself and rested
				within the concepts of my new found occupation and I worked damm bloody hard to get
				to the top of the pole. I succeeded. Barely.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b07d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="14">When I was 20. I
				moved on, totally unconvinced that small time obscurities could satisfy my appetite
				for power. I joined a national paper and met my wife.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b17d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="15">Her father
				worked for himself, well equipped to succeed in his line of work. Decorating.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b27d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="16">I thought I
				loved her, maybe I did, I could only love once, I surmized with such a total honest
				sincerity. Why? I don’t know. The answer would not aid me.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b37d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="17">We had three
				kids, they’ve all left now, gone forever, to strive like I have. <sic>Shes</sic><corr>she's</corr> dead. Must be
				ten years ago now. Motor accident that killed her. <sic>Shes</sic><corr>she's</corr> safe now though.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b47d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="18">The paper
				carried me. Through my whole life I wanted something. I didn’t know what. I know I
				haven’t found it.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b57d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="19">That it really.
				Not much is it. Those kids playing now are <sic>tomorrows</sic><corr>tomorrow's</corr> losers, but they’ve time to
				work things out, think and plan ahead. They have got a chance; it’s a <sic>dam</sic><corr>damn</corr> shame
				really.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b67d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="20">Here am I,
				locked away in my room, house, my home, and the clock of life is still ticking, but
				it slowly wanes, and very soon, it will cease to <sic>exsist</sic><corr>exist</corr>; gone, <sic>forgotton</sic><corr>forgotten</corr>, with
				no-one to care, and no-one to member. That clock is really me, its just a
				reflection. This is, perhaps, my last message to the world, and, like before, no-one
				has heard.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>