<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 88(b)</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-c89bb525-d7ad-4a03-a37f-db89238f74b2</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-f262f677-1cec-4622-821a-640656e1930b</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-567f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflecting</note>
      <u xml:id="q-577f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">Looking back on
				the years of my life which started at the age of 15 1978. I can remember it was a
				nice year with the summer flowers just blooming. In the months to <sic>came</sic><corr>come</corr> I was
				searching for a job which could <sic>satisfie</sic><corr>satisfy</corr> me this took some time and by then I had
				made many friends. After many cold winters and job going well, I got married to a
				person who I would call ideal.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-587f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">Then after being
				married for several years money was coming in well but the years before had been bad
				with many people being made redundant, my husband being one of those life became
				more exciting and my husband and I had twins they were grand chaps James and mark
				was their names. We had to buy a better place to live in as the place we were living
				in was only two rooms. After looking around for some time we moved into this place a
				grand old place was it then and <sic>quiet</sic><corr>quite</corr> modern. It was good in those days with all the
				countryside around yah and the people that did live near where good friends of yours
				to, but life went on and with the house and children to look after I couldn’t go out
				to work.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-597f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">Years went by and
				the twins grow up and I got old and by this time I couldn’t have any more children.
				My husband who was a keen musician left his disco <sic>acwipment</sic><corr>equipment</corr> to <sic>are</sic><corr>our</corr> son James who
				took after his father who by this time had retired and my husband and I decided that
				we would go on a short holiday to get away from the house, a short while after me
				son Mark got married and his with Kathy was expecting a child. Whilst my other son
				James was not even thinking of getting married, my husband and I only talked about
				the past and how grand it has been.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>