<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 130</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-67c282a4-9485-4909-90ef-1bf0093d0c0e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-43bee4bd-ce78-4bb3-9781-aac0782eef50</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-b2805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflecting</note>
      <u xml:id="q-b3805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">When I was
				fifteen I dreamed about being a good hairdresser so that it could lead on to better
				things. I hated school but I didn’t really want to leave. Like a lot of us I was
				scared but I knew I had to leave at some time so I left at the end of the 5th year.
				I started work in a small hairdressing salon with a very low wage and doing all the
				jobs no-one else wanted to do. I often thought of giving it up and working in a
				factory but I know? Couldn’t do that. The thing I hated most was going to college
				one every week. While I was at school I really dreaded doing the <sic>apprentaship</sic><corr>apprenticeship</corr> and
				thought the time would drag by but it didn’t and soon I was a qualified hairdresser.
				I was offered a job in a large salon and the pay was good.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b4805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I got married
				when I was 23 to someone with a fair bit of money.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b5805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">We never had any
				children and I continued working until I had enough money to open a salon of my
				own.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b6805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">My aim was to
				take as many juniors as I could because through my own experience I found it
				difficult to get a job with a manager willing to train me. After we trained a lot of
				apprentices I started taking on regular staff. I had a fantastic house with <sic>every thing</sic><corr>everything</corr> I’d ever wanted in it. This was partly the reason I never had any children, I
				didn’t want everything messed up. Another was that I didn’t like them. My husband
				and I lead our own lives and only occasionally went out together. We didn’t have
				rows because we didn’t see that much of each other. He knew I only married him for
				his money and accepted it. We mostly went around with our own groups of friends
				meeting different people. We might as well not have got married really but we never
				thought about it at the time.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-b7805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">He died when he
				was 45 and though we never behaved like we were married I missed him more than I
				ever thought I would, but then I was always like that I never really wanted anything
				until it was gone. Just like the salon after I retired and sold it I missed it but
				still have the house which is my most treasured possession. I’m not <sic>affraid</sic><corr>afraid</corr> of dying
				in fact a I’ve always looked forward to it and I do believe there’s something after
				death otherwise living’s not worth it.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>