<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd"
	xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 144</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-26fa7363-73b4-45e6-8887-b51b7df241d8</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-b630607f-36d5-4235-818f-206b416b3cdf</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<note xml:id="q-b465e5fb-0a7d-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1"
				>Reflections</note>
			<u xml:id="q-b565e5fb-0a7d-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">67, what an age to be,
				no work to do because you’ve been retired. The family’s up and left, and i'm all on
				my own. There’s all these young people going past the window all day long without a
				care in the world. Just think I used to be like that, before I got the job. Going
				out whenever the weather permitted and staying in when it didn’t. Going out for the
				whole days on the bikes, great bunches of us, and arriving home at night.</u>
			<u xml:id="q-b665e5fb-0a7d-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">But things all changed
				when I got myself a job. My whole attitude to life changed I was more careful about
				what I spent my money on and not just wasting it on silly things, I cared about the
				way I looked in the eyes of other people, I made sure that I always wore smart
				clothes to work, not jeans and T-shirts or jumpers all the time.</u>
			<u xml:id="q-b765e5fb-0a7d-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">Of course, I still used
				to go out but I never stayed out quite as late as before, although my parents never
				knew at what time I ever arrived home because I had a flat at that time which was
				all my own. Well I didn’t ever fancy the thought of sharing with anyone.</u>
			<u xml:id="q-b865e5fb-0a7d-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">But of course things
				all changed and I had reached the age of 26 I was engaged and had been for a few
				years, this was because we were saving up for a for house and the houses when I was
				that age were quite expensive for us, but when I look at the prices now and look
				back to how much they were when we were saving, it makes me wonder how the young
				people of today manage. I know that we did, although it did take some time. Then
				when we did get the house I had to leave my job because I had him and the house to
				look after, and i’ve looked after them up until the present day.</u>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
