<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 40</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-489fac1a-a752-44d3-a870-876be3c7bb35</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-b841d4b0-356a-4a39-8b4d-35e47d41cbaf</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-1a7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-1b7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">I left school
				when I was sixteen and then I worked at Chatham Dockyard as an apprentice Electrical
				fitter and I turned out to be a good job and I ended up getting a lot out of it,
				when I was eighteen I got a brand new ford escort popular, this was a nice car, I
				end up changing my car 3 times, I got married to Chris carter, she was twenty three
				when I got married and she was a really nice woman. We bought a house in <sic>crawley</sic><corr>Crowley</corr> and
				lived happy there for many years, we had children when I was 27 and we had twins.
				Every Christmas, and bank holidays we visited mum and dad, I suppose mum and dad
				missed me. We went on holiday about 4 times. During my married life, I made a lot of
				new friends at the dockyard and eventually got to be foreman there getting over a
				hundred pounds a week, now I am in retirement, now my two sons are forty, one is a
				worker at sheerness steel and the other is in <sic>iran</sic><corr>Iran</corr> working for British aerospace. My
				life has had its good and bad times but altogether a good life, my mum lived to 88
				and dad to 79 they both had good times. My sister is 58, married with 3
				daughters.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>