<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 27</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-99f3609b-8d3c-451f-a3a5-da26bf292e7a</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-917e2216-169d-41fa-9a60-1a9a47bedaf4</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-e77d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">My Past</note>
      <u xml:id="q-e87d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">{Crossed out
				plan}</u>
      <u xml:id="q-e97d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">Plan: Left school
				16. Job. Apprentice 21 Finish apprenticeship, get job off the island. Get married,
				raise family. Get <sic>morga</sic><corr>mortgage</corr>. Buy own home.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ea7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">I left the
				Sheppey School in the summer of 1978. I found this school more boring every year. I
				did not agree with some of the teachers attitudes. It was hard finding a job, I
				failed a few chances, but eventually got what I wanted locally, a craft
				apprenticeship. I done a four year apprenticeship, the money was not spectacular,
				but it was worth it in the long run.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-eb7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">When I finished
				my apprenticeship I got a job away from home. The money was a lot better and I was
				able to get my own home. My craze on motorcycling never wore off, and I often was
				off for weekends on my machine. When I was in my mid-<sic>twentys</sic><corr>twenties</corr> I started <sic>too</sic><corr>to</corr> settle
				down and get married. My wife and I decided not <sic>too</sic><corr>to</corr> have children immediately, we
				had a good time while we could, before we were tied down with our children. I was
				always worried about my children, educational wise. I wanted them <sic>too</sic><corr>to</corr> have a better
				education than I had. My wife is quite bright and sensible, and has a smashing
				personality. She also likes a good ride.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ec7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">I am just coming
				up for retirement now. I am looking forward <sic>too</sic><corr>to</corr> retiring, I will be able <sic>too</sic><corr>to</corr> spend
				more time with my children and grandchildren. I have stayed with the same firm all
				my life. I think when I die I will want <sic>too</sic><corr>to</corr> be <sic>crimated</sic><corr>cremated</corr>. I have enjoyed my life. I
				have lived it how I wanted too. I have had a few worries in life but I have enjoyed
				it. I hope my children or grandchildren don’t put me in a home.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>