<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 118</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-466e318c-98b7-4fdf-9b3b-efdf9abe8642</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-cb71d95a-4a74-45da-95e1-45b5e62fc684</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-50805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Looking back</note>
      <u xml:id="q-51805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">In the summer of
				1978, at the age of 16, I left school, I had been courting steady for nearly two
				years, and had plans to get engaged in the near future. I was lucky enough to have a
				summer job to go into, and if no job came up for me elsewhere, I had the <sic>oppertunity</sic><corr>opportunity</corr>
				to stay on. At the <sic>begining</sic><corr>beginning</corr> the following year I became engaged, and was accepted in
				another job, which liked a lot. My job went smoothly, and <sic>withen</sic><corr>within</corr> 3 years I was
				promoted, by this time I was nearly 20 and very pleased at getting a higher position
				with more responsibility. In the spring of 1982 I was married, and had gone in for
				our own house. I now had more responsibility. Another year went by and I had had my
				first of many children. At 25 I was the mother of a baby girl and had to give up my
				job, to look after the baby. I stayed at home until the baby could go to playschool
				and then got a part-time, <sic>withen</sic><corr>within</corr> another year I was expecting again, this time
				twins! I was nearly 31 by this time and had just my house for a bigger one, once
				again I gave up work and stayed at home. Once all 3 children were at school I began
				a full time job again, and went on a holiday for the first time in years alone with
				my husband, The eldest of the children was 14 when at 36 I went into hospital for an
				operation on my arm, so she became the mother and had to cook and clean, she soon
				began courting, and before I knew it, was married at the age of 19. At the age of
				45; I became a Grandmother and started to take my grandson out for walks. I gave up
				my job and again began a part time one, the twins were now making wedding plans and
				had a double wedding. For the first time since I met my husband I felt lost, at the
				age of 49, I had no children around me and wished I had had more when I was younger,
				my husband was now all I had, and we were very happy together.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-52805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I had 5
				grandchildren at the age of 60, the eldest being 15, the youngest being 4. The only
				enjoyment my husband had, now that he had retired was his grandchildren, and day
				after day was spent just sitting playing and making children laugh. My eldest
				grandchild is now making plans to get engaged, and I hope she has a happy 65 years
				as I had. My husband died soon after he was 70, and I was in a home where I get
				regular visits from my grandchildren.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>