<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 93</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-a56a174b-c7d1-48e8-90b2-331d2e547de1</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-10992628-7ada-4e32-a84e-42f290534c9f</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-6e7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-6f7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">I left school at
				sixteen- I was slightly under sixteen actually with five o’levels. I had provisional
				entry to the College of Technology at Maidstone and only needed four o’levels to get
				in.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-707f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I went to college
				and spent two years doing a Business Studies course. I had a good time there- it was
				a lovely place- and left with an Ordinary National Diploma in Business Studies. This
				opened up many possibilities for me, such as managerial schemes run by firms,
				accountancy, banking and so on. All I wanted to be was a personal secretary so I
				applied for posts in Maidstone and Sheerness. I did think of London but it was too
				far to travel and I didn’t fancy living in.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-717f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">Anyway I got the
				job in Sheerness at the Olau Line ferry company as a junior secretary. I left there
				after nearly a year and went to work as a personal secretary in Maidstone.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-727f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">It was here that
				I met my husband. I had been working there for over a year when I met him. He’d been
				with the turn for a couple of years and had just been promoted.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-737f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">We started going
				out together and after about a year we got married.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-747f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">I didn’t give up
				work altogether but took a part time job with the firm instead.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-757f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">That had to stop,
				though, when we had our first child, Christine. She was a lovely little baby and
				really looked like her dad.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-767f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">She was two when
				Michael came along.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-777f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="10">By this time our
				house was getting crowded and rather than move, we decided to extend. That done, we
				had another boy. When he was five my husband prompted me to take another job so I
				did.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-787f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="11">The kids grew up
				really fast and it seemed like no time until Chris got married. She was 22 and at 25
				had her first child, my first grandchild.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-797f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="12">Mike remained
				single until he was nearly 29 because he had joined the Navy. However, he got
				married and provided me with grandchildren, as well.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-7a7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="13">Chris and her
				husband had another girl and decided to limit the family to two.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-7b7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="14">Actually we did
				talk over the possibility of having another child ourselves but decided not to
				because, as my husband put it, we couldn’t stand all that again!</u>
      <u xml:id="q-7c7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="15">By this time the
				other boy John was doing very well for himself. He had become area manager to some
				firm or other and was working very hard. He got married at 26 and had a family of
				his own.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-7d7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="16">Now my first
				grandchild was nearly 10 and the other were growing up fast!</u>
      <u xml:id="q-7e7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="17">Now I sit here
				with them all around me at the ripe old age of 69 and remenise. I can remember
				little facts that I thought I had forgotten, over the years.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>