<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 136</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-1940d82b-2fe9-4601-b7f2-0ca832790296</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-8b79d57e-b89b-4afd-aec3-7a6d0343029b</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-d7805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflecting</note>
      <u xml:id="q-d8805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">At thirteen I
				started to think seriously about my career. I was taking O level exams in Biology,
				English, French and maths, and C.S.E.s in Economics, Geography, Dance and English
				Literature. I passed all of the ‘o’levels with a lot of help from teachers, and
				attained grade two’s and three’s from the C.S.E.s</u>
      <u xml:id="q-d9805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">Up until I left
				school I had thought about a career in a bank, so I had several interviews with the
				careers officer to find out if there was anything going, not too far away. The
				careers officer was very helpful, she found many places offering jobs to school
				leavers with a training college to go to twice a week.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-da805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">I applied to five
				banks, and got an appointment for an interview with four of them. Of course, the
				interviews were very “nerve-racking”, but I got through them and was accepted at two
				of the banks. One of the banks gave a good salary plus luncheon vouchers, and a good
				training college which was not too far away. But the other bank had a training
				centre which was further away and they gave a smaller salary, so I chose the first,
				Barclays.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-db805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">I enjoyed the
				work at the bank and after three years of college I worked full time at the bank.
				But I would never have made it without the help of teachers and the careers
				officer.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-dc805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">I soon got a
				steady boyfriend and after two years we got engaged. We agreed that when we were
				married I would give up my job at the bank, because we thought we could live well
				enough on the money Phillip brought home as an Electrical fitter.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-dd805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">Phillip and I got
				married after one and a half years and had a son Mark. We lived very well as a
				family, now my husband is retired and my son is married with two children.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>