<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 15</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-86083e7a-a411-4a44-b43b-3ca584f90e3f</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-638e25a8-1100-4c74-ab49-5f45c1508c77</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u xml:id="q-927d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="1">Looking back on
				my past I have few regrets, I know that if I had my time all over again it would be
				no different. People say the teens are the best time of your life, no worries or
				responsibilities, how wrong they are. Firstly I remember the conflicts between my
				parents and I, and how they thought I didn’t care about my future, they were so very
				wrong. They couldn’t understand how much I worried about getting a decent job, and
				that stomach pain that you had when you failed that test for the career you had been
				counting on.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-937d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">The teachers were
				only doing their job and they didn’t care whether you got the job or not, and it was
				the same after school as well, when I left, people would ask how you were getting
				on, but they didn’t really care, what was it to them if I was penniless with a
				dismal future.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-947d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">Another worry was
				the girls, you couldn’t concentrate on much for long without thinking about that
				dishy bird sitting opposite, and how you’d like to get off with that.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-957d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">When I eventually
				got a decent job and settled down with a nice girl, there were the problems of that
				smarmy bloke getting with that managerial job you’d been hoping to get promoted
				to.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-967d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">Oh yes, there
				were good times as well, like when you find out your wife has just had a lovely baby
				boy, and you win a couple of grand on the horses, which was just enough to add to
				your savings to put a deposit on that new six bedroomed house.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-977d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">But now, I’ve
				made a lot of money and I’ve no need to work for the rest of my days, but money
				isn’t everything, sometimes I wonder what would’ve happened if I hadn’t been lucky
				in business, if I didn’t make the money I had now. Would I be like my school friend
				Mark who is still working at the factory job he found when he was sixteen and how
				lucky I thought he was to take home £40 a week although we’re probably equally as
				happy now.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-987d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">Now I’ve only to
				see my grandchildren running around me, to make me happy, and only death to look
				forward to. But my children will never have to graft like I did, at least I’ve got
				the money to give them and <sic>thats</sic><corr>that's</corr> one thing <sic>Marks</sic><corr>Mark's</corr> children will never have.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>