<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 126</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-51c09529-cbef-45c1-b864-51e46a03e50d</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-833a6ac7-f4e6-4484-9e13-2b6fc3dde28d</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-93805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">My Past</note>
      <u xml:id="q-94805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">At nineteen I
				left school after my exams were over in June.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-95805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">In September of
				1978 I started my first job as a mechanical fitter at a nearby garage.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-96805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">I was employed to
				fix cars and in all aspects of the job I succeeded. At the age of twenty I finished
				my four year apprenticeship and continued at the garage for another four years until
				I saved up enough money to buy a small holding about ten miles from my first
				house.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-97805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">I left the garage
				that year and established my own garage after about six months hard work and
				business started coming in quick.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-98805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">By the age of
				thirty I had built my own extension onto the garage and was now employing three full
				time mechanics which included one driver for the rescue service and one for the
				motorcycle shop on the premises.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-99805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">That year I got
				married and my wife was kept busy as a personal secretary, as well as a housekeeper.
				We had a four bedroomed detached house at the back of the garage and two acres of
				land as well. A year later my wife gave birth to twins, boys, and she then had her
				hands full with housework.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-9a805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">By that time I
				had a few thousand stashed away even though we were living well.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-9b805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">At the age of
				forty even my two sons left school, one of them became an apprentice electrician at
				the dockyard and the other worked as a bank clerk. Five years later I had earnt
				enough money to sell up and retire. I bought myself a camper van and a little two
				bedroom bungalow just down the road. I sold up the garage, complete with the house
				and put it all into the bank, the money I earnt.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-9c805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="10">After selling up
				the business my wife and I went on a world cruise then settled down to a quiet
				retirement. My two sons got married at twenty and twenty one and went to live abroad
				with their aunts.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-9d805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="11">My wife and I
				went touring. In the summer and the rest of the time was spent in the garden, house
				or at friend’s houses.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-9e805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="12">At sixty five my
				wife died of cancer and now I live on my own, with my memories and my house and
				home.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>