<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 97</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-7fcb5df6-9e1c-4664-bd38-e4bf014ed686</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-d7c8b623-75dd-4d4f-971e-2f5b4f774d31</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-987f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-997f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">As I reflect back
				on my past, I think I feel contented that my life served its purpose well and was
				not one of sheer tragic disaster.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-9a7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I left school in
				1979 with five CSE all of average grades and qualifications in commercial studies. I
				found my first job as a copy typist in the local factory in a tiny office with old
				tables as the desk. The pay wasn’t particularly good but it was the <sic>expiereance</sic><corr>experience</corr> that
				I was after not the money.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-9b7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">That job however
				lasted 3 months and I found myself looking very hard for another which I feel was
				the first real stop in my life. It was then that I realised that I had truly left
				school and all its security and I was now to face the big outside world and take
				life and its problems as a mature adult.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-9c7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">Another emotional
				stage was the fact that I was engaged to my boyfriend whom I loved dearly. Although
				some thought it a bit young, we had been going steady for two years and clearly knew
				what we were doing and knew that we could never be apart. My fiance’s parents ran a
				successful lorry business and after a short time I went to work as a secretary
				there. At first I didn’t like the idea of working with family, but as it expanded I
				was working for other directors while my future in-laws sat back and enjoyed the
				money. This time in my life was spent saving every <sic>penney</sic><corr>penny</corr> going until we could
				afford a deposit on a house. This I think I took a very childishly mainly due to the
				excitement of getting married and I didn’t really understand the financial side of
				the affair.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-9d7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">We eventually
				found a flat, which was very large and modern and I found great delight in
				decorating it just how I wanted. It was then that I felt really an adult even though
				I jumped about like a five yr old opening his Christmas presents.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-9e7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">After a few
				months we set about making wedding plans. My wedding was something special and with
				the money my father-in-law gave us we had a wonderful two week honeymoon in Southern
				Spain.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-9f7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">When we returned
				I settled at once into being the model housewife and after a year of <sic>marrige</sic><corr>marriage</corr> I
				longed for a baby.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-a07f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">By this time my
				husband had gone into his father’s business as a director and money was coming in
				quite fast. We had moved into a cosy house and so I fell for a baby. Giving birth to
				my daughter was a very painful and emotional part of my life. When I held her for
				the first time and saw how happy I had made my husband, I felt very proud and
				content with my precious gift.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-a17f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="10">The next few
				years as I watched her grow up, got us past the ups and downs as our finances
				increased and decreased.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-a27f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="11">The business
				fell so bad that I had to go back to work in an office in a solicitors to bring in
				extra money.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-a37f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="12">When things
				finally shot up again I was able to have another child. This time I gave birth to a
				bouncing boy who although a little devil grew up to be a “mummys boy” and a
				proudness in his <sic>fathers</sic><corr>father's</corr> eye. My husband felt reluctant to let my daughter grow up
				as he needed to mother her but when he saw her in her bridal gown he realised how
				much life we had both seen together and we concentrated on living life for us and
				when we watched our grandchildren grow up we both felt contented and continued to
				grow old still as much in love as the day we got engaged, or as I feel when we left
				school and grew up.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>