<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd"
	xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
				<title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 146</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
				<idno type="qudexsource">q-bdafe763-94b2-4421-935b-7af6017af1b2</idno>
				<idno type="qudexdocument">q-334dac4f-1efe-46a9-b4e8-e6f657e6bc79</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<note xml:id="q-c265e5fb-0a7d-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1"
				>Reflections</note>
			<u xml:id="q-c365e5fb-0a7d-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">I am now sixty seven
				years old, when I look back over my life three aspects of my life seem the most
				important, first - I left school at seventeen to work as a costing clerk in a
				factory. It was a good job with plenty of scope for promotion. My tasks were
				interesting I met people from all walks of life, my work included typing shorthand
				filing and other office duties. To me my job was all I wanted as a career, and the
				people I met <sic>seamed</sic><corr>seemed</corr> to enjoy their work and life. I learnt to drive and my car was
				the first thing I saved up for from my wages. When I had enough money to buy my car
				it <sic>ment</sic><corr>meant</corr> <sic>alot</sic><corr>a lot</corr> to me, it was the <sic>simble</sic><corr>symbol</corr> of the money which I had earned during my
				first two or three years of employment. The second most important thing in my life,
				was getting married. I carried on working for a couple of years after getting
				married, trying to save up enough money to put down on a mortgage for a house. This
				was the most important thing I had ever saved for, which we could bring children up
				in.</u>
			<u xml:id="q-c465e5fb-0a7d-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">The house was small but
				modern, a typical town house was small but modern, a typical town house on a new
				estate, it was home. After working for the money for a house we decided to start a
				family. We had two children a boy and girl with two years difference between the
				two. Now they have left home, they both have good jobs and families. Now we wonder
				when we will become grandparents, to us this is very <sic>impertant</sic><corr>important</corr> it will make us feel
				young again, just like when we had our own.</u>
			<u xml:id="q-c565e5fb-0a7d-e311-a968-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">The third most
				important aspect of my life, was <sic>retireing</sic><corr>retiring</corr>. We had saved up enough money during the
				years, to sell our town house and to buy a cottage in the country, (this is a dream
				most people have). Here we are now living it is small but <sic>plesent</sic><corr>pleasant</corr> and we are both
				quite happy. We still have hobbies I enjoy doing part-time typing for a small <sic>locial</sic><corr>local</corr>
				firm, and my husband enjoys golf and fishing. We still go on holidays abroad and to
				us they are very important. One day I hope to go on a world <sic>cruse</sic><corr>cruise</corr>, to see the sights
				that I have always wanted to see during my life, and to live out the rest of my days
				enjoying life and everything it has to offer.</u>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
