<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 38</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-8dd59208-5525-4df9-b4dd-9e8138831c0b</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-51a9a307-8a5a-4a14-9f07-b6d7d386a1d4</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-167e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">My Past</note>
      <u xml:id="q-177e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">One Sunday
				afternoon whilst lazing around the Garden in my deck chair saw myself. Way back over
				50 years I was going to work, my life was exactly the opposite of what I wanted. I
				had a job that wasn’t worth a spit in eye, and I’ve never had car since I’ve been
				married. Which is 48 years I have 2 sons 3 daughters and 6 grandchildren, When I was
				30 I was made foreman and the hours went down and wages went to £80. My job by the
				way is at Keresley paper mill shift work, I met my wife whilst sitting in the pub
				and after a while we got engaged and about three years later we got married. I lost
				one of my best mates in a car crash when we were drunk, I was 43 we brought our
				house a bungalow in Leysdown and we’ve lived there ever since that day. But the day
				came when I started to feel old and. My racing pigeons got more <sic>envolved</sic><corr>involved</corr>, Right
				until the Mill shut down. I got made redundant and collected £14,000 redundancy
				money plus my pension, we are ending our lives happily as best we can. But when I
				look back it wasn’t as bad as I thought after all, I had a wife a house and money in
				my pocket.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>