<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 115</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-983cf834-57f1-47d9-ba1c-33e8b2220c4c</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-9ebd7526-0fdd-4b53-8a59-e1857ea3cacd</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-35805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">My Past</note>
      <u xml:id="q-36805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">As I look out of
				my window and see my grandchildren playing in the big playing field, I wonder if
				their life would be like mine. I doubt it very much. Things seem to change over the
				years I never grew up like my mother. She was so different from me.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-37805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">When I left
				school I lived with my stepmother, my real mother left all of us children and my
				father when I was twelve then my father when I was twelve then my father died two
				years later. So I was left with a step-mother. When I left school I had no
				qualifications although I went in for quite a lot. I failed everything, but I got a
				good grade in art. Which wasn’t much use. I went straight on the dole for a couple
				of months until my brother got me a job with him in a garage. I wasn’t any mechanic
				just a petrol pump attendant. I stayed there for a few years because I liked the
				job. I was quite contented to get a job and to get on well with the people I worked
				with. It wasn’t boring because I met all different kinds of people.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-38805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">While I had this
				job I got engaged to the boy who I was going out with while I was still at school.
				Just as I started on another job which was working with my cousin in a fashion shop
				I got married.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-39805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">We had a
				beautiful wedding. Well I thought it was beautiful but to any other person it could
				have been just another wedding to them. My eldest brother gave me away and my
				youngest sister was a bridesmaid because when she was living at home with us she
				decided to go and live with her real mother. She was only ten at the time. My real
				mother came to the wedding as well but I wouldn’t invite the man she had ran off
				with, I always have hated him and I always will. After the wedding we went on
				honeymoon to Tenariff for a week, it was lovely.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-3a805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">After the
				honey-moon I went back to the job in the shop and Larry went back to his job in the
				dockyard.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-3b805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">Two years later
				we had a baby boy. We named him Paul after my brother and Larry’s cousin. I had
				finished work just before I had Paul, to become a housewife. At first life was
				exciting to have a baby to look after and a husband a house but as the years went by
				it became dreadfully boring, until I had another child. This time a girl. We named
				her Sam, short for Samantha. When Sam was three we moved away from Sheerness to
				London. We <sic>didnt</sic><corr>didn't</corr> like it in London much so we moved again to Rochester. Here we
				settled. Larry got a job and with the help of a friend gradually built up a small
				business. When both of the children went to school I started on another job in a
				factory but it was terrible and I packed it up very quickly.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-3c805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">Later I had
				another boy. We named him Mark. After Mark I <sic>didnt</sic><corr>didn't</corr> get another job I was quite
				content to be a mother, wife and housewife.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-3d805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">Now my <sic>childrens</sic><corr>children's</corr>
				children have grown, I wonder what their future will be.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-3e805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="10">I hope it will be
				as good or better than mine. Everyone had their ups and downs. <sic>Lets</sic><corr>Let's</corr> just hope there
				<sic>wont</sic><corr>won't</corr> be many downs.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>