<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 23</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-fd62b26c-cf4f-4f70-847e-2d0b93808ff7</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-97ad2baa-ac4f-4525-b19c-48d26726383a</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-d27d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Past Life</note>
      <u xml:id="q-d37d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">I left school at
				16 after passing two ‘o’ levels and failing a third. With these qualifications, I
				was able to get the job of clerical assistant in H.M Customs and Excise offices at
				Sheerness dock. I continued to live at home but paid for my keep. The first thing I
				done with my wages was to buy a motorbike for reasons of transport and ego. I soon
				joined a parachuting club and the next few years of my life were {illegible} to the
				learning of proper parachuting. My weekly income was sufficient to pay for my board,
				my fuel and my hobby. I used very little for petty things like drink. During my
				second year I took a weekend in Holland, <sic>toaring</sic><corr>touring</corr> with my bike. I travelled by {Ocean
				line?} and only had to pay £7.50 for fare. After I had learned and experienced as
				much as I wanted to in parachuting, I moved on to hang-gliding, which proved to be
				an expensive sport. During this time I attended evening classes to obtain further
				‘o’ levels in physics, English literature and French. When I had passed these (which
				I did first time) I applied for the next step in my career, the post of clerical
				officer. There was some delay before I was situated in this position, but with my
				extra qualifications and a good 4 year work record already, I was accepted. Many
				times I had given thought to the idea of renting a flat, but this was just
				un-economical, and actually pointless as I could live with a certain degree of
				comfort with my parents for a relatively small amount of money.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-d47d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">However, this
				became impossible when I became seriously involved with a girl. I would not take
				part in a religious marriage ceremony as this would have been hypocrisy, me never
				having been to church since I decided not to. We agreed to have a registry office
				wedding. With the decision to marry, came flat hunting. I was able to afford a
				reasonable flat with my recent promotion, and we found one after many months of
				searching.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-d57d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">During the next
				few years, I switched my hobby again and felt a sense of achievement after reaching
				a high degree of skill in each of my past pass-times. The marriage was a good one,
				as we understood each other not only emotionally but spiritually as well (we were
				both vegetarian and had been since we began to think reasonably). No children were
				born as we wouldn’t take part in the act of bringing a child into the world, until
				it was a better place. However, our joint sex life was mutually satisfying.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-d67d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">Promotion was
				again within sight and this I nearly failed the interview when the question of
				politics came up and I had to be satisfied with labelling myself as politically
				non-active, although I firmly believed in a form of Marxist society as the ideal
				society.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-d77d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">The marriage
				ended with my wife becoming a statistic on a death rate accident paper.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-d87d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">My life
				continued, with me changing from hobby to hobby, each offering a taste of what life
				had to offer. I made my will and enclosed a request that a party should be held
				after my cremation, as I had once felt grief and wouldn’t inflict it on anybody
				else. Now I’m 60 and still going strong. There are still hobbies to try and I won’t
				grow old.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>