<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 20</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-404aadbb-f35e-485f-8654-79b2e0bebe21</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-471aeb96-25c1-4132-8d04-6f86dee41c01</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-be7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-bf7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">Although in some
				places my life has been poor, the majority has been rather good to me.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c07d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">Upon leaving
				school in 1978 I obtained, much to my surprise, five ‘o’ level passes and with these
				I managed to get an apprenticeship which gave me a good start in the world. Although
				the pay was extremely low, I was getting the training that I required.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c17d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">When I was
				seventeen, I <sic>bout</sic><corr>bought</corr> a car and my social life lifted somewhat and I enjoyed my self.
				My apprenticeship was totally neglected until I met a girl who was understanding and
				calmed me down and made me take interest again.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c27d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">By the age of 20
				I had married and lived in a flat, which we <sic>barly</sic><corr>barely</corr> could afford, and at 21 my
				apprenticeship was complete.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c37d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">The firm which
				had trained me now offered me a job with them in tool-making, I <sic>decsided</sic><corr>decided</corr> that I
				didn’t want this, having been there five years, and left.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c47d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">Being skilled in
				my work, I thought I could get a job any where, but I was rong and I was out of work
				for about five <sic>mounths</sic><corr>months</corr><sic>befor</sic><corr>before</corr> I was offered a job with a small company which was
				going places.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c57d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">The pay was the
				best I had had and we got ourselves a new house. By this time I was the proud father
				of a little girl, I wanted a boy- less trouble.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c67d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">With the pay I
				was getting I got a nice large family car, which at the time was the pride of my
				life. I also wanted more children to fill it but my wife rejected the idea, my
				<sic>dauter</sic><corr>daughter</corr> was a difficult bird and she did not want to go through with it again.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c77d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="10">After about a
				year we finally had a son, it was at this time we decided to move to Germany where
				my work was expanding and I was given a promotion to manager of that part of the
				company.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c87d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="11">I gave my new
				family the best education I could afford and my wife was content in her new
				surroundings. When working late one night with my secretary we got talking and when
				we had finished we went out for a drink, or two. This was the <sic>evill</sic><corr>evil</corr> beginning of an
				affair which some how my wife discovered.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-c97d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="12">By the age of 30
				my marriage was on the verge of destruction, but being what I was I was able to make
				things up and it turned out to be stronger than it ever had been <sic>befor</sic><corr>before</corr>.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>