<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 92</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-45dcc67f-6937-467e-9154-05b0019b6798</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-9ade66df-dbfa-4dfd-bc62-6bcc3b4d9cb3</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-697f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">My Life</note>
      <u xml:id="q-6a7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">Looking back over
				my life feel I have enjoyed it, if only I took advantage of the opportunities that
				were open to me I would have done better in this world but as it is <sic>hear</sic><corr>here</corr> I am 60
				years old and nothing really behind me, but <sic>happyness</sic><corr>happiness</corr>.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-6b7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">After leaving
				school at the age of 18 I went to a teacher training college I was very lucky to get
				one of those much envied places in the college as they were very scarce. I passed
				out of the college with a diploma for teaching and many praises from members of
				staff there saying how well I had done. But <sic>dispite</sic><corr>despite</corr> all this I still failed in the
				world. I got my first job in a school after being out of college for nearly 9 months
				but this was only a temporary job so I was back on the dole <sic>que</sic><corr>queue</corr> after 6 months and
				there I stayed for many months. I gave up the hope of getting a job as a teacher as
				only about 1 in a 100 people leaving college get a job. During the time I was a
				college I met up with a young man that I knew during my childhood. We saw each other
				for about 10 months then we got engaged. We were engaged for about 2 ½ years and
				<sic>dispite</sic><corr>despite</corr> all the trouble I had trying to find a job in this time we got married. We
				were very lucky in our marriage as he lived in a house on his own after the death of
				his parents so I moved straight into this house with him. Our life has been very
				happy and has lasted a long time we have now been married coming up 40 years and are
				still as happy as the day we met.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-6c7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">After having
				trouble finding a job I started to do child minding during the day as I was
				qualified due to the teaching diploma. I was very happy in this and kept children
				daily up until I had my first child. As soon as this came it was hard work. And I
				didn’t really have time for another job. When my first child was 3. I had another
				child this time a boy and we went on another 5 years before having our second
				girl.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-6d7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">The children all
				grew up very quickly and before I knew where I was they were all at school and the
				oldest one just about to take exams I could see the children having all the same
				sort of problems that I had with boy and girlfriends and then exams. Only my
				youngest girl stayed on at school. And despite her hopes of becoming a teacher I
				persuaded her to become a nurse and now she is still in that career and very happy
				with it after working her way right up to the top. But the others didn’t do quite as
				well as her. The oldest left school and 16 and became a police woman and the boy got
				an apprenticeship but has <sic>resently</sic><corr>recently</corr> started his own firm. All my children have grown
				up very happy and have never had long terms unemployed. After the children grew up
				and started to get married and move away. I started to get lonely. So I got my self
				a small job teaching again. It was in the remedial department in a big comprehensive
				school I really enjoyed this work teaching the youngsters to read. I found it so
				pleasing looking back at then and remembering my own children and my happy childhood
				<sic>dispite</sic><corr>despite</corr> many upsets we all stuck together. I stayed in this job for about 13 years
				right up until about 3 weeks ago when I finally had to retire. On my 60th birthday.
				That is why now I am looking back on my life with both happy and sad memories. With
				my children and many grandchildren always popping in to see me. I am so happy. And
				it another year it will be better as my husband is finally retiring also so now we
				can spend some much <sic>disurved</sic><corr>deserved</corr> time together. We are going to be so happy in our
				<sic>retiremen</sic><corr>retirement</corr> just the two of us. So <sic>dispite</sic><corr>despite</corr> my upsets at the begging of my life with
				the failure of my one ambition. It all changed and turned out right in the end.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>