<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 96</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-010bab2e-a038-4add-9106-f3abc0277d8e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-7a9b36cf-7e31-4437-8026-311d32a1eebd</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-937f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">My Past</note>
      <u xml:id="q-947f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">As I now look
				back to the days of when I first left school I think about my mates who I used to
				work in the shirt factory on the isle of Sheppey with and what times we use to have
				going out with our boyfriends to disco and youth clubs just like youngsters do
				nowadays. It was a great experience for me to go and collect my wage packet, my
				first ever wage packet from the <sic>bosses</sic><corr>boss's</corr> office, I use to make up wonderful dreams on
				how I would go off to Canada and marry a rich millionaire and we would live happy
				ever after, just like it was said in story books but instead I met Robert. Robert
				was a year younger than myself but we used to have fun going out together, motorbike
				racing, to discos, swimming, and his age didn’t seem to matter to me at all. I can
				always remember how he proposed to me, he fell down a flight of stairs and landed in
				my arms and said “Darling will you marry me”, and of course that was it.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-957f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">We had moved from
				Sheppey up into Ascon just outside Doncaster and that where our four little girls
				grew up and got married. Robert was a motorbike racer up <sic>their</sic><corr>there</corr> and I got a job as a
				bar assistant. It was quite pleasant really because you met different kinds of
				people.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-967f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">Although I didn’t
				mind Robert going racing, I was always sure some kind of accident would happen and
				it did, his bike crashed and he was taken to hospital with a broken back, legs, his
				pelvis and he lost the sight in his left eye. When he came out from hospital he was
				confined to a wheelchair, so I had to leave my job as a bar assistant and stay at
				home with Robert to look after him.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-977f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">That’s now it is
				{rocky?} my Robert in a chair and my four daughters grown up with children of their
				own, but to me it was all I ever really wanted.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>