<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 79</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-2306186d-8439-4aef-8ead-92b7905e329b</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-fb586008-7c78-4612-aa5b-a48072e78e30</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-0e7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-0f7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">Looking back on
				my life I see nothing particularly exciting or eventful in the past.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-107f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I left school at
				eighteen with, I thought adequate qualifications that would net me a ‘satisfactory’
				job. However all the jobs I did have, <sic>inevitable</sic><corr>inevitably</corr> involved clerical work of one
				description or another, which meant, though boredom mainly, that I didn’t hold them
				down long. Perhaps eventually it was my fault that I got landed with those sorts of
				jobs, after all I did decide to work at school, which when I look back now was
				fortunate, for a manual job would have horrible, compared to a typically clerical
				job, and those were at least tolerable.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-117f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">Money was whole
				point of this ‘the Rat Race’ which started at school and hasn’t yet finished. The
				whole idea you see, was that by working at school and gaining qualifications, you
				didn’t have to work so much when it came to a job, be nice if things were like
				that.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-127f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">As for as making
				money is concerned I was surprised <sic>acidemic</sic><corr>academic</corr> qualifications were in many cases. 1 an
				old friend of mine when I met in my second job made his fortune by being a <sic>burgaler</sic><corr>burglar</corr>.
				Obviously in that occupation, academic qualifications were <sic>unnessecarary</sic><corr>unnecessary</corr> which was
				just as well for him since he had none. In the process of his criminal activities he
				made use of a network of friends all of whom he could trust, and that’s why he never
				caught.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-137f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">One particular
				thing I’ve learnt is that money is important, no matter what people say. True, just
				because you have a lot of money doesn’t mean to say you’ll be happy, but it helps.
				Money provides power, a useful thing to have.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-147f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">If you ever have
				to <sic>chose</sic><corr>choose</corr> between a friend say, and the state, when it comes to a clash of loyalties
				always <sic>chose</sic><corr>choose</corr> the friend, because to the state, be you servant, informer or what and
				how {irrelevant?} ever, you are still a statistic, a mark on a piece of paper to be
				stored, accounted for and classified to a friend you are a person.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-157f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">As for advice
				what you do, do your self and don’t accept anything the government says, unless it
				matches your opinion.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>