<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 87</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-7ee34ac8-3f9a-4002-af81-47e513a179a3</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-ca4681aa-8c97-4cc6-8540-ece99e225646</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-437f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-447f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">Looking back over
				the past fifty eight years of my life overall I am pleased with what I achieved. I
				became a teacher when I was twenty three. From then on I was happy I had achieved
				what I wanted to be as a person and was living pretty comfortably. But things in
				those days were not easy to come by, mind you with what I had been told when I was
				sixteen I was getting things easy. I didn’t think so.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-457f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">When I was about
				thirteen and had joined the local comprehensive school, the only question which came
				up was ‘what are you going to do when you leave school’. Of course then I had no
				idea what I was going to do. Halfway through the first year of the school we had to
				think very seriously what we were going to do in the coming last two years of our
				official school life. This same as a not too welcome surprise. I mean nothing of
				this sort of division making had been done in the previous school. It was suddenly
				<sic>sprang</sic><corr>sprung</corr> upon me.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-467f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">Perhaps I was
				fortunate in having parent that helped me make the right decision. I did make the
				correct division in my eyes. In the following two years my work was of a slightly
				above average standard.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-477f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">But the last year
				of compulsory schooling thing started becoming more worrying. I was on one hand
				hoping violently that I would get a good result on my exams so I could carry on in
				the sixth form and eventually go to college. For I had made up my mind to be a
				trader in the end of the last year of compulsory schooling. But on the other hand I
				was dreading the exam results to be negative. For that then meant I would have to
				leave school and find work. This was particularly unpleasant because unemployment at
				that time was terrible and secondly I would never <sic>achive</sic><corr>achieve</corr> another substitute to what
				I really wanted to be. This carried on for about eight months before the exam
				results had come through.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-487f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">I had passed some
				of the exams but unfortunately failed some as well. I persuaded my parents to let me
				stay on at school where I managed to get to college everything was fine. It was just
				the getting off the ground part of the school which held you in torment.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-497f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">As the years
				progressed on, I saw what I had hoped it would be like when I was at the end of my
				compulsory school life. Young people were being prepared for what they had to decide
				on in their later life in the last year of the middle schools. There was also a
				greater chance for young people to stay on at school for their benefit. As
				unemployment came down more employees gave more of an opportunity of work for them
				instead of the usual letter of <sic>disappiontment</sic><corr>disappointment</corr>.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-4a7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">The pupils I used
				to teach never seemed bothered by the worries I had. Perhaps the generations had
				changed their view or was it that the worries did not exist anymore. I do not really
				know, but I hope for the <sic>youngsters</sic><corr>youngsters'</corr> sake that the latter reason is correct.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-4b7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">The money of a
				teacher at the early stages was not an amount one could boast about. But I enjoyed
				my job and as the years went by so did the money. Until now retired I think that it
				was worth it, but should anyone have to go through the worry of his or her future at
				such a late time?</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>