<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 135</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-6d8d1064-611c-43fb-9f47-dfbc48fe9fe7</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-97598525-c53c-4c17-9bce-b995c9aa0656</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-d0805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflecting</note>
      <u xml:id="q-d1805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">I have led a
				pretty normal life. I left school when I was nearly eighteen and got a job. The
				money was quite good, but carried on living with my parents. I kept that job for
				eight months and then got a job as a personal secretary because the money was much
				better. When I was nineteen, I got married to my boyfriend who I’d known at school.
				It was good at school because you met so many people and had so many friends. We
				used to go out <sic>alot</sic><corr>a lot</corr> to school discos and have a good time. When I left school, I
				missed it even though I made new friends at work, but everything became more
				serious.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-d2805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">Two years after I
				got married, I gave up working to have my first child. As soon as the child was old
				enough to go to school, I started working again- not because we were poor but it
				doesn’t hurt to have a bit of extra money, and I got bored being stuck at home all
				day. With both my husband and myself working, we came fairly well off. This meant I
				could have lots of new clothes and could afford to go out more often. We still saved
				<sic>alot</sic><corr>a lot</corr> of money though.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-d3805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">At the age of
				twenty-eight I had my second child, and so, had to give up working again, but this
				didn’t last for long. As soon as my second child went to school, I went back to
				work. I gave my children a good upbringing so that I could be proud of them. One of
				my children gained some A levels, whilst the other one got some o levels and left
				school, but they both got good jobs.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-d4805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">My father died
				when I was forty although I knew he’d die sooner or later, I was still shocked and
				upset. Five years later, my mother died and I inherited a fairly large sum of
				money.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-d5805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">Now I’m eighty- I
				don’t know how I’ve managed to live this long. My children have left and got married
				and have also made me a grandmother three times. But I’m alone now. My husband has
				gone. When he died, I thought I’d die without him, but I lived.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-d6805d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">Now, all I have
				to look forward to, is my funeral and being buried next to my husband.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>