<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 6</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-06c6bc37-604d-431e-aa6a-c5e6953868d7</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-3d7257f6-7753-4503-887a-5fcf0f530b2c</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-6d7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflections</note>
      <u xml:id="q-6e7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">When I look back
				on life, I see why the older generation cannot tolerate the younger. Partly because
				of changes in a person’s life which makes them different from others. I look out of
				my {window?}, and see children going from school, some leaving, some staying on to
				study.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-6f7d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I remember that
				when I was sixteen and after passing my exams, I was excepted as an apprentice at a
				motor trade company. I was on that trade for four years. A lot of things happened
				during that time. At seventeen I joined a group. We played rock music, mainly on the
				old Island where I once lived. We were well known but had to split up as three
				members of the group had got married. After two years of the apprenticeship I got
				engaged. I couldn’t get married until I was twenty because I didn’t finish the
				apprenticeship until then. At nineteen, I passed the City and Guilds certificate.
				This meant a rise in pay.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-707d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">When I was
				exactly twenty, I proposed to my girlfriend. Two months later we were married. It
				was only a matter of a few months before my wife was pregnant. I was earning a lot
				of money, so we decided to put a deposit down on a house. We had one in Basildon in
				Essex. There a got a job as a mechanic working on Post office vans. Soon our first
				child was born. We felt pleased with our-selves, and a year later we decided to have
				another.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-717d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">After our second
				child was born I had an accident at work, I crawled out from under a van, and I was
				run over by a car, not completely only my legs. Both of them were broken and I was
				in hospital for the next few months. This was one of the worst times of my life. All
				there was on the family was worry. The bills needed paying, the children feeding,
				and mortgage had to be <sic>payed</sic><corr>paid</corr>. My sick pay and insurance helped, but it was not
				enough. My wife hired a baby sitter and got a job.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-727d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">When I got out of
				the hospital, I found that my place as an engineer was taken as it could not have
				been left without another had for so long. It was <sic>severn</sic><corr>seven</corr> weeks before I got another
				job and I had to <sic>travell</sic><corr>travel</corr> twenty miles there and back six days a week. When I was
				twenty nine, I changed jobs as the firm I worked for went bankrupt because there
				electrical materials had been replaced by new methods of power and engineering. I
				got a job in a steel mill at Norwich. It was a long way to travel and further
				education was needed for use of new <sic>machinary</sic><corr>machinery</corr>, <sic>lazers</sic><corr>lasers</corr> and things like that. I stayed
				at that job until I was thirty five. At thirty three, the first child was thirteen
				and the second was eleven. I joined a group and we got known quickly. When I was
				thirty five, we were offered a recording <sic>contrack</sic><corr>contract</corr> by CiF.I a new major record
				company. I went along with the group a lot, in fact <sic>to</sic><corr>too</corr> much. I love music and my
				wife and that was the problem. While I was travelling she stayed at home and we see
				less of each other. After two years, she couldn’t take no more and our marriage
				ended in the divorce courts. She had right to the children. This really broke me
				down and I went on to taking drugs as a lot of musicians did at that time.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-737d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">I became a
				nervous wreck after a year then I became religious. Something I never expected to
				happen. This brought me out of drugs.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-747d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">I was religious
				up until I was <sic>fourty</sic><corr>forty</corr> eight but I retired from the music seen at the age of forty
				five.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-757d5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">I brought 1 house
				in the countryside in England. There I was <sic>excepted</sic><corr>accepted</corr> as just another person, not like
				some stars. I got so lonely in the house. When I was fifty two I moved to a flat
				just outside Basildon. I felt like committing suicide but a visit, a surprise at
				that was when my daughter and son turned up at my door. They had married and had two
				sons and a daughter each. My ex wife had died. The eldest was a boy, who was eight.
				At sixty, eight years later, he made a visit and asked me about what he should do
				because he was old enough to leave school and get a good job. I couldn’t give him
				any <sic>advise</sic><corr>advice</corr> because my life had been a <sic>failier</sic><corr>failure</corr>. I only warned him to take care and
				think. When he left everything went <sic>quite</sic><corr>quiet</corr> and dark, and time stood still.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>