<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 51</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-987095fe-ec22-40c4-bf88-6e72b27dc679</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-03af6c27-ec75-49a7-9b75-cd7ce5a66f30</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u xml:id="q-5f7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="1">When I like
				{look} back to the pass I had such great time when I left school at the age of
				sixteen I started work at a D.I.Y. shop learn the trade going out doing job then I
				brought myself a piece of land with all the knowledge behind me. I could build my
				own house to have <sic>somethink</sic><corr>something</corr> to have eversince I had left school what I had in mind
				and that is what happen and once I had finish that house I would work myself up for
				a foreman on a building site to <sic>desian</sic><corr>design</corr> new place in different town all across the
				country make my firm very famous in what I had <sic>acheived</sic><corr>achieved</corr> since working at a shop.
				Then when I got to the age of <sic>retiarment</sic><corr>retirement</corr> I would live in a little Bungalow and have
				a Nice Long and wide garage full of working tools ready to make doors to sell to
				{hom?} would like to use the {doors?}. and that is what happen it was such an
				<sic>intresting</sic><corr>interesting</corr> life now all I do is sit in the armchair near the coal fire and just
				relax I found that it was such a good life for all the <sic>gloryies</sic><corr>glories</corr> think which had
				happen after I had left school. When I first start in a shop then built my own house
				then went to a building firm made my name there the returned and start {?}
				{carpeters?} work and just plodding along that is what happen in my pass now I am at
				eighty five I just sit <sic>adn</sic><corr>and</corr> rest and I think that I deserve a nice long rest after
				all those year of hard work. Also during those year of hard work I married a nice
				young lady I had a house out at the countryside had three children and had my own
				yard with all of the firm digger dump etc. And I use to do out there when I had a
				{?} work like{?} and also {?} and keep them in a {?} working order so that we could
				get more work done with good reliable machine work. We all use to help one another
				out of trouble when we were not at work like repair our car etc and in my spear time
				I like garden a lot growing think and all at repair my car of my own {?} I have had
				the odd moments when we had trouble at work when there was a Strike <sic>everone</sic><corr>everyone</corr><sic>hat</sic><corr>had</corr> to
				stop for a fortnight so we lost a lot of time because we was on contract work so
				{within?} 3 month we made-up that time by doing overtime and then we was back on our
				feet as normal I think that I had a good life with the good think and the back then
				what happen I would love to have my life all over again what a <sic>intrest</sic><corr>interesting</corr> life I have
				had.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>