<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 48</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-626a53b5-81ff-48a7-a3ed-3d98e743f4fa</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-cf3ed735-b69e-4382-aaf5-f177ad7e3a2b</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-4b7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">My Past</note>
      <u xml:id="q-4c7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">At the age of
				sixteen, a week away from my exams, life like hell, revising this and that, working
				out which place went where, sorting out Charle’s law, and Boyles law. Life was not
				as bad as it seemed because when my marks came through the post the results where
				what I had expected. They were not good enough to get in my in to the job that I had
				wanted for so long which was an Airframe/propulsion aircraft fitter in the Royal Air
				Force but it did get me there in to my next most wanted job a direct entrant and to
				specialise on one job only, that of airframes.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-4d7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">Getting the job
				was hard enough but doing the job was a different matter all together. First of all
				I had to go to the R.A.F. Swinderby for six weeks basic training and this was like
				being at school again but learning different things such as drill, rifle drill, P.E.
				Training, hiking across rough country and boy was it hard, and that drill sergeant
				he was a right nasty piece of work who never stopped shouting from the minute we
				walked on to the parade square, until the minute we walked off again.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-4e7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">Still six weeks
				went passed as fast as eny thing and then on to R.A.F. Haltonwhere I went to get
				another school and learnt all about the airframe of an aircraft, still it was worth
				it because no sooner than joining the class we were leaving it of to foreign parts,
				I did not go far, in fact I stayed in Great Britain and went to R.A.F. Scampton in
				Lincolnshire for nine years where I worked on Vulcans and Victors.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-4f7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">I left the
				airforce at the age of 24, and went and worked for British Airways where I met a
				nice girl and got to know her and sure enough two years later I got married. We
				<sic>where</sic><corr>were</corr> quite happy where we lived in the country but it was too far for me to go each
				day to work but this was not all that stopped me from going to work because at
				British Airways a large strike was on I had no choice but stay away.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-507e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">At the age of 40
				I had left British airways and was working in a small office just outside of
				Hampshire as this was my dream place where I had always wanted to live.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-517e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">I had been
				married 14 years and have got three lovely children the oldest of which is 11 and
				the youngest 6. I have the responsibility of making sure the insurance <sic>polecies</sic><corr>policies</corr>, of
				all the major airports in Britain are <sic>keeped</sic><corr>kept</corr> up to date. I stayed with this job
				until I was 64 when I retired, but ran a light aircraft in which I did most of my
				travelling abroad and on a little sight seeing.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-527e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">My three children
				have all been married and are living in Manchester, Sheffield and Bristol.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-537e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">I look down
				towards the floor where two of my grandchildren are making plastic aircraft kits and
				also reading some of my <sic>pamphletes</sic><corr>pamphlets</corr> I had as a boy and comparing then with to-days
				more advanced ones which I do not even understand as a direct entrant as I had done
				all those years ago, we will just have to wait and see.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>