<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 82</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-d9a19349-0e0f-4841-a85d-4c70fcaf1b0c</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-a77a7892-f19b-4a6a-bcdc-2af77771866f</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-287f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflecting</note>
      <u xml:id="q-297f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">Looking back over
				my life I haven’t really fulfilled all of my hopes and ambitions.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-2a7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">When I was
				leaving school at the age of sixteen I was quite unprepared. In school the teachers
				had filled my head with everything they thought I must know before leaving.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-2b7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">They talked about
				marriage, divorce and emphasised on starting a job. One lesson a week was spent
				talking about these things, but most of the time, we were just ignorant of the fact
				that it wasn’t long before we would be leaving.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-2c7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">We were told
				about how critical the job shortage was, and how we could overcome this fact. I had
				one appointment for an interview at the careers office for <sic>advise</sic><corr>advice</corr> as did everybody.
				I was told about all of the jobs available and which I could apply for. The chance
				of me getting the job which I hoped for was almost nil, as there were many other
				school leavers applying to the same firm.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-2d7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">I had filled in a
				questionnaire about myself to help the interviewer. I was interviewed by a woman and
				she was very helpful. It was quite a well organised careers centre, plus, which I
				think was a very good idea the centre was on the school grounds. I think that all
				schools should have a careers office or centre on their grounds.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-2e7f5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">I was given
				plenty of forms to send of for jobs and more interviews. Really I think that schools
				should make mock interviews for separate students to get them used to it. I was
				given only one interview which lasted only twenty-five minutes. The interviewers
				should also keep in touch with some of the students to see how they get on. I did
				obtain an apprenticeship in what I wanted but there still seems to have been
				something missing. Most of the things which I did were different to what the school
				advised. I retired on a pension at sixty-five.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>