<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 75</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-ccc138de-2447-4df5-bdef-0962c1c51216</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-2861d623-1463-4e30-96bc-be8d1f67d59a</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <u xml:id="q-f97e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="1">When I was 16 I
				left school coming out into the large rough world. When I left I had to look around
				for a job. Till one day some one took me on as a part time cleaner not having much
				brains. This is all was fit for I stayed there <sic>till</sic><corr>until</corr><sic>is</sic><corr>I</corr> was about 18 ½ were I left
				and decided to look around for something better <sic>till</sic><corr>until</corr> I was about 19 I did not have a
				job I could not afford any equipment for hobbies. So one day I was walking down to
				the social <sic>securets</sic><corr>security</corr> office when I saw a poster skilled men wanted. I took note and
				decided to go for an interview next day I went to the works and met the manager he I
				ask me questions and I answered him not knowing much about it. He then said thank
				you very much we will consider you. I waited and waited till one day a little brown
				letter addressed to me came through the door it said</u>
      <u xml:id="q-fa7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">Dear Sir</u>
      <u xml:id="q-fb7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">You have been
				consider for a <sic>aprentership</sic><corr>apprenticeship</corr> for the job £90.00 per week. I could not <sic>belive</sic><corr>believe</corr> it. When
				I started the job I found it hard but with a little <sic>super vision</sic><corr>supervision</corr> I picked it up
				quickly. After I had been there for a few months I was rich. 21 and I was smartly
				dressed had my own house my own car and my hobbies started coming. Most of the time
				I would be fishing or shooting till one night I went to my friend party I had a few
				drinks and was social but I also met a girl and went out with her after about a year
				and a ½-2 we decided to get married. I’d just turned 23 the years shot by and I had
				now turned 36 I never felt so fed up I had to stay in and help the wife every night
				could not go with my mates down the pub. Soon my hair turned grey my wife died and I
				was a lonely old man I was 59 my job was still going well. A few years later I was
				an old aged pensioner and I sat there thinking of when I was young. What I could do
				all those things n now I can only stay indoors and watch <sic>telley</sic><corr>telly</corr> or listen to the
				radio.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>