<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="collectiondisplaylabel">School Leavers Study</title>
        <title type="sourcedisplaylabel">Essay by 63</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <idno type="qudexcollection">q-41037361-714f-493f-94bd-18ee7e3fa29e</idno>
        <idno type="qudexsource">q-03e00e62-c314-4520-84ed-c7b39bb4cd93</idno>
        <idno type="qudexdocument">q-15466b2e-95c0-4f71-8bcd-3b421b723cdc</idno>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>School Leavers Study, 1978</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <note xml:id="q-a07e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" type="heading1" n="1">Reflecting</note>
      <u xml:id="q-a17e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="2">After leaving
				school, some 50 years ago, I got a job in a bakery. This was just moving bags of
				flour and yeast around, and learning about baking bread. I was offered a place for
				an <sic>apprenteship</sic><corr>apprenticeship</corr> at a college in baking but I turned this down, because in 2 <sic>months</sic><corr>months'</corr>
				time (20th September) I was going to join the army.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-a27e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="3">I had worked at
				Woods for about five weeks. I would have liked to work there for another two months
				(until it was time to join the Army), but alas the bakery had to shut down. It had
				run out of funds. First all the shops shut down. Then I was made ‘redundant’.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-a37e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="4">I could of sat
				down all day, doing nothing, for two months, but I didn’t really like the idea.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-a47e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="5">Employment on
				this ‘Island’ was very low, but according to the statistics there were plenty of
				jobs. I didn’t know where though, I must have looked all day for two weeks, but
				still couldn’t find a job.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-a57e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="6">But then the firm
				my dad worked for got a government grant for £350,000 to help them put a railway
				line through their ‘yard’ as well as buying docking facilities etc…</u>
      <u xml:id="q-a67e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="7">Which was
				estimated at the time to cost around £1 ½ million to develop. I thought this was
				ridiculous as they were already £800,000 in the red!</u>
      <u xml:id="q-a77e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="8">This scheme was
				to create an extra 14 jobs. I got one of them. My Brother who had worked there
				before also got a job. So did my friend who had just lost his job he too was going
				into the Army with me.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-a87e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="9">I worked with
				{Flame cap?} until the 10th of September I stopped work because in 10 <sic>days</sic><corr>days'</corr> time I
				was going to join the Army.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-a97e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="10">The 19th of
				September soon came. Colin (my friend who lives across the road) and me had our
				cases packed and were ready to leave. We were both going into the same regiment
				(REME) .</u>
      <u xml:id="q-aa7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="11">Our first 18
				weeks of basic training was spent at Brompton barracks. About two - three miles from
				where our previous job had been. We got a 72 hour pass after weeks. My father picked
				us up. Then we had a four day leave six weeks in Basic Training.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ab7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="12">Then we were
				posted to Corsham barracks in Wiltshire we <sic>finneshed</sic><corr>finished</corr> our <sic>apprenticips</sic><corr>apprenticeships</corr>. I got a
				degree in vehicle mechanics but Colin just failed.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ac7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="13">Colin signed on
				for 3 years. But I signed on for 9 years. We visited many European countries
				(Germany, Belgium etc…) and after 3 years Colin signed on for another six.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ad7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="14">When I was 21 I
				went to Ulster. At first I was scared. But our unit was lucky. We didn’t get posted
				to Belfast but to a border town. There was very little trouble here.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-ae7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="15">The only
				‘trouble’ we had when an I.R.A. <sic>excution</sic><corr>execution</corr> squad try to hide in the town. These were
				not given accommodation, because earlier a type of this squad had hid up in the town
				ad murdered about 10 young children when a car bomb went ‘off’ at a school
				crossing.</u>
      <u xml:id="q-af7e5d94-362c-e311-93c1-000bdb5cc6d5" who="R" n="16">Two of the squad
				had been killed.</u>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>